<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Eloquent Words Of Legendary Writers</title>
    <meta content="Y02WRI$23" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSPECTIVE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Twentieth Century</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6D91038F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1479" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Eloquent Words Of Legendary Writers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Twentieth century sports columnists who had greatest impact on their profession as both reporters and writers recalled; excerpts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until the beginning of the 20th century, the coverage of sports in newspapers, except for the occasional heavyweight title fight or a local football or baseball game, was little more than an afterthought. Then, with increasing leisure time for readers to both play and watch, sports grew more important to life and lifestyle. Editors caught on, and sportswriting began to flourish.</p>
        <p>Following is a list of seven sports columnists -- in roughly chronological order -- who have arguably had the greatest impact on their profession as both reporters and writers. There have been numerous other distinguished sports journalists in the last 100 years -- from Charles Dryden to Frank Graham to Shirley Povich -- but space dictates that the list be limited.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until the beginning of the 20th century, the coverage of sports in newspapers, except for the occasional heavyweight title fight or a local football or baseball game, was little more than an afterthought. Then, with increasing leisure time for readers to both play and watch, sports grew more important to life and lifestyle. Editors caught on, and sportswriting began to flourish.</p>
        <p>Following is a list of seven sports columnists -- in roughly chronological order -- who have arguably had the greatest impact on their profession as both reporters and writers. There have been numerous other distinguished sports journalists in the last 100 years -- from Charles Dryden to Frank Graham to Shirley Povich -- but space dictates that the list be limited.</p>
        <p>Those included here range from Ring Lardner, who began writing about baseball in 1906, to Jim Murray, who wrote his sports column nearly up to the day he died, in 1998. Lardner, Damon Runyon and Grantland Rice were giants for the first half of the century. Red Smith, Jimmy Cannon, Dick Young and Murray were prominent in the second half.</p>
        <p>Red Smith (1905-1982)</p>
        <p>Born Walter Wellesley Smith, he worked for newspapers in Milwaukee, St. Louis and Philadelphia before being hired in 1945 by The New York Herald Tribune. He became the most widely syndicated sports columnist of his generation. Smith joined The New York Times in 1971, and won the Pulitzer Prize for Distinguished Commentary in 1976 at age 70. His Pulitzer citation praised his humor and humanitarianism, as well as ''the erudition, the literary quality, the vitality and freshness of viewpoint'' of his columns.</p>
        <p>On the final day of the 1951 season, the Dodgers needed a victory to tie for the National League pennant. It was the bottom of the 12th inning at Shibe Park and it was getting dark. The Phillies had the bases loaded and two out. Eddie Waitkus smashed a drive toward center field. Jackie Robinson, wrote Smith, ''flings himself headlong at right angles to the flight of the ball, for an instant his body is suspended in midair, then somehow the outstretched glove intercepts the ball inches off the ground. He falls heavily, the crash drives an elbow into his side, he collapses. . . .  stretched at full length in the insubstantial twilight, the unconquerable doing the impossible.''</p>
        <p>Grantland Rice (1880-1954)</p>
        <p>Rice was generally considered the best-known sportswriter of his generation. He read widely and brought a certain literate quality to sportswriting that hadn't quite been there before. He began writing for The Nashville News in 1901, after graduation from Vanderbilt. He later wrote for The New York Mail and The New York Tribune. In 1930 he began his popular syndicated sports column, ''The Spotlight.'' Of the two so-called schools of sportswriting in the early part of the century -- the skeptical ''Aw Nuts'' writers versus the more romantic ''Gee Whiz'' writers -- Rice was clearly in the latter group.</p>
        <p>He wrote perhaps the most famous opening paragraph in sports-writing history. It appeared on Oct. 19, 1924, as a lead to his report on the Notre Dame-Army football game, won by Notre Dame, and which starred the Fighting Irish backfield: ''Outlined against a blue-gray October sky, the Four Horsemen rode again. In dramatic lore they are known as Famine, Pestilence, Destruction, and Death. These are only aliases. Their real names are Stuhldreher, Miller, Crowley and Layden.''</p>
        <p>Ring Lardner (1885-1933)</p>
        <p>Lardner began his career as a sportswriter for The South Bend (Ind.) Times, but made his greatest impact in newspapers as the ''Wake of the News'' sports columnist for The Chicago Tribune. His literary fame, however, rests primarily on his short stories, such as ''Alibi Ike'' and ''You Know Me Al.'' His inventions in language and perspective also enlivened his sports columns.</p>
        <p>From a column in 1910 in which he assumes the role of a spectator for a Chicago White Sox-Philadelphia Athletics game:</p>
        <p>''On my right sat a gent who knew something, and he soon gave evidence of the fact. Morris Rath opened the Sox attack with a safe bunt. He was nailed at second when Lord missed his swing on a hit and run.</p>
        <p>'' 'Stealing second with nobody out,' remarked the guy who knows. 'And the papers call him a brainy ballplayer. If he had good sense, he'd trade all his brains for a little bit of ability.' ''</p>
        <p>Damon Runyon (1884-1946)</p>
        <p>He began writing for newspapers when he was 12 years old. He worked for newspapers in Pueblo, Colo., Colorado Springs, Denver, San Francisco and became one of the country's star reporters -- and sports columnists -- with The New York American. He covered wars, murder trials and World Series with equal distinction. Like Lardner, it is Runyon's short stories that enlarged his fame. His ''Runyonesque'' characters live on in the musical ''Guys and Dolls,'' adapted from his short stories.</p>
        <p>From the lead in a column from the 1930 Kentucky Derby:</p>
        <p>''Say, have they turned the pages</p>
        <p>Back to the past once more?</p>
        <p>Back to the racin' ages</p>
        <p>An' a Derby out of the yore?</p>
        <p>Say, don't tell me I'm daffy,</p>
        <p>Ain't that the same ol' grin?</p>
        <p>Why it's that handy</p>
        <p>Guy named Sande,</p>
        <p>Bootin' a winner in!''</p>
        <p>Jimmy Cannon (1909-1973)</p>
        <p>He was born in New York and grew up in Greenwich Village. He wrote for several New York newspapers, covered the city and worked as a war correspondent, but in 1946 he began his syndicated sports column for The New York Post. He later moved on to The Journal-American. His rich prose made him one of the most distinctive columnists of the century, but he may have been best known for the occasional column, ''Nobody Asked Me, But. . . . ''</p>
        <p>Following are some lines over the years from ''Nobody Asked Me, But. . . . '':</p>
        <p>''It's almost impossible for a girl to be homely with a gardenia in her hair.'' . . . ''I've never seen a circus clown I thought was funny.'' . . . ''I can't ever remember staying for the end of a movie in which the actors wore togas.'' . . . ''The trouble with the big leagues is that there aren't enough big leaguers.''</p>
        <p>Dick Young (1918-1987)</p>
        <p>He revolutionized sports coverage when, as a beat reporter for The Daily News assigned to the Brooklyn Dodgers in the early 1940's, he began to go into the clubhouse after games to find out what the players had seen and thought during the game. Before this, reporters in the press box wrote solely what the reporters had seen and thought during a game. In 1957, Young began writing his column, ''Young Ideas,'' after the team owner, Walter O'Malley, decided to move the Dodgers to Los Angeles. In 1982 he moved on to The New York Post. Writing with wit and a hard-hitting, direct style, he was frequently in verbal battles with an assortment of sports figures throughout his years as a columnist.</p>
        <p>The following is from a 1957 column:</p>
        <p>''This is called an obit, which is short for obituary. An obit tells of a person who has died, how he lived, and of those who live after him. This is the obit on the Brooklyn Dodgers.</p>
        <p>''Preliminary diagnosis indicates that the cause of death was an acute case of greed, followed by severe political implications. . . . and, now, Walter O'Malley leaves Brooklyn a rich man and a despised man.''</p>
        <p>Jim Murray (1919-1998)</p>
        <p>Murray, who won a Pulitzer Prize in 1990, began his career as a reporter for The New Haven Register. He moved on to write for The Los Angeles Examiner, Time magazine and Sports Illustrated, before joining The Los Angeles Times as a sports columnist in 1961. He soon became widely syndicated, and was highly praised for his acerbic wit (and, not surprisingly, highly denounced by some of the subjects of his wit). But, like all good writers, he could also touch a sensitive chord.</p>
        <p>From a column in 1979, in which he tells of the loss from an operation of his ''good eye'' -- the other eye had seen only a hazy world -- and now admitted that he was virtually blind: ''I'd like to see Sugar Ray Robinson or Muhammad Ali giving a recital, a ballet, not a fight. Also, to be sure, I'd like to see a sky full of stars, moonlight on the water, and yes, the tips of a royal flush peaking out as I fan out a poker hand, and, yes, a straight two-foot putt.</p>
        <p>''Come to think of it, I'm lucky. I saw all of those things. I see them yet.''</p>
        <p>PERSPECTIVE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
