<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="02GUID" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DF1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1433" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Barbara Delatiner</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>When it comes to win-win situations, the Islip Arts Council's annual Winter Chamber Music Series can't be topped. Talented young professional musicians get to perform (and be paid for their efforts), often trying out programs they will later play in New York City venues, and Long Island audiences get to attend significant concerts in lovely settings for a very appealing price -- all the events are free. The newest edition of the series begins today at 2 p.m. in the Carriage House at Bayard Cutting Arboretum in Oakdale. The Azure Chamber Ensemble, consisting of Susan Glaser, flutist; Leo Suzuki, violist; and Jennifer Hoult, harpist, offers a program featuring the Debussy ''Trio.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>When it comes to win-win situations, the Islip Arts Council's annual Winter Chamber Music Series can't be topped. Talented young professional musicians get to perform (and be paid for their efforts), often trying out programs they will later play in New York City venues, and Long Island audiences get to attend significant concerts in lovely settings for a very appealing price -- all the events are free. The newest edition of the series begins today at 2 p.m. in the Carriage House at Bayard Cutting Arboretum in Oakdale. The Azure Chamber Ensemble, consisting of Susan Glaser, flutist; Leo Suzuki, violist; and Jennifer Hoult, harpist, offers a program featuring the Debussy ''Trio.''</p>
        <p>After four more concerts at the arboretum, the series moves to Fortunoff Hall on the Oakdale campus of Dowling College. Among the artists appearing this season are Ayako Yoshida, violinist, and James Lent, pianist -- both Concert Artist Guild prize-winners -- next Sunday and Feb. 6, respectively; the Amelia Piano Trio, which played Carnegie Hall last June, Jan. 23, and Edward Arron, cellist, who performed at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in the fall. Seating, on a first-come, first-served basis, is limited at the Carriage House, so get there at 1:30 p.m. (631) 224-5420.</p>
        <p>Playing Barrymore</p>
        <p>As a child growing up in Mineola, Ed Dennehy always considered John Barrymore a hero. Although he never saw Barrymore on stage -- Mr. Dennehy is 53 and ''much too young to have done that'' -- he did study Barrymore's films, admiring his ''flamboyance and sheer theatricality.'' In addition ''there was the acting-family thing, and we were a theater family ourselves,'' said Mr. Dennehy, whose brother is Brian Dennehy, the stage and film star.</p>
        <p>And so for Ed Dennehy, a popular and busy actor-director on Long Island, playing Barrymore is ''kind of fulfilling a dream,'' paying homage to that hero. Last fall, Mr. Dennehy appeared in ''I Hate Hamlet'' at Hofstra University, portraying a comic, off-the-wall Barrymore. On Friday, again via Hofstra USA Productions, he opens in ''Barrymore,'' William Luce's one-man drama set in 1942 on the stage of the Plymouth Theater as the actor tries to recreate his legendary performance of Richard III. It is an entirely different Barrymore, one ''dealing wth the terrors of alcoholism and the ghosts in his mind,'' said Mr. Dennehy.</p>
        <p>With the playwright's permission, Mr. Dennehy and his co-director, Bob Spiotto, have made some changes in the play, which was an acclaimed vehicle for Christopher Plummer on Broadway. Instead of ''Barrymore talking to a presence off-stage, there is now a prompter, seen in shadows on-stage.'' Too, ''the voices that haunt him, the ghosts in his mind, that he created on stage in the original, are now produced electronically from sites throughout the theater,'' Mr. Dennehy said. The production runs through Jan. 23 at the Spiegel Theater on Hofstra's Hempstead campus (516) 463-6644.</p>
        <p>Perfect Children</p>
        <p>At the turn of the century, when most people aren't thinking much about certain social niceties that time has eroded, the Friends of Raynham Hall Museum are keeping such matters on the top of their transitions list. They are offering ''Children's Etiquette and Dining Skills for the Millennium,'' a four-session weekly course designed to teach youngsters from 7 through 12 how to watch and improve their P's and Q's. Using role-playing exercises, instructive materials and workbooks, Dorothy B. Cohen, director of Biarritz Protocol Consultants, will help participants develop self-esteem and confidence as they learn how to eat soup properly, answer a telephone call correctly, shake a hand firmly and sit properly. The course starts Saturday at 11 a.m. at Raynham Hall on West Main Street in Oyster Bay (516) 922-6808.</p>
        <p>Night Skies</p>
        <p>Just because it's winter, the Marine Program run by the Cornell Cooperative Extension of Suffolk does not shut down. On Friday, the first of three off-season programs takes place at the Marine Center in Southold: ''Night Skies of Winter,'' a session of star-gazing with Jim Benson,  an astronomy buff, who will teach the curious how to identify the major stars and constellations as well as some nebula, galactic clusters and galaxies. Participants are advised to dress warmly and bring binoculars for the program from 7 to 9:30 p.m. at the center on Cedar Beach Road. On Jan. 28, there is a naturalist-led ''Owl Prowl'' at 8:30 p.m., which is a slide-lecture followed by a hike at Hubbard County Park in Flanders, while on Feb. 4 the astronomy workshop will be repeated at the extension's Education Center in Riverhead (631) 852-8660.</p>
        <p>'Americana'</p>
        <p>Surveying chamber music from all over the world in their International Music Festival, the Long Island Chamber Players reach ''Americana'' on Saturday. Linda Sinanian, violinist; Barry Crawford, flutist; Jeffrey Forden, French hornist; and Christine Dore, pianist, offer ''a celebration of American music at the turn of the century,'' playing works by such diverse composers as Dvorak, Lucas Foss, Gershwin, Peter Schickele and Gary Schocker at 8 p.m. as part of the ''Music at Greenlawn'' series at the Greenlawn Presbyterian Church on Pulaski Road (631) 262-3306.</p>
        <p>New Age Music</p>
        <p>New Age music figures in the latest concert at the Inter-Media Art Center in Huntington on Friday. Courtesy of Windham Hill's ''Winter Solstice Tour,'' David Arkenstone, multi-instrumentalist; Liz Story, composer-pianist, and the Angels of Venice, a Los Angeles-based female trio, appear in a New Age concert at 9 p.m. at I.M.A.C. on New York Avenue (631) 549-9666.</p>
        <p>Irish Music</p>
        <p>Big Grey Concerts, a presenting group devoted to Celtic music, opens its 21st century run with Morning Star, a quartet. A popular New York-regional band that performs traditional and contemporary vocal and instrumental tunes, the group features Mary Courtney on vocals, guitar and bodhra'n, or Irish frame drum; Margie Mulvihill on tin whistle, John Reynolds on fiddle and John Nolan on button accordion. The last three are All-Ireland champions and Mr. Nolan was the first American to win the senior All-Ireland title. The concert is at 8 p.m. at the Searing-Roslyn United Methodist Church on I.U. Willets Road in Albertson (631) 321-1582.</p>
        <p>Experimental Art Forum</p>
        <p>Given Walt Whitman's impact as an innovator, it is fitting that his  birthplace should provide a platform for what is new and daring in the arts. That platform is provided by the Body Electric Cafe, an experimental art forum for the community that gives exposure to ''words, music, art, people.'' Run by the Body Electric Art Collective, founded by a group of young visual, literary and performing artists, the monthly cafe is meant to ''change the idea of a passive audience,'' said Alan Semerdjian, a poet and English teacher at Herricks High School who is the caretaker at the Whitman Birthplace. The next cafe session, featuring Frank Portella, a poet, is Saturday at 8 p.m. at the Whitman Home on Old Whitman Road in Huntington Station (631) 427-5240.</p>
        <p>At the Libraries</p>
        <p>Having taken a few weekends off because of the holidays, local libraries get right back into the cultural swing of things. So on Wednesday at 1 p.m. Monica Randall comes to the Syosset Library on South Oyster Bay Road with ''Winter Dreams,'' her multi-media lecture that recreates seasonal celebrations on Long Island estates during the 19th century (516) 921-7161. Come Saturday, and the Something Special Big Band, the 17-member orchestra that performs classics from the golden age of big-band music, appears at 8 p.m. at the Plainview-Old Bethpage Library on Old Country Road in Plainview (516) 938-0077.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TOMORROW -- The Borders Book Shop in Levittown greets the new century with a ''Health Awareness Week,'' courtesy of Shapeshifters, a Long Island-based health and fitness outfit. It starts with a session devoted to the ''Power of Movement and Eating Smart'' at 7 p.m., and then continues daily except Wednesday, through next Sunday, with sessions on such subjects as ''Spiritual Health and Healing Practices,'' Tuesday; ''Healing Herbs for the Cold Season,'' Thursday; both 7 p.m., and even a luncheon at noon on Friday, via Dr. B Well's Health Food Store (reservations: 631-579-2474). The shop in on Hempstead Turnpike (516) 579-6880.</p>
        <p>BARBARA DELATINER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
