<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Love Of a Priest</title>
    <meta content="02PERS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000109T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN PERSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alaya, Flavia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Henry J (Rev)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Under the Rose (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1D61738F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Love Of a Priest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA SUHAY</byline>
      <dateline>PATERSON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Flavia Alaya, author of book Under the Rose which describes 23-year affair with prominent New York City Roman Catholic priest, Rev Henry J Browne, who died in 1980; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FLAVIA ALAYA is a staunch feminist and a dyed-in-the-Italian-wool heretic whose 20-year relationship with a Roman Catholic priest has been laid bare in her newly published confessional memoir.</p>
        <p>The 64-year-old Ms. Alaya, a history professor at Ramapo College here, began the writing of ''Under the Rose,'' published by the Feminist Press in October, shortly after the 1980 death of the priest, the Rev. Henry Browne, as a journey through grief and self-discovery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FLAVIA ALAYA is a staunch feminist and a dyed-in-the-Italian-wool heretic whose 20-year relationship with a Roman Catholic priest has been laid bare in her newly published confessional memoir.</p>
        <p>The 64-year-old Ms. Alaya, a history professor at Ramapo College here, began the writing of ''Under the Rose,'' published by the Feminist Press in October, shortly after the 1980 death of the priest, the Rev. Henry Browne, as a journey through grief and self-discovery.</p>
        <p>With its release, she finds herself damned by the faint praise of a culture that is besieged by confessional books. Fifteen years ago, when the Rev. Andrew M. Greeley, a Roman Catholic Priest in Chicago, began writing about lust, love and the shattering of priestly vows, there was great consternation. But as the century draws to a close, it is more of a sigh of indifference.</p>
        <p>''You'd be surprised how many priests do have relationships with women or homosexuals,'' Ms. Alaya said in an interview at her home here. ''Celibacy among Roman Catholic priests is really a fiction.''</p>
        <p>As for her own life's drama, Ms. Alaya says she met Father Browne, 16 years her senior, while both were on Fulbright scholarships in Perugia, Italy, in the 1950's. Twenty-two-years-old at the time and one of three children born in New Rochelle, N.Y., to Italian immigrants, she says she chose to cast off the family that ''smothered her with their love'' and embarked on a 23-year love affair with the priest, who grew up in New York City's Hell's Kitchen.</p>
        <p>''There are still some people who think Henry and I were bad people, that what we did was terrible,'' she said. ''I think it's a good thing that people at the turn of this century can take this more in stride.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Alaya added, ''I have the profoundest respect for people who are Catholic and use their religion in a positive way, even though I have a somewhat more workmanlike approach.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Ms. Alaya, who has written biographies of Paterson's notable figures and has delved into its historic places, views religion as more of an ethnic echo in her life than a system of beliefs.</p>
        <p>''I am Catholic in the same way that I am American,'' she said. ''I don't believe in the way the state behaves, yet I am a citizen here. My Catholicism is an accident of history, not an act of faith. I can't shed it like a dress. Still, I have always said that love is never a scandal. If there is something that makes love impossible, then it must be re-examined.''</p>
        <p>For its part, the Diocese of Paterson, which oversees churches in Passaic, Morris and Sussex Counties, while in disagreement with the generalizations made about priests and the church, is unmoved by the book. Joseph Zwilling, a spokesman for the Archdiocese of New York, declined to comment about Father Browne or the book.</p>
        <p>''Men entering the seminary know that celibacy and chastity are part of the commitment,'' said Marianna Thompson, a spokeswoman for the diocese. ''They make that choice going in and if they change their minds can petition to leave the priesthood and be married. The message of the Church is goodness, hope and redemption. I think what will interest some people about this book is that it is about dysfunction. But it is not a dysfunction that affects the vast majority, who practice complete fidelity to their calling.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Ms. Alaya notes that the book was more an instrument taken up to purge the experience and ''to write myself into existence as feminists say so often,'' rather than to affect changes in doctrine.</p>
        <p>Ms. Alaya's tell-almost-all memoir was written after Father Browne died of leukemia in 1980. Subjects only lightly touched upon in the stream-of-consciousness tale of passion and pain are the death of Father Browne and her current relationship with Sandy Feddema.</p>
        <p>Though never legally or religiously married to either Father Browne or Mr. Feddema, Ms. Alaya refers to them as her husbands and the relationships as marriages. She refers to her daughter Nina's current partnership as a marriage though she, too, was not officially wed.</p>
        <p>''I think it was a true validation of my life and relationship with Henry that my daughter does not need any official governing body or church to validate her as a wife or someday a mother,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Feddema, 52, runs a wholesale ravioli business here and is often aided in the kitchen by his Italian-American partner.</p>
        <p>Conversing with the professor, it is hard to find the passionate young woman in the book. The only outward trace may be in the throaty tones in which Ms. Alaya speaks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Feddema, for his part, is uneasy about discussing the book.</p>
        <p>''It's, you know, difficult,'' Mr. Feddema said. ''I'm not jealous of him. But he knew a different Flavia than I know. I feel like I know Henry now and in a way I know that passionate Flavia.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''I admit I envied Henry in some ways, but she was enriched by their time and so in a way he did me a favor.''</p>
        <p>What Mr. Feddema would like is for Ms. Alaya to be released from the grip of the past that has taken hold of her since the book was published. It seems that all the interviews and attention have Ms. Alaya flying in a holding pattern over her past, and Mr. Feddema would like her to come in for a landing sometime soon.</p>
        <p>''I'm loaning her to him for a while, but I'll have her back,'' he said. ''This is my time now.''</p>
        <p>Harry Browne, the first child of Ms. Alaya and Mr, Browne, an editor for the Irish Times in Dublin, said in a telephone interview: ''The book as published is fascinating for me. I learned a lot about their situation that I had been unaware of growing up.''</p>
        <p>Though Ms. Alaya says she has purged herself of the past, she is often overcome with emotion when discussing her book.</p>
        <p>The interview pauses and restarts at various intervals as Ms. Alaya recomposes herself.</p>
        <p>Questions were often met with the plea: ''Just find that part in the book. It was hard enough to write without having to relive it in interviews.''</p>
        <p>The book tells the reader that it all began in Perugia, a place where the young woman fell hopefully in love with a priest. Though she says the couple began the affair in Italy and continued it on New York's Upper West Side, where Father Browne was pastor of St. Gregory's Church, it was to the anonymity of New Jersey that Ms. Alaya fled after she became pregnant with their first child, Harry Jr., in 1963.</p>
        <p>Two more children would follow, Christopher and Nina. Through it all, Ms. Alaya endured the years of separation, raising their children essentially as a single mother in Ridgefield.</p>
        <p>She kept the identity of the father of her children a secret from her family and friends, but not from the children themselves. They were simply told that the man who visited on Sunday afternoons -- without a cleric's clothing -- was their father and that his work as a teacher kept him away from home.</p>
        <p>In one interview, Ms. Alaya recalled: ''Ridgefield was a perfect place to be because there were a lot of people with broken marriages and bad circumstances that kept each to their own. Everyone just assumed I was married or divorced. As far as the children were concerned, the subject of where their father was and what he did was addressed by telling them he was a teacher, away at work.''</p>
        <p>It was not until 1970 that Mr. Browne left active duty as a priest and moved into a home in Paterson with Ms. Alaya and children -- the same Victorian home with leaded glass windows and wrap-around porch  that Ms. Alaya and Mr. Feddema occupy today.</p>
        <p>''Before that, in the 1960's, we were in our most secretive phase,'' she said. ''Henry would be so busy with his work as an anti-war activist that he had to note us in his appointment book to remember to come home twice a week to be with us. He used to draw this little house, like the ones they use in Monopoly, on the dates because he never dared write our names. If he ever left the book lying around or lost it, that would have been it for him.''</p>
        <p>The change was not brought about by the church, but by Ms. Alaya's illnesses -- ulcers and fainting spells -- circumstances she says were attributable to the strain of single parenting and being separated from her lover.</p>
        <p>Finally she gave him an ultimatum: he had to choose between the relationship or his parish and social causes.</p>
        <p>''I told him he could still have access to the children,'' she said, ''but not to my bed.''</p>
        <p>His decision to leave his parish and move to New Jersey nearly ended their relationship. When the secrecy and intrigue left, it took the passion and romance with them.</p>
        <p>''Writing that part of the book was the hardest for me, that and his death,'' she said. ''It was hard for him to shrink into a husband, into a lesser role than he'd been in, while I was growing and coming into my own. I was by then a feminist and I began to resent all that I had sacrificed.''</p>
        <p>The anger -- stored up from what she called ''the ordeal'' -- exploded in rage. ''It was over, but still I raged at him for what I had been through,'' she recalled. ''Suddenly the kids, a house and a job replaced something that had been transcendent.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Browne, who never left the priesthood, became ill with luekemia in 1978, and died in 1980. And in 1982, in recognition of Father Browne's efforts on behalf of the poor and his social activism during the Vietnam War era, New York City renamed a block of West 90th Street -- between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenues -- Henry J. Browne Boulevard.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Alaya, the completion of ''Under the Rose'' was her way of writing away Father Browne's ghost.</p>
        <p>As for her son, Harry, he spoke for the three children when he said, ''While it has affected our relationship with my father's family, we remain fiercely loyal to Flavia, first and foremost.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Alaya said, ''Henry's family, I don't think will ever understand it. Like some others, they still think of our relationship as something nasty I suppose. I can't get into their heads. Still, I think I've gained more than I've lost in writing the book. It varies. I suppose time will tell.''</p>
        <p>IN PERSON  Correction:  January 9, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about Flavia Alaya, who has written a book about her 20-year relationship with a Roman Catholic priest, the Rev. Henry J. Browne, misstated her current marital status. She is in fact married -- to Sandy Feddema, a businessman in Paterson.</p>
        <p>The article also misidentified Dr. Alaya's subject area, and the location of Ramapo College. She is a professor of literature and cultural studies, not history, and Ramapo is in Mahwah, not Paterson.</p>
        <p>In addition, the article misstated her parents' origins and size of her family. Only one parent, her father, was an immigrant, from Italy; her mother was American-born. Dr.  Alaya was one of four children, not three. The article also misstated the name and birthplace of Dr. Alaya's  first child; he is Harry, not Harry Jr., and she returned to Italy for his birth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 9, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about Flavia Alaya, who has written a book about her 20-year relationship with a Roman Catholic priest, the Rev. Henry J. Browne, misstated her current marital status. She is in fact married -- to Sandy Feddema, a businessman in Paterson.</p>
        <p>The article also misidentified Dr. Alaya's subject area, and the location of Ramapo College. She is a professor of literature and cultural studies, not history, and Ramapo is in Mahwah, not Paterson.</p>
        <p>In addition, the article misstated her parents' origins and size of her family. Only one parent, her father, was an immigrant, from Italy; her mother was American-born. Dr.  Alaya was one of four children, not three. The article also misstated the name and birthplace of Dr. Alaya's  first child; he is Harry, not Harry Jr., and she returned to Italy for his birth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
