<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nominees May Be Chosen Quickly in Rare Competitive Primary Season</title>
    <meta content="Y02CAM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000105T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED91038F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nominees May Be Chosen Quickly in Rare Competitive Primary Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Presidential primary season is the most competitive in 40 years, and it could also be the shortest because several states have moved up their primaries in order to exercise greater sway; map with primary and caucus schedules; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only 22 days until the first votes are cast in Iowa, the chairmen of the Republican and Democratic parties say they are bracing for a presidential primary season that is so competitive -- and unexpectedly so -- that they have to reach back 40 years to come up with a comparison.</p>
        <p>Yet the entire exercise may be over soon after the public begins to pay attention. This will be the speediest -- critics say hastiest -- dash to the nomination ever because several states, seeking greater political sway, elbowed their way in by moving up the dates of their contests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Only 22 days until the first votes are cast in Iowa, the chairmen of the Republican and Democratic parties say they are bracing for a presidential primary season that is so competitive -- and unexpectedly so -- that they have to reach back 40 years to come up with a comparison.</p>
        <p>Yet the entire exercise may be over soon after the public begins to pay attention. This will be the speediest -- critics say hastiest -- dash to the nomination ever because several states, seeking greater political sway, elbowed their way in by moving up the dates of their contests.</p>
        <p>The rejiggered calendar means the races will go off like a string of firecrackers, beginning with the caucuses in Iowa on Jan. 24 and the New Hampshire primary on Feb. 1, followed by primaries in the electoral giants of California, New York and several other states on March 7. After a six-week rush of voting -- less than half the National Football League's regular season schedule -- the nominees to be the leader of the free world may well be apparent.</p>
        <p>As recently as last summer, advisers to the two front-runners, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, expressed few qualms about the truncated schedule. They were so immersed in constructing what they viewed as organizational juggernauts that they did not seem particularly alert to threats from within their ranks. And they anticipated wrapping up their nominations quickly and tidily so they could turn to the general election. Instead they now have no choice but to strategize over how the outcome of one contest could affect the next one.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore are still the favorites; they may well face each other in November 2000. But now, in an unaccustomed position for the leading contenders, they are playing catch-up, at least in the high-profile  state of New Hampshire, where polls show that both contests are too close to call. Mr. Gore must contend with an unanticipated, and threatening, challenge from former Senator Bill Bradley of New Jersey, and Mr. Bush faces one from Senator John McCain of Arizona.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush are comfortably ahead in national surveys, their challengers hope that those campaigns become unglued in New Hampshire -- and never recover. Adding to their credibility, and political muscle, Mr. Bradley and Mr. McCain made striking gains in fund-raising near the end of 1999.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be an unbelievable six weeks,'' said Ed Rendell, general chairman of the Democratic National Committee. ''On our side, you might see ups and downs and twists and turns in an eight-day period. You will think one of the candidates has the upper hand and -- bingo! -- he loses the next week.''</p>
        <p>Recalling the presidential campaign of 1960, Mr. Rendell, who retires tomorrow as mayor of Philadelphia, said, ''You've got to go back to Kennedy and Johnson to find two co-equals who are really battling head to head. And I don't recall the last primary campaign when we've had two candidates who are so well known and so well funded.'' But the truth is, Lyndon B. Johnson was never viewed as much a threat to John F. Kennedy as Mr. Bradley is now to Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Jim Nicholson, chairman of the Republican National Committee, also said this year's campaign reminded him of the high stakes on both sides in 1960. Even so, Richard M. Nixon never came close to losing the nomination to Nelson A. Rockefeller or other rivals, who were not considered as potent as Mr. McCain is this year. ''If you want to include both parties in the calculus, this might be the most competitive situation since 1960,'' he said. ''There's a lot at stake and it's just going to get more intense.''</p>
        <p>Asked to handicap the Republican race, Mr. Nicholson, in unusually candid comments for a party chairman, all but brushed off four contenders. ''Bush is clearly the front-runner in terms of money,'' he said. ''But Senator McCain is a great candidate who has shown real skill at retail campaigning in New Hampshire and is a very authentic American hero. So anything can happen in this thing.'' Mr. Nicholson hastened to add that the potential of Steve Forbes, with millions from his family fortune at his disposal, should not be disregarded.</p>
        <p>After a prelude to 2000 that was hardly sedate -- candidates piled up millions of dollars in donations and traded jabs throughout the year -- the contenders are about to enter the most frenzied, and possibly ferocious, stretch thus far. This week, candidates will practically move to Iowa and New Hampshire. They have accelerated their deluge of 30-second television commercials.</p>
        <p>And the schedule of successive debates might hearten even advocates of good-government: Democrats will face off in New Hampshire on Wednesday; followed by Republicans on Thursday; Republicans in South Carolina on Friday, and Democrats in Iowa on Saturday. That accounts for just this week.</p>
        <p>''They stick their signs everywhere,'' said Ted Bailey, describing how politicking -- and cold weather -- have overtaken Chichester, N.H., where he is a selectman. ''But they're going to find it hard sticking signs in now because the ground's frozen.''</p>
        <p>The major contenders are also keeping an eye just off center stage, where a drama is unfolding over who will carry the mantle of Ross Perot and the Reform Party he founded. While Patrick J. Buchanan, the conservative commentator, and Donald J. Trump, the real estate tycoon, are campaigning most aggressively and organizing in several states, other possible contenders include Gov. Jesse Ventura of Minnesota. And few are counting out a surprise re-emergence of Mr. Perot himself.</p>
        <p>The significance of the 2000 campaign reaches far beyond the White House. It is no exaggeration to say that all three branches of government are at stake. Democrats need a net gain of only six seats to retake control of the House. It is far less likely that Republicans will lose the Senate, although Democrats could pick up seats. And because of expected retirements, the next president may well fill between three and five vacancies on the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>And the election of state legislators in November is critically important. Nearly two dozen legislative chambers are so evenly divided that either party could win control of them. But those legislators, along with the governors, will use results of the 2000 census to redraw boundaries of districts of Congressional candidates in 2002 and the four subsequent elections. The process could affect who controls the House of Representatives for years.</p>
        <p>Still, with the exception, perhaps, of the expected high-octane match between Hillary Rodham Clinton and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani for a Senate seat from New York, the presidential competition is certain to command the most interest.</p>
        <p>''Probably in March of last year I thought, 'I bet I don't get very worked up about this,' '' said Tom Brokaw, anchor of the NBC Nightly News, who expects that his program will soon begin broadcasting campaign stories every day. ''But people are slowly awakening that there's a real race going on here. McCain and Bradley have opened the door to a lot of public interest.''</p>
        <p>In fact, one explanation for the allure of the McCain and Bradley insurgencies is that some journalists, as well as ordinary voters, seem charmed by them personally -- and have a hankering for some drama.</p>
        <p>Despite the ferment in New Hampshire, history is on the side of Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush. Mr. Gore's advisers reel off their institutional advantages -- from the power of the White House, to committed delegates to endorsements from labor groups to important elected officials -- that have dragged their predecessors across the finish line.</p>
        <p>Karl Rove, the mastermind of the Bush operation, recites the history like a mantra. ''No Republican candidate who has led by double digits in August of the Gallup Poll the year before the election has failed to win the nomination,'' he explained. ''If history is the guide, Bush stands a very good chance of being the Republican nominee for president.''</p>
        <p>But this is no ordinary presidential year. No one knows how the short-circuited season will alter the dynamic and, ultimately, affect who comes out on top.</p>
        <p>Most strategists on both sides agree that Mr. Bradley has a better chance of toppling Mr. Gore than Mr. McCain does of snatching the nomination from Mr. Bush, because the Democrats are evenly matched financially. In addition, while Mr. McCain is concentrating his resources in New Hampshire, Mr. Bradley has assembled a national organization.</p>
        <p>This much seems clear: the New Hampshire primary is a make-or-break battle for Mr. McCain and Mr. Bradley. That is where they have made the most impressive showings. And they are each counting on wins there to energize their candidacies -- and to demonstrate that Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush are not invincible.</p>
        <p>''If McCain wins there I'm not sure he's very well poised to convert that into a national campaign,'' said William G. Mayer, a political scientist at Northeastern University in Boston. ''Bradley's better positioned to do that. He's managed to stay pretty even with Gore in fund-raising.''</p>
        <p>Because of the high expectations in the Granite State, Mr. Bradley and Mr. McCain no longer have the luxury of sneaking up on the front-runner -- as Gary Hart did against Walter F. Mondale in 1984.</p>
        <p>After their charmed campaigns in 1999, Mr. Bradley and Mr. McCain are certain to face tougher scrutiny in coming weeks from their opponents and from the news media. And a loss in New Hampshire could be devastating to either politician, not only because of expectations but because their opponents have established ''firewalls'' with potent organizations in several of the subsequent primary states.</p>
        <p>But the Bradley and McCain camps contend that if they win New Hampshire, the excitement and momentum after those triumphs would allow them to trump the institutional advantages of Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore. After New Hampshire, Republicans have showdowns in South Carolina on Feb. 19 and Arizona and Michigan on Feb. 22 before the multistate voting on March 7. But the Democrats will have a five-week breather between New Hampshire and the March 7 contests.</p>
        <p>Former Senator Warren B. Rudman of New Hampshire, who backs Mr. McCain, said his candidate and Mr. Bradley are poised to do well with independent voters in his state. And victories there, he said, could make them unstoppable.</p>
        <p>''I can't remember when you had it on both sides like this,'' Mr. Rudman said. ''Bradley and McCain are both going to take huge chunks of independent voters.'' Arguing that Mr. McCain has far more potential than prevailing in New Hampshire, he added, ''People are whistling through the cemetery if they think that's going to be the end of it.''</p>
        <p>The state of the race is far less settled than on the eve of the primaries four years ago, when President Clinton faced no opposition and Bob Dole towered over the field. Mr. Dole was bruised and battered more than he expected, but still managed to crush his rivals.</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding the emergence of Mr. McCain, the most striking aspect of the 2000 campaign has been Mr. Bush's success. Though he was twice elected governor of Texas, Mr. Bush had no national political seasoning and popped up virtually out of nowhere to amass a staggering, record-breaking war chest of more than $67 million. He captured the early support of far more Republican members of Congress, governors and conservative leaders than Mr. Dole did at this point in the 1996 race.</p>
        <p>And his political might forced half the Republican field out of the race, including former Vice President Dan Quayle, Elizabeth Dole, Representative John R. Kasich of Ohio and former Gov. Lamar Alexander of Tennessee. The only others left standing are Mr. McCain, Mr. Forbes, Senator Orrin G. Hatch of Utah, Alan Keyes, a former State Department official, and Gary Bauer, the former head of the Family Research Council.</p>
        <p>The outpouring for the Texas governor has offended some Republicans who think it appears that he is being crowned. Craig Grimes, a foreman for a power company in Youngstown, Ohio, who responded to a New York Times/CBS News Poll, said he was taken aback by how Rush Limbaugh and Republican luminaries defend Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''It's like a football game and they're all running ahead and clearing the way, running interference and blocking for Bush,'' said Mr. Grimes. ''They've poured the money into him. And it scares me because he's going to owe big time whoever it is who is pushing him.''</p>
        <p>The challenge, now, for Mr. Bush is to meet the high expectations he helped create by actually winning some elections. He also needs to overcome an image from debates that he is not as versed in the issues or as nimble on his feet as some Republicans had hoped. And while Republicans enjoy a tradition of nominating their front-runner, Mr. Bush has less national campaign experience than any Republican nominee since Dwight D. Eisenhower, who was elected president in 1952.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore had a far rockier year than Mr. Bush. That was especially apparent because he was confronted only by one rival and had expected to glide to the nomination unimpeded. Instead, Mr. Bradley showed such political potency last year that he forced the vice president to practically reinvent his campaign and shed many trappings of incumbency.</p>
        <p>''Had Gore not altered the terrain in September, he'd be gone by now,'' said Senator Joseph R. Biden, a Delaware Democrat who has not endorsed either candidate. ''He was on such a slide through the summer. But he's righted the ship.''</p>
        <p>The two Democrats seem to agree on the leading issues -- health care, education, Social Security and campaign finance reform -- but they have argued vehemently over the details. The Republicans, by contrast, have been wrangling over a different set of issues, namely tax cuts, foreign policy and social issues like abortion.</p>
        <p>Yet perhaps because no one burning issue has seemed to have grabbed the electorate, the candidates are devoting much time to talking about themselves as human beings, from their upbringings to their decisions to enter politics. They are also trying, perhaps, to set themselves on a higher moral plane than Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''I can't name issues that excite the public so we have to create issues, like health care,'' said Gerald H. Gamm, chairman of the political science department at the University of Rochester. ''When the economy is in the midst of its most robust economic expansion in most of our lifetimes, when the nation, economically, is on top of the world, voters aren't paying attention to issues. So what is new now is that candidates are being aggressive in marketing their private lives.''</p>
        <p>But the biggest concern of the party chairmen is not the choice of issues, but the amount of time candidates will have to discuss them.</p>
        <p>''This is a crazy way to determine the nominees of the parties because there's really no time for almost anyone to have a cogent debate,'' said Mr. Rendell, the Democratic chairman. ''It just lends itself to those god-awful 30-second ads.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 5, 2000, Wednesday  A chart on Sunday listing events in the presidential primary season misstated the timetable for Democrats in Delaware and Washington State to select delegates to the party's national convention. While Delaware has a nonbinding primary on Feb. 5, it will select delegates in caucuses on March 27. And while Washington has a nonbinding primary on Feb. 29, it will select delegates in caucuses on March 7.</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 12, 2000, Wednesday  A chart on Jan. 2 listing events in the presidential primary season misstated the location of Democratic and Republican debates to be held on Jan. 26. It is New Hampshire, not Iowa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 5, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A chart on Sunday listing events in the presidential primary season misstated the timetable for Democrats in Delaware and Washington State to select delegates to the party's national convention. While Delaware has a nonbinding primary on Feb. 5, it will select delegates in caucuses on March 27. And while Washington has a nonbinding primary on Feb. 29, it will select delegates in caucuses on March 7.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: January 12, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A chart on Jan. 2 listing events in the presidential primary season misstated the location of Democratic and Republican debates to be held on Jan. 26. It is New Hampshire, not Iowa.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
