<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GOING OUT</title>
    <meta content="02TOWN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDB1538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GOING OUT</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; by fax to (212) 556-7219, or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>BURGDORFF CULTURAL CENTER The Bill Charlap Jazz Trio. Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $17.50; $15 for the elderly; $8 for students. 10 Durand Road, Maplewood. (973) 378-2133.</p>
        <p>COUNT BASIE THEATER The New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, featuring Philippe Entremont, conductor and pianist, in music of Beethoven, Haydn and Ravel. Saturday at 8:30 p.m. Tickets: $14 to $46. 99 Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (732) 842-9000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; by fax to (212) 556-7219, or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>BURGDORFF CULTURAL CENTER The Bill Charlap Jazz Trio. Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $17.50; $15 for the elderly; $8 for students. 10 Durand Road, Maplewood. (973) 378-2133.</p>
        <p>COUNT BASIE THEATER The New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, featuring Philippe Entremont, conductor and pianist, in music of Beethoven, Haydn and Ravel. Saturday at 8:30 p.m. Tickets: $14 to $46. 99 Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (732) 842-9000.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS The New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, featuring Philippe Entremont, conductor and pianist, in music of Beethoven, Haydn and Ravel. Thursday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $14 to $46. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>J.C.C. ON THE PALISADES ''In Love With Broadway,'' musical revue. Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $18; $15 for members. J.C.C. Thurnauer School of Music presents Duo Cavatina, featuring Carol Shansky, flutist, and Seth Himmelhoch, guitarist. Next Sunday at 3 p.m. Free. 411 East Clinton Avenue, Tenafly. (201) 569-7900.</p>
        <p>MONMOUTH COUNTY LIBRARY Carol Fredette and Trio, jazz. Next Sunday at 2 p.m. Free. Eastern Branch, 1001 Route 35, Shrewsbury. (732) 431-7242.</p>
        <p>MOSTLY MUSIC CHAMBER MUSIC SERIES Featuring Ruth Laredo, pianist, and Ani Kavafian and Philip Setzer, violinists, in a program of Brahms and Tchaikovsky. Next Sunday at 3 p.m. at Morrow Memorial Church, 600 Ridgewood Road, Maplewood. Next Sunday at 7:30 p.m. at Temple Emanu-el, 756 East Broad Street, Westfield. Tickets: $20; $18 for the elderly; $10 for students. (973) 762-8486.</p>
        <p>PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH OF CHATHAM TOWNSHIP Lyrica Chamber Music presents ''Dvorak in America.'' Today at 3 p.m. Tickets: $14 and $18. 240 Southern Boulevard, Chatham. (973) 701-1734.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY RICHARDSON AUDITORIUM The New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, featuring Philippe Entremont, conductor and pianist, in music of Beethoven, Haydn and Ravel. Friday at 8:30 p.m. Tickets: $14 to $46. Dryden Ensemble presents an all-Bach program. Next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $20; $18 for students. Alexander Hall, Princeton. (609) 258-5000.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY TAPLIN AUDITORIUM The University Gospel Ensemble. Next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $5. Fine Hall, Washington Road, Princeton. (609) 258-5000.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER The New Jersey Symphony Orchestra, featuring Philippe Entremont, conductor and pianist, in music of Beethoven, Haydn and Ravel. Next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $14 to $46. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>STOCKTON PERFORMING ARTS CENTER ''Two Contrary Russians: Rachmaninoff and Prokofieff,'' featuring Jeffrey Siegel, pianist. Next Sunday at 4 p.m. Tickets: $18 and $24. Jim Leeds Road, Pomona. (609) 652-9000.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>BANANAS COMEDY CLUB Paul Bond, Chris Rich and Jason Maxwell. Friday at 9:30 p.m.; Saturday at 8 and 10:30 p.m. Tickets: $12; $10 on Friday. Holiday Inn, 283 Route 17 South, Hasbrouck Heights. (201) 727-1090.</p>
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY PLAYERS ''Arsenic and Old Lace.'' Through Jan. 29. Friday and Saturday at 8:30 p.m.; next Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $12; $10 on Sunday. The Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-4200.</p>
        <p>GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE ''Syncopation,'' by Allan Knee. Through Feb. 6. Previews: Saturday at 8 p.m.; next Sunday at 7 p.m. Tickets: $32 on Saturday; $24 on Sunday. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7717.</p>
        <p>HELEN HAYES PERFORMING ARTS CENTER ''A Christmas Carol.'' Today at 2 and 7 p.m. Tickets: $25 to $35. 117 Main Street, Nyack, N.Y. (914) 358-6333.</p>
        <p>MURDER TO GO THEATER ''Killing Mr. Withers.'' Ongoing. Fridays and Saturdays at 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $45 on Fridays; $48 on Saturdays, includes four-course dinner. Il Giardino, Cedar Knolls. (973) 301-0562.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY PERFORMING ARTS CENTER Stuttgart Ballet. Saturday at 8 p.m.; next Sunday at 3 p.m. Tickets: $12 to $56. 1 Center Street, Newark. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY REPERTORY COMPANY ''The Play's the Thing,'' by Ferenc Molnar. Through Jan. 23. Thursday through Saturday at 8 p.m.; next Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $25. Lumia Theater, 179 Broadway, Long Branch. (732) 229-3166.</p>
        <p>PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE ''Noises Off,'' by Michael Frayn. Through Feb. 13. Wednesday and Friday at 8 p.m.; Thursday at 2 and 8 p.m.; Saturday at 2:30 and 8 p.m.; next Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m. Tickets: $36 to $60. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (973) 376-4343.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>ABC GALLERY ''Heart and Soul,'' dolls by Brook Lachelle Beatty and paintings by Cory S. Dale. Through Jan. 15. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 1 to 9 p.m.; Fridays, 1 to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Lambertville Public Library, 6 Lilly Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0275.</p>
        <p>ARTISTS' GALLERY ''Small Works Show.'' Through Jan. 22. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. 32 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-4588.</p>
        <p>BROOKDALE COMMUNITY COLLEGE ''Keyhole Series,'' mixed-media works by Grace Graupe-Pillard. Through Saturday. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; other times by appointment. 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (732) 224-2520.</p>
        <p>CHAMOT GALLERY ''Rough and Ready,'' sculpture by William Rodwell and Steven Singer. Through Jan. 31. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 610-1468.</p>
        <p>CITY WITHOUT WALLS 18th annual Metro Show, featuring small works. Through Friday. Hours: Tuesday through Friday, noon to 6 p.m. 1 Gateway Center, Newark. (973) 622-1188.</p>
        <p>COOPER GALLERY ''Art of This Century,'' including paintings by Stephan Shedrowitz, Teri Richardson and Seren Morey. Through Jan. 29. Reception: Friday, 7 to 10 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 7 p.m. 295 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-1074.</p>
        <p>FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON UNIVERSITY ''Wall Works,'' sculptures by Walt Swales. Through Jan. 28. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 2 p.m. Edward Williams Gallery, 150 Kotte Place, Hackensack. (201) 692-2449.</p>
        <p>GROUNDS FOR SCULPTURE Fall exhibition, including a one-woman show by Beverly Pepper. Through April. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Tuesdays through Thursdays by appointment. 18 Fairgrounds Road, Hamilton Township. (609) 586-0616.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS ''Natural Images in Black and White,'' photography by Norman Adams and Jay Goodkind. Through Jan. 23. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>HUNTERDON MUSEUM OF ART ''Mud Like a Blessing: Elemental Clay Sculpture,'' featuring works by five artists. Through next Sunday. ''The Knitted 'Knest,' '' an interactive installation. Through next Sunday. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415.</p>
        <p>J.C.C. ON THE PALISADES ''Israel and Spain,'' photographs by Al Stewart. Through Jan. 25. Reception: next Sunday, 1 to 3 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 9 a.m to 10 p.m.; Fridays and Sundays, 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. 411 East Clinton Avenue, Tenafly. (201) 569-7900, extension 433.</p>
        <p>JERSEY CITY MUSEUM ''In This House, Trujillo is Chief,'' paintings by Freddy Rodriguez. Through March. 18. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10:30 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Wednesdays to 8 p.m. 472 Jersey Avenue, Jersey City. (201) 547-4514.</p>
        <p>JOHNSON &amp; JOHNSON HEADQUARTERS GALLERY Paintings by Ivan Valencia. Through Jan. 21. By appointment. 1 Johnson and Johnson Plaza, New Brunswick. (732) 524-3698.</p>
        <p>LIBERTY SCIENCE CENTER ''Earth, Wind, Fire and Water,'' photography by members of the New Jersey Photography Forum. Through March 31. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 9:30 to 5:30 p.m. Environment Level, Liberty State Park, 251 Phillip Street, Jersey City. (908) 790-8820</p>
        <p>MACCULLOCH HALL HISTORICAL MUSEUM ''Focusing on New Jersey's Heritage,'' photography. Through next Sunday. ''Prize Pottery: One Hundred Years of Children's China.'' Through May 14. Admission: $3; $2 for students and the elderly. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. 45 Macculloch Avenue, Morristown. (973) 538-2404.</p>
        <p>MONMOUTH COUNTY HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION ''Angels in the Household: Childhood Life in Monmouth County, 1700-1920.'' Through June 30. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Admission: $2; $1.50 for the elderly; $1 for those ages 6 to 18; free for children under 6. 70 Court Street, Freehold. (732) 462-1466.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM ''Paris 1900: The 'American School,' '' a re-creation of the American display at the Universal Exposition in Paris in 1900. Through Jan. 16. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays and Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Thursdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $10; $5 for members; $8 for the elderly and students; free for children under 12; free for everyone on Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 2 p.m. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (973) 746-5555.</p>
        <p>MORRIS COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY ''Keepers of Time: Clocks and Watches in the 19th- and 20th-Century America.'' Through January 31. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Admission: $4; $2 for students. Acorn Hall, 68 Morris Avenue, Morristown. (973) 267-3465.</p>
        <p>MORRIS MUSEUM ''The Collected Century, 1900 to 2000.'' Through March 26. ''The Amazing Maze,'' a walk-through labyrinth. Through Feb. 13. Hours: Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays to 8 p.m. Admission: $5; $3 for the elderly and for children under age 3. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (973) 538-0454.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE AMERICAN HUNGARIAN FOUNDATION ''The Hungarian Spark in America.'' Through Jan. 31. Donation: $3. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. 300 Somerset Street, New Brunswick. (732) 846-5777.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS ''Three Artists: Three Stories,'' featuring works by Nancy Cohen, Kay Walkingstick and Bisa Washington. Through Jan. 12. Reverse paintings on glass by Agnieszka Solawa. Through Jan. 21. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, noon to 4 p.m. and Thursdays, 7 to 9 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 2 to 4 p.m. Palmer Gallery, 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY ''New Jersey Snapshots,'' historic photographs, documents and objects. Through February. ''History's Mysteries,'' interactive exhibition. Through June. ''Dining In, Dining Out,'' featuring photographs, video clips and more. Through August. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. 52 Park Place, Newark. (973) 596-5400.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM ''The Modernists.'' Through Jan. 23. ''The Regionalists and Precisionists.'' Through Jan. 30. ''Sunstruck.'' Through March 12. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 4:45 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Free. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6464.</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM ''Vitali and DiNardo: A Collaboration in Silver and Glass.'' Through next Sunday. ''From the Sacred Realm: Treasures of Tibetan Art.'' Through Jan. 20. ''Tibetan Buddhist Costumes and Ceremonial Textiles.'' Through Jan. 20. ''The Pulling of the Threads by Thelma Mathias.'' Through June 27. ''Needless Necessity: Jewelry, Silver and Personal Meaning.'' Through June. ''Africa: The Arts of Power,'' featuring a Ghanian eagle coffin. Through 1999. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.; Thursdays (after hours) until 8:30 p.m. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (973) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>NOYES MUSEUM OF ART ''Birds and Men,'' sculptures by Brian Meunier. Through next Sunday. ''Talk Back: The Community Responds to the Collection.'' Through May 14. Folk art from the collection. Continuing. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Admission: $3; $2 for the elderly and students. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848.</p>
        <p>OLD CHURCH CULTURAL CENTER ''Portfolio Alumni Exhibition.'' Through Jan. 21. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. 561 Piermont Road, Demarest. (201) 767-7160.</p>
        <p>PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE ''Recent Paintings 1994-1999,'' by Craig Manister. Through Jan. 20. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. Broadway Gallery, Broadway and Memorial Drive, Paterson. (973) 684-5448.</p>
        <p>PATERSON MUSEUM ''The Great Atlantic and Pacific Tea Company: 140 Years of Service to America, 1859 to 1999,'' multimedia exibition. Through Feb. 27. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 12:30 to 4:30 p.m. 2 Market Street, Paterson. (973) 881-3874.</p>
        <p>SETON HALL UNIVERSITY ''Remembering the Lenape: New Jersey's First People.'' Through Friday. Hours: Tomorrow through Friday, 10:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Walsh Library Gallery, 400 South Orange Avenue, South Orange. (973) 275-2033.</p>
        <p>WILLIAMS GALLERY ''Going Global: Contemporary Fine Art From Around the World.'' Through Jan. 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m.; other times by appointment. 8 Chambers Street, Princeton. (609) 921-1142.</p>
        <p>YOGI BERRA MUSEUM Artifacts from the life of the baseball player and exhibits on the history of the Yankees, baseball in New Jersey, Negro Leagues, evolution of equipment, and baseball during World War II. Ongoing. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Tickets: $4; $2 for children. Montclair State University, 8 Quarry Road, Little Falls. (973) 655-2377.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>LIBERTY SCIENCE CENTER ''The Robot Zoo.'' Through Jan. 9. Hours: daily, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Liberty State Park, 251 Phillip Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-0006.</p>
        <p>MONMOUTH MUSEUM ''Holidays With Mother Goose,'' featuring a garden with over-sized fairytale characters. Through Jan. 9. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $4. 761 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (732) 747-2266.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY PERFORMING ARTS CENTER The Hudson Vagabond Players presents ''Los Tres Reyes: The Three Kings.'' Saturday at 2 p.m.; next Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $18; $9 for children. 1 Center Street, Newark. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>PECK SCHOOL The Philharmonic of New Jersey presents ''Improvise!'' as part of its ''Music for Kids'' series. Next Sunday at 4 p.m. Tickets: $10. 247 South Street, Morristown. (908) 226-7300.</p>
        <p>STUDIO PLAYHOUSE Magic Trunk Childrens Theater presents ''Pinocchio.'' Through Jan. 16. Saturday and next Sunday at 1:30 and 3:30 p.m. Tickets: $6. 14 Alvin Place, Montclair. (973) 744-9752.</p>
        <p>UNION COUNTY ARTS CENTER ''The Hundred and One Dalmatians.'' Next Sunday at 1 and 4 p.m. Tickets: $9. 1601 Irving Street, Rahway. (732) 499-8226.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Peter Chelnik and Jack Wiler, poets. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Route 46 West, West Paterson. (973) 812-0180.</p>
        <p>ETC.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Laser Nutcracker. Today, Saturday and next Sunday at noon, 1 and 3 p.m. Tickets: $6. Planetarium, 205 West State Street, Trenton.(609) 777-9444.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE PARK SERVICE ''New Year's Hike.'' Today at 11 a.m. Cheesequack State Park. Information: (732) 566-3208.  el3  TRAILSIDE NATURE AND SCIENCE CENTER ''The Reason for the Season,'' planetarium show. Today at 3:30 p.m. ''Calendar.'' Next Sunday at 2 and 3:30 p.m. For ages 6 and up. Tickets: $3; $2.55 for the elderly. 452 New Providence Road, Mountainside. (908) 789-3670.</p>
        <p>AT THE CASINOS</p>
        <p>All tickets are available through Ticketmaster, (800) 736-1420.</p>
        <p>BALLY'S PARK PLACE ''Legends in Concert,'' impersonations of Stevie Wonder, Little Richard, Elvis Presley, Linda Ronstadt and Michael Jackson. Mondays through Thursdays at 3:30 and 7:30 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 and 10:30 p.m.; Sundays at 7:30 and 10 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $25. Park Cabaret, Boardwalk and Park Place. (800) 225-5977.</p>
        <p>CAESARS ATLANTIC CITY Alabina, Gypsy rumba band. Tonight at 8. Tickets: $45 to $65. Circus Maximus Theater, 2100 Pacific Avenue. (800) 677-7469.</p>
        <p>CLARIDGE HOTEL War. Tonight at 7. Tickets: $40. Palace Theater, Boardwalk and Park Place. (609) 340-3700.</p>
        <p>RESORTS CASINO HOTEL The Spinners. Tonight at 7:30. Tickets: $25. 1133 Boardwalk. (888) 771-1786.</p>
        <p>SANDS HOTEL AND CASINO Isley Brothers. Tonight at 8. Tickets: $60. Copa Lounge, Indiana Avenue and Brighton Park. (609) 441-4137.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
