<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Small but Forceful Coalition Works to Counter U.S. War on Drugs</title>
    <meta content="02DRUG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Legalization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lindesmith Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Soros, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nadelmann, Ethan A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wren, Christopher S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E4DB1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1347" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Small but Forceful Coalition Works to Counter U.S. War on Drugs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wren, Christopher S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coalition of libertarians, liberals, humanitarians and hedonists pursues sophisticated crusade to end nation's criminal laws against marijuana and other psychoactive drugs; says war on drugs has packed nation's prisons, offered addicts little treatment and contributed to spread of AIDS; critics say coalition's agenda is actually the legalization of marijuana and other drugs; Ethan A Nadelmann, director of Lindesmith Center, a drug policy center set up in New York with money donated by billionare George Soros, says nation must learn to live with drugs so they cause the least possible harm and the best possible good; phhoto (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When voters in Maine went to the polls in November and endorsed the use of marijuana as a medicine, it was more than a victory for cancer patients and others who say marijuana will help relieve their pain.</p>
        <p>For a small coalition of libertarians, liberals, humanitarians and hedonists, the vote was another step forward in a low-profile but sophisticated crusade to end the nation's criminal laws against marijuana and other psychoactive drugs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When voters in Maine went to the polls in November and endorsed the use of marijuana as a medicine, it was more than a victory for cancer patients and others who say marijuana will help relieve their pain.</p>
        <p>For a small coalition of libertarians, liberals, humanitarians and hedonists, the vote was another step forward in a low-profile but sophisticated crusade to end the nation's criminal laws against marijuana and other psychoactive drugs.</p>
        <p>Using polls, focus groups and advertising, the coalition has selected and promoted causes that might arouse sympathy among Americans, like giving clean syringes to heroin users to prevent the spread of AIDS, or softening tough penalties for drug use. The most successful has been medicinal marijuana, which has been endorsed by the District of Columbia and seven states.</p>
        <p>What brought together the disparate elements of the coalition, however, is a far broader cause: changing the critical way that Americans think about drugs. Proponents say they want to end a war on drugs that has packed prisons, offered addicts little treatment and contributed to the spread of AIDS. Some want to go further and drop criminal penalties for personal drug use, or even make drugs legal.</p>
        <p>The term they have carefully chosen for their goal is ''harm reduction'': reducing the harm caused by those people who cannot or will not stop using drugs.</p>
        <p>''We accept drugs are here to stay,'' said Ethan A. Nadelmann, director of the Lindesmith Center, a drug policy center set up in New York with money donated by the billionaire George Soros. ''There never has been a drug-free society,'' Mr. Nadelmann said. ''We must learn how to live with drugs so they cause the least possible harm and the best possible good.''</p>
        <p>Critics say the agenda is more ominous: the legalization of marijuana and other drugs. At a Congressional hearing in June, the White House director of national drug policy, Gen. Barry R. McCaffrey, warned of ''a carefully camouflaged, well-funded, tightly knit core of people whose goal is to legalize drug use in the United States.''</p>
        <p>Sue Rusche, director of Families in Action, a coalition in Atlanta working to help parents prevent children from using drugs, accused Mr. Nadelmann and his supporters of systematically distorting the picture of what drugs do.</p>
        <p>''Yes, we're concerned about children, but we're concerned about everybody,'' said Ms. Rusche, who likened Mr. Nadelmann to the tobacco industry. ''He denies that drugs have the capacity to hurt people, and takes no responsibility for the consequences.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadelmann describes his position differently. ''Drugs are not bad,'' he said. ''Drugs are good, bad or indifferent, depending on how you use them.''</p>
        <p>The movement's supporters range beyond the Lindesmith Center and other efforts financed by Mr. Soros.  Supporters include marijuana-smokers represented by the National Organization for the Reform of Marijuana Laws, or Norml, libertarians who argue that personal drug use is nobody else's business, and old-fashioned liberals who castigate the government's campaign against drugs as worse than the problem.</p>
        <p>''The core is the people who to my mind get it, the people who connect the dots,'' Mr. Nadelmann said. ''We believe that the war on drugs is a fundamental evil in our society.''</p>
        <p>The crusade to make drugs socially respectable has no precedent in the United States, said Dr. David F. Musto, a medical historian at the Yale School of Medicine and the author of ''The American Disease: Origins of Narcotics Control'' (Oxford University Press).</p>
        <p>''You have these groups funded by wealthy individuals that are a constant critic of drug policy, and these groups use very sophisticated marketing techniques,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Surveys show that most Americans still oppose making illicit drugs legal. While voters have been tolerant of letting ill people smoke marijuana, a Gallup poll this year reported that 69 percent of respondents opposed making marijuana legal for everyone.</p>
        <p>Mark A. R. Kleiman, a professor of public policy at the University of California at Los Angeles, said, ''When you look at all these medical marijuana initiatives, they pass by big margins, but the governors and legislators go the other way.''</p>
        <p>Because constituents expect their politicians to be hard-nosed, Professor Kleiman said, ''a legislator who votes for medical marijuana could lose votes from people who voted for medical marijuana.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadelmann said he had commissioned a poll to learn whether voters would support personal cultivation of marijuana; 65 percent of those sampled thought that growing marijuana should remain a crime.</p>
        <p>A result of this research into public attitudes has been the deliberately vague idea of harm reduction. By casting the issue in friendlier terms that resonate across the political spectrum, crusaders like Mr. Nadelmann say, they hope to induce Americans to tolerate, if not embrace, the elimination of criminal penalties against marijuana -- and as a few see it, the eventual legalization of all psychoactive drugs.</p>
        <p>Critics call the medicinal marijuana issue a stalking-horse for drug legalization. ''My guess is the real agenda is to promulgate marijuana as a benign substance outside the boundaries of conventional medicine,'' General McCaffrey said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadelmann did not contradict him. ''Will it help lead toward marijuana legalization?'' he said. ''I hope so.'' But he said that reports of his support for harder drugs have quoted him out of context.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadelmann has advised the campaign putting medicinal marijuana on state ballots, which is spearheaded by a group calling itself Americans for Medical Rights, with no mention of marijuana. The campaign's director, Bill Zimmerman, explained, ''You pick the name with a view toward winning support for the organization.''</p>
        <p>Not all critics of government drug policy want to make illicit drugs legal. Some assert that prohibition has not stopped drug use. Others say that money would be better spent treating addicts who committed crimes rather than locking them up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadelmann wants to enlist such people in his cause of repealing all penalties for drug use. ''What we reformers do is to use these coalitions on one issue to educate our allies about the broader implications of the drug war,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Rob Stewart, a senior policy analyst for the Drug Policy Foundation, another group in Washington supported by Mr. Soros, said that lifting criminal penalties for marijuana use would be sufficient. Writing in the group's newsletter, he explained, ''decriminalization makes the point that adults should not be arrested for using marijuana as they would use a martini.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart described the Drug Policy Foundation as ''agnostic'' about other illicit drugs. But its founder, Arnold S. Trebach, told journalists in 1997 that everything from cocaine and heroin to steroids should be freely available.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadelmann objects to stigmatizing recreational drug use. ''People shall not be discriminated against based on the substances they consume,'' he said. ''The extension of the notion of equality is going to have to include drug users.''</p>
        <p>The American Civil Liberties Union also endorses the right to consume drugs. Ira Glasser, its director,  said this year, ''The A.C.L.U.'s position is basically that criminal prohibition is inappropriate in matters that involve a person's own behavior.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Glasser is also chairman of the Drug Policy Foundation. Holding both posts, he said, poses no conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nadelmann said that a fresh initiative on medicinal marijuana would be voted on next year in Colorado, where an earlier referendum was declared illegal, and in Nevada, where the proposal must be approved twice. Other states that have passed such initiatives, he said, would be encouraged to get involved in producing and distributing marijuana for medicinal purposes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
