<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Guide</title>
    <meta content="02GUID$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7DA1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Guide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Benefit for Library</p>
        <p>Frank McCourt, author of ''Angela's Ashes'' and '' 'Tis,'' will give a reading, followed by a reception, on Thursday at 7 p.m. for the benefit of the Mount Pleasant Library.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Benefit for Library</p>
        <p>Frank McCourt, author of ''Angela's Ashes'' and '' 'Tis,'' will give a reading, followed by a reception, on Thursday at 7 p.m. for the benefit of the Mount Pleasant Library.</p>
        <p>The event is to be held at the Greenburgh Multiplex Cinema, 320 Saw Mill River Road, Elmsford, where the film ''Angela's Ashes'' will be screened. Tickets are $50 and may be bought at the Mount Pleasant Library in Pleasantville and the library's branch in Valhalla, or by calling 769-0906.</p>
        <p>King's Vision Perpetuated</p>
        <p>''Implementation of the Dream Through Education'' is the theme of the 22nd banquet commemorating the vision of Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. It will take place next Saturday at 6 p.m. at the Westchester Marriott Hotel in Tarrytown, organized as it is every year by the Antioch Baptist Church of Bedford Hills. Tickets at $60 may be obtained by calling 241-0189. Proceeds will go toward scholarships and college programs.</p>
        <p>The keynote speaker will be Joe Clark, a former Army drill instructor who in the 1980's became principal of Eastside High School in Paterson, N.J. Within two years, after expelling 300 disruptive students, he transformed Eastside from a chaotic locus of drugs, vandalism, fights and pervasive academic failure into a model school.</p>
        <p>His success in the use of so-called tough love -- a combination of discipline and high expectations for students, was nationally recognized in news magazines and on television and in the Warner Brothers film ''Lean on Me,'' starring Morgan Freeman as Mr. Clark.</p>
        <p>Other events related to Dr. King include a memorial service on his birthday, Jan. 15, at 7:30 P.M. in the South Salem Presbyterian Church, 111 Spring Street. On Jan. 17 from 8 a.m. to noon, a memorial seminar will be held at Antioch Baptist Church, 86 Main Street, Bedford Hills. The subject of a panel discussion will be ''Education -- Pre-K Through Adulthood: A Process, Not Just a Grade.'' For more information, call 666-9280.</p>
        <p>Art Exhibit in Peekskill</p>
        <p>Art that may be seen through Jan.  29 at the Hudson Valley Institute for Art and Photographic Resources in Peekskill is concerned with the application of paint to canvas, watercolor to paper and other 20th-century  forms of visual expression.</p>
        <p>''Surfaces,'' the title of the show, features the work of 15 artists working in a variety of 20th-century mediums, which include painting, photography, sculpture, installation, conceptual and video art.</p>
        <p>The institute's stated goal for 2000 and beyond, however, is, ''to promote Peekskill as a leading-edge center for computer-digital-based art forms and a magnet for new electronic-computer based businesses.'' It hopes to attract to the community  skilled computer operators, scanners, Web page designers, artists involved in computer imaging and corporations to employ them.</p>
        <p>In the spring the institute will begin to carry out its goal with an exhibition of computer-generated art, which it believes will be the first such show in the region. It is situated at 101 South Division Street, open Thursdays through Saturdays from noon to 5 p.m., or by appointment. The phone number is 734-1111.</p>
        <p>Classes in Tai Chi</p>
        <p>Tai Chi, that soothing form of exercise, which is practiced by so many Chinese people first thing in the morning, is to be taught by Wendy Cali in classes at the New York United Hospital Medical Center in Port Chester on Wednesdays from 10:30 to 11:30 a.m., beginning this week.</p>
        <p>Tai Chi is said to stimulate blood circulation, increase flexibility, improve posture and enhance weight-bearing ability. Its low-impact, flowing movements are also said to improve balance and foster a feeling of meditative relaxation. It is used in China, according to the hospital staff, to treat addictions, muscle injuries, arthritis and nervous disorders. The fee for eight one-hour sessions is $48.</p>
        <p>The hospital is at 406 Post Road.  To register, call 934-3096.</p>
        <p>Works by Clay Fried</p>
        <p>Clay Fried's paintings of trucks on the highway, power lines, passing airplanes and other snapshots of the American scene can currently be seen at two venues and at a third later in the month.</p>
        <p>A group show containing his work is on view at the Upstream Gallery on Main Street in Dobbs Ferry through Jan. 16. Call (914) 674-8548 for visiting hours.</p>
        <p>An opening reception for a second show that includes Mr. Fried's work will be held at the Howland Cultural Center on Main Street in Beacon on Saturday from 3 to 5 p.m. The exhibition will remain through Jan. 30, open Fridays through Sundays from 1 to 5 p.m. or by appointment. Call (914) 831-4988 for information.</p>
        <p>The third show will open Jan. 14 at the Ansonia Gallery in the Ansonia Hotel, Broadway at 73rd Street in Manhattan, continuing through Feb. 25. The reception will take place on Jan. 14 from 7 to 9 p.m., and hours thereafter are Mondays through Fridays from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. The phone number is (212) 595-5500.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fried, 44, received his bachelor of fine arts degree from Purchase College and a master of fine arts degree from Vermont College, and he served as an assistant to Elaine and Willem de Kooning and Joan Mitchell. He has exhibited in New York State, New Jersey and various Eastern cities. His work is thought by some dealers to be reminiscent of Edward Hopper, Charles Sheeler or Rackstraw Downes.</p>
        <p>ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
