<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Andes, A Fiesta Is Serious Fun</title>
    <meta content="PUNO.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Titicaca</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Andes Mountains</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Puno (Peru)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chatfield-Taylor, Joan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Puno</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4DA1E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2364" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Andes, A Fiesta Is Serious Fun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN CHATFIELD-TAYLOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chatfield-Taylor, Joan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joan Chatfield-Taylor article on colorful festival of Virgin of Candelaria, held each January in Puno, on shores of Peru's Lake Titicaca; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN January, the rains turn Peru's high plains into a river of silvery green grass, flowing between mountainous outcroppings and an occasional jumble of dun-colored adobe and cinder block buildings. In this muted landscape, it was pure surrealism to drive into a town called Ayaviri and find almost everyone in bear costumes, spangled drum-majorette dresses, silver and black matador suits or many-skirted dresses and shawls of cut velvet and damask.</p>
        <p>All these splendid creatures were practicing dance routines for the festival of the Virgin of Candelaria to be held a few days later in Puno, a city of about 80,000 some 90 miles away on the shores of Lake Titicaca. The afternoon my friend Paola Gianturco and I arrived last February, Ayaviri's residents were polishing their routines on the rough field where they keep their llamas at night, then proceeding to the soccer stadium to compete for prizes that included a glittering five-foot-tall trophy and new shovels and hoes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN January, the rains turn Peru's high plains into a river of silvery green grass, flowing between mountainous outcroppings and an occasional jumble of dun-colored adobe and cinder block buildings. In this muted landscape, it was pure surrealism to drive into a town called Ayaviri and find almost everyone in bear costumes, spangled drum-majorette dresses, silver and black matador suits or many-skirted dresses and shawls of cut velvet and damask.</p>
        <p>All these splendid creatures were practicing dance routines for the festival of the Virgin of Candelaria to be held a few days later in Puno, a city of about 80,000 some 90 miles away on the shores of Lake Titicaca. The afternoon my friend Paola Gianturco and I arrived last February, Ayaviri's residents were polishing their routines on the rough field where they keep their llamas at night, then proceeding to the soccer stadium to compete for prizes that included a glittering five-foot-tall trophy and new shovels and hoes.</p>
        <p>We kept happening upon similar rehearsals as we crossed the Altiplano on our way to the festival. In Lampa, a pretty town known for its pink stucco facades and its replica of Michelangelo's Pieta, we were sharing a sunny afternoon with some playful kids and a few women presiding over soft-drink stands in the main square when dozens of young people burst into the plaza to the sound of bass drums and flutes. They were dressed in thoroughly modern jeans and sweats, but the young women were dipping and weaving through the steps of a traditional dance. The men parked their drums in three straight lines at the door of Lampa's huge cathedral, everyone knelt outside  and then filed into the church to pray for the power to win in Puno.</p>
        <p>Puno's festival honoring the Virgin of Candelaria (credited with saving the town from invaders in 1781) is one of the largest, longest and most lavish celebrations in fiesta-mad Peru. Thousands come from the surrounding Indian villages, the Quechua tribe to the north of Puno, the Aymara to the south. They come to a city that despite its spectacular location on the shores of Lake Titicaca is not particularly attractive, with its jumble of generic adobe and cinder-block buildings.</p>
        <p>Last year, there were more than two weeks of almost nonstop dancing, music, religious celebrations and fireworks displays with most of the action on the two weekends after Feb. 2, which is the Virgin's feast day and the start of the festival. Considerable numbers of Peruvian visitors come to town, but relatively few foreign tourists brave the rainy season and the altitude (12,565 feet) to see the event.</p>
        <p>Puno residents have expressed their devotion through music and dance for centuries, but the festival began to take on its present form in 1956, when the Instituto Americano de Arte organized a parade of the local dance clubs, known as conjuntos. Groups from outlying areas that had once been forbidden to appear in their native costumes at the festival were encouraged to participate, and authenticity was increasingly valued.</p>
        <p>Last year, so many conjuntos were competing that the contest, in Puno's soccer stadium, was spread over two weekends. The grupos autoctonas -- the indigenous people from country villages -- competed on the first weekend. The following weekend, hundreds of more citified groups, whose costumes and dance steps show greater Spanish influence, took the spotlight.</p>
        <p>There is nothing casual about these competitions. Dancers, many of whom learned the traditional steps as children, start rehearsing months ahead. Groups must have specific numbers of participants, depending on the dance, and perform for exactly eight minutes in front of a packed stadium of transfixed spectators. Six judges, lined up along the field, allot points for costumes, choreography, music and authenticity. The groups from the country may not wear synthetic fabrics, nor have a preponderance of brass instruments in their bands.</p>
        <p>As the whistle blows, as many as 60 or 70 dancers swirl on to the field, twirling and marching and dipping to music performed on flutes, panpipes, drums, tiny guitars and cymbals. Women spin like multicolored tops to show off their full skirts, worn as many as six at a time. Their headdresses vary from neat derbies to wide-brimmed hats trimmed with flowers or tassels to flat squares with floating panels of fabric. Shawls and cummerbunds, striped or embroidered, add flashes of color.</p>
        <p>The men are equally colorful, many wearing brightly striped pants, handsome ponchos, woolen masks, flower-trimmed hats and wide cummerbunds. Other applause-winners were the Ayarachis in their towering conical feather headdresses and the men who wore pyramids of totoras, the reeds used to construct islands, boats and houses on nearby Lake Titicaca.</p>
        <p>Some villagers also present vignettes of their daily lives. One group brought an alpaca onto the field and proceeded to shear it. Another town chose weaving as its theme. Male dancers wore looms on their backs, women danced with drop spindles in their hands, and a pair of laughing women set up a loom on the ground and tossed bright balls of yarns back and forth to create a warp.</p>
        <p>Last year, 74 indigenous groups participated. Even with the eight-minute requirement, the contest was an all-day marathon starting at 7 a.m. Each time we thought we couldn't sit through one more dance, a group would appear dressed all in tassels or would get the crowd applauding for its slapstick humor or especially impressive choreography, and we were hooked for another hour.</p>
        <p>The dancing is not limited to the stadium. After competing, many groups just keep on dancing, filling the narrow streets of the town with sound and color.</p>
        <p>The day after this competition, we were assured that nothing, nothing at all, was happening, making it a good day to visit the floating reed islands on the lake. Back in town, we were checking on faraway reality in an Internet cafe when we heard the alluring sound of massed pan flutes and drums. We dashed down to the corner just in time to catch a parade of villagers, some leading llamas with bright tassels in their ears, others dancing, others carrying loads of sticks on their backs. A dashing group of men wearing handsome ponchos rode on small, delicate horses, while others were dressed as women or wore rough masks made of animal skins.</p>
        <p>After watching this unexpected procession, we went to the artisans' market, where each woman, knitting briskly, presides over her wares in a canvas cubicle. Bargaining finished and purchases completed, we were wandering back to our hotel when a drumbeat lured us to the plaza in front of the cathedral. Each of the groups in the parade was dancing madly around bonfire pyres,  not yet lighted, that they had built from their burdens of sticks.</p>
        <p>The men in masks or female clothes turned out to be raunchy comedians, to the delight of the crowd. As darkness fell, the dancers lighted the fires one by one, filling the air with clouds of thick smoke and the smell of pungent herbs. The dancers swirled around the flames. Young people urged beer on us (we weren't sure whether they were selling or giving), and the whole scene seethed with unfettered, primitive energy -- intense but friendly.</p>
        <p>In comparison, the following day, the central date of the festival, began quietly at the picturesque Church of San Juan, home of the statue of the virgin and the favorite church of the Indian people of the region. The sweet-faced statue, affectionately referred to as Mamacita Candelaria, smiled down from her perch on a huge cloud of pale blue tulle. By 10 o'clock, the hour of the most important Mass of the day, the pews and aisles were jammed, Indians in traditional dress pressed against men and women in the modern attire of prosperous Peruvians from Lima.</p>
        <p>The front rows were occupied by the alferados, local dignitaries who work all year to organize the festival. Later that day, the dignitaries would be part of the virgin's procession through the streets of town.</p>
        <p>By Friday, the city was gearing up for two more days of nonstop dancing. During the afternoon, in the Parque de Pino, men were building three 40-foot towers out of bamboo sticks. By nightfall, the square was packed with people waiting for a fireworks display. A little after 8, a young man lighted one of the pinwheels attached to the structure. Gradually, all three towers began exploding with whirling pinwheels throwing sparks into the crowd, and rockets skidding into the night sky and along the gutters of nearby buildings for perhaps a half hour.</p>
        <p>By 7 the next morning, the soccer stadium was packed for the climax of the festival -- the competition of conjuntos from Puno and neighboring cities. The contest is called Danzas con Trajes de Luces (Dances With Suits of Light). Dozens of costume shops work all year to create hundreds of new costumes, so that young women can shimmy in spangled drum-majorette dresses, older women twirl gracefully in damask and cut velvet skirts, men and boys swelter in bear and gorilla suits, and athletic young men dance in black and silver matador costumes or in tiered contraptions of jewel-encrusted metal.</p>
        <p>The most astonishing costumes of all are those worn in a dance called the Diablada, representing a confrontation between St. Michael the Archangel and the forces of evil. The archangel is turned out splendidly in glittering robes and sculptured wings, but he loses the fashion contest to the devils, whose sculptured and painted masks, bug-eyed and adorned with figures representing the seven deadly sins, are works of art.</p>
        <p>These dances are accompanied by much larger and louder bands than the villagers' drums and pan flutes. Each group has its own assemblage of drums, cymbals, trombones, trumpets and sousaphones. Listening to the oompah music, watching the girls in their drum majorette dresses, we had the impression that we were at the world's longest half-time show.</p>
        <p>Even after we left the stadium, we had plenty of opportunities to see the dancers, who take to the streets after they finish competing. We discovered that one of the best vantage points is in front of the cathedral, where bleachers are set up. In addition, the entire event, from start to finish, is broadcast on both radio and television, complete with on-the-field interviews with prominent dancers.</p>
        <p>While we were eating lunch, a radio announcer was describing each dance group in detail. Suddenly, our waiter dashed out the door and ran toward the stadium. His daughter is about to dance, someone explained.</p>
        <p>Later in the afternoon, we were watching the street scene from a second-floor hotel room. Suddenly, two of the hotel waiters rushed in and began draping the balcony with damask, then hanging a glittering banner from the railing. Slowly down the crowded street came the Virgin of Candelaria, on a cloud of yellow tulle, surrounded by the festival organizers and conjuntos. As she passed our balcony, the waiters joyously flung down basketfuls of marigold petals.</p>
        <p>A young Peruvian explained this heartfelt enthusiasm, saying, ''You know we can't afford to go away on holiday, so a festival is like a vacation for us.''</p>
        <p>High in the Andes, a devotion to the Virgin and to dancing</p>
        <p>The Fiesta of the Virgin of Candelaria starts on Feb. 2, with the traditional village dances this year on Feb. 6 and the climactic  Trajes de Luces dances on Feb. 13.</p>
        <p>This is the rainy season, but that should mean occasional rain rather than a continual downpour; travelers should take raingear. Days can be cool and nights cold. A handknit alpaca sweater can be bought at the market for $25 or less, at 3.45 nuevo soles to the dollar.</p>
        <p>Getting There</p>
        <p>We went to Puno from Cuzco, roughly a 250-mile trip that allows one to see the wide open spaces of the Altiplano, or high plateau. Trains leave Cuzco for Puno at 8 a.m. Monday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday and return at 8 a.m. Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday and Saturday ($35 one way). The trip takes about 10 hours.</p>
        <p>We rented a van with an excellent driver, Willy Valdivia, through Auqui Mountain Spirit Travel Agency Post Office Box 554, Cuzco; (51-84) 251-278, fax (51-84) 235-334. The fee is $450 round trip for up to six people, plus $60 for each day the van and driver remain in Puno. The trip takes about seven hours, allowing time for a picnic lunch and many stops to photograph llamas.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>In Puno, the Posada del Inca, (51-54) 364-152, fax (51-54) 363-672, opened Nov. 15. It has 62 rooms in rustic, earthy colors, and a restaurant. A double room costs $105.</p>
        <p>The Hotel Colon Inn, (51-54) 351-432, is clean, comfortable and right in the middle of town; a small restaurant that serves dinner, including excellent pizzas. Doubles: $53.</p>
        <p>Three miles from town, on an island linked to the mainland by a causeway, is the Golden Tulip Hotel Libertador Isla Esteves, (51-54) 367-780, fax (51-54) 367-879, a large modern edifice with 126 rooms. A standard double costs $135, a suite $175.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Puno is not a place for fine dining, and we ate mostly at hotel restaurants. But for lunch, we went to the Restaurant Internacional at 161 Libertad, (51-54) 352-502, next to the Hotel Internacional. It lives up to its name, serving inexpensive Chinese, Italian and Peruvian specialties in an unadorned setting. Lunch with a soft drink is $2.50 a person.</p>
        <p>JOAN CHATFIELD-TAYLOR</p>
        <p>JOAN CHATFIELD-TAYLOR works in San Francisco and Paris.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JOAN CHATFIELD-TAYLOR works in San Francisco and Paris.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
