<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Town Aspires to Landmark Status</title>
    <meta content="02COLU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165614"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Columbus (Ind)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pei, I M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saarinen, Eliel (1873-50)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saarinen, Eero (1910-61)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roche, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pelli, Cesar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meredith, Robyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3DB1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1411" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Town Aspires to Landmark Status</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBYN MEREDITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meredith, Robyn</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBUS, Ind., Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Local preservation group in Columbus, Ind, will seek National Historic Landmark status for group of buildings that were designed by some of 20th century's greatest architects; Cummins Engine Foundation began financing unusual architectural program in 1957, jump-starting effort to attract notable modern architects, among them I M Pei, Eliel Saarinen, Eero Saarinen, Kevin Roche and Cesar Pelli; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a matter of months, this Midwestern small town of big-city architecture that is a who's who of post-war design may boast yet another distinction: a group of its buildings is likely to become the first in modern architecture to win National Historic Landmark status, an honor more often bestowed on the nation's earliest buildings.</p>
        <p>On one downtown block alone, there is a library by I. M. Pei; a sculpture by Henry Moore; a church across the street by Eliel Saarinen; a bank down the block by his son, Eero Saarinen, and a company headquarters next door designed by Kevin Roche. There are schools, firehouses, churches, factories and a Cesar Pelli shopping mall, all part of a collection of about 65 buildings by nationally known architects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a matter of months, this Midwestern small town of big-city architecture that is a who's who of post-war design may boast yet another distinction: a group of its buildings is likely to become the first in modern architecture to win National Historic Landmark status, an honor more often bestowed on the nation's earliest buildings.</p>
        <p>On one downtown block alone, there is a library by I. M. Pei; a sculpture by Henry Moore; a church across the street by Eliel Saarinen; a bank down the block by his son, Eero Saarinen, and a company headquarters next door designed by Kevin Roche. There are schools, firehouses, churches, factories and a Cesar Pelli shopping mall, all part of a collection of about 65 buildings by nationally known architects.</p>
        <p>Not bad for a city of 37,000 nestled between farmland and factories in the middle of the prairie.</p>
        <p>Historians who will evaluate the application said the architecture here amounted to an unusual grouping of significant modern buildings. ''It is almost like raisins in a pudding -- you have all these raisins studding a pudding, and they are all wonderful in their own right, but it's the combination of all the raisins that makes the pudding good,'' said Patty H. Henry, a historian with the National Historic Landmarks division of the National Park Service.</p>
        <p>And these works are found far from American architectural meccas like Chicago, New York, San Francisco or Boston. ''You're talking Columbus, Ind.,'' she said. ''To find that little gem of a collection out there is what makes it unique.''</p>
        <p>Architects who have worked here agreed. ''It is at once a classic American town -- it has a Main Street -- and at the same time, it has this highfalutin architecture,'' said Robert C. Venturi, who built Fire Station No. 4 here in 1967. He is now one of the nation's leading architects, at Venturi, Scott, Brown &amp; Associates in Philadelphia. ''I admire the architecture there very much.''</p>
        <p>How did a small city about halfway between Indianapolis and Louisville, Ky., come by such an astounding collection of modern architecture? It is, after all, a surprise after the 43-mile drive south from Indianapolis, where the fields are nearly flat, and this time of year, pancake-colored, interrupted by worn-down gray barns, copses of bare-boned trees and the occasional scruffy silo.</p>
        <p>The buildings here reflect another incongruity, a partnership between heavy industry and high art.</p>
        <p>A small part of the price of a Dodge Ram pickup with a diesel engine goes to support architects working here. The same goes for the electric company bills from major utilities, which help pay for standby generators, and a tiny piece of the price of most anything shipped on an 18-wheeler. That's because those diesel engines and generators are built by Cummins Engine Company Inc., the patron of this company town and its architecture.</p>
        <p>The company's retired chairman, J. Irwin Miller, has long been a fan of modernists, and in 1957 his company began financing an unusual architecture program through its nonprofit foundation, the Cummins Engine Foundation. That jump-started the effort to persuade notable modern architects to build here.</p>
        <p>The foundation pays architectural fees in Columbus's Bartholomew County for new public buildings and for renovations of existing buildings, as long as the public agencies agree to choose an architect from a list of contemporary designers selected by an independent panel of distinguished architects. Agencies also must give the architects they hire responsibility for planning and designing the entire building, including landscaping and furnishings.</p>
        <p>''Good architecture needs a good client as well as a good architect,''  Mr. Venturi said. ''I would love to build another one there -- it is a sympatico environment.''</p>
        <p>The Cummins foundation has spent $13.8 million on 43 projects since 1957, including 13 new schools, three fire stations, the Post Office, the triangular City Hall by Edward Charles Bassett and a number of renovations of existing buildings.</p>
        <p>But the nonprofit group's example has also inspired others. Fewer than half of the notable buildings here have been paid for by the foundation. The rest have been backed by other local companies, residents and congregations.</p>
        <p>The collection of modern churches alone is remarkable. Mr. Miller got the ball rolling, when he persuaded the congregation of his church, First Christian, to hire Eliel Saarinen to build its church here in 1942. The result was one of the nation's first churches with modern architecture.</p>
        <p>Then came Eero Saarinen's 1964 North Christian Church, with a sanctuary cupped in the structure like a chalice, topped by a 192-foot steeple with a delicate cross rising to the heavens. A year later, Harry Weese built First Baptist Church, with steep triangular shapes and a low, T-shaped entrance. In 1998 Gunnar Birkerts built St. Peter's Lutheran Church, with tall, thin walls like fins and floor-to-ceiling windows.</p>
        <p>The 1942 Eliel Saarinen church, the 1954 Eero Saarinen bank building and his 1964 church, the 1965 Weese Baptist church, a 1960 school by John Carl Warnecke and Mr. Miller's own house, built in 1957 by Eero Saarinen with landscape architecture by Dan Kiley, are the six buildings expected to be included in the application for National Historic Landmark status.</p>
        <p>A local preservation group, called Preserve to Enjoy, is expected to file the application in January, and a decision is expected this summer. If the landmark designation is granted, other Columbus buildings may be added in the future.</p>
        <p>The application is extremely unusual, Ms. Henry said, because it violates two nearly iron-clad rules at the landmark commission.</p>
        <p>Typically, buildings must be a minimum of 50 years old, and the group of Columbus buildings dates from 1942 to 1965. At the dawn of the year 2000, even the 1960's can seem long ago, but the landmark commission makes only rare exceptions.</p>
        <p>In addition, the landmark commission seldom honors the work of living architects, and the school's designer, Mr. Warnecke, is retired but quite alive.</p>
        <p>Still, the architects who built here are so notable that exceptions may well be granted. ''They are very well-known modern architects that will no doubt stand the test of time,'' Ms. Henry said.</p>
        <p>The Columbus application will focus on two areas: the important modern architecture and the role of the Cummins Engine Foundation in bringing it to this unlikely spot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, 90, has handed many architectural cares to his son, Will Miller, chairman of what townspeople here simply call ''the Bank.'' That's the Irwin Financial Corporation, a local bank and mortgage company with $2 billion in assets that early this century was the financial backer of Cummins Engine.</p>
        <p>''In a lot of ways, the architecture in Columbus has raised standards across the board, not just in bricks and mortar,'' said Mr. Miller, who like his father is an aficionado of modern architecture. ''It is an example of Churchill's notion that first we shape our buildings and thereafter they shape us.''</p>
        <p>Remarkably, these Midwestern Medicis have managed to create such an interesting collection of buildings that leading architects clamor to design small-scale buildings here.</p>
        <p>''It is nice to be in that selected group of architects to build there,'' said Kevin Roche of Roche, Dinkeloo and Associates in Hamden, Conn. He designed the 1970 Post Office, a 1973 Cummins engine factory, the 1983 Cummins headquarters along with some additions and renovations. ''It is quite prestigious because you are in the company of distinguished architects.''</p>
        <p>He praised the move to try for National Historic Landmark status. ''It is good for the buildings because it helps preserve the buildings,'' Mr. Roche said.</p>
        <p>There are fewer than 2,300 landmarks nationwide -- the program is far more selective than the National Register of Historic Places, which has about 70,000 listings. Landmark status can protect historic buildings from alterations or demolition by requiring reviews of any changes to the buildings if federal funds or permits are involved.</p>
        <p>A landmark listing would be an honor for both the city and the architects. Louis D. Joyner, a Columbus architect who is helping with the application, said, ''The National Historic Landmark designation is just like winning the Academy Award.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
