<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Talk of the Archdiocese: Who's Likely to Succeed the Cardinal</title>
    <meta content="02ARCH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cardinals (Roman Catholic Prelates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Louis (Mo)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baltimore (Md)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rigali, Justin F (Archbishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McCarrick, Theodore E (Archbishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keeler, William (Cardinal)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Brien, Edwin F (Archbishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, John (Cardinal)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland/Baltimore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri/St. Louis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cardinals (Roman Catholic Prelates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DD1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Talk of the Archdiocese: Who's Likely to Succeed the Cardinal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Archbishop Justin F Rigali of St Louis, Archbishop Theodore E McCarrick of Newark, Cardinal William Keeler, archbishop of Baltimore, and Archbishop Edwin F O'Brien, who oversees archdiocese of military services, are mentioned as possible successors to Cardinal John O'Connor as archbishop of New York; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the shepherd to 2.4 million parishioners and a man whose utterances are closely monitored, the archbishop of New York has historically had the tallest pulpit in the Roman Catholic Church in the United States.</p>
        <p>By nature of the position, he can be the Vatican's leading spokesman in America, a figure whom foreign dignitaries feel they must meet and a religious leader whose views carry great weight among other faiths. Since Cardinal John O'Connor, the archbishop since 1983, is likely to retire soon, speculation and hope are swirling within church circles about whom Pope John Paul II will appoint to this powerful post. Many who speak about it do so only on background.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the shepherd to 2.4 million parishioners and a man whose utterances are closely monitored, the archbishop of New York has historically had the tallest pulpit in the Roman Catholic Church in the United States.</p>
        <p>By nature of the position, he can be the Vatican's leading spokesman in America, a figure whom foreign dignitaries feel they must meet and a religious leader whose views carry great weight among other faiths. Since Cardinal John O'Connor, the archbishop since 1983, is likely to retire soon, speculation and hope are swirling within church circles about whom Pope John Paul II will appoint to this powerful post. Many who speak about it do so only on background.</p>
        <p>The men most often cited in interviews with Catholics who take a keen interest in church politics share certain characteristics. They are mostly archbishops, in their late 50's and 60's, with experience of important posts in Rome. They include the archbishop of St. Louis, a man with strong diplomatic skills who is considered close to the pope; the head of the Newark archdiocese, one of the most ethnically diverse in the church, and the archbishop of the American military, who has long enjoyed a close relationship with Cardinal O'Connor. A handful of others, some with close ties to New York, round out the list.</p>
        <p>The archbishop's office, said the Rev. Thomas Reese, editor of the Jesuit magazine America, really involves the equivalent of four full-time jobs: administrator and fund-raiser, national Catholic spokesman, leader among bishops and consultant on American issues to the pope.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, perhaps, Cardinal O'Connor, through his outspokenness on issues ranging from opposition to abortion to defense of immigrants' rights, has established a tone some people now associate with the office itself. He has re-defined the job, said George Weigel, author of a biography of Pope John Paul II, ''Witness to Hope'' (HarperCollins, 1999), and a senior fellow at the Ethics and Public Policy Center in Washington. Like the pope himself, Mr. Weigel said in an interview, the cardinal has ''recovered a much more ancient notion of the bishop as an evangelist.''</p>
        <p>But the cardinal has indicated that he expects to retire soon. Last summer, he underwent brain surgery for a tumor. And he will turn 80 on Jan. 15, the age at which, by church law, he loses his vote in the College of Cardinals, the Vatican body that elects the next pope. In November, the cardinal wrote what sounded like a farewell letter to American bishops.</p>
        <p>Catholics in the 4,700-square-mile archdiocese, which incorporates Manhattan, Staten Island, the Bronx and seven counties to the north, do not lack opinions about the qualities an archbishop should bring to the job. In a New York Times poll conducted from Nov. 29 to Dec. 5, Catholics in the archdiocese said the next archbishop should be compassionate and humane, help the poor and the homeless, and show strong leadership.</p>
        <p>Interviews with New York Catholics turned up similar sentiments. ''I want a direct, outspoken and very humanitarian leader,'' said Lorraine Cortes-Vazquez, president of the Hispanic Federation, a network of nonprofit organizations. ''One who is loving, clear, extremely responsible and holds people accountable, but who is very interested in hearing other perspectives.''</p>
        <p>Mario M. Cuomo, who endured the cardinal's criticism as a Catholic politician who supported abortion rights while governor, said, ''If Catholics all knew about Cardinal O'Connor, they would want someone very much like him.'' He said the cardinal has been ''perhaps the strongest'' pro-labor archbishop in New York's history.</p>
        <p>Mary Ellen McDonnell, a parishioner at St. Boniface Church in Brooklyn, said she favored the idea of an archbishop with the ability to listen: ''The church does not work by consensus, and I understand that, but to be an effective leader, one must be sensitive to differences, especially in New York.''</p>
        <p>And one priest said ''the big thing'' the next archbishop ought to have is administrative skills.</p>
        <p>Father Reese said that if one added up what Catholics wanted in a New York archbishop, ''it ends up being a saint with an M.B.A. from Harvard Business School.''</p>
        <p>The potential successor whose name comes up the most often is Archbishop Justin F. Rigali of St. Louis, a city the pope visited for two days in January 1999, his only stop in the United States after a pastoral visit to Mexico. Prior to his appointment in 1994, Archbishop Rigali, 64, earned a doctorate in canon law and spent three decades in Rome, much of that time in the Vatican's diplomatic offices. Not surprisingly, he is credited with excellent diplomatic skills. Like Cardinal O'Connor, he is viewed as a church conservative but is considered to be more reserved. He enjoys the ''great confidence'' of Pope John Paul II, according to one authority on the church.</p>
        <p>And then there is Archbishop Theodore E. McCarrick of Newark, 69, a native of New York City who once served as an auxiliary bishop in the archdiocese. Among American bishops, he has a reputation as a leader on international issues. He travels widely and has been an outspoken advocate of debt relief for the world's poorest nations. In 1998, he organized a major conference on the issue, bringing together bishops from impoverished countries with bankers and government officials. People in the church describe him as gregarious and accessible.</p>
        <p>In Newark, he presides over a diocese that has received immigrants from all over the world. He is fluent in Spanish -- which would be an asset in New York, where Hispanic parishioners, at 36 percent of the diocese, are one of its fastest growing groups. He holds a doctorate in sociology.</p>
        <p>Another prelate whose name often comes up is a man long close to Cardinal O'Connor, Archbishop Edwin F. O'Brien. He is head of the archdiocese for the military services, the Washington-based jurisdiction over Army, Navy, Air Force and Coast Guard chaplains. Archbishop O'Brien, 60, served as vice chancellor and director of communications in the New York archdiocese, and has experience as a former rector of seminaries in New York and Rome. He is described as a somewhat quiet but personable man. He, too, has a doctorate, in moral theology.</p>
        <p>Other possible successors include Cardinal William Keeler, the archbishop of Baltimore since 1989.</p>
        <p>He is 68 and has a reputation for extensive work in interfaith relations, particularly between the church and Jews, a major segment of the Baltimore population. However, some in the church say it would be unusual for the Vatican to relocate someone who has already been elevated to cardinal.</p>
        <p>Another name that is mentioned is that of Bishop Henry J. Mansell, 62, of Buffalo, a former auxiliary bishop of New York, who has served in Buffalo since 1995.</p>
        <p>Like Archbishop O'Brien, he is  close to Cardinal O'Connor, and during his time in New York was popular with the archdiocese's priests.</p>
        <p>Bishop Donald W. Wuerl, 59, of Pittsburgh is also a possibility. Bishop Wuerl once served as a bishop coadjutor in Seattle, appointed by Rome to exert greater papal authority over the liberal former archbishop in Seattle, Raymond Hunthausen.</p>
        <p>He has earned considerable praise during his 11 years in Pittsburgh, where he is regarded as an effective pastoral leader and administrator.</p>
        <p>But he is more often spoken of as a likely successor to either Cardinal Anthony Bevilacqua in Philadelphia or Cardinal James Hickey in Washington, both in their late 70's.</p>
        <p>Two other names mentioned are Archbishop Charles J. Chaput of Denver, an outspoken conservative with American Indian ancestry who formerly served as bishop of Rapid City, S.D., and Bishop Sean O'Malley, 55, of Fall River, Mass., a Franciscan priest who is fluent in Spanish and previously served as a bishop in the Virgin Islands.</p>
        <p>Yet the speculation amounts to only educated guesses. The insiders have been surprised before.</p>
        <p>In late 1996, for example, as Cardinal Joseph Bernardin, archbishop of Chicago, was dying of cancer, speculation focused on half a dozen well-known bishops, mainly Midwesterners with close Chicago connections. But the following April, the Vatican chose Francis George, the archbishop of Portland, Ore., who just 11 months before had held the relatively obscure post of bishop of Yakima, Wash.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
