<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chechnya's Capital Becomes A Deadly Zone for Russians</title>
    <meta content="02CHEC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Movements and Secession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Grozny (Chechnya)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chechnya (Russia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Chechnya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5DC1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1389" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chechnya's Capital Becomes A Deadly Zone for Russians</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>ALKHAN-YURT, Russia, Jan. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grozny, capital of Chechnya, becomes a deadly killing zone as Russian troops run into fierce resistance from heavily armed, experienced and motivated rebels; make inroads, but still do not control city center; official casuality figures understate Russian losses, which are estimated at 10 soldiers a day; popularity of Vladimir V Putin, acting president, is based in large part reports of low casualties; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he is asked about the fighting in Grozny, Konstantin Kukhlovets shows the red splotch on his index finger. The 24-year-old lieutenant said he was firing his machine gun so furiously that he was scalded by the heat of the gun barrel.</p>
        <p>Three of his men were wounded in a 10-minute firefight, and Lieutenant Kukhlovets says his entire unit might have been annihilated if they had tried to fight their way into the center of the city against entrenched Chechen rebels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he is asked about the fighting in Grozny, Konstantin Kukhlovets shows the red splotch on his index finger. The 24-year-old lieutenant said he was firing his machine gun so furiously that he was scalded by the heat of the gun barrel.</p>
        <p>Three of his men were wounded in a 10-minute firefight, and Lieutenant Kukhlovets says his entire unit might have been annihilated if they had tried to fight their way into the center of the city against entrenched Chechen rebels.</p>
        <p>''We have been fighting all over Chechnya, but Grozny is the first place we have come across such intense resistance,'' he said at this settlement, four miles southwest of the Chechen capital. ''The rebels have fortified their positions, and it is much harder to fight inside a city.''</p>
        <p>For the first three months of their military campaign, Russia made short work of the militants. Russian forces raced through the northern plains of Chechnya before seizing the lowlands to the south.</p>
        <p>Grozny, however, is different. The sprawling city has turned out to be, once again, a deadly killing zone. The Russian soldiers have made inroads, but still do not control the city center -- a fact that could shape into a major challenge to Vladimir V. Putin, the newly appointed acting president of Russia, whose current popularity is based in large part on the reportedly low Russian casualties up to now in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>Under the division of war chores among Russian forces, the Interior Ministry troops are charged with the thankless task of clearing Grozny's apartments, alleyways and basements of rebels. According to the official statistics, 21 Interior Ministry soldiers have been killed in Grozny and 56 wounded in the last week, since the military began the drive on the Chechen capital.</p>
        <p>But senior Interior Ministry officials acknowledge that those statistics understate the actual Russian losses. Russian troops are officially counted as dead only after their bodies are found and identified. As the fighting has raged in Grozny's streets, the Interior Ministry's actual losses have sometimes averaged 10 soldiers a day.</p>
        <p>''The situation in Grozny is extremely difficult,'' said Valery P. Zhuravel, the deputy commander of the Interior Ministry troops in the region. ''The rebels have prepared many strongholds. The militants are mainly in the center of the city, but they are able to move around a lot.''</p>
        <p>The street fighting is more than a military matter. The Kremlin sold the war to the Russian public by insisting that Russian casualties would be held to a minimum.</p>
        <p>If the toll continues to mount, public support for the war -- and for Mr. Putin -- may begin to wane. The prospect of a long war may be one reason why Boris N. Yeltsin decided to retire now as president and to organize early elections while Mr. Putin's ratings are still relatively high.</p>
        <p>Today, eight more soldiers were reported to have died in an exceptionally fierce assault on Grozny. Low-flying jets dropped scores of bombs on the city, and tanks in the nearby hills fired hundreds of shells.</p>
        <p>Stationed in a chilly field near Alkhan-Yurt, the 21st Brigade does not spend much time debating politics. The troops are mostly young draftees who were quietly serving their tour of duty in Sofrino, a small town near Moscow, when the fighting erupted in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>They fought the rebels in Dagestan in August and were sent to Chechnya in October. Chechnya was clear sailing, they said, until Grozny. The fighting there weighs heavily on their minds. Part of their unit is still engaged in house-to-house fighting in the city. After they are withdrawn in a few days, many of the troops now waiting their turn here will have to face the Grozny meat grinder.</p>
        <p>''Our first real losses started when we entered Grozny,'' said Aleksei G. Lyulin, a 20-year-old private from the Belgorod region. ''We have had many wounded.''</p>
        <p>Pvt. Sergei Chigayev, a 19-year-old with rosy cheeks, chimed in that he was afraid that he would soon end up in Grozny.</p>
        <p>''Even going to a small village to look for firewood is scary,'' he said. ''You can see from the way the villagers stare at us that they really don't want us here. But the idea of going to Grozny is really frightening. We have had no special training for what we have do there.''</p>
        <p>What the Russian troops have to do in Grozny is certainly a dangerous job. In Moscow, Russian spokesmen have promised that the troops will not ''storm'' Grozny, a allusion to the first war in Chechnya, when a Russian armor column zoomed into the center of the city on New Year's Eve in 1994 and was quickly annihilated.  Instead, they assert, Russian troops are conducting a ''special operation'' to take the city, implying that sophisticated tactics are being used to keep Russian losses to a minimum.</p>
        <p>In reality, Russian troops say they are involved in messy urban warfare with heavily armed, experienced and motivated rebels.</p>
        <p>These are the Russian tactics, as described by commanders and soldiers here: First, Russian artillery and warplanes pound the city, trying to stun and weaken the rebel resistance. Then the Russian troops move in. A special ''rapid deployment team'' of commandos leads the way. Interior Ministry troops come next, followed by Russian tanks.</p>
        <p>The soldiers surround a building. After it is sealed off, they go from room to room, searching for rebels and arms. If the Russians run into heavy resistance, they withdraw and call in artillery and airstrikes.</p>
        <p>Chechen paramilitaries commanded by Bislan Gantamirov, the former mayor of Grozny -- who was convicted of embezzlement but let out of jail so that he could fight on the side of the Kremlin -- are not in most of the heavy fighting, Lieutenant Kukhlovets said. Despite Mr. Gantamirov's claims of battlefield prowess, it is the Russian soldiers who play the main role.</p>
        <p>The rebels, however, are not acting according to the Russian script. Instead of running at the sound of Russian artillery, they hide in Grozny's cellars and ride out the strikes. The artillery, Russian troops conceded, generally destroys the upper stories, but leaves the basements intact.</p>
        <p>When the Russians return, the rebels shoot at them from carefully fortified positions, nestled among the ruins of Grozny's buildings and surrounded by sandbags. The militants are often deployed in two-man teams.</p>
        <p>Armed with automatic weapons and grenade launchers, they are good shots. Lieutenant Kukhlovets said one rebel with a grenade launcher had hit the driver of a Russian armored personnel carrier in the head.</p>
        <p>The rebel fire is so deadly that it is usually too dangerous to maneuver an armored personnel carrier through the city. The militants generally evacuate their dead, so Russia troops often have no idea how many casualties they are inflicting.</p>
        <p>In a week of fighting, the Russian troops have seized most of the northwestern part of the city. But the rebels still control much of the city center. And even the northwestern area slips from Russian control at night.</p>
        <p>''At night anything that moves will be shot at,'' Lieutenant Kukhlovets said. ''So nobody goes out at night, neither the rebels not us. If my soldiers have to go to the bathroom, I tell them to do it out the window. The slightest movement is forbidden.''</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Kukhlovets returned two days ago from Grozny. Apart from a slight concussion, he had not been hurt. Two other officers were killed in the fighting.</p>
        <p>Judging from his account, there is tough fighting ahead. If the rebels' confidence has been shaken by Russian firepower, it was not apparent to Lieutenant Kukhlovets's platoon. During one chilly night in Grozny, the rebels taunted the soldiers, yelling out from their hiding places that ''Ivan'' and other ''Russian fools'' have come to Grozny to die.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
