<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: David W. Belin, b. 1928 - Leonard C. Lewin, b. 1916; The Paranoia Gap</title>
    <meta content="MB101212" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hoaxes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">belin, david w (1928-99)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">lewin, leonard c (1916-99)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, John Fitzgerald (1917-63)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1D91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: David W. Belin, b. 1928 - Leonard C. Lewin, b. 1916; The Paranoia Gap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Sullivan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew Sullivan article on David W Belin, lawyer for Warren Commission, and Leonard C Lewin, journalist who wrote parody of government study into awful consequences that could result from peace in Vietnam, who both died in 1999; cites them as veterans of paranoia's glory days; notes even Belin eventually conceded that commission's stand that Pres John F Kennedy was murdered by lone gunman was overwhelmed by public doubt; Lewin's pseudo-report, liberal fantasy about evils of military-industrial complex, has been taken up by militia right in 1990's as real government document; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The year 1999 was not, it turned out, a vintage year for paranoia. Heaven knows why. We were prepared for all manner of hysteria: survivalist panics, religious retreats, cultic chaos. None of it materialized. Perhaps it was the genuine fear of a Y2K computer crash that distracted us from premillennial fantasies. Perhaps it was the transparency of the Internet and the power of hackers that made government secrecy seem less intimidating. Or maybe the paranoids of the mid-1990's simply blew themselves out with their ''X-Files'' excesses.</p>
        <p>Remember Ted Kaczynski and Timothy McVeigh, millennial paranoids who made murder their therapy? Or Oliver Stone, Ross Perot and Johnnie Cochran, all of whom parlayed this American pathology into career highs? But in retrospect, they were all swimming upstream. By the last decade of the century, paranoia was not what it once was. In the whimpering end of the post-cold war decade, we saw James Bond replaced by Austin Powers, the fantasy of nuclear winter by the Sci-Fi Channel, George Smiley and Joe McCarthy by Mulder and Scully.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The year 1999 was not, it turned out, a vintage year for paranoia. Heaven knows why. We were prepared for all manner of hysteria: survivalist panics, religious retreats, cultic chaos. None of it materialized. Perhaps it was the genuine fear of a Y2K computer crash that distracted us from premillennial fantasies. Perhaps it was the transparency of the Internet and the power of hackers that made government secrecy seem less intimidating. Or maybe the paranoids of the mid-1990's simply blew themselves out with their ''X-Files'' excesses.</p>
        <p>Remember Ted Kaczynski and Timothy McVeigh, millennial paranoids who made murder their therapy? Or Oliver Stone, Ross Perot and Johnnie Cochran, all of whom parlayed this American pathology into career highs? But in retrospect, they were all swimming upstream. By the last decade of the century, paranoia was not what it once was. In the whimpering end of the post-cold war decade, we saw James Bond replaced by Austin Powers, the fantasy of nuclear winter by the Sci-Fi Channel, George Smiley and Joe McCarthy by Mulder and Scully.</p>
        <p>Two veterans of paranoia's glory days died in 1999. One was David W. Belin, Republican lawyer for, and chief defender of, the Warren Commission. As he lay in a coma, friends confirmed his lack of consciousness by whispering into his ear that they believed there had been a government conspiracy to kill President Kennedy. For the first time, Belin said nothing in response.</p>
        <p>Belin's almost noble calling was to believe in the ordinary. In an article in this magazine 11 years ago, he reiterated his plain belief that ''the truth is that Lee Harvey Oswald was the lone gunman who murdered President John F. Kennedy.'' Not many believed him then -- or, for that matter, even now. Even Belin eventually conceded that his own commission had been hopelessly overwhelmed by public doubt. Oliver Stone didn't help. Nor did the accumulating details of the Kennedy administration's enmeshment with the Mafia.</p>
        <p>President Ford later appointed Belin to investigate the secret activities of the C.I.A. Weirdly enough, he discovered that the day Kennedy was assassinated, the C.I.A. was equipping an agent, code-named Am/Lash, with a poison-pen device to kill Fidel Castro. By then, even Belin suggested a Congressional investigation into ''whether or not there is any credible evidence of a foreign conspiracy. . . . The Warren Commission found none, but the Warren Commission did not have any information concerning the C.I.A. assassination plots.''</p>
        <p>The truth, he continued to believe, was out there, and he spent the rest of his life, valiantly enough, in journalism. Which is where Leonard C. Lewin began. In 1967, inspired by an idea from Victor Navasky, Lewin invented a secret government document called ''Report From Iron Mountain.'' The idea was hatched when Navasky read one day, at the height of the Vietnam War, that there had been a stock-market dive because of a ''peace scare.'' ''Report From Iron Mountain'' was a parody of an elaborate government study into the awful consequences for society if indeed peace were to break out -- and upon publication found a large and credulous audience. U.S. News and World Report claimed the study was commissioned by the Kennedy administration, and that when Lyndon Johnson had discovered it, he had ''hit the roof.'' Esquire ran a 28,000 word excerpt. The hoax was maintained by the publishing house, Dial Press, and even kept going by phony reviews by the likes of John Kenneth Galbraith (under a pseudonym) in The Washington Post.</p>
        <p>The report itself was a deft parody of the institutional prose of the time, riddled with plausible-sounding footnotes, even praising the hawkish Herman Kahn of the Hudson Institute for his ability to think about the war without ''getting bogged down in questions of morality.'' A liberal fantasy about the evils of the military-industrial complex, it was so successful that when Lewin finally confessed to the hoax, five years later, not everyone believed him. That was after the publication of the real Pentagon Papers, which Lewin called ''as outrageous, morally and intellectually,'' as his own jeu d'esprit. ''The charade is over,'' he wrote, indignantly.</p>
        <p>Well, not quite. As proof of Garry Wills's argument that antigovernment paranoia knows no ideological barriers in America, the pseudo-report was later taken up by the militia right in the 1990's. The report's new life was part of the late-century transformation of American paranoia from being an influential legacy of the antiwar left to a fringe passion of the antigovernment right. Lewin eventually resorted to suing the Liberty Lobby, an antigovernment group, to stop disseminating pirated copies of the book. The lobby, in response, gamely claimed there was no copyright restriction because it was a government document. Even now, Simon &amp; Schuster, which publishes a new version, is trying to stop unapproved citation of the report on the Web.</p>
        <p>It's an uphill battle. The proliferation of paranoids on the Web is proportionate to their failure to capture a more general public audience. But they don't really care if anyone else cares either. Paranoia, like everything else, is a subculture now.</p>
        <p>Andrew Sullivan is a contributing writer for The New York Times Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Andrew Sullivan is a contributing writer for The New York Times Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
