<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lost in the Big Picture, Small, Special Moments</title>
    <meta content="02NOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE YEAR 2000: CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1D61038F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lost in the Big Picture, Small, Special Moments</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James, in Critics Notebook column, discusses television coverage of New Year's Eve celebrations around world (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the disasters that did not happen, planes did not fall from the sky, terrorists did not have their way, and after nearly 24 nonstop hours as anchor of ABC's extravagant New Year's coverage, Peter Jennings did not turn into Jerry Lewis and start singing ''You'll Never Walk Alone.'' That may seem a small satisfaction compared with the absence of computer mayhem, but television's millennium display was often more revealing in its smaller moments than in its scope.</p>
        <p>Its genuine highlights included stunning fireworks from Paris and London. But there was much dutiful blanket coverage that seemed like a cross between a National Geographic documentary (dancing on Pacific islands, a chapel carved from ice in Sweden) and the Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade (a stream of exquisite oversize puppets carried through Times Square). And nearly lost in the sheer mass of reporting were a few moments of startling truth from people as different as the heroic Nelson Mandela and the purple-haired Dame Edna Everage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among the disasters that did not happen, planes did not fall from the sky, terrorists did not have their way, and after nearly 24 nonstop hours as anchor of ABC's extravagant New Year's coverage, Peter Jennings did not turn into Jerry Lewis and start singing ''You'll Never Walk Alone.'' That may seem a small satisfaction compared with the absence of computer mayhem, but television's millennium display was often more revealing in its smaller moments than in its scope.</p>
        <p>Its genuine highlights included stunning fireworks from Paris and London. But there was much dutiful blanket coverage that seemed like a cross between a National Geographic documentary (dancing on Pacific islands, a chapel carved from ice in Sweden) and the Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade (a stream of exquisite oversize puppets carried through Times Square). And nearly lost in the sheer mass of reporting were a few moments of startling truth from people as different as the heroic Nelson Mandela and the purple-haired Dame Edna Everage.</p>
        <p>Television was looking for Big Moments, but ended up conveying safety, and not only because there were no disasters to report. Everyone adopted a conventional, comfort-blanket approach.</p>
        <p>Scant coverage was given to one of the day's most eloquent scenes, when Mr. Mandela arrived for a ceremony of reconciliation on Robbin Island, where he had been imprisoned during South Africa's era of apartheid. Carrying a single candle instead of arriving in a shower of fireworks, his gesture went against the grain of the heady celebrations and visual glitter  that characterized the day.</p>
        <p>PBS and the cable news channels, including MSNBC, CNN and Fox News, chased midnight across the time zones from Kiribati on the Pacific to California. But ABC's bigger-is-better strategy got the most advance hype, if only because it is rare for a network anchor to pull an all-nighter. Mr. Jennings, who began at 4:50 a.m. Friday on ABC, was smooth and charming, peering out over Times Square. By the time his stint ended at 4 a.m. yesterday, he seemed like your new best friend.  Throughout Friday he fielded reports: Charles Gibson was wry and smooth in London; Barbara Walters had an unmatchable view of the Eiffel Tower. But Mr. Jennings overstated things when he spoke of the ''sense of awe'' the day inspired; it was perfectly pleasant.</p>
        <p>Or, as Jay Leno told Katie Couric in the early evening on NBC, as she was reporting with Tom Brokaw from outdoors in Times Square, the day's nonevents had been ''very dull. I knew this thing was in trouble when I turned the channel and I saw Peter Jennings interviewing Dame Edna.''</p>
        <p>Well, that may be professional jealousy talking. The spangle-clad Dame Edna (the alter ago of the actor Barry Humphries) spoke for many of us when Mr. Jennings asked how she felt about the millennium. Looking slightly ruffled, the grand Dame answered, ''I'm trying to feel something about it.''</p>
        <p>Of course, no one was meant to watch all day long, and only fanatics needed to start before 6 in the evening Eastern time, when the millennial Ferris wheels began spinning on the Champs-Elysee. Until then, the five-minute hourly highlights that NBC offered through the day, part of its effective, streamlined approach, did just fine.</p>
        <p>Carrying football during the day, CBS saved most of its New Year's coverage for the evening, when it presented the official White House-sponsored celebration on the Mall in Washington. With Will Smith as host, the show offered easy-listening patriotism and middle-of-the-road pop performers, like Luther Vandross and Trisha Yearwood. But the other networks often outdid it with more vibrant performances: NBC had Sting live in its studio; ABC offered a laid-back Harry Connick Jr. performance and Elton John glitz.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of the Washington celebration, a new 20-minute Steven Spielberg film called ''The Unfinished Journey,'' was an anticlimax. It is a graceful montage of the American images from the 1900's arranged by theme, from immigration to war to movies. The live narrators included Bill Clinton reading words from Abraham Lincoln. But the film evoked too many clip montages from the Oscar shows, and John Williams's music is too predictable to be stirring anymore.</p>
        <p>CBS did have the most revealing split screen, though. As midnight arrived in New York and Washington, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani appeared on the right; two seconds later Hillary Rodham Clinton, his likely rival in New York's Senate campaign, turned up on the left. As they say in Paris, city of Ferris wheels: the more things change, the more they stay the same.</p>
        <p>THE YEAR 2000: CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
