<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Only a Gloomy Man Could Have Made Hostility So Funny</title>
    <meta content="02STRU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Doren, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strum, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thurber, James (1894-1961)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Thurber: The Life and Hard Times (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D91638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Only a Gloomy Man Could Have Made Hostility So Funny</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES STRUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strum, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adam Van Doren discusses his PBS television biography of writer James Thurber; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE notion that writers of short, humorous pieces ''are gay of heart and carefree is curiously untrue,'' James Thurber wrote in 1933.</p>
        <p>''To call such persons 'humorists,' a loose-fitting and ugly word, is to miss the nature of their dilemma and the dilemma of their nature,'' he continued. ''The little wheels of their invention are set in motion by the damp hand of melancholy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE notion that writers of short, humorous pieces ''are gay of heart and carefree is curiously untrue,'' James Thurber wrote in 1933.</p>
        <p>''To call such persons 'humorists,' a loose-fitting and ugly word, is to miss the nature of their dilemma and the dilemma of their nature,'' he continued. ''The little wheels of their invention are set in motion by the damp hand of melancholy.''</p>
        <p>Poignant revelation, leavened with wit, from a man whose crystalline prose appeared primarily in The New Yorker for 30 years. A son of Columbus, Ohio, Thurber came to New York in the 1920's (where he would forever mourn his failure to write the great novel -- or any novel) and found himself compelled, instead, to pen satire and scrawl scathing, libidinous cartoons, many of which serve to this day as timeless dispatches from the battle of the sexes.</p>
        <p>''He had no control over his environment,'' said Adam Van Doren, whose hourlong video biography of Thurber (1894-1961)  will be broadcast on Thursday at 10 p.m. on PBS. ''What writing did was give him control. Writing was a way in which he could deal with -- keep -- his sanity. He once said, 'If I couldn't write, I couldn't breathe.' ''</p>
        <p>But he did write, almost to the very end of his life, curiously ignoring the major issues of his time -- the Depression and World War II -- and focusing instead on the fallout from the major issues of his life: his pleasant but ineffectual father; his eccentric, domineering mother (a frustrated actress); and the fools, bureaucrats and lunatics who criss-crossed his consciousness each day. Some read like fables, some like memoirs. All are reports from a two-front conflict: Thurber versus Thurber, and Thurber versus the world.</p>
        <p>In his documentary ''Thurber: The Life and Hard Times,'' Mr. Van Doren seeks to capture his subject from a writer's perspective. He has enlisted, among others, Edward Albee, Roy Blount Jr., Fran Lebowitz, John Updike and his own grandfather the poet and critic Mark Van Doren, a Thurber neighbor in Cornwall, Conn.</p>
        <p>Certainly these other famous writers are fans, even cheerleaders, but they are also witnesses to or commentators on the Thurber who was the Pagliacci of sophisticated American humor. In their recollections, Thurber is the tortured man who struggled with the gradual loss of his sight. The tall, urbane wit who could be a nasty drunk. The Thurber who, in E. B. White's view, gave in to the lure of televised celebrityhood in the 1950's, even as White (Thurber's office mate and early writing mentor) debarked to the insular safety of the Maine coast.</p>
        <p>Adam Van Doren took the title of his documentary from Thurber's first book, ''My Life and Hard Times,'' an ironic name for a collection of stories about Thurber's upbringing and family life in sleepy Columbus before the First World War. Its opening piece is among Thurber's best known, ''The Night the Bed Fell,'' an account of various eccentric relatives and the catastrophes that never quite materialize during one noisy, sleepless night in the Thurber household.</p>
        <p>Dramatis personae: Briggs Beall, a cousin who shares Thurber's bedroom and insists on being awakened every hour at night, lest he die of suffocation. Aunt Sarah Shoaf, ''who never went to bed at night without the fear that a burglar was going to get in and blow chloroform under her door through a tube.'' Aunt Gracie Shoaf, who threw shoes down the hallway at night to keep (nonexistent) burglars at bay. And Grandfather, who was absent that tumultuous night -- a godsend, since his sense of time and place ended with the Civil War.</p>
        <p>''Nothing really ever happens in a Thurber story,'' Mr. Van Doren said. ''It's a tone he helped set in The New Yorker.</p>
        <p>''But what you do get is a wonderfully precise treatise on behavior. Somehow Thurber really grabs people, and they don't always know it. It's sort of like a slow-running stream underground.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lebowitz and Mr. Updike describe coming to Thurber at an early age. Ms. Lebowitz says she was 10 when she discovered ''My Life and Hard Times'' in the library, secreted it behind her geography book in class and eventually was thrown out for laughing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Van Doren, who is 37, says he, too, discovered Thurber in childhood, but in a loftier library, that of his grandfather, who maintained a bookcase in Cornwall filled with volumes written by friends and inscribed to him. Thurber's books were among them, his signature growing larger and shakier as his eyesight failed. Adam Van Doren said the cartoons of the uniquely doughy Thurber people grabbed his interest first; then came the stories.</p>
        <p>''In the cartoons, you can try to make sense of your chaotic world and the world of your own family,'' he said. ''But here's the significant thing about his writing. Thurber is two-pronged. He hits you as a kid, and you might just leave him there. But he also hits you as an adult.''</p>
        <p>A painter of watercolors who shares a studio on West 57th Street with several other artists, Mr. Van Doren said the notion to proceed with a Thurber documentary bubbled to the surface about four years ago.  Along the way he was able to rely on the memories and material of Thurber's only child, Rosemary, who now lives in Michigan and is the product of Thurber's first marriage, to an Ohio State University sweetheart named Althea Adams. They divorced in the early 1930's. His second wife, Helen Wismer, died in 1986.</p>
        <p>From all accounts, it was the failure of Thurber's first marriage and a wrenching separation from his daughter that turned him seriously to drink and to some of the darker, more introspective pieces in his collections.</p>
        <p>''He could be a repository of deep sadness,'' Mr. Van Doren said, ''and he could dig deep into this well. It was down there and he could pull it out and he could level you with it. His desire to create was so intense -- look at the drive to create, to publish when you're blind.''</p>
        <p>The combination of hostility and humor was played out over and over.</p>
        <p>In ''Mr. Preble Gets Rid of His Wife,'' one of more than a dozen scenes in ''A Thurber Carnival'' (the 1960 Broadway review for which Thurber won a special Tony Award), Mr. Preble decides to run off with his stenographer. But first he must do away with Mrs. Preble, a formidable presence who eventually foils her husband's murder plot.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to bury you in the cellar,'' Mr. Preble says. ''I've got my mind made up. I don't know how I could make it any plainer.''</p>
        <p>''Listen,'' Mrs. Preble says, ''will you be satisfied and shut up if I go down in the cellar? Can I have a little peace if I go down in the cellar? Will you let me alone then?''</p>
        <p>''Yes, but you spoil it by taking that attitude,'' Mr. Preble says.</p>
        <p>By and by, he reveals the shovel.</p>
        <p>''What have you got there?'' Mrs. Preble asks.</p>
        <p>''I was going to hit you over the head with this shovel.''</p>
        <p>''You were, huh? Well, get that out of your mind. Do you want to leave a great big clue right here in the middle of everything where the first detective that comes snooping around will find it? Go out in the street and find some piece of iron or something.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Preble, it's all downhill from there.</p>
        <p>In the last 20 years of his life, Thurber, who had lost his left eye in a childhood accident, was reduced to seeing only light and shadow in the right eye. He stopped drawing in 1950. Numerous operations failed to help.</p>
        <p>It was after one of these, in 1941, that Mark Van Doren encountered Thurber, at a party in Martha's Vineyard. Thurber asked for a moment alone with Van Doren, which Van Doren describes on a film clip that was part of a 1961 filmed conversation called ''Dialogues With Archibald MacLeish and Mark Van Doren.''</p>
        <p>''So we went out -- I led him out -- and we found chairs and we sat down, and I looked at him and he was weeping,'' Van Doren said. ''Tears were literally running down his face, and I said, 'What's the matter, Mr. Thurber?' He said: 'This is a punishment. This blindness is a punishment.' I said: 'Why? What for? How could it be a punishment?'</p>
        <p>''He said: 'Well, in my writings I have always dealt with meanness and stupidity. My subject has never been goodness and strength. I have always talked about poor, weak people. I made fun of them. So this is punishment. I have been stricken blind.'</p>
        <p>''Think of a man like that thinking such a thing,'' Van Doren said. ''But he really did think it. Well, I had to think fast myself. And I said what anyone might have said. I said: 'You know, Mr. Thurber, everyone who's ever read you knows that you are for goodness and strength. But you deal with it in reverse, so to speak. You are a satirist and you deal with the opposites of goodness and strength in order to reveal your true belief.' He said I'd saved his life.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
