<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fed Up With Lean Pay, Cabbies Head to Court</title>
    <meta content="02YORK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORKERS &amp; CO."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6DD1238F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fed Up With Lean Pay, Cabbies Head to Court</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eight New Yew City cabdrivers are suing their leasing companies over what they call unfair business practices, including the fees they charge drivers and the conditions under which they reposssess the cabbies' lease-to-own cars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RIZWAN RAJA always considered himself good at keeping track of money. As an accountant in his native Pakistan, he was hired to help audit large companies, calculating their earnings with pen and paper.</p>
        <p>But as the driver of a yellow cab in New York, Mr. Raja said, he watched helplessly as his hard-earned cash slipped away like the ticking of a meter. The industry has bled him for money, he said, and he has decided to sue his former leasing company in Queens Civil Court for $20,700 in damages and lost earnings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RIZWAN RAJA always considered himself good at keeping track of money. As an accountant in his native Pakistan, he was hired to help audit large companies, calculating their earnings with pen and paper.</p>
        <p>But as the driver of a yellow cab in New York, Mr. Raja said, he watched helplessly as his hard-earned cash slipped away like the ticking of a meter. The industry has bled him for money, he said, and he has decided to sue his former leasing company in Queens Civil Court for $20,700 in damages and lost earnings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Raja, 28, is the first of eight taxi drivers who are suing or planning to sue such companies over what they call unfair business practices, including the fees they charge drivers and the conditions under which they repossess the cabbies' lease-to-own cars. Mr. Raja filed his suit early last year. Another driver, Malik Majeed, filed his in State Supreme Court on Dec. 20. The others are expected to bring their suits in various courts before March.</p>
        <p>Industry experts and lawyers say these are among the first instances of drivers, generally considered the weakest figures in the taxi industry, taking legal action against lease companies, commonly known as taxi brokers or medallion agents. Many of the drivers are being represented pro bono in their attempt to identify and hold accountable certain parties within a multilayered business fraught with financial pitfalls.</p>
        <p>''This happened to me because I'm a new person, I'm an immigrant here,'' said Mr. Raja, who moved to New York in 1996. About two-thirds of the city's cabbies come from the Indian subcontinent. ''I didn't know all the laws then, or the people to turn to, or the agencies I can look for if I'm being cheated.''</p>
        <p>For many drivers, the $1.5 billion taxi industry can be a morass of multilevel companies, arcane contracts and medallion owners whose names sometimes remain veiled by bureaucratic paperwork. There are 12,187 medallions -- essentially cab-operating licenses -- that have been auctioned off by the city and are worth an average of $275,000 each.</p>
        <p>Taxi brokers lease a medallion from its owner and then rent it to a driver. Sometimes the broker and medallion owner are two separate companies with the same owners. The brokers charge drivers an average of $650 to $750 a week for a medallion and around $250 per week for a cab, which the driver usually gets to own after about two and a half years.</p>
        <p>This system has its roots in the 1970's, after many of the city's large garage fleets, for whom taxi drivers worked as employees on commission, shut down because of the recession and a move to unionize drivers, said Bruce Schaller, an industry consultant and a former policy analyst with the city's Taxi and Limousine Commission. The current setup, with the drivers working as independent contractors, emerged after the medallions from those fleets entered the marketplace.</p>
        <p>BUT for years, some drivers have complained that their leases have unforgiving terms. Mr. Schaller said the high cost of medallions  often leads brokers to insist on cab-leasing contracts that put drivers at a disadvantage. Add to this the immigrant drivers' limited economic clout, he said, and what you often get are contracts that allow a leasing company to repossess a car if the driver is even a single day late with a payment.</p>
        <p>''It's legal because that's what the lease agreement says,'' Mr. Schaller said. ''But it's certainly not appropriate or a good way of doing business.''</p>
        <p>The drivers' lawsuits cover a variety of issues. In the complaint filed in his case  against a leasing company called Tri Star Operating, for example, Mr. Raja claims that Tri Star seized his lease-to-own cab in September 1998, informing him that the medallion he was driving under had been sold. Tri Star, according to the complaint, informed Mr. Raja that he would have to drive a replacement car until the original one got a new medallion.</p>
        <p>The complaint says Tri Star violated the lease agreement by taking back the original cab and medallion, an action that would result in Mr. Raja having to pay ''considerable amounts of money'' so that his original car could pass an inspection required by the Taxi and Limousine Commission for all cabs getting a new medallion. In his complaint, Mr. Raja said that a similar situation had happened to him before at Tri Star.</p>
        <p>But Richard R. Rio, a lawyer for Tri Star, says that it is customary to have medallions sold in the industry, and that the broker had a right to take the original cab off the road temporarily as long as Mr. Raja was given a replacement. As for re-inspection costs, ''Tri Star was willing to do everything for him to get his old car re-hacked,'' Mr. Rio said. If Tri Star mistreated drivers, he added, ''they would be out of business.''</p>
        <p>In an answer filed with the court, Tri Star asked to have the suit dismissed and countersued the cabbie, saying Mr. Raja defaulted on his payments, failed to repair the vehicle and didn't pay tickets.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the New York Taxi Workers Alliance, an 1,800-member drivers' advocacy group, has been helping the other six disgruntled cabbies with their lawsuits. ''You would think that an industry that is publicly scrutinized and regulated would not have these kinds of violations,'' said Bhairavi Desai, the organizer of the group.</p>
        <p>Ms. Desai said that drivers are often reluctant to complain to public agencies because they perceive those groups to be hostile. That perception has grown with rules adopted in 1998 which, in part, set stiffer fines and higher insurance premiums for cabbies.</p>
        <p>The Taxi and Limousine Commission rarely receives driver complaints against brokers, according to Allan J. Fromberg, a department spokesman. He added that the disputes often involve contractual disagreements that are best settled in court.</p>
        <p>Such was the advice that one of the other cabbies planning to sue, Vivian Borges, said she received from the commission when she complained about her taxi broker. Ms. Borges became a cabbie to prove to her father, a driver of 36 years, that she, too, could succeed in the business.</p>
        <p>Instead, she said, after paying King Brokerage in Brooklyn almost $120,000 toward a medallion and a car for two and a half years, the company repossessed her cab in November 1998. During that time, she said, she often worked 100-hour weeks but averaged only $100 a week in profits. She said the company overcharged her by $16,000 and repossessed the cab because she had refused to sign another financing agreement.</p>
        <p>''What they did to me, they ripped my heart out,'' Ms. Borges said. ''I had my blood, sweat and tears in that car.''</p>
        <p>Nadeem Waeen, Ms. Borges's lawyer, said he planned to file a suit this month.</p>
        <p>''Let her take me to court,'' said Angel Oswald, who owns King Brokerage. ''I've got nothing to hide.'' He said he repossessed the cab because Ms. Borges owed him $10,000 in back payments.</p>
        <p>As for Ms. Borges' car, he said simply that ''it's back on the street.''</p>
        <p>NEW YORKERS &amp; CO.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
