<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Helping Orphan Settle Into a New Home</title>
    <meta content="02NEED$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165641"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE NEEDIEST CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labarge, Allison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peebles, Verna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Branch, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5D91138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Helping Orphan Settle Into a New Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLISON LABARGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labarge, Allison</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on how New York Times Neediest Cases Fund is helping Verna Peebles raise her 7-year-old grandnephew Steven Branch, who was born addicted to drugs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As she lay in bed dying of cancer, Verna Peebles's sister asked for one last thing: that Ms. Peebles raise her 7-year-old grandson.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peebles, 58, had already raised four children of her own -- her oldest is 38, her youngest 28 -- but on Dec. 9, 1998, she waited for the car that would bring Steven Branch, her grandnephew,  from Norfolk, Va., to her home in the Bedford-Stuyvesant section of Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As she lay in bed dying of cancer, Verna Peebles's sister asked for one last thing: that Ms. Peebles raise her 7-year-old grandson.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peebles, 58, had already raised four children of her own -- her oldest is 38, her youngest 28 -- but on Dec. 9, 1998, she waited for the car that would bring Steven Branch, her grandnephew,  from Norfolk, Va., to her home in the Bedford-Stuyvesant section of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''The night he came, he cried a lot,'' Ms. Peebles said in a recent interview. ''He wanted to come, but then he didn't want to come.''</p>
        <p>Steven's grandmother had raised him since he was only a few months old. His mother had dropped him off one day for a few hours of baby-sitting, but had never come back to pick him up.</p>
        <p>When Steven arrived in New York, Ms. Peebles showed him some sights of the city, like downtown Brooklyn, Macy's and Grand Central Terminal. Like many boys his age, he was fascinated by the way people travel in New York. ''I love the city,'' he said. ''It has buses and trains.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Peebles enrolled him in school and set about getting to know her grandnephew. ''It was a big change,'' she said. ''Before, I didn't really have anything to do. But it was a good change.''</p>
        <p>But problems began to surface. Born addicted to crack cocaine, Steven was often jumpy, suffered from severe mood swings and banged his head at night.</p>
        <p>His teacher began calling daily, saying that Steven acted out in class and cursed at his fellow students. ''She told me I had my hands full,'' Ms. Peebles said, ''but I knew that.''</p>
        <p>The teacher put Ms. Peebles in touch with the Bedford-Stuyvesant Family Center, one of two such centers run by the Brooklyn Bureau of Community Service. The Brooklyn Bureau is one of the seven local charities supported by the New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Laurel Stanley Glynn, a social worker at the center, set up family therapy sessions for Steven and Ms. Peebles to see how they were relating to each other and how Steven's entry into Ms. Peebles's life was affecting her.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peebles says she values the sessions, which have helped her to understand the problems associated with children born addicted to drugs and have given her someone to talk to about her grandnephew.</p>
        <p>In individual sessions, Ms. Glynn has Steven use pictures and puppets to act out his feelings. ''The focus there is on his loss and grief,'' Ms. Glynn said. ''Children are better able to vocalize and get their feelings out in play therapy.''</p>
        <p>The arrival of her grandnephew had also put a financial strain on Ms. Peebles, whose only source of income is federal Supplemental Security Income, a form of assistance for poor Americans with disabilities. The family center used $400 out of money it received from the Neediest Cases Fund to buy Steven some school clothes, a winter jacket, new shoes and a few toys.</p>
        <p>Steven had begun to show signs of improvement at school, but Ms. Glynn suspected that his acting out was a result of his being placed in an inappropriate grade. Steven had not attended school regularly in Virginia, and although he could not read or write, he had been assigned to the second grade.</p>
        <p>''He really didn't understand what was going on,'' Ms. Glynn said. ''The material was way above his head.''</p>
        <p>Testing by the Board of Education revealed that Steven's skill level was that of a kindergartner. The school then moved him to special-education classes, and the family center provided him with tutoring.</p>
        <p>At home, Ms. Peebles helps Steven practice writing the alphabet during her own tutoring sessions with him, but takes time out for breaks. ''We just have fun,'' she said, laughing. ''Sometimes, you'd think there were three or four people in the house.''</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to P.O. Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087, or any of these  organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK  Church Street Station, P.O. Box 4100, New York, N.Y. 10261-4100</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Donations may be made with a credit card online, courtesy of the Qpass digital commerce service, at www.nytimes.com/neediest. Online donors receive a free trial subscription to the crossword puzzle of The New York Times on the Web.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on Federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded: $3,428,006.94  Recorded Thursday: $164,651.29</p>
        <p>Total: $3,592,658.23</p>
        <p>THE NEEDIEST CASES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
