<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leagues Under the Sea</title>
    <meta content="Y02LEA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSPECTIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Twentieth Century</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischer, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5D71338F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1381" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leagues Under the Sea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FISCHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischer, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Failed sports leagues of 20th century recalled; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not all professional sports leagues formed in the past 100 years made it to the next. While the Women's National Basketball Association has survived three seasons, its rival, the American Basketball League, did not. The sports landscape has been littered with ignominious moments from defunct leagues gone by.</p>
        <p>Federal League, 1914-15</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not all professional sports leagues formed in the past 100 years made it to the next. While the Women's National Basketball Association has survived three seasons, its rival, the American Basketball League, did not. The sports landscape has been littered with ignominious moments from defunct leagues gone by.</p>
        <p>Federal League, 1914-15</p>
        <p>The Indianapolis Hoosiers, paced by Benny Kauff's league-leading .370 batting average, captured the Federal League flag in 1914. The Hoosiers became the Newark Peps in 1915, the only major league baseball pennant-winner to move to a new city the following year.</p>
        <p>American Professional Football Association, 1920-22</p>
        <p>In its first year the league had two rival football teams in Chicago: the Cardinals and the Tigers. The owners knew there were only enough fans to support one team, so they decided to play a game against each other with the provision that the loser had to leave the city. Only one touchdown was scored that day, by Cardinals quarterback Paddy Driscoll. The Cards -- forerunners of the National Football League's Arizona Cardinals -- won, 6-3, and the Tigers left town.</p>
        <p>American Football League, 1926-27</p>
        <p>In 1925, the National Football League got its first superstar when Red Grange, the Galloping Ghost, signed with the Chicago Bears. The next season, Grange's manager, C. C. (Cash and Carry) Pyle, wanted the Bears to increase the player's pay. When the Bears' owner, George Halas, refused, Pyle formed the American Football League with Grange and his team, the New York Yankees, as its main attraction. The war between the leagues ended in 1927 when Grange caught his cleats in the grass and ruined his knee. Without its superstar, the A.F.L. folded.</p>
        <p>American Basketball League, 1925-31</p>
        <p>After the Original Celtics had won the A.B.L. title in 1927 and 1928, officials decided the team was too good for the league. They broke up the squad and sent the players to different teams. Nat Holman and George (Horse) Haggerty, both former Celtics, found themselves on opposing teams in a tight game. With seconds left, Haggerty had the ball. Then he heard someone call, ''Hey, Horse!'' It was Holman. Without thinking, Haggerty threw the ball to his old teammate. Holman took the pass and scored an easy bucket, winning the game.</p>
        <p>All-America Football Conference, 1946-49</p>
        <p>In 1946 two African-American players, Woody Strode and Kenny Washington, signed to play with the Los Angeles Rams of the N.F.L. Bill Willis, a fellow African-American, wanted to play pro football, too, but his only offer was a tryout with the Montreal Alouettes of the Canadian Football League.</p>
        <p>While traveling to the Alouettes' training camp, Willis stopped to visit his former college coach, Paul Brown, then coach of the Cleveland Browns of the newly formed A.A.F.C. Brown persuaded Willis to practice with his team. Willis was so impressive, Brown signed him immediately. Nine days later, presumably because Brown thought Willis would need a black roommate on road trips, the team signed Marion Motley. The Browns won all four A.A.F.C. championships and then, after joining the N.F.L., won its 1950 title.</p>
        <p>National Basketball League, 1937-49</p>
        <p>Chuck Connors, a 6-foot-5-inch forward for the Celtics, splintered a wooden backboard in Boston Arena during warmups with the Chicago Stags in 1946. A visiting rodeo provided a replacement backboard so the game could be played. Connors would go on to star in the TV series ''The Rifleman,'' prompting one former teammate to say, ''He went from being the worst shot in the East to the best shot in the West.''</p>
        <p>American Basketball Association, 1967-76</p>
        <p>The Dallas Chaparrals' owner, Roland Speth, traveled alone to the expansion draft in New York in 1967 and chose players according to a list provided by team scouts. What Speth did not realize was that the players were listed alphabetically, not by talent. So Jim Burns of Northwestern was drafted ahead of a star player from Kentucky named Pat Riley.</p>
        <p>The San Diego Conquistadors' head coach, Wilt Chamberlain, skipped three games in the 1973-74 season, one so that he could attend a book signing of his autobiography and two for unknown reasons. San Diego finished 37-47.</p>
        <p>World Hockey Association, 1972-79</p>
        <p>The Calgary Broncos' general manager, Scotty Munro, selected the Soviet premier, Aleksei Kosygin, in the initial free-agent draft. Neither the Broncos, who were out of money, nor Kosygin played a game in the W.H.A.</p>
        <p>World Football League, 1974-75</p>
        <p>The Memphis Southmen had a grizzly bear cub as their mascot. During one game, the cub playfully chewed through the insulation of a wire lying on the ground; when he got to the core he gave himself a terrific shock that threw him over on his back and shorted out the stadium scoreboard for 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>The week before the 1975 season finale, the Hawaiians, who played in Honolulu, asked their players to take pay cuts to save the franchise. Both quarterbacks refused and quit. Two days before the game, the team recruited two replacements: Milt Holt, who had played at Harvard, and Jim Fassel, who had been a player-coach for the Hawaiians in their first year. Holt was taken from a desk job at Honolulu City Hall, and Fassel, now the head coach of the Giants, had been driving a truck in Los Angeles. The Hawaiians lost to the Southern California Sun, 26-7.</p>
        <p>World Team Tennis, 1974-79</p>
        <p>Vitas Gerulaitis, star player for the Pittsburgh Triangles in 1974, ordered the public-address announcer at the Civic Arena to invite the crowd of nearly 11,000 to proceed from a match to his 20th birthday observance at a nearby hotel. Gerulaitis had reserved the top floor. The result: heavy partying and at least one broken bathtub.</p>
        <p>Jimmy Connors, star of the Baltimore Banners, wondering why his team was called the Banners: ''Who's Francis Scott Key? I thought we were named after some guy named Banner.''</p>
        <p>In 1979, though not because of the Connors comment, the W.T.T. disbanded. It re-formed in 1981 and still exists, but without the Banners or the big-name stars.</p>
        <p>North American Soccer League, 1968-84</p>
        <p>The Washington Diplomats were affectionately referred to by headline writers in the 1970's as the Dips. No shorthand nickname was used for the Hartford Bicentennials, who would have been known as the the Bis.</p>
        <p>A game between the Seattle Sounders and the Tulsa Roughnecks in 1980 included 70 fouls, two ejections and five yellow cards. After the Sounders had won in a shootout, Seattle goaltender Jack Brand went after the Tulsa general manager, Noel Lemon. Brand, his fists clenched, was pulled away by players from both teams as fans and police officers poured onto the field.</p>
        <p>Women's Basketball League, 1978-81</p>
        <p>The Iowa Cornets led the league in attendance for two seasons, but like 10 of the original 18 franchises, the team folded in 1981. Among the reasons was the owner George Nissen's $1 million investment in ''Dribble,'' a movie starring Pete Maravich and featuring several Cornets, which was never released.</p>
        <p>Major Indoor Soccer League, 1979-91</p>
        <p>Kevin Slaten of the St. Louis Steamers was thrown out of a 1981 playoff game for trying to punch a player from the other team. Slaten was the Steamers' announcer.</p>
        <p>United States Football League, 1983-85</p>
        <p>After Coach George Allen's Chicago Blitz had lost, 21-15, to the Boston Breakers in a meeting of contenders for the league's lone wild-card spot in 1983, Allen threatened to cut the backup quarterback Tom Rozantz for enjoying himself on the plane ride home. At 30,000 feet, Allen said, ''Anybody who isn't dedicated can leave now.''</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles Express brought in John Hadl as head coach in 1984 to mentor the rookie quarterback Steve Young. The year before, Hadl had been John Elway's quarterback coach in Elway's rookie season with the Denver Broncos. Hadl's assessment: ''Elway will be the greatest drop-back passer in the game. He throws better than anybody except maybe Namath. Steve has a tendency to scramble -- make a big play on his own. You can't go wrong with either one.''</p>
        <p>PERSPECTIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
