<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What 72 Artists Figured Out About Boxes Measuring 1 by 1 by 1</title>
    <meta content="02ART.$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greenwich Arts Council (Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D71F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What 72 Artists Figured Out About Boxes Measuring 1 by 1 by 1</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews Visions of the Millennium, exhibition works by 72 artists at Greenwich Arts Council in Greenwich, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN many ways the millennium is an especially communal celebration, but as with every New Year's, there is room for individual reflection and prognostication about what lies ahead. At the gallery of the Greenwich Arts Council in Greenwich, both possibilities are entertained.</p>
        <p>''Visions of the Millennium'' is a show, a gathering really, of 72 boxes each measuring one foot in all dimensions. Seventy-two artists were asked to make a box conforming to this size with the millennium as its theme. While the format stays constant, what's in, or in some cases on, the box is personal -- but not completely. Part of the enjoyment of this uneven display is the search for common interpretations of the theme.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN many ways the millennium is an especially communal celebration, but as with every New Year's, there is room for individual reflection and prognostication about what lies ahead. At the gallery of the Greenwich Arts Council in Greenwich, both possibilities are entertained.</p>
        <p>''Visions of the Millennium'' is a show, a gathering really, of 72 boxes each measuring one foot in all dimensions. Seventy-two artists were asked to make a box conforming to this size with the millennium as its theme. While the format stays constant, what's in, or in some cases on, the box is personal -- but not completely. Part of the enjoyment of this uneven display is the search for common interpretations of the theme.</p>
        <p>There are a lot of references to nature -- embodied in a lot of birds and butterflies. Dana Milton, perhaps taking a cue from Joseph Cornell, has created a densely packed box featuring a few feathers, titled ''Bird Dream of the New Millennium.'' Perhaps the bird in question is freeing itself from the chaos and clutter of the past. A thick border of fluffy white feathers surrounds the facade of Ellen Colcord's ''Incubation,'' but it looks like the eggs inside are stone.</p>
        <p>The butterfly in Leslie Mueller's ''Butterfly Caught in Time'' is in the center of a wire mesh cage, while Ursula E. Mathias confounds biology with a work called ''Transformation'' in which butterflies are emerging from eggshells. She's prompted not by an interest in bio-technology but with age-old symbols: the egg means birth and the butterfly transformation.</p>
        <p>There was a time when most Americans envisioned the 21st century as a triumph of streamlining. Some pieces embody that dubious notion. Robert Perless's ''Light Bath,'' looking rather like the floor in a discotheque, shines with colored light. Most Buck Rogers-like, at least in its title, is ''Portal to the Cosmic Future,'' by David Horton. The opposite of Ms. Colcord's feathers, Mr. Horton's piece is framed with a wide border of metal; the box is painted gray but the only image is a conical shape topped by a propeller, the kind that might be on a beanie. Kendal Kennedy's ''Timeline'' is not an enclosed box but rather a copper spiral with turns that are more angular than round. Shadows cast by the wire complete the box shape.</p>
        <p>Just as in the 20th century, the palpable future belongs to children. Nina Bentley makes a somewhat creepy comment on this with ''Millennial Doubts/Bio-Babies,'' a plexiglass box filled with a lot of glass tubes, and pink dolls of different sizes who seem as buoyant as cherubs, unaware they are experiments. And Heidi Bassett Blair's screen and speakers carry pictures and voices of exuberant children.</p>
        <p>In the exhibition the past gets just about equal emphasis with the future. Mireille Lemarchand's ''Timeless'' is a generic terra cotta head in an open cube. ''Tabernacle (early 21st C),'' by Alica Carla Pennisi, is a box given a few gilded gables to look like a medieval reliquary. But inside it's a medicine cabinet, stocked with the kind of over-the-counter pain relievers Americans have used for decades. The outline of a neolithic fertility goddess adorns one of the outer sides of Lori Don Levan's box with the imposing title ''Homage to Goddess: A Self-Portrait for the New Millennium.'' Myriad starfish approach the cut-out of a woman who is Ms. Levan's maternal figure.</p>
        <p>Some mystical works should be anticipated and there are many more than those to be summarized.  ''Mandola II,'' by Patricia Miranda, features a plaster hand in gold with the tops of the fingers broken off; an almond shape outlined in red is on the palm, like a stigmata.</p>
        <p>The engaging part of Natasha Cohen's ''Eye of the Beholder'' is the pair of garden trowels positioned like portals on the front of the box. Inside, a thicket of wire and a ground covering of pearls leads to a drawing of an eye in glass. But it's not a reflection of the viewer's eye, so the meaning of Ms. Cohen's title remains arcane.</p>
        <p>Some boxes are novel supports on which an artist can make a many-sided painting. The untitled work by Pouran Jinchi has a lively red shape like a curling ribbon traveling across several of its many faces. The camellias on the eponymously named corrugated cardboard box by Jee-Yeon Koo are elegantly painted and a nice foil to the humble material of the box itself.</p>
        <p>Images based on the poetry of Yeats decorate Anne Rockwell's ''And Louder Sing'' (and one could have a worse guide to the period ahead than Yeats). Gamal Eleish slit the sides of his box and splayed it so that it becomes a Christian cross; on it are scenes that might have been inspired by Blake. Constance Pierce uses her box as a means of displaying her sketchbooks.</p>
        <p>Unconventional presentations of the box itself include Carol Dixon's ''Recycle: Will History Repeat Itself?'' It is placed so the viewer looks down on it; Ms. Dixon has made the equivalent of a grocery box filled with recyclable goods. Lori A. Kent constructed her solid cube, ''Black and White Thinking,'' by alternating slabs painted black and white.</p>
        <p>The most ingenious use of the given format is Arthur Burke's ''Deck Illusion.'' The chief content is playing cards. If viewers position themselves at the edge of the box, a nifty optical illusion occurs that could only be done with mirrors.</p>
        <p>The millennium statement that jibes most closely with this writer's is ''Same As It Ever Was,'' by David Newton. Mr. Newton's box is displayed like a altarpiece, and on each is painted in pale colors an every day event, including going shopping in the rain. Mr. Newton isn't being cynical when he predicts sameness. He paints evocatively, so that shopping in the rain seems like a marvelous event.</p>
        <p>''Visions of the Millennium'' is at Greenwich Arts Center Gallery through Jan. 9.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
