<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fantasy and the Fact Of New Stock Offerings</title>
    <meta content="02STRA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STRATEGIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulbert, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Strategies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7DB1238F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fantasy and the Fact Of New Stock Offerings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK HULBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulbert, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Hulbert (Strategies) article discusses initial public offerings (IPO's); says rarely have investor expectations diverged as much from reality as they do now with regard to IPO's; says reality of such offerings is that even if you are lucky enough to be among few allowed to participate in the offering at its opening, odds are slim of being able to double or triple your money on offering day, and even if you can, chances are less favorable that stock will continue to perform well (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to initial public offerings, rarely have investor expectations diverged as much from reality as they do now.</p>
        <p>The fantasy, of course, is that you can get rich quickly -- that all you have to do is buy a new issue at the offering price and you have it made.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to initial public offerings, rarely have investor expectations diverged as much from reality as they do now.</p>
        <p>The fantasy, of course, is that you can get rich quickly -- that all you have to do is buy a new issue at the offering price and you have it made.</p>
        <p>In this dream, the shares will double, triple or more on the day the company goes public, as they did in early December for VA Linux Systems. Better yet, the stock's potential after that first day is even larger -- as has been the case with Cisco Systems, prime fodder for the fantasy. It is up some 84,000 percent since it went public in 1990.</p>
        <p>But it is time for a dose of reality. Assuming you are lucky enough to be among the few allowed to participate in the offering at its opening, the odds are still slim of being able to double or triple your money on the offering day. And even if you can, the chances are even less favorable that the stock will continue to perform well.</p>
        <p>Consider the average first-day premium on a new issue -- that is, the amount that it rises above its offering price during its first day of trading. Historically, that premium has been quite modest, according to Jay Ritter, a finance professor at the University of Florida. During the 1970's and 1980's, he found, it averaged just 6 percent.</p>
        <p>And though the average first-day premium has risen somewhat in the 1990's, it is still a far cry from the investor fantasy: from 1990 through 1999, according to Professor Ritter, it averaged just 21 percent.</p>
        <p>But that's not all that's wrong with the fantasy. Over their first few months of trading, as many new issues decline in price as rise, he finds. Indeed, 57 percent of the new issues in 1998 were trading below their offering prices on Dec. 31 of that year. Nor was 1998 unique. The average for each of the two previous years was close to 50 percent.</p>
        <p>The source of the fantasy isn't hard to figure. During 1999, new issues performed far better, on average, than in any year since 1975.</p>
        <p>The average first-day premium of new issues during 1999 was 70 percent, nearly five times the average for the rest of the the 1990's. Furthermore, as of Dec. 22, according to Professor Ritter, just 27 percent of the year's new issues were trading below their offering prices, compared with about 50 percent for previous years.</p>
        <p>Clearly, last year was the exception that has led many investors to forget the rule.</p>
        <p>If you still believe that the 1999 results will become the norm, remember that all this data assumes that investors are allowed to buy into each new issue at its initial offering price. That is unrealistic. So consider what would have happened if an investor had bought each of the new issues of 1999 at the closing price on its first trading day -- in contrast to its offering price. His return would have been 81 percent as of Dec. 28 -- still impressive, but less than half the 199 percent he would have made from buying at the offering price.</p>
        <p>Moreover, more than half the time, an investor would have done better last year buying an unmanaged Nasdaq composite index fund than buying an initial public offering at the close of the first day of trading.</p>
        <p>Professor Ritter notes another reason that the biggest new issues of 1999 are unlikely to keep producing huge percentage gains: today's new stocks tend to have far larger market capitalizations from Day One -- meaning that they often don't have as much room to grow. For example, Cisco had a market cap of just $300 million at the end of its first day of trading. By contrast, 14 of the nearly 500 new issues last year had market caps of more than $3 billion after their first day of trading, accounting for more than half the total initial market capitalization.</p>
        <p>I'm willing to bet that these recent issues won't produce gains over the next decade anywhere close to 84,000 percent.</p>
        <p>STRATEGIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
