<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Friends Divorce, A Look Within</title>
    <meta content="02COLM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Felicia R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DC1438F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Friends Divorce, A Look Within</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Felicia R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on coping with divorce of best friends; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''ARE you sitting down?'' my friend asked over the telephone. She had some bad news, the kind that didn't qualify as tragedy but was more serious than gossip. I sat. She spoke. Not one, not two, but three couples we know were divorcing, she said.</p>
        <p>Juicy details were forthcoming on some of the uncouplings but the one that just made us sad involved a woman I have known for almost 20 years. She and her husband are part of a network of friends, mostly journalists, who have worked in the same cities over the years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''ARE you sitting down?'' my friend asked over the telephone. She had some bad news, the kind that didn't qualify as tragedy but was more serious than gossip. I sat. She spoke. Not one, not two, but three couples we know were divorcing, she said.</p>
        <p>Juicy details were forthcoming on some of the uncouplings but the one that just made us sad involved a woman I have known for almost 20 years. She and her husband are part of a network of friends, mostly journalists, who have worked in the same cities over the years.</p>
        <p>This group -- generally lucky, hard-working and living out the promises of our fancy educations and talents -- shares not just memories but has the kind of closeness that comes with living in the world at the same time and being the same age: owning the same records (not CD's), remembering the same TV commercials, feeling fondness for the same silly fashions, like bell bottoms and platform shoes the first time around.</p>
        <p>When my now-divorcing friends met, fell in love and threw themselves an incredible wedding in the Caribbean in the early 90's, it seemed both a fairy tale and a birthright. They had a daughter the year before we had a son. They gambled with their career choices and the pieces fell in place.</p>
        <p>Through it all, they were good friends to each other and their other friends. Now it was over.</p>
        <p>The millennium madness has made us all introspective about time and its meanings. In my own little world, with people seemingly divorcing right and left, I am struck anew by how one of the most potent measures of the passage of time is the lives of our friends.</p>
        <p>Who they love, their marriages, their children, their houses, are a running snapshot of the years, a continuing soap opera against which we measure our own passions, triumphs and defeats.</p>
        <p>This seems to be our divorce epoch, our sojourn into middle age and the recognition that things often don't turn out as we had hoped. Still, despite how glaringly common divorce is, it feels strange and hurtful when it happens to your friends. This act of putting asunder is at once powerfully private and public.</p>
        <p>Do you call and ask for details? Do you offer condolences or congratulations? Do you tell them how much their breakup hurts you? No one has easy answers.</p>
        <p>''Some divorces need to happen,'' one friend said. ''I don't think it's necessarily sad. This is the stage in life where we are now.''</p>
        <p>But as another friend pointed out: ''In New York, when we're so far from family, when your friends divorce it's like a divorce in the family. You count on these people. You expect some things to last and they don't.''</p>
        <p>Diane M. Churchill, a psychotherapist with a private practice in the West Village, assured me that feelings of confusion are common when people hear that friends are divorcing.</p>
        <p>Many people expect others to stick it out, she said, a sort of dogged determination that is the glue that keeps a lot of things together in this society.</p>
        <p>On another level, she said, there can be a kind of envy of the newfound freedom of divorcing couples, even though most people want their own relationships to work. And the reality that a friend's marriage can falter, she said, is a reminder that ours can, too.</p>
        <p>''When we hear someone has fallen off the path we feel betrayed in the struggle; the person has let us down,'' Ms. Churchill said. ''It projects on someone else our internal struggles with responsibility.</p>
        <p>''There is a copycat phenomenon,'' she said of my observation that divorces -- like marriages and babies -- tend to come in waves. ''We see possibilities, doors that we can step through. Sometimes we do.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Doris Brothers, a psychoanalyst with a practice on the Upper West Side, said there was no prevailing social etiquette for divorce. How could there be, she said, given that each relationship and each breakup is so different. People want details, she said, because they want to make sense of the uncertainty and the trauma.</p>
        <p>''It's often tempting in a situation like this to create a good guy and a bad guy,'' she said of the common phenomenon of taking sides in a divorce. ''If you hang on to those simplicities it is a way of dealing with uncertainty.''</p>
        <p>I know, I know. If only my friend's husband had absconded with with a 23-year-old model. If only she had put her career ahead of the family or run her credit cards to the max.</p>
        <p>There was nothing like that, of course. Just the same soggy story of people deciding that they were more different than alike and that they needed different things from life.</p>
        <p>''Everything turns out to be difficult,'' Ms. Churchill said. ''There are periods of joy but everything in life turns out to be more difficult than we thought. There's something about our generation, baby boomers, that was not prepared for difficulty.''</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
