<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arnold Stang, the Top Cat of New Canaan</title>
    <meta content="02STAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stang, Arnold</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moss, Marven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4D61F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1037" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arnold Stang, the Top Cat of New Canaan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARVEN MOSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moss, Marven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of 74-year-old comedian Arnold Stang, resident of New Canaan, Conn, who comments on his work in film, television and radio over past six decades; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REMEMBER Arnold Stang, the impish, goggle-eyed comedian with the exuberant delivery and a lisp so thick he seemed to spritz? Or how about the cartoon character Top Cat? Mr. Stang did the voice.</p>
        <p>At 74, and at an elfin 110 pounds on a 5-foot-3 frame, Mr. Stang is a familiar figure in New Canaan, especially around the post office in the center of town, covering the three miles between his home and town with a lope that belies his age. He said he walks for the exercise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REMEMBER Arnold Stang, the impish, goggle-eyed comedian with the exuberant delivery and a lisp so thick he seemed to spritz? Or how about the cartoon character Top Cat? Mr. Stang did the voice.</p>
        <p>At 74, and at an elfin 110 pounds on a 5-foot-3 frame, Mr. Stang is a familiar figure in New Canaan, especially around the post office in the center of town, covering the three miles between his home and town with a lope that belies his age. He said he walks for the exercise.</p>
        <p>He still appears in cameos on TV and his brash and quirky nasality can be heard in reruns of ''Top Cat.'' He also has done television commercials for clients as diverse as AT&amp;T and Burger King.</p>
        <p>His latest voice-over work is as several characters in two episodes of ''Courage the Cowardly Dog'' on the Cartoon Network, a cartoon about a dog who protects an elderly couple.</p>
        <p>Risa Neuwirth, associate producer for Stretch Films in New York, worked with Mr. Stang on the episodes.</p>
        <p>''We were simply honored to have him with us,'' she said. ''He lends so much to characterization. His comic timing and his delivery are impeccable, and he obviously knows what he is doing.''</p>
        <p>In six decades of film, television and radio, Mr. Stang has worked as a sidekick to many entertainment icons including Al Jolson, Fanny Brice and the Marx Brothers, Jack Benny, Fred Allen, Lucille Ball, Frank Sinatra, Milton Berle, Bob Hope and Bill Cosby.</p>
        <p>As a teenage actor in Hollywood, Mr. Stang was tutored by Victor Mature, who died early last year, and is recalled by Mr. Stang as ''not at all like the gruff, hard-bitten personalities'' Mr. Mature portrayed in films such as ''Demetrius and the Gladiators.'' In Chelsea, Mass., where Mr. Stang grew up, his mother got weekly reports on her son's well-being in letters from Rita Hayworth, who was seeing Mr. Mature at the time.</p>
        <p>Of all his roles, Mr. Stang may best be recalled as Francis, the obnoxious, wisecracking stagehand on Mr. Berle's TV show in the 1950's, a nebbish with a bite.</p>
        <p>''To counter Berle, the blowhard and egomaniac,'' Mr. Stang explained, ''my character was raffish, unsophisticated and caustic, contrived to cut him off at the ankles.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Berle said that Mr. Stang was ''a dependable, multifaceted actor with a one-of-a-kind delivery that belies a sharp intellect.''</p>
        <p>''Stang's face and voice are unmistakable,'' Mr. Berle said. ''But he has been unheralded as a performer. Like many superb character actors, he has never been properly acclaimed for his talent.</p>
        <p>''Stang never deviates from his character,'' he explained. ''On my old show, we reversed roles. He heckled me. He delivered the put-downs. I was the straight man. It always worked. A comedian always knows how to feed someone else the lines.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Berle said Mr. Stang was especially adept at the challenges of live television.</p>
        <p>''Stang was clever at masking a fluff or a blooper,'' Mr. Berle said. ''Remember this was in the era of live TV, before cue cards or teleprompters. If you blew a line, you lived with it. It never fazed Stang. He could improvise and allow you to ad lib yourself back into the script.</p>
        <p>''Arnold knows comedy forwards and backwards. O.K.,'' Berle added, unable to resist his own opening, ''maybe backwards isn't so good.''</p>
        <p>His whimsical caricatures in the same television genre also appeared in ''December Bride,'' ''The Goldbergs'' and the ''Great Talent Hunt,'' a forerunner to ''The Gong Show'' that Mr. Stang said lost its sponsor after only one week when the host, Henry Morgan, joked that Life Savers was cheating the public by drilling holes in its candy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stang's lisp is a theatrical affectation. And his oeuvre isn't restricted to comedy. He achieved acclaim in dramatic portrayals such as the character of Sparrow with Mr. Sinatra and Kim Novak in ''The Man With The Golden Arm,'' a 1956 movie about drug addiction.</p>
        <p>''Other people find what I do amusing,'' Mr. Stang said over coffee at Starbuck's on Elm Street in New Canaan. ''I approach every part, comedic or otherwise, as a dramatic role. My preparation is always serious. In my early years in radio, I discovered comedy was more lucrative for me. But I played sensitive characters and menacing murderers, too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stang moved to Greenwich from Los Angeles about 30 years ago to be closer to his work in New York, and went to New Canaan in 1980.</p>
        <p>''New Canaan has a relaxed beauty that we enjoy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The funniest performer Mr. Stang ever saw?</p>
        <p>''It would be disloyal of me to single out one comedian from among all those with whom I've worked. But I will say the warmest person was Jack Benny. He exuded gentleness. Anyone could talk to him.</p>
        <p>''The most brilliant was Fred Allen. He was supremely gifted. Radio was his metier. TV was not his medium. He called it 'chewing gum for the eyes.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stang described radio as far more challenging than television. ''Radio depends on your intelligence,'' he said. ''You paint the sets, you design the costumes, you create the ambience. Someone once said, and I agree, that 'TV has dumbed down America and made tastes much coarser.' ''</p>
        <p>Who makes Mr. Stang laugh today?</p>
        <p>''Charlie Chaplin,'' he said. ''My wife tells me the only time I laugh out loud is when I watch the old silent movie comedians.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stang's wife, JoAnne, is a writer who has done profiles of balky personalities like Mr. Sinatra, Marlon Brando, Woody Allen, Tennessee Williams and Stanley Kubrick.</p>
        <p>''Bill Cosby never talks to me about my work,'' Mr. Stang said. ''He always wants to know what my wife is doing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stang's ambition is ''to continue what I'm doing.'' Retirement? ''Only the undertaker is going to retire me,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
