<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Back to the States, Still Sharply Modern</title>
    <meta content="02DANC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stuttgart Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kandell, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EED61738F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Back to the States, Still Sharply Modern</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KANDELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kandell, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leslie Kandell reviews performance by Stuttgart Ballet at New Jersey Performing Arts Center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Stuttgart Ballet generated a terrific stir in 1969 when Sol Hurok brought it to Lincoln Center. John Cranko, the troupe's founder and artistic director, introduced dances of sharpness and charm. The graphic energy of his gifted performers added a modern edge to the ballet vocabulary.</p>
        <p>Cranko died in 1973 and in the following years, the company made a couple of quick trips to the United States, but nothing like the tour it is now undertaking. Before heading to the West Coast, it is to appear in New Jersey for the first time, with four performances, and after another four in Detroit, follows with four more in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Stuttgart Ballet generated a terrific stir in 1969 when Sol Hurok brought it to Lincoln Center. John Cranko, the troupe's founder and artistic director, introduced dances of sharpness and charm. The graphic energy of his gifted performers added a modern edge to the ballet vocabulary.</p>
        <p>Cranko died in 1973 and in the following years, the company made a couple of quick trips to the United States, but nothing like the tour it is now undertaking. Before heading to the West Coast, it is to appear in New Jersey for the first time, with four performances, and after another four in Detroit, follows with four more in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Because 30 years have elapsed since the Hurok tour, much about the Stuttgart, now led by Reid Anderson, a Canadian who was one of the young dancers on that first tour, is new. There are to be five American premieres -- four choreographed especially for the company -- and a whole roster of new dancers, notably Vladimir Malakhov, who was seen in American Ballet Theater's recently televised performance of ''Le Corsaire.'' This time, the dance world's attention is less on Cranko's signature works like ''Initials R.M.B.E.,'' scheduled at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center, than on the troup's current look and focus.</p>
        <p>''There are two ways of moving forward,'' Mr. Anderson, said, speaking by telephone from Stuttgart. ''One is producing dancers and helping their progress. The other is the making of new work. On Dec. 11, we introduced our 15th brand-new ballet in under four years.'' That was ''Jupiter,'' a large-scale ballet set by William Forsythe, to Mozart's last symphony.</p>
        <p>The tour schedule also suggests a trend toward single-act ballets in which form and pattern are valued over plot, and visible body movement over traditional costumes and sets. The troupe is traveling light, without live music or stagy, full-evening ballets like ''Romeo and Juliet.'' The women are mostly in body suits, the men bare-chested.</p>
        <p>Aside from ''R.M.B.E.,'' (the first initials of Cranko dancers) the works on this tour were choreographed during Mr. Anderson's directorship, which began in 1996. Cranko encouraged his dancers to choreograph, and part of his legacy is that some of the new works are by Stuttgart dancers.</p>
        <p>All reflect the cross-section of nationalities the dancers represent. At the moment the Stuttgart is predominantly Russian and Spanish. After the first American tour, Mr. Anderson said, it picked up a number of Americans, but oddly, it has never had a majority of Germans.</p>
        <p>The McCarter program's ''Delta Inserts,'' choreographed by Kevin O'Day to music by John King, is purely American.  Mississippi is the delta, and Mr. King, who lives in New York, composed a blues-based score. In Mr. Anderson's metaphor, dancers and pas de deux seem to be inserted into it.  Though the ''Delta'' score was commissioned for the choreographer, Mr. Anderson stressed the inspiration for other dances from Brahms Piano Concerto No. 2.</p>
        <p>''Solo'' and ''Kleines Requiem'' are by the Dutch choreographer Hans van Manen, with whom the Stuttgart has an ongoing relationship. Neither dance is what the title suggests. Mr. van Manen intended to make a solo to a Bach violin partita, but ''Solo'' got away from him and became too demanding for one person. Judging from video excerpts, the result is a busy, feisty sort of relay race for three men, who hand off solos to one another with a lot of attitude, and dance in mad parallel at the end.</p>
        <p>''Kleines Requiem,'' set to Henryk Gorecki's ''Little Requiem for a Polka,'' a peppy little polka, is also not what it would seem. It is a highly directional, modern-style piece, with the ensemble scuttling  about in ever-tightening patterns, while the music jolts between funereal chimes and motoric hysteria. It also contains a loving male duet, reminiscent of the one in Lar Lubovitch's ''Concerto Six Twenty-Two,'' with dancers moving as one, mirroring each other's long, slim-lined movements.</p>
        <p>The central pas de deux of ''Kazimir's Colors'' is by contrast angular and irregular. Maura Bigonzetti's choreography is driven by the cheeky, noisy music of Shostakovich's early piano and trumpet concerto, and the blocklike shapes and colors used by Kazimir Malevich, the Russian painter.  Lighting by Carlo Cerri creates designs that give structure to the bare stage, filling in for sets and enhancing the percussive feel of the other movements' ensembles.</p>
        <p>STUTTGART BALLET</p>
        <p>New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark</p>
        <p>Jan. 8, 8 p.m., Jan. 9, 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>(888) 466-5722</p>
        <p>McCarter Theater, 91 University Place, Princeton</p>
        <p>Jan. 10 and 11 at 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>(609) 258-2787</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
