<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Dusty Springfield, b. 1939; The Sound of ... Pop</title>
    <meta content="MB102652" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Springfield, Dusty (1939-99)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoerburger, Rob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1D91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Dusty Springfield, b. 1939; The Sound of ... Pop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rob Hoerburger</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoerburger, Rob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rob Hoerburger tribute</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When I met Dusty Springfield in 1995, she was in the pocket -- a musician's term akin to ''in the zone'' for athletes. She was enjoying renewed acclaim for her 60's recordings, which covered a virtually unplottable graph of moods and styles, from the girl-groupy joy ride of ''I Only Want to Be With You'' to the breathy eroticism of ''The Look of Love.'' She had just won a round in her battle with cancer and seemed in no hurry to get back to the recording studio. ''Although, if someone let me record an album of every cover I've ever dreamed of singing, I might think about it,'' she coolly intoned.</p>
        <p>Sadly, she never got to make that album. But here's what it might have sounded like:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When I met Dusty Springfield in 1995, she was in the pocket -- a musician's term akin to ''in the zone'' for athletes. She was enjoying renewed acclaim for her 60's recordings, which covered a virtually unplottable graph of moods and styles, from the girl-groupy joy ride of ''I Only Want to Be With You'' to the breathy eroticism of ''The Look of Love.'' She had just won a round in her battle with cancer and seemed in no hurry to get back to the recording studio. ''Although, if someone let me record an album of every cover I've ever dreamed of singing, I might think about it,'' she coolly intoned.</p>
        <p>Sadly, she never got to make that album. But here's what it might have sounded like:</p>
        <p>Track 1: ''Star Dust.'' The Hoagy Carmichael standard gets a torchy blues treatment, no sweat for Dusty but not dissimilar to countless others. Never one for convention, she changes gears midsong and spins into a techno fever dream, inspired by the breathless version recorded in the 60's by Shirley (''The Name Game'') Ellis. Synthesizer programming: Moby (a lifelong fan). Background vocals: Cher (a lifelong fan).</p>
        <p>Track 2: ''Son of a Preacher Man.'' Dusty covers Dusty. She first recorded this Southern-fried R&amp;B song in 1968 for her legendary album ''Dusty in Memphis,'' but always claimed to prefer Aretha Franklin's later version. Here Dusty mimics Aretha's phrasing, emphasizing the ''who'' instead of the ''ever'' in the line ''the only boy/who could ever reach me.'' After 97 takes, she realizes what everyone else has known for 30 years: that Aretha was wrong and she was right.</p>
        <p>Track 3: ''Purple Haze.'' Rock critics were stunned when Dusty held her own with Jimi Hendrix on her BBC-TV series. She turns his signature song into a bossa nova breeze, thus wedding Hendrix with another guitar god, Antonio Carlos Jobim. ''There was so much Jimi could have done,'' she writes in the liner notes.</p>
        <p>Track 4: ''If.'' Just so rock critics don't get too possessive of her, Dusty offers this double scoop of 70's treacle, originally recorded by the supersoft group Bread. To madden the crits further, she sings the third verse in French with Charles Aznavour. Guitar solo: Jimmy Page.</p>
        <p>Track 5: ''Billie Jean.'' Michael Jackson's cautionary tale of sexual ambiguity moonwalks off Dusty's lips -- she was a forerunner of the gay revolution, having come out way back in 1970, but after that she never kissed and told. She was a gay icon more for her skyscrapered hair and geologic makeup than for her love life.</p>
        <p>Track 6: ''My Heart Will Go On'' (love theme from ''Titanic''). A song that someone born after 1975 will recognize. Background vocals: Lulu, Petula Clark. Handclaps: Celine Dion. Tea and scones: Mariah Carey.</p>
        <p>Track 7: ''1999.'' Prince's electro-funk apocalypse. Background vocals: Anthony Newley, Mel Torme. Trumpet solo: Lester Bowie.</p>
        <p>Track 8: ''Eleanor Rigby.'' Dusty never had much use for the Beatles, but recording ''Eleanor'' appeals to her perverse sense of humor: she lost the first of two Grammys she was nominated for to Paul McCartney, who, absurdly, was separated out from the group for this song and thrown into a gender-bending category -- Best Pop Vocal Perfomance -- with Dusty and Nancy Sinatra. Dusty's majestic ''You Don't Have to Say You Love Me'' was thus a victim of the Great Grammy Robbery of 1966. Background vocals: Peggy Lee (Dusty's other Grammy spoiler).</p>
        <p>Track 9: ''You Only Tell Me You Love Me When You're Drunk.'' Written by the Pet Shop Boys, who engineered Dusty's comeback in the late 80's, it's especially pointed because so many people in the business thought, after Dusty's travails in the 70's, that she'd have an exit  la Garland or Holiday. But she outlived the dire predictions, and many of the predictors.</p>
        <p>Track 10: ''I'm Still Here.'' In the 80's, Dusty auditioned for the London revival of ''Follies,'' hoping to sing Broadway's ultimate ode to survival. ''I wanted it because I could sing one song, stop the show and go home,'' she said. But then, she didn't need a part in ''Follies'' to do that.</p>
        <p>Rob Hoerburger, an editor of The Times Magazine, is co-author of ''My Name Is Love: The Darlene Love Story.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Rob Hoerburger, an editor of The Times Magazine, is co-author of ''My Name Is Love: The Darlene Love Story.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
