<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 25 Years, Home to an Owl</title>
    <meta content="02OWL.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Owls</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Science Center of Connecticut</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Polk, Nancy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5DB1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 25 Years, Home to an Owl</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NANCY POLK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Polk, Nancy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on great horned owl, which has spent entire life at Science Center of Connecticut in West Hartford; was rescued after tumbling from nest in 1975; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DUNCAN, a great horned owl in residence at the Science Center of Connecticut in West Hartford, is celebrating his 25th birthday this month.</p>
        <p>Brian Kleinman, the animal curator at the Science Center, said it was unusual for an owl to live past 20 in the wild.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DUNCAN, a great horned owl in residence at the Science Center of Connecticut in West Hartford, is celebrating his 25th birthday this month.</p>
        <p>Brian Kleinman, the animal curator at the Science Center, said it was unusual for an owl to live past 20 in the wild.</p>
        <p>In 1975, as a baby owl, Duncan tumbled out of his nest at the West Hartford Reservoir. He imprinted the wildlife rehabilitator who rescued him and he was taken to the Roaring Brook Nature Center. That center took the owl to the science center where he has spent his whole life.</p>
        <p>Jay Kaplan, the director of the Roaring Brook Nature Center, met Duncan as a baby and now when he visits the science center, the owl ''goes crazy'' according to Mr. Kleinman, apparently an indication of his early imprinting with humans.</p>
        <p>Much to the surprise of visiting children, the great horned owl has no horns; rather they have tufts of fur that resemble horns or ears that are useful for camouflage.</p>
        <p>Wild owls eat anything smaller than they are. They swoop down onto their live prey, which includes rodents, other owls and an occasional small cat or dog, and carry them away after grabbing them with their sharp talons. They have flat faces designed to tunnel sound to their ears. Their ears are off center, helping them focus on the precise location of their prey. Their hearing is so keen, they are able to hear a mouse rustling in leaves.</p>
        <p>Hank Gruner, vice president for programs and exhibits at the science center, explained that owls can move silently because their feathers are edged with a soft fringe that blunts sound and allows the owl to swoop onto its prey.</p>
        <p>Duncan, unlike his wild counterparts, does not eat live food, so every day his keeper gives him a pair of dead mice or one dead rat for lunch.  Duncan's food is always placed in the same spot because the one noticeable effect of aging has been a cataract on his left eye.</p>
        <p>The bits of his lunch that are undigested are regurgitated as pellets. Schoolchildren can dissect Duncan's pellets at the center where they may find small bones and fur.</p>
        <p>Duncan, a popular fixture at the Science Center, will occasionally flirt with the visitors by hooting and ruffling his chest feathers, making him appear larger than his five pounds. ''He thinks he's human but he knows he's male,'' Mr. Gruner said.</p>
        <p>Owls are nocturnal so Duncan is usually dozing in the daytime but can be roused from his nap if he is taken out of his cage.</p>
        <p>When the center is quiet, Duncan goes outside at the end of a 30-foot flight leash to exercise his wings. The leash is attached to a leather band on his leg called a jess, a falconry term. A metal clip is attached to the jess and onto the leash. Then he is released and shows a wingspan of about four feet.</p>
        <p>Great horned owls stay in Connecticut woods throughout the winter, well camouflaged with brown, gray and white feathers. According to Mr. Kleinman, the best time to spot an owl is late February or March when they hoot to attract mates. Their nest area can be identified by white streaks on tree trunks and piles of fuzzy owl pellets on the ground. They breed earlier than other birds and lay their eggs in late March or April.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gruner said owls are fairly common in Connecticut and it is possible for humans to attract them. He suggested buying or making a tape of hoots and bringing it into a patch of woodland. Visitors are welcome to practice in the center's hooting booth and they can also make their recording.</p>
        <p>At the center, Duncan lives in a tree in his cage. In the wild, owls appropriate nests from crows and other large birds and then add on with more twigs. The rebuilt nests are large enough to accommodate a mating pair and their young.</p>
        <p>Duncan will receive some extra attention in January when the center begins its celebration of birds of prey, called raptors. ''Hunters of the Sky'' will focus on eagles, hawks, falcons, ospreys and of course, owls. Duncan is the only resident raptor but there will be displays of mounted birds of prey. The center staff is organizing a series of live programs with visiting birds.</p>
        <p>''Hunters of the Sky'' will run from Jan. 22 to June 14 at the Science Center of Connecticut (860-231-2824 or 860-231-2830) in West Hartford. Admission is $6, $5 for children and people over 55.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
