<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Budget Helps Efforts To Protect U.S. Parks</title>
    <meta content="02REP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Property</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Park Trust</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0DC1E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Budget Helps Efforts To Protect U.S. Parks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Budget passed by Congress last November includes more than $450 million to buy land for conservation this fiscal year; National Park Trust, nonprofit group that buys land, warns of threat from 'inholdings,' millions of acres within national parks and forests that are held by private owners (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LYNDON B. JOHNSON used to talk about the modest Texas rancher who only wanted to settle down on his own little spread, and acquire the immediately surrounding property. For the National Park Service and other federal agencies, though, the task of preserving the public's property sometimes boils down to acquiring the little private properties that the government's land surrounds.</p>
        <p>That should be easier to afford this year, because the budget that passed Congress before Thanksgiving included more than $450 million to buy land for conservation this fiscal year, which ends Sept. 30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LYNDON B. JOHNSON used to talk about the modest Texas rancher who only wanted to settle down on his own little spread, and acquire the immediately surrounding property. For the National Park Service and other federal agencies, though, the task of preserving the public's property sometimes boils down to acquiring the little private properties that the government's land surrounds.</p>
        <p>That should be easier to afford this year, because the budget that passed Congress before Thanksgiving included more than $450 million to buy land for conservation this fiscal year, which ends Sept. 30.</p>
        <p>Private owners hold title or rights to use millions of acres within the national parks, and much more within the boundaries of state parks, national forests and other public lands. Conservationists are worried that there is increasing pressure to develop these lands, known as ''inholdings.''</p>
        <p>Paul Pritchard, the president of the National Park Trust, a private nonprofit organization that buys land for conservation, calls development on these lands the single greatest threat to national and state parks. In the United States Virgin Islands, for example, the trust says that investors from around the world have purchased tracts inside the Virgin Islands National Park and are offering undeveloped quarter-acre lots for $1 million each.</p>
        <p>With the federal budget surplus swelling, it seems possible that more threatened tracts than ever could be bought by the government if Congress permanently increases spending by the Land and Water Conservation Fund, which is financed by revenues from offshore drilling leases.</p>
        <p>Early this year, President Clinton proposed a land-acquisition budget of about $1 billion a year, paid for out of the fund. Republicans and Democrats offered competing proposals to spend even more. But despite widespread political support, legislation that would lock in spending of billions of dollars for years to come got bogged down in the broader debates over how to allocate the prospective surplus in future years, and did not come to the floor of either the House or the Senate.</p>
        <p>Still, conservationists were thrilled with the amount set aside for buying land this year. In the past, the typical $900 million in annual oil-lease revenues vastly exceeded the amount that the government spent to buy land. This year, the federal government will be spending about half the $900 million. Conservationists hope that in future years, the remainder will be handed over to the states for land purchases.</p>
        <p>The National Park Trust says that there are about seven million acres of private property in the national parks. The amount of private property within federal lands grew by 1.6 million acres in the last decade (mainly because of the protection of new lands, like those in the Mojave Desert, which surround extensive private property). By some federal estimates, there is as much as $10 billion worth of private property within federal boundaries.</p>
        <p>High Country News, a Colorado newspaper that covers the Rocky Mountain region, reported last year that the scarcity and popularity of recreation property in the West has sent the value of inholdings ''into the stratosphere,'' and that owners are holding out for high prices or threatening to develop the land to spur federal agencies into making generous bids.</p>
        <p>According to the Park Service, about 200,000 of the 7 million acres in national parks held by private owners are threatened with development. For example, when Death Valley National Park was expanded in 1994, it encompassed a defunct mine, creating a new inholding, and the owners tried to reopen the mine. But they recently agreed to sell the property to the federal government for $2.5 million, according to the Wilderness Society, the conservation organization.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in California, the group says, there are more than 24,000 acres of inholdings in national forests -- at least $1 million worth of land, where owners are free to build homes, cut timber or develop in other ways. (The society publishes a list of acquisition priorities at www.wilderness.org/ eyewash/lwcfproposed.htm.)</p>
        <p>While land acquisition enjoys considerable public support, there is also an active lobby of private owners who oppose government purchases of land. The American Lands Rights Association, which claims 18,000 members, says there are 1.2 million inholders nationwide.</p>
        <p>Charles S. Cushman, executive director of the association, told the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee in April: ''More than 115,000 landowners have already lost their land to the Park Service alone since 1966 because of the Land and Water Conservation Fund. Often, the only reason a landowner wants to sell is that he has been harassed and driven half crazy trying to deal with the Park Service, which generally fails to negotiate in good faith.''</p>
        <p>But Kevin Collins, legislative director of the National Parks and Conservation Association, says that these fears are unfounded. ''There has never been any danger of the National Park Service indiscriminately taking over public land.'' He says a bill that passed the House Resources Committee in November ''actually strengthens private property safeguards.''</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
