<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Trail of the Audacious</title>
    <meta content="02THEA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDA1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Trail of the Audacious</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Focus on outlook for Connecticut's venerable theater institutions, many of which are in transition; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT good is forecasting a mere year without speculating on the future of Connecticut's venerable, oldest established theater institutions in transition?</p>
        <p>With such developmental centers as the Eugene O'Neill Theater Center in Waterford and showcases like Lucille Lortel's White Barn in Westport, lies the real future of nurturing theater for the ages, as opposed to producing the sort of polished product so many audiences expect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT good is forecasting a mere year without speculating on the future of Connecticut's venerable, oldest established theater institutions in transition?</p>
        <p>With such developmental centers as the Eugene O'Neill Theater Center in Waterford and showcases like Lucille Lortel's White Barn in Westport, lies the real future of nurturing theater for the ages, as opposed to producing the sort of polished product so many audiences expect.</p>
        <p>The more theatergoers appreciate the importance of process and become stimulated by it, the more innovative and audacious theater will be.</p>
        <p>Play after play by August Wilson was developed in Waterford, went on to full production at Yale Repertory in New Haven -- both coincidentally led by Lloyd Richards -- and after evolving in other regional theaters, were honed to the sheen Broadway expects. The honors, including the Pulitzers, followed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richards no longer guides the National Playwrights Conference in Waterford and Mr. Wilson's plays are in shorter supply; the latest one opened the new O'Reilly Theater in Pittsburgh, the playwright's hometown, last month.</p>
        <p>But the O'Neill, which includes components for the development of musicals and the perpetuation of cabaret, has been ill-defined of late, struggling to sustain communication among its various divisions.</p>
        <p>If new leadership at the O'Neill remains to be felt, what about the White Barn, which requires an infusion of new talent and ideas? Lortel, who died last year, provided for the perpetuation of her singular showcase, which was curtailed over the years from a theater for plays, whole plays with whole casts, to a two-night-a-week tryout spot for solo or cabaret type shows, given the rigidity of Actors Equity rules. And what of Shakespeare at Stratford? Never mind. The same questions have been asked for more than a decade.</p>
        <p>With the dwindling of summer stock and its old-time star packages that once thrived on a circuit that could sustain one production for three months or longer, the Westport Country Playhouse needs to be redefined. And so its future is being pondered by an advisory council with Joanne Woodward as its head.</p>
        <p>Restoration will come with redefinition -- and plans for a year-round season. Once, the Fairfield County Stage Company, known as Boston Road Stage Company before that, moved into a reconfigured summer theater in Westport, but failed to catch on. Whatever the luminaries and philanthropists, who include Maureen Anderman, Jayne Atkinson, James Naughton, Paul Newman and Christopher Plummer, come up with, the 70-year-old playhouse cannot go on with the hit or miss repertory it has been doing for years.</p>
        <p>When one talks of new musicals, or the lack thereof, the future of Goodspeed Opera in East Haddam cannot be far behind -- especially since the theater has the luxury of a musicals-in-progress center, the Norma Terris in Chester, one town away.</p>
        <p>Surely, it is jolting to realize that ''Man of La Mancha,'' a brand new Goodspeed musical on the main stage 35 years ago, is to open the new season in East Haddam come April. Of Connecticut's high visibility Tony Award winning regional theaters -- Goodspeed has won two -- this is the only one to last under the same artistic and producing command, that of Michael Price. Before April, it will be essential for Mr. Price to make an evaluative mission statement about once and future musicals -- and about Goodspeed, its problems and its audiences.</p>
        <p>As musical go, Connecticut is to get mostly the same old retreads and national tours, from the inferior ''Victor/Victoria,'' in a non-Equity bus and truck starless stopover, at the Garde Art Center in New London, to, unbelievably, ''The Civil War'' at the Bushnell in Hartford.</p>
        <p>If Frank Wildhorn's banal, pseudo-historical generic pop hybrid flopped once, at the Shubert in New Haven last year and then on Broadway, there is no reason why it can't keep on flip-flopping all over the country. His ''Scarlet Pimpernel,'' in the third streamlined version, is to play the Shubert in February.</p>
        <p>And ''Annie Get Your Gun'' in Peter Stone's pointless revision, now on Broadway, is to be at the Shubert in May. Who's Annie? Not Susan Lucci, who is filling in for Bernadette Peters for two weeks in New York. Spokesmen for the musical say that Ms. Lucci will not tour -- of course not, there is that soap -- and they cannot name the names being bandied about for the show's tour, which reportedly has not been cast at all.</p>
        <p>Oddly, the show stopper in the new production is ''Old Fashioned Wedding,'' the new number Irving Berlin wrote for the 1966 revival, which starred Ethel Merman, 20 years after she created the role. Some stars had it and made it pay.</p>
        <p>Is there a star Annie Oakley today, besides Ms. Peters? Of course, yes. Faith Prince is a fine idea. But don't talk about Patti LuPone, who did two performances, with Peter Gallagher as Frank Butler, in a concert version for the benefit of Lincoln Center three years ago. Ms. LuPone had a triumphant, joyous go at the role. But she was not offered the Broadway production a year later. No way can they pay her enough to consider it now.</p>
        <p>Ms. LuPone opened the new Garde Arts Center in October. ''A Night to Remember,'' it was called, and that it was. And the evening may have signaled the dawning of a theater form, big time. In regional theater the art of cabaret is an alternative to the life support needs of the musical. Much is made of the absence of new plays on Broadway but that's only a gripe of relevance to tourists. New plays thrive Off Broadway and in the regions but musicals are the pretenders to life, everywhere.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
