<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fuzzy Images, and a Debate Over Who's at Fault</title>
    <meta content="02CAME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automated Teller Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5D81538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fuzzy Images, and a Debate Over Who's at Fault</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City officials are demanding that state give local agencies the authority to inspect video cameras at ATM's; recent police investigations have been hampered by failure of video cameras to help identify robbers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following recent police investigations that were hampered by the failure of video cameras in A.T.M.'s to help identify robbers, city officials are demanding that the state give local agencies the authority to inspect such devices.</p>
        <p>From 1992 to 1996, the city's Consumer Affairs, Buildings and Police Departments all had the right to inspect A.T.M.'s to make sure they had the required cameras, mirrors and lighting. In 1997, a state law turned enforcement over to the State Banking Department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following recent police investigations that were hampered by the failure of video cameras in A.T.M.'s to help identify robbers, city officials are demanding that the state give local agencies the authority to inspect such devices.</p>
        <p>From 1992 to 1996, the city's Consumer Affairs, Buildings and Police Departments all had the right to inspect A.T.M.'s to make sure they had the required cameras, mirrors and lighting. In 1997, a state law turned enforcement over to the State Banking Department.</p>
        <p>Now, the Department of Consumer Affairs is drafting a bill to be submitted to the State Legislature that would again allow city agencies to cite banks for violating A.T.M. safety regulations, said Jules Polonetsky, the consumer affairs commissioner.</p>
        <p>''Every day, there are tens of thousands of consumers who use these A.T.M.'s and expect they've got some security they can rely on,'' Mr. Pol onetsky said. ''No bank would ever operate a branch that consumers walked into without having a security guard. It's irresponsible to set out a cash machine without any measure of protection.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polonetsky said that the state agency's wider geographic jurisdiction prevents it from focusing enforcement efforts on New York City's A.T.M.'s.</p>
        <p>But Ted McElroy, a spokesman with the State Banking Department, said that ''it appears that Mr. Polonetsky has to acquaint himself with the facts.'' He said the state had inspected about 1,500 A.T.M.'s in the city since November 1997, a rate that he said was more than double that of city agencies.</p>
        <p>Consumer affairs officials said they did not have statistics on the number of inspections the city had done, but said that city agencies issued about 400 citations between 1993 and 1996 to banks for failing to meet A.T.M. safety standards. State officials could not provide the number of violations identified by inspectors.</p>
        <p>In the past three years, some high-profile police investigations have been hampered because dark, grainy images from A.T.M. cameras could not be used to identify suspects. The most recent instance was at an Apple Bank branch in Rockefeller Center, where a rapist forced his victim to try withdrawing money on Dec. 21.</p>
        <p>But a fuzzy close-up image from the A.T.M. camera could not be used for identification because the camera's videotape had not been changed in several years, said Marilyn Mode, deputy police commissioner for public information. ''It was way past the useful date,'' she said of the tape. ''It should have been replaced some time ago.''</p>
        <p>James Matera, a spokesman for Apple Bank, said the tape ''had only been used for a total of 16 to 20 weeks.'' He said that ''Apple Bank's surveillance of its A.T.M. lobby was in compliance with all legal requirements.''</p>
        <p>In 1997, an A.T.M. camera failed to help identify someone who used a bank card belonging to Jonathan M. Levin to get $800 from a Chase Manhattan A.T.M. on the Upper West Side about the time Mr. Levin was slain. Again, the image was too grainy, the police said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mode said other investigations related to A.T.M. robberies have been hampered by low-quality video images. ''It's certainly a concern,'' she said, ''and it's something that's so easy to correct with some vigilance and good habits.''</p>
        <p>EDWARD WONG</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
