<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Win or Lose, Jets Will Face Off-Season of Alterations</title>
    <meta content="02JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Seahawks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Seattle Seahawks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E5DF1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Win or Lose, Jets Will Face Off-Season of Alterations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets, preparing for game against Seattle Seahawks, are aware that many of key players, coaches and front-office officials who played role in their late-season turnaround may not be back next season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets enter today's season finale against Seattle believing they are one of the best teams in pro football. They've won three straight games, six of the last eight and are conquerors of Dan Marino (twice), Troy Aikman, Doug Flutie and Drew Bledsoe. Peyton Manning had his least productive game of the season against the Jets.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, many key players, coaches and front-office officials who have been part of the turnaround cannot -- or will not -- say whether they will be back next season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Jets enter today's season finale against Seattle believing they are one of the best teams in pro football. They've won three straight games, six of the last eight and are conquerors of Dan Marino (twice), Troy Aikman, Doug Flutie and Drew Bledsoe. Peyton Manning had his least productive game of the season against the Jets.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, many key players, coaches and front-office officials who have been part of the turnaround cannot -- or will not -- say whether they will be back next season.</p>
        <p>The Jets are 7-8. Their chance for a .500 season, following a 1-6 start, ''is our Super Bowl,'' according to Curtis Martin. The Seahawks (9-6) can clinch the American Conference West with a victory.</p>
        <p>''If we could have just got the formula early in the season, it might have been different,'' said Marcus Coleman, the emerging cornerback.</p>
        <p>''Do you think,'' said fullback Richie Anderson, ''we've come all this way for Sunday's game not to mean anything?''</p>
        <p>What today in Giants Stadium means is today, says Parcells. He doesn't believe these late-season surges necessarily carry over. But he does believe that winning helps steel a club for the future.</p>
        <p>But that future has never been cloudier in his three-year Jets reign than it is now:</p>
        <p>*There will be a new owner soon.</p>
        <p>*Parcells' return is not certain.</p>
        <p>*Some players will be gone -- either to free agency or dropped for salary-cap reasons.</p>
        <p>*There could be dramatic front-office changes.</p>
        <p>*The status of the entire coaching staff, especially Bill Belichick, is murky.</p>
        <p>Despite the uncertainty, the Jets arguably will start the season next year stronger in the most important position of all -- quarterback. Vinny Testaverde claims his rehabilitation for his torn Achilles' tendon has gone better than he hoped. And the Jets at last have a backup -- and potential starter -- in Ray Lucas.</p>
        <p>Players like to believe Parcells will be back. If you took a hard look at what motivates him, you would think so, too. He has helped create a credible franchise in what was a moribund operation, but he knows there is unfinished business.</p>
        <p>Still, if he does come back, will he have his outstanding coaching staff as well? Probably. The No. 1 question as usual surrounds Belichick, whose title is assistant head coach. He is the defensive genius whose unit has been confusing each outstanding quarterback in the division.</p>
        <p>Belichick's contract calls for him to succeed Parcells eventually. Still, Belichick did speak to the Raiders' Al Davis two years ago about taking over that club. He had some interest last year from the Bears and Chiefs. The Patriots' owner, Robert K. Kraft, conceded he was interested in Belichick following Parcells's departure after the 1996 season.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Parcells has given the ''supervisory'' tag to a pair of other longtime assistants: offensive coordinator Charlie Weis and linebackers coach Al Groh. This designation means that another club can talk to either Weis or Groh only if the team doing the talking is offering them a head coaching job. Carolina called about Groh before last season.</p>
        <p>Parcells has had a long-term relationship with his coaches. They don't leave him. The reason is simple to Parcells: ''I pay them real well.''</p>
        <p>As of now, he has gotten no calls about assistants, but then again there are no openings. ''This is the first time I can remember going to Christmas and there are no vacancies,'' Parcells said.</p>
        <p>Weis's future? His game plans are innovative, but Parcells has taken over the play-calling completely. Weis is still the coordinator and has shifted from coaching the F-backs to running the receivers' corps. That had been the domain of Todd Haley, but Haley is now called the assistant receivers' coach. Will he come back after a virtual demotion?</p>
        <p>There is also the question of Dan Henning. He is the quarterbacks' coach whom Parcells credits with Lucas's transformation into a leader able to engineer three straight comebacks in the final quarter.</p>
        <p>The uncertainty extends to the front office and the players.</p>
        <p>Dick Haley, who runs the draft, is going into his 40th season as player and official.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, several Jets are contemplating the prospect of free agency. They include linebacker Mo Lewis, who has been to the Pro Bowl, and Coleman, whose five interceptions tie him for the team lead. The Jets are believed to have offered Coleman a multimillion-dollar contract that would make him the team's highest-paid cornerback.</p>
        <p>Then there are the well-compensated starters such as left tackle Jumbo Elliott, whose big salary and history of back problems could make him expendable. In that category, add the two one-time Pro Bowl players the Jets acquired this year, but who have been injured -- tight end Eric Green and free safety Steve Atwater.</p>
        <p>And don't forget those still injured, such as cornerback Otis Smith, whose season ended with a broken collarbone. Parcells talks about how difficult it will be for Smith to return at the age of 35 after being out a year.</p>
        <p>Yet, for all the people returning from injuries -- Smith and Testaverde, as well as linebackers Bryan Cox and Chad Cascadden, offensive lineman Jason Fabini and third-down specialist Leon Johnson -- the prognosis is generally good. It will take months, though, before they can be assessed accurately.</p>
        <p>The only certainty about next season? Bill Hampton, the equipment manager since 1964, is retiring to Florida.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
