<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Hermann Merkin, b. 1907; The Public Father</title>
    <meta content="TLTLMERKT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merkin, Hermann (1907-99)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merkin, Daphne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2D91E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1089" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Hermann Merkin, b. 1907; The Public Father</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Daphne Merkin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Merkin, Daphne; Merkin, Hermann (1907-99)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daphne Merkin article on her</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>My father died last March, at the age of 91, in his own bed, surrounded by his family; it was a sober, patriarchal, even old-world death, befitting his life. He had been ailing for close to two years, from heart failure and then lymphoma, but it still came as a surprise to see him yielding at last instead of rallying, as he had so many times before. My mother took the most extraordinary care of him, which included packing him off to the office for a few hours every day, right up until the week of his death. I rarely visited my father at his office, where he worked as an investment banker, but I knew that its ongoing affairs were more crucial to him, in many ways, than the life he led at home -- just as I knew that his public face as a philanthropist was easier to read than his private face as a father or husband. My father was an Orthodox Jew who had grown up in Leipzig, Germany; he remained committed to Jewish causes until his death, and his knowledge of the dizzying intricacies of Israeli politics was impressive. Throughout his life my father supported Jewish scholarship; he also helped endow the kosher kitchen at Mount Sinai, as well as the Merkin Concert Hall on West 67th Street (which is silent from Friday at sundown to Saturday at sundown, in observance of the Sabbath).</p>
        <p>I consider him to have been something of an enigma -- to himself, and certainly to his children. When I was younger I imagined that he was a spy in disguise, someone out of the K.G.B. or C.I.A., who only appeared to lead an ordinary existence but was really off stalking the inner corridors of power. He was constitutionally secretive, and it would have been nice to be let in on the secret, to know what was going on in his busy, obsessive mind. The things that caught his attention were wide-ranging and difficult to predict, from a small fact in an article to someone's personal style, a way of walking or speaking, or simply an excessive use of the hands when talking. This last mannerism my father was particularly irritated by, especially in women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>My father died last March, at the age of 91, in his own bed, surrounded by his family; it was a sober, patriarchal, even old-world death, befitting his life. He had been ailing for close to two years, from heart failure and then lymphoma, but it still came as a surprise to see him yielding at last instead of rallying, as he had so many times before. My mother took the most extraordinary care of him, which included packing him off to the office for a few hours every day, right up until the week of his death. I rarely visited my father at his office, where he worked as an investment banker, but I knew that its ongoing affairs were more crucial to him, in many ways, than the life he led at home -- just as I knew that his public face as a philanthropist was easier to read than his private face as a father or husband. My father was an Orthodox Jew who had grown up in Leipzig, Germany; he remained committed to Jewish causes until his death, and his knowledge of the dizzying intricacies of Israeli politics was impressive. Throughout his life my father supported Jewish scholarship; he also helped endow the kosher kitchen at Mount Sinai, as well as the Merkin Concert Hall on West 67th Street (which is silent from Friday at sundown to Saturday at sundown, in observance of the Sabbath).</p>
        <p>I consider him to have been something of an enigma -- to himself, and certainly to his children. When I was younger I imagined that he was a spy in disguise, someone out of the K.G.B. or C.I.A., who only appeared to lead an ordinary existence but was really off stalking the inner corridors of power. He was constitutionally secretive, and it would have been nice to be let in on the secret, to know what was going on in his busy, obsessive mind. The things that caught his attention were wide-ranging and difficult to predict, from a small fact in an article to someone's personal style, a way of walking or speaking, or simply an excessive use of the hands when talking. This last mannerism my father was particularly irritated by, especially in women.</p>
        <p>He wasn't the kind of father I would have ideally wished for, an image cobbled together from the paternal figures I warmed to on television or in the movies, attentive and playful and full of wise counsel, like the father on ''Gidget.'' He wasn't invested in the homely details of my existence or those of my five siblings: I don't think he ever knew the name of any of my teachers, and he couldn't tell my friends apart. He didn't teach me to ride a bike (he couldn't ride one himself) or drive a car (he couldn't drive one himself). He didn't, in other words, lend himself to helping me master the world, the role often attributed to fathers in the developmental histories of daughters. He hadn't much use for feelings, which were what interested me the most, then as now. I couldn't go to him with my problems or my passions, partly because he spoke the language of businesslike resolution while I specialized in the articulation of finely honed conflict. On those infrequent times when I would officially meet with him in his study -- a room that bordered on the sacrosanct -- to discuss some girlhood difficulty, I would invariably find myself cut off at the pass by his decisiveness. My habit of questioning everything wilted before his focus on the bottom line. Later I would find some of my relationship with him expressed in Kafka's famous, importuning letter to his father, with its futile wish for a communion that doesn't exist.</p>
        <p>These days I find myself looking for my father, as though now that he is gone I might still get to know him better. There are superficial associations: I saw a movie in which the Savoy Hotel in London was briefly featured, and I was immediately reminded of my father's fondness for it when he traveled on business -- and for the ashtrays he filched. And there are deeper ones, as well: When I'm around people -- especially men -- who seem too obvious in their thought processes, I think with affection of my father's utterly idiosyncratic, curvy mind. I keep wondering what has happened to the all the bits of information he stored in his head, the phrases he wrote down -- in English, or Hebrew, or German, or French -- with his ubiquitous, freshly sharpened No. 2 pencils on little white notepads. I found the combinations of things he scribbled in his vertical, almost mathematical handwriting -- practical reminders mixed in with cerebral notations, isolated vocabulary words mixed in with stock quotes and dollar signs -- invariably intriguing. Language meant a lot to him, and though I never shared his fondness for punsters or a certain kind of briskly witty columnist, I could see that he liked words to crackle on the page.</p>
        <p>Since he wasn't given to communicating his emotions, I had to guess at them much of the time. In the end, I think he was genuinely different from other people, put together from strange and incongruous parts. I know he took pride in my being a writer, and I always enjoyed it when he came to literary gatherings, where he greeted everyone with relish, acting perfectly oblivious to anything ungenerous about him or my family that I might have written. He didn't, in fact, much care what other people thought of him -- which struck me as both annoying and admirable, but made him socially unembarrassable. I miss his impersonal yet oddly reassuring presence in the world, sitting in a chair in his study filled with seforim, his scholarly books, his round bald head covered with a flat black crocheted yarmulke. Write about me, he said, shortly before he died, squeezing my hand, which was his version of a hug. Did he mean it? And would he have recognized himself on the page?</p>
        <p>Daphne Merkin is a staff writer at The New Yorker and the author of the essay collection ''Dreaming of Hitler.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daphne Merkin is a staff writer at The New Yorker and the author of the essay collection ''Dreaming of Hitler.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
