<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Derelict School Gets New Life With the Arts</title>
    <meta content="02NEPT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Neptune (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Demasters, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DD1438F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Derelict School Gets New Life With the Arts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DeMASTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Demasters, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>OCEAN GROVE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Old Neptune (NJ) High School Building, constructed in 1898 but shuttered for past 20 years, is saved from demolition and is being restored by volunteers, many of whom were former students; building is being turned into self-sustaining arts and education center; 600-seat auditorium, with Italian and French decorative moitifs, will be used for performances and classrooms will be rented out to arts and education groups; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OVER the years, the old Neptune High School building here saw thousands of students come and go. Then, 20 years ago, the 1898 building was closed. The board of education did not want it, municipal officials did not want it, the Chamber of Commerce and local historical societies did not want it.</p>
        <p>It seemed the wrecking ball was inevitable until Herbert Herbst came along. Now, thanks to him, the building is being turned into what should be one of the few self-sustaining arts and education centers in the state. Not only will the 600-seat theater -- formerly the auditorium, with moldings from Italy and ceiling from France -- be used for performances, but the 16 classrooms will be rented to arts and education groups, with the income used to provide an estimated $38,000 needed each year for the building's upkeep.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OVER the years, the old Neptune High School building here saw thousands of students come and go. Then, 20 years ago, the 1898 building was closed. The board of education did not want it, municipal officials did not want it, the Chamber of Commerce and local historical societies did not want it.</p>
        <p>It seemed the wrecking ball was inevitable until Herbert Herbst came along. Now, thanks to him, the building is being turned into what should be one of the few self-sustaining arts and education centers in the state. Not only will the 600-seat theater -- formerly the auditorium, with moldings from Italy and ceiling from France -- be used for performances, but the 16 classrooms will be rented to arts and education groups, with the income used to provide an estimated $38,000 needed each year for the building's upkeep.</p>
        <p>The auditorium and classrooms surround a 14-foot-wide staircase that dominates the center hallway.</p>
        <p>''This building is a gem that is unparalleled in the state,'' said Mr. Herbst, 63, who has been a resident of the Ocean Grove section of Neptune since shortly after his retirement in 1990 as a telephone company executive in Manhattan. ''It won an award at the 1906 World's Fair for architectural splendor, but after it was closed nobody wanted it.''</p>
        <p>Nobody, that is, except Mr. Herbst and the people he could persuade to help him. The nonprofit Ocean Grove Historic Preservation Society was formed so there would be an entity to take charge of the building, which was sold by the board of education for $1. Then came the hard part.</p>
        <p>''The building was sound, but it was badly deteriorated,'' Mr. Herbst said. ''The ceiling of the auditorium was lying on the floor. There were huge holes in the roof and walls; the windows were broken. We didn't have money, so we asked for help.''</p>
        <p>The Preservation Society wanted to create a center that would bring arts and cultural education to young people in Monmouth County -- many in the immediate neighborhood are from underprivileged families -- but they also wanted a center that would pay for itself.</p>
        <p>''Eighty-five percent of the children in this area have never seen a ballet or an opera,'' Mr. Herbst said. ''We want to change that and at the same time we want to give local performers and artists a place to show their talent. Of course, we hope one of them will be discovered and then remember us when he or she is famous.''</p>
        <p>Although the Preservation Society does not expect to have to ask for money once the center is open sometime early this year, Mr. Herbst has done plenty of soliciting up till now.</p>
        <p>''He has a way of convincing people of his vision that makes them want to give time and donate their products,'' said Alyn Hein, a retired educator and writer living in Ocean Grove who is chairman of the Preservation Society artistic committee.</p>
        <p>Much of the renovation work has been done by volunteers, who are mostly retired men and women living in the community. In addition, Mr. Herbst has managed to persuade local merchants to donate their time and services. Many of those who have helped either went to school in the building or had children who did.</p>
        <p>''We have an old boy network here,'' said Jack Foley, 74, of Ocean Grove, who is doing most of the electrical work at the school. ''My daughters went to school here when this was the only high school in Neptune Township. ''We've got an architect, an accountant, a lawyer and others all doing their work as volunteers.''</p>
        <p>''It took 405 gallons of paint to do the inside after the walls were repaired,'' Mr. Herbst said. The paint was donated by a local paint store. A woodworker made new arms for the seats in the auditorium. The organization has received a total of $300,000 from the state, and an auxiliary has raised an additional $35,000 to help pay for major structural work, installation of an elevator and other things that could not be done by volunteers.</p>
        <p>After opening the bottom floor and renting the eight classrooms there, the Preservation Society hopes to open the second floor  and to finish the exterior with the distinctive cupolas that were removed years ago. The building should blend with the character of Ocean Grove, known for its preservation of historic buildings. Until the center is open, the Preservation Society, Post Office Box 55 Ocean Grove, N.J. 07756, continues to look for donations and volunteers.</p>
        <p>Preservation Society address ''We have already had numerous inquiries from people interested in renting space,'' said Mr. Hein.</p>
        <p>Any renters will have to agree to put on four performances or exhibitions during the year for schoolchildren. The center also will have performances for the public.</p>
        <p>''We will work with the schools,'' Mr. Herbst said. ''Our goal is for students to learn about a play or some piece of music, then they will come here and see it performed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
