<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Mario Puzo, b. 1920; Sammy the Bull Explains How The Mob Got Made</title>
    <meta content="TLTLPUZOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gravano, Salvatore</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Puzo, Mario (1920-99)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Godfather, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2D91E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Mario Puzo, b. 1920; Sammy the Bull Explains How The Mob Got Made</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeffrey Goldberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Jeffrey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>sammy the bull expla</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Salvatore (Sammy the Bull) Gravano is dining on the patio of a Ruth's Chris Steakhouse in Phoenix. A cold wind blows in from the desert. The patio is empty. In movies, people get whacked on nights like this. The waiter, whose name tag reads ''Sean,'' recognizes Gravano. Sean avoids our table as much as he can.</p>
        <p>Gravano, late of the Gambino crime family, is dining on filet mignon, and calling me a liar. Here is the reason he is calling me a liar: I told him, in the course of a rambling conversation about the ''The Godfather,'' that Mario Puzo wrote the book, and collaborated on the screenplays, without the expert advice of the mob.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Salvatore (Sammy the Bull) Gravano is dining on the patio of a Ruth's Chris Steakhouse in Phoenix. A cold wind blows in from the desert. The patio is empty. In movies, people get whacked on nights like this. The waiter, whose name tag reads ''Sean,'' recognizes Gravano. Sean avoids our table as much as he can.</p>
        <p>Gravano, late of the Gambino crime family, is dining on filet mignon, and calling me a liar. Here is the reason he is calling me a liar: I told him, in the course of a rambling conversation about the ''The Godfather,'' that Mario Puzo wrote the book, and collaborated on the screenplays, without the expert advice of the mob.</p>
        <p>''No way,'' Gravano says. ''Somebody had to be helping him.''</p>
        <p>I ask Gravano why he is so sure about this.</p>
        <p>''Because he knew about our life cold,'' he answers. ''He had the whole atmosphere, the way we talked. That wedding scene -- I mean, that was so real. I mean, my book isn't a pimple on his book, and I'm in my book.''</p>
        <p>I remember being surprised myself when Puzo told me he made the whole thing up. He did research, in libraries and newspaper morgues, but he made it up. There is no reason to disbelieve him.</p>
        <p>Puzo once shared with me one of his mother's favorite expressions: ''Never go outside, because you can get in trouble if you go outside.'' Puzo, especially in his last years, seldom left his house in Bay Shore, on Long Island. He was a homebody, I tell Gravano.</p>
        <p>Gravano accepts this, grudgingly. ''If you say so,'' he says.</p>
        <p>The reason I came to Arizona, where Gravano now lives -- he left the witness security program (''They wanted me to live in Utah. No way was I living in Utah''), but he still lives under an assumed name -- is that I wanted to know why so many mobsters continue to believe that the obviously mythical ''Godfather'' is an on-target depiction of the gangster life.</p>
        <p>''I'll give you a for-instance,'' Gravano says. ''Remember that scene when Michael goes to whack that drug dealer and the police captain?'' he asks. I nod. Like most American men, I have seen ''The Godfather'' 5 or 10 times.</p>
        <p>''Remember how Michael couldn't hear anything as he's walking up on them? Remember how his eyes went glassy, and there was just the noise of the train in the background, and how he couldn't hear them talk? That's just like I felt when I killed Joe Colucci.'' Joe Colucci was the first man Gravano killed. ''Somebody who wrote that scene had to have a feeling for that. I mean, I felt like I was pulling the trigger myself.''</p>
        <p>I ask Gravano if the ''The Godfather'' influenced the way he behaved.</p>
        <p>''Well,'' he answers, ''I killed 19 people.''</p>
        <p>But what has that got to do with ''The Godfather''?</p>
        <p>''I only did, like, one murder before I saw the movie.''</p>
        <p>What is this, a wise-guy Twinkie defense? It was Puzo who put that gun in my hand, officer.</p>
        <p>''Nah, I'm just saying it didn't hurt our image,'' Gravano says. ''It made our life, I don't know, it made our life seem honorable. I would use lines in real life like 'I'm gonna make you an offer you can't refuse,' and I would always tell people, just like from 'The Godfather,' 'If you have an enemy, that enemy becomes my enemy.'''</p>
        <p>So it wasn't the mob that influenced Puzo, but Puzo who influenced the mob?</p>
        <p>''He influenced the life, absolutely.''</p>
        <p>Puzo, no doubt, would find this amusing. He wasn't much of a tough guy; he was, he liked to say, ''a literary man.'' He won critical acclaim for his early work -- The Fortunate Pilgrim'' was called ''a small classic'' by The New York Times Book Review, and he was destined to become the Italian Henry Roth. But then he wrote ''The Godfather'' because he was broke, and wanted commercial success. He got it, without regret. ''I am terribly, terribly grateful that I have stopped writing small classics,'' he told me. He was occasionally asked to write nonfiction articles about the mob, but he would decline, professing to know nothing about the real-life Mafia. Which was true: his Mafia was an idealized Mafia, which may be why it influenced a generation of mobsters the way it did.</p>
        <p>Like most mob turncoats, Gravano says that it was not he who betrayed the Mafia, but the Mafia that betrayed him. ''There's no scruples anymore,'' he says. ''No respect for rules and regulations. 'The Godfather' has respect in it, but that doesn't exist anymore.''</p>
        <p>Mobsters will get one more chance to learn from Mario Puzo. Random House is bringing out a half-million copies of his final novel, ''Omerta,'' in June. Gravano says he'll be buying himself a copy. ''I guess he didn't get any help with that one either?'' he says. No, I say. ''Well, I don't know. Either he was getting help, or he was some kind of genius.''</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Goldberg, a contributing writer for the magazine, wrote a cover article last year about the decline of the Gambino crime family.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jeffrey Goldberg, a contributing writer for the magazine, wrote a cover article last year about the decline of the Gambino crime family.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
