<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Party: More Business Than Sparkle</title>
    <meta content="02WASH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165613"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">White House (Washington, DC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henneberger, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">White House (Washington, DC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3DB1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Party: More Business Than Sparkle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henneberger, Melinda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres and Mrs Clinton hold millennium party at White House, but it seems oddly like a business dinner, with more than a few of the 360 guests taking opportunity to plug some project or product (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite the beluga and the rack of lamb, Elizabeth Taylor in a pink boa and Lara Flynn Boyle nuzzling Jack Nicholson at a table near the back of the East Room, the White House Millennium supper seemed oddly like a business dinner.</p>
        <p>As arriving guests -- some 360  artists, scientists and fund-raisers, along with major donors, loyal senators and favorite employees -- filed past reporters in the entryway of the White House, more than a few took the opportunity to plug some project or product.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite the beluga and the rack of lamb, Elizabeth Taylor in a pink boa and Lara Flynn Boyle nuzzling Jack Nicholson at a table near the back of the East Room, the White House Millennium supper seemed oddly like a business dinner.</p>
        <p>As arriving guests -- some 360  artists, scientists and fund-raisers, along with major donors, loyal senators and favorite employees -- filed past reporters in the entryway of the White House, more than a few took the opportunity to plug some project or product.</p>
        <p>''I'm celebrating the 21st century in telecommunications infrastructure,'' said one sentimentalist. Terry McAuliffe crowed about raising $16 million to pay for the millennial extravaganza, and Mary Tyler Moore noted that she was celebrating her ABC movie ''Mary and Rhoda,'' scheduled for 8 p.m. on Feb. 7: ''I've just seen the rough cut and I'm very proud.'' Mary Wilson announced a reunion of the Supremes.</p>
        <p>Others said outright that they felt they had gotten their money's worth in return for major donations to pay for the festivities. And inside the dinner, executives seated near Commerce Secretary William M. Daley were openly lobbying him on behalf of their businesses.</p>
        <p>There was a conspicuous lack of flashy jewelry on display, and as many women in low-key velvet pants and tunics as in taffeta gowns. Some, presumably, were dressing to accommodate the silk long johns recommended by the White House to keep warm while watching the show on the Mall later in the evening.</p>
        <p>Still, a few guests were sparkling, and the hostess, too: Hillary Rodham Clinton's black silk dress was offset by a collar of glittering stones. And when a rather baldly appreciative  reporter asked Sophia Loren whether she would be able to keep warm in her low-cut black dress, she said, ''I have a little wrap,'' and seemed to gesture toward the diamonds and rubies around her neck.</p>
        <p>The president began the dinner with a toast, and on the last New Year's of the century, Mr. Clinton asked his guests, who were packed Paris-bistro close in both the East Room and the State Dining Room, to make a wish, and said he would do likewise. He kept his own hopes to himself, but spoke of a better future that ''I hope every American will take a moment to imagine on this Millennium Eve.''</p>
        <p>Then, joking that he could hardly be expected to recap the last 1,000 years when ''in the State of the Union I get a whole hour to talk about a single year and usually I run over,'' he asked the crowd to join him in a three-part toast to themselves, to Mrs. Clinton, and to the future itself.</p>
        <p>Guests included the Nobel prize-winning scientist Murray Gell-Mann, who gamely tried out some jokes on Sid Caesar, and Muhammad Ali, who got a bear hug from the president.  Walter Kaye, the political supporter responsible for first bringing Monica Lewinsky to the White House, was also on the guest list.</p>
        <p>Senator Edward M. Kennedy, accompanied by his wife, Victoria Reggie Kennedy, and his sister, Jean Kennedy Smith, a former ambassador to Ireland, came in shouting, ''See my pretty sister the ambassador?'' Lynda Johnson Robb said her red brocade jacket had begun life as a smoking jacket worn by her father, President Lyndon B. Johnson.</p>
        <p>The contingent of actors included in the crowd, including Ossie Davis, Julie Harris and Robert DeNiro, who raced past reporters while they were arguing over whether Mr. Nicholson had just said he was glad to be there because ''this is America here,'' or ''this is America, dear.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor arrived about an hour late after being ''either caught in traffic or lost,'' a White House spokeswoman said. Wearing a deep red velvet gown, she laughed with gusto as she was led with halting steps toward the East Room, while an assistant pushing a wheelchair followed her. Chelsea Clinton, who was dressed in midnight blue, joined her parents in the receiving line, the first time she had taken on such official host duties.</p>
        <p>After dinner -- tastes of caviar, foie gras and oyster veloute and a main course of rack of lamb served with roasted artichoke and pepper ragout, followed by a green salad and chocolate and champagne dessert -- guests were bused to the Mall.</p>
        <p>The show at the foot of the Lincoln Memorial was nothing if not eclectic, with Tom Jones singing, ''It's Not Unusual,'' to Bobby McFerrin, Jessye Norman and Kathleen Battle performing, ''He's Got the Whole World in His Hands.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
