<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOD: The Lives They Lived: Grace Zia Chu, b. 1900; West Meets East</title>
    <meta content="TLTLFOODT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="57" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jen, Gish</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chu, Grace Zia (1900-99)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D91E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOD: The Lives They Lived: Grace Zia Chu, b. 1900; West Meets East</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gish Jen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jen, Gish</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>west meets east**A</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In China, Grace Zia Chu had been a gym teacher; in 1950's America, she became Madame Chu, a well-known Chinese-cooking expert whose Manhattan cooking classes and cookbooks initiated a whole generation of Americans in the mysteries of the stir-fry. Today, we are struck by the enormous gulf that Madame Chu sought to span and by the tone with which she spanned it: she opens her groundbreaking 1962 cookbook, ''The Pleasures of Chinese Cooking,'' with the tremendous poise of an ambassador. ''We Chinese,'' she begins, ''like to think of cooking as a distinctive art form.''</p>
        <p>In fact, by the time those words were published, Grace Zia Chu had graduated from Wellesley and worked for the Chinese Embassy in Washington; she had been an American citizen for seven years. Yet she inhabits both the alienation and majesty of the phrase ''we Chinese'' with a graciousness that is touching. Did she feel she had a choice? Did she ever weary of being seen as a foreigner? Did she feel caught between worlds? If so, she gave no sign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In China, Grace Zia Chu had been a gym teacher; in 1950's America, she became Madame Chu, a well-known Chinese-cooking expert whose Manhattan cooking classes and cookbooks initiated a whole generation of Americans in the mysteries of the stir-fry. Today, we are struck by the enormous gulf that Madame Chu sought to span and by the tone with which she spanned it: she opens her groundbreaking 1962 cookbook, ''The Pleasures of Chinese Cooking,'' with the tremendous poise of an ambassador. ''We Chinese,'' she begins, ''like to think of cooking as a distinctive art form.''</p>
        <p>In fact, by the time those words were published, Grace Zia Chu had graduated from Wellesley and worked for the Chinese Embassy in Washington; she had been an American citizen for seven years. Yet she inhabits both the alienation and majesty of the phrase ''we Chinese'' with a graciousness that is touching. Did she feel she had a choice? Did she ever weary of being seen as a foreigner? Did she feel caught between worlds? If so, she gave no sign.</p>
        <p>Hers were innocent times, it is true. Other books advertised in the paperback version of her volume include ''How to Carry On a Conversation'' and ''Bowling for Women.'' Yet Madame Chu was more than the innocent emanation of innocent times. She wrote as a woman aware of her situation in society and chose the words that befit that situation. But she also wrote as someone who gauged her audience perfectly.</p>
        <p>The fantastic restraint involved in her enterprise is apparent when we compare her first book with her second. The recipes in ''The Pleasure of Chinese Cooking'' start off with the most popular dishes in what she calls ''Chinese-American'' restaurants -- chop suey, chow mein and egg foo yong. Painstakingly, she works the reader up to Chinese dishes using ingredients from American supermarkets, and then to Chinese dishes, using authentic Chinese ingredients like hoisin sauce.</p>
        <p>In contrast, ''Madame Chu's Chinese Cooking School,'' published 13 years later, explodes with recipes involving pork kidneys, fish and hog maws, longans, laver, taro, yuca, amaranth, silver fungus, lotus seeds, hairy melon, hairlike seaweed and more. Whereas the first book focuses on the proper use of chopsticks and of the ''Chinese-style'' cleaver (''a heavy knife with a broad and -- believe it or not -- rectangular-shaped blade''), the second blithely assumes a reader undaunted by tasks like carving potatoes into reindeer or turning a duck inside out while deboning it, then restoring it to its skin.</p>
        <p>But of course, by 1975, times had changed so markedly that her second book begins with</p>
        <p>the subtitle ''Why Another Chinese Cookbook?'' There is still cultural distance to navigate. In the ''Questions and Answers'' section, Madame Chu entertains queries like ''Do the Chinese have birth-day parties?'' and ''Is it true that Chinese people do not have high blood pressure?'' She explains</p>
        <p>that fortune cookies were invented in America and originally filled with Bible verses selected by a Presbyterian minister; also that the Chinese referred to sizzling rice dishes as ''Bomb Tokyo'' during World War II -- and considered this patriotic.</p>
        <p>Her tone, though, is much altered. The sweeping ''We Chinese'' is sometimes replaced, awkwardly, by references to ''the Chinese.'' Sometimes she reaches, evasively, for the passive voice. Never does she write ''We Americans.'' Self-consciousness and the complexities of assimilation have finally caught up with Madame Chu; the core of her second book is wavering and nascent.</p>
        <p>Yet what she has lost in certainty she seems to have gained in human connection and simple joy. She closes her book with recipes her students have invented. You do not have to be Chinese, she says, to invent Chinese dishes.</p>
        <p>In the cover photo of her second book, Madame Chu is dressed in a qipao. She is not mugging for the camera, Martha Stewart-style. She is not even looking at the camera, but rather, head bent, at a bit of garnish she is putting in place. Look at my food, she seems to be saying. Or else, maybe, Just eat. Her modesty recalls a story she tells in her first book about the empty chair left at a banquet table for a famous Chinese chef. He never occupied that chair, of course, being far too busy in the kitchen. Yet the place was left for him. He was present in his absence; his place was and was not his place. Madame Chu similarly seems to have been present and absent -- to have had a place in America, and to have had no place.</p>
        <p>Chicken Chow Mein  (From ''The Pleasures of Chinese Cooking,'' by Grace Zia Chu, Simon &amp; Schuster, 1962)</p>
        <p>8 ounces thin spaghetti</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons peanut oil, plus oil for deep frying</p>
        <p>1/2 cup shredded Chinese cabbage</p>
        <p>1/2 cup shredded celery</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons soy sauce</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon sugar</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon monosodium glutamate</p>
        <p>1/2 cup clear chicken broth</p>
        <p>1/2 cup fresh or canned bean sprouts</p>
        <p>1 cup cooked chicken, shredded</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon cornstarch.</p>
        <p>1. Drop spaghetti in 2 quarts of boiling water and boil for 3 minutes. Drain, and then steam in a steamer for 20 minutes. The spaghetti will not stick together. Remove spaghetti from steamer and deep fry in hot oil until crisp. Set the spaghetti aside.</p>
        <p>2. Heat the 2 tablespoons of peanut oil in a frying pan over high flame and saute the Chinese cabbage and celery for about 2 minutes. Add the soy sauce, sugar and monosodium glutamate. Mix well. Add the chicken broth and bring to boil. Add bean sprouts and shredded chicken and mix.</p>
        <p>3. Dissolve 1 tablespoon cornstarch in 2 tablespoons water. When the broth begins to boil again, thicken with the cornstarch and water.</p>
        <p>4. Place fried spaghetti on a large platter and pour the chicken-and-vegetable mixture over it. Serve hot.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Tips: Chow mein has become so popular that prefried noodles are now available in many food stores. These preprepared noodles save time and effort. But if you like to start from scratch, thin spaghetti is the nearest thing to Chinese noodles.</p>
        <p>Cooked beef, shrimp and other ingredients may be used in place of chicken to make beef chow mein, shrimp chow mein, etc.</p>
        <p>Clams in Black Bean Sauce  (From ''Madame Chu's Chinese Cooking School,'' by Grace Zia Chu, Fireside, 1975)  To most Americans, clams rank just below apple pie in any list of typically American foods, so it may come as a surprise to find that Chinese living in coastal areas, who have never heard of clam chowder, eat and enjoy clams. Here, clams are cooked with black beans, a favorite Chinese accompaniment for seafood.</p>
        <p>18 to 20 littleneck clams (about 2 1/2 pounds)</p>
        <p>2 cups liquid, preferably the juice of the clams</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon vegetable oil</p>
        <p>4 thin slices fresh ginger</p>
        <p>2 cloves garlic, crushed</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons crushed fermented black beans (see Tips, below)</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons oyster sauce</p>
        <p>2 1/2 tablespoons cornstarch dissolved in 3 tablespoons water</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons chopped scallion, green part.</p>
        <p>1. Wash and clean clams. Soak in water for about 1 hour, then drain. Heat 2 quarts of water to a boil and add half the clams. As soon as each opens, remove it; then add the remaining clams and repeat the process. Pour cooking liquid into a container and let sand settle to the bottom. Measure out 2 cups of liquid for making sauce.</p>
        <p>2. Heat oil in a saucepan. Add ginger, garlic and fermented beans. Let them sizzle in the oil for a minute. Add 2 cups clam liquid. Let it boil for 2 minutes. Discard ginger and garlic.</p>
        <p>3. Add oyster sauce and mix a few times. Thicken with the predissolved cornstarch mixture (stirring again to make sure the water and cornstarch are thoroughly mixed).</p>
        <p>4. Arrange clams on platter and sprinkle scallions on top. Pour boiling sauce over clams. Serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Tips: Fermented black beans and oyster sauce, both staples that have many uses and keep well on the shelf, are available in Chinese grocery stores. To crush the black beans, place them on a flat surface and hit hard with a heavy object, like the flat side of a cleaver. After the package of beans has been opened, place the remaining beans in a plastic bag, tied securely, or in a jar with a good lid.</p>
        <p>Duck Sauce  (from ''Madame Chu's Chinese Cooking School,'' by Grace Zia Chu, Fireside, 1975)  The name ''duck sauce'' was created in the United States because this sauce was originally served with deep-fried pressed duck, which had no sauce of its own. Duck sauce became popular as a dip for any food -- from spareribs and egg rolls to almost anything else imaginable. There are so many versions of duck sauce that it is hard to decide which kind to make. However, I have created and tested the following, which I feel produces the best taste:</p>
        <p>1 cup Chinese plum sauce</p>
        <p>1 cup apricot preserves</p>
        <p>1 cup peach preserves</p>
        <p>1 cup applesauce</p>
        <p>2 teaspoons dry mustard</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon garlic powder</p>
        <p>1/2 cup chili sauce.</p>
        <p>1. Pick out from the canned or bottled plum sauce any solid pieces, like ginger, pimento or other spices. Discard these.</p>
        <p>2. Combine all the ingredients in a large mixing bowl and mix thoroughly with chopsticks or fork.</p>
        <p>3. Store in jars and leave in the refrigerator. The duck sauce will keep for months.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 12-ounce bottles.</p>
        <p>Tips: Chinese plum sauce can be bought in Chinese grocery stores. Some supermarkets and specialty stores also stock it.</p>
        <p>Gish Jen is the author of the recent story collection ''Who's Irish?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gish Jen is the author of the recent story collection ''Who's Irish?''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
