<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE YEAR 2000: THE 90's -- A Look at Lasts For 1999; As the Champagne Goes Flat, A Final Toast to a Final Year</title>
    <meta content="02LAST$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Twenty-First Century</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">My Second Home (Mount Kisco, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Our Towns (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4DA1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1270" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE YEAR 2000: THE 90's -- A Look at Lasts For 1999; As the Champagne Goes Flat, A Final Toast to a Final Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matthew Purdy Our Towns column on senior citizens at My Second Home day care center in Mount Kisco, NY, and their thoughts about living in another century (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The year 2000 is well under way. Most people have overcome their hangovers; some have already broken their New Year's resolutions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The year 2000 is well under way. Most people have overcome their hangovers; some have already broken their New Year's resolutions.</p>
        <p>But 1999 should not pass without a proper farewell. The final year of the 1900's ended with a bang in New York City: crime was low, the stock market was supercharged and the Yankees could lay claim to the title Best Team of the Century.</p>
        <p>So here's a toast in the form of a completely subjective list of lasts in New York City. Bottoms up!</p>
        <p>The last baby born was apparently William Vera 3rd, who appeared at exactly 11:30 p.m. at St. Vincents in Manhattan. He was 7 pounds 2 ounces.</p>
        <p>The last baby at the Bronx Zoo was Pashmina, a lesser bird of paradise, which hatched on Tuesday in an incubator in the World of Birds. By age 5 it should be a yellow-plumed adult, two and a half feet long and weighing half a pound. But now it is a featherless 15 grams.</p>
        <p>The last arrest was of a 21-year-old man picked up at 34th Street and Fifth Avenue, about 11 p.m., by police officers who noticed that he had a bulletproof vest. The man, whose name was not available, was released after it was determined that he was a marine and was authorized to have the vest. Officers said that unauthorized possession of such a vest is a crime.</p>
        <p>The New York State Department of Environmental Conservation filed the last federal lawsuit in Manhattan on Thursday, suing the owners of an abandoned paper mill in Napanoch, N.Y., for the multimillion-dollar cost of cleaning up toxic waste at the site.The last poll on the New York race for Senate was conducted Dec. 7-12 by Quinnipiac College and showed 42 percent for Hillary Rodham Clinton and 46 percent for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani among registered voters.</p>
        <p>The Empire State Building ended the year bathed in red and green lights for Christmas.</p>
        <p>The last bottle of Champagne sold at Sherry-Lehman's on New Year's Eve was a $249.95 bottle of Dom Perignon Rose purchased by a man named David Dawson who said he was going to drink it at home with his friends and family.</p>
        <p>The last item auctioned at Sotheby's was the prison jacket worn by Elvis Presley in the 1957 film ''Jailhouse Rock.'' It sold for $13,800 on Dec. 18.</p>
        <p>On Wall Street, the last initial public offering of the year was StreaMedia Communication, a ''multimedia content generator, enabler and aggregator'' based in Manhattan that hit the market on Dec. 22, said Richard Peterson, a market strategist for Thomson Financial Securities Data of Newark. StreaMedia (Nasdaq ticker: SMILU) was priced at $8.50, opened at $8.625, peaked at $12.50 on Dec. 27 and fell back down. On Friday, the Dow closed at 11,497.12, up 26,130 percent for the century.</p>
        <p>The last film running at the Film Forum was ''Dr. Strangelove.''</p>
        <p>The last game played at Yankee Stadium was on Oct. 27, when the Yankees beat the Atlanta Braves, 4-1, to sweep the World Series. It was the Yankees' 25th championship of the century.</p>
        <p>The last game played at Shea Stadium ended on Oct. 17, when the Mets beat the Atlanta Braves 4-3 on Robin Ventura's 15th-inning home run, a shot that briefly kept the Mets' pennant hopes alive.</p>
        <p>The year's last game at Giants Stadium was on Dec. 26, when the Minnesota Vikings beat the Giants 34-17.  And the last professional sporting event at Madison Square Garden ended in a tie: The New York Rangers and the New Jersey Devils tied 3-3.</p>
        <p>The last meal at Le Bernardin, the four-star fish emporium in Manhattan, was an order just after 10 p.m. on Thursday from the table of an investment banker for Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>He and five guests chose the seven-course, $120-per-person tasting menu, featuring thinly sliced geoduck marinated with wasabi and soy-ginger dressing, and scallops with black truffle sauce.</p>
        <p>''Then we opened several magnums of Champagne for the kitchen staff,'' said Eric Ripert, the chef. ''We were cooking with a smile.''</p>
        <p>The last personal ad to run in the Village Voice (under the ''Anything Goes'' category) began: ''Y2K TOGETHER (Your place/mine) BiW/M sks very fem TV cross-dresser.''</p>
        <p>Because the theaters in Times Square are closed on New Year's Eve, the last song sung in a Broadway musical was in ''Marie Christine,'' which was able to have a special 7 p.m. New Year's Eve performance at the Vivian Beaumont Theater in Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>The last clue in the last New York Times crossword puzzle was 64 down, three letters that define ''When D.S.T. ends.'' (Answer: ''2AM.'')</p>
        <p>The last H&amp;H bagel sold at the company's 80th Street store was a poppy seed bagel purchased moments before midnight by Ezra Millstein, of West 73rd Street.</p>
        <p>At 6:30 p.m. Thursday, New York City's oldest bookstore, Gotham Book Mart, sold its last book, to a woman from Los Angeles named Young-Im Yoo: a $7 paperback, illustrated by Edward Gorey, of T.S. Eliot's ''Old Possum's Book of Practical Cats,'' on which the deathless Broadway musical ''Cats'' was based. As they say, now and forever.</p>
        <p>Capt. Bob Fischer, six months short of his retirement after 34 years flying with T.W.A., was at the controls of the last commercial flight out of Kennedy International Airport.</p>
        <p>The plane -- a year-old Boeing 767-300 that can hold 229 passengers -- took off at 10:17 p.m. for the 10-hour nonstop flight to Tel Aviv with a mere 12 paying passengers on board.</p>
        <p>The last steak served at the Peter Luger Steakhouse in Brooklyn was an enormous, five-pound, medium-rare ''triple'' ($92.85), split by two cousins, Anthony Mekel, 29, of Brooklyn, and John Boulos, 27, of Staten Island.</p>
        <p>The last cheesecake served at Juniors on Flatbush Avenue in Brooklyn was a large strawberry ($34.50) to go, purchased by Hilda Brown of Brooklyn moments before midnight. ''She was on her way to a party, and I think she was going to be late for the millennium,'' said Kevin Rosen, one of the restaurant's owners. ''She probably celebrated with the cheesecake in her car.''</p>
        <p>The last CD sold at the Tower Records store on West Fourth Street in Manhattan was of the piano music of the Norwegian composer Edvard Grieg -- mostly selections from ''Norwegian Peasant Dances'' -- performed by Einar Steen-Nokleberg. It cost $6.99 plus tax.</p>
        <p>The last joke told at Caroline's Comedy Club came from the comic and actor Kevin Meaney. It was delivered by Mr. Meaney from the street just outside the club on Broadway against a backdrop of screaming Times Square ball watchers and was televised inside the club on a video screen. The joke, Mr. Meaney's ''last scoop of the century,'' was that it was actually Sean Combs who stabbed George Harrison.</p>
        <p>The last question posed to the New York Public Library's Telephone Reference Service came from a caller who wanted to know where Hemingway got the phrase ''A Moveable Feast'' for the title of his memoir. In it, he describes Paris as a ''moveable feast'' that stays with you ''wherever you go for the rest of your life.''</p>
        <p>The phrase, it turns out, refers to feasts that move in time, not space, said the reference line's supervisor, Harriet Shalat. According to the Book of Common Prayer, Christian holidays like Easter that fall on different days each year are moveable feasts. Christmas is not. The millennium is definitely not moveable, although there is disagreement over when it should be celebrated.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
