<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Nassau's Halls of Justice Nearly Come Tumbling Down</title>
    <meta content="02COUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courthouses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ain, Stewart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0DF1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Nassau's Halls of Justice Nearly Come Tumbling Down</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEWART AIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ain, Stewart</byline>
      <dateline>MINEOLA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nassau County, LI, has many courthouses in poor condition, with peeling paint, water leaks, falling plaster, duct tape holding celing tiles in place and broken chairs in jury rooms; county says it spends $1.3 million a year for maintenance of its state courts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUSTICE EDWARD McCABE, Nassau County's administrative judge, pointed to the original industrial carpeting put down when the Supreme Court building was built in 1964. After 35 years of stains and wear, it still covers most of the floors.</p>
        <p>''They put duct tape over the holes in the carpet,'' he said. ''Carpeting is the obligation of the county and they have not replaced it. In one courtroom, I got the Office of Court Administration to put in new carpeting because the jurors kept tripping on the worn carpeting as they left the jury box.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUSTICE EDWARD McCABE, Nassau County's administrative judge, pointed to the original industrial carpeting put down when the Supreme Court building was built in 1964. After 35 years of stains and wear, it still covers most of the floors.</p>
        <p>''They put duct tape over the holes in the carpet,'' he said. ''Carpeting is the obligation of the county and they have not replaced it. In one courtroom, I got the Office of Court Administration to put in new carpeting because the jurors kept tripping on the worn carpeting as they left the jury box.''</p>
        <p>Duct tape was also used to cover a screw protruding from a metal saddle in the doorway of one of the judge's offices, to hold ceiling tiles in place and to keep the unwary from trying to sit on two broken chairs in the jury empaneling room.</p>
        <p>''Whoever invented duct tape is making a lot of money,'' quipped George Moser, first deputy chief clerk of the Supreme Court. But Justice McCabe was not amused.</p>
        <p>''Our place is a mess,'' he said. ''I don't see any reason for it. We're the richest county in the state and we should have decent public buildings.''</p>
        <p>Nassau County says it spends about $1.3 million a year for the maintenance of its state courts. But a look at all the peeling paint, water leaks, falling plaster and accumulated grime is enough to make one wonder where the maintenance money went. And with the county opening the year with an estimated budget deficit of $110 million, it's hard to imagine where the fix-up money will come from.</p>
        <p>Since 1977, counties have been required to provide the state with courthouses and to maintain them. A spokesman for the state Office of Court Administration, David Bookstaver, said the state covers the cost of furnishings and reimburses the counties half of their maintenance costs, a figure that is scheduled to rise to 75 percent in April.</p>
        <p>In the 1998-99 fiscal year, Nassau County billed the state about $650,000 for maintenance fees -- a fact that enrages Justice McCabe.</p>
        <p>''The state Office of Court Administration has a contract with the county for it to do the cleaning, and it is not living up to it!'' he fumed. ''I don't know what their excuse is.''</p>
        <p>Poor maintenance of the court buildings is not anything new, according to Michael J. Murphy, president of the Court Officers Benevolent Association. He said that when he first became a court officer in Nassau in 1980, the state Supreme Court building in Mineola ''was the showcase building.''</p>
        <p>''But for the last 10 to 15 years, there has been a steady deterioration in the daily maintenance of all of the court buildings,'' he said. ''We have had to deal with constant problems, from air quality to water quality and the condition of the restrooms.''</p>
        <p>Judith A. Jacobs, the new presiding officer of the county Legislature, said she was ''appalled and disturbed'' to learn of conditions in the courthouses.</p>
        <p>''It is indicative of the mismanagement that has been running rampant in this county,'' said Ms. Jacobs, who along with her fellow Democrats won control of the Legislature in November.</p>
        <p>''The problem,'' she said, ''is not the work force but the top-heavy management and the lack of recognition of what was needed financially. We are in a mess fiscally, and seeing buildings like this is a horror.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Jacobs said the court buildings were not alone in having maintenance problems. She said the County Executive Building in Mineola where she works has only one person to clean the five-story building and ''he is in charge of two other buildings as well.''</p>
        <p>''How do you expect one person to care for a five-story building of this size and two others besides?'' she asked. ''Who's kidding whom? I'm not looking for maid service, but normal maintenance.''</p>
        <p>Deputy County Executive Cheryl Petri said she was unaware of many of the conditions complained about but said the county Legislature allocated $500,000 to survey the courts in the county and come up with a multiyear capital improvement program.</p>
        <p>''The investigative phase began with a kickoff meeting in early November,'' she said. ''Our Department of Public Works is working with the state Dormitory Authority, which hired an architectural firm to produce a plan and is managing the project. The plan is to be completed by June and then submitted to the Legislature for adoption.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Petri said that a portion of any money allocated for capital improvements could be used to replace carpeting.</p>
        <p>Justice McCabe said he knew of the study but questioned why he has yet to be contacted and asked what improvements he would suggest.</p>
        <p>To illustrate how rundown the buildings have become, Justice McCabe took a reporter and photographer on a tour of the Supreme Court and County Court buildings in Mineola. The first thing a visitor notices when entering the Supreme Court's west entrance is the sign to the left of the doors identifying the building as the ''Supreme Court of the State of  e</p>
        <p>ork.'' And the large county and state seals on the side of the building are covered with pigeon droppings.</p>
        <p>Inside, after demonstrating the versatility of duct tape, Justice McCabe walked into a courtroon and pointed out the condition of the wood fixtures -- the judge's bench, the clerks' desks, the walls, the doors and railings. All were heavily scratched and worn.</p>
        <p>''They have never been maintained,'' he said. ''It's all beautiful wood. It's just a matter of sanding it down and refinishing it.''</p>
        <p>On the fourth floor, the vinyl wallpaper below the water fountain was buckled, apparently from an old leak in the fountain. The judge said that none of the 24 water fountains in the building have been operational for nearly three years. They were turned off after a 1997 test of the water by the State Department of Labor found high concentrations of lead.</p>
        <p>Ms. Petri said that the county hired a company to come up with ways to solve the problem and that it will take $300,000 to implement the recommendations. County Executive Thomas S. Gulotta proposed issuing a bond to cover the cost. But since October, the Legislature has failed to consider it, she said.</p>
        <p>Justice McCabe said that when visitors and employees complained about the lack of water in the courthouse, the county put more than a dozen portable water coolers throughout the building. But he said empty water bottles are sometimes not replaced for days and that when there is water, there are often no cups.</p>
        <p>Such was the case recently with a fourth-floor water cooler that stood outside a room lawyers once used to take pre-trial depositions. Mr. Moser said he was forced to close the room when ''concrete started falling from the ceiling because of water leaks. For three years we have been waiting for it to be repaired.''</p>
        <p>In the nearby jury assembly room, a half dozen chairs were either broken or without seat cushions. The commissioner of jurors, Thomas G. DeVivo, said these were the original chairs and that the cushions were so worn on several of them that jurors sat on springs.</p>
        <p>Across the street in the County Court, Mr. DeVivo pointed to the ceiling in one of his offices. Nearly a dozen acoustical ceiling tiles had fallen and employees were working beneath other tiles that appeared about to fall. He said one employee had been hit on the head by one of the lightweight tiles.</p>
        <p>In the office of Mr. DeVivo's deputy, a plastic cover was placed over the computer equipment to shield it from a leak above. And there were water stains on the floor and the walls.</p>
        <p>''There are air conditioning units that were installed in the 1960's, but half of them don't work,'' Mr. DeVivo said.</p>
        <p>Justice Ira Wexner, supervising judge of the County Court, showed visitors a cracked window and broken window blinds in one of the courtrooms. A tour of the men's room was cut short when a court officer, walking out, advised: ''Better hold your nose before going in.''</p>
        <p>Looking up into the rotunda, the most impressive feature of the 1938 W.P.A.-built courthouse, a large water stain could be clearly seen running down the wall of the third floor; paint from the ceiling was flaking.</p>
        <p>A survey of conditions in the County Court building prepared for the state by court officials found that the building's fire extinguishers were last inspected in 1996 and that light bulbs in the emergency lighting system were missing.</p>
        <p>Justice McCabe noted that when there was a power failure in November, the emergency lights failed to activate in the Supreme Court building.</p>
        <p>''It turns out that the generator that was supposed to work didn't,'' he said. ''The county has no plan of regular maintenance and no one had checked to make sure it was working.''</p>
        <p>The judge pointed out also that outdoor lights along the paths surrounding the Supreme Court building did not work because of electrical problems, and that many of the street lights had been broken and never repaired. He said the county had also been subject to lawsuits from people who had fallen on broken or missing slate walks around the building.</p>
        <p>Nor is the problem confined to the central complex. At First District Court in Hempstead, Deputy Supervising Judge Ira J. Raab pointed out numerous cracks in the walls -- he said he counted nine -- along the second floor hallway, as well as missing and broken ceiling tiles. He also walked into several empty courtrooms to introduce a visitor to what he called the ''shadow people'' -- images of people sitting in the jury box and spectator seats that were outlined on the vinyl wallpaper.</p>
        <p>''It's the grease from people's heads and shoulders,'' the judge explained. ''These walls have not been washed since the building opened in 1989.''</p>
        <p>Judge Raab then walked to the east side of the building to point out all of the windows the staff had opened that morning, even though the outside temperature was in the 30's.</p>
        <p>''It's 82 degrees in there,'' said the judge after checking the room thermostat in one courtroom where a large floor fan was running and lawyers and court personnel were working in shirtsleeves. ''Did you ever expect to see a fan going in a courtroom the day before Christmas? And in the summer, you freeze in this courtroom.''</p>
        <p>He said he was told that faulty equipment prevented building engineers from properly adjusting temperature levels.</p>
        <p>As Judge Raab took the visitor to another part of the building, he entered the public corridor where an officer at a security table sat in front of a console.</p>
        <p>''What's that for?'' the judge asked.</p>
        <p>''I have no idea,'' replied the officer. ''It has never worked.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Jacobs said she plans to meet with Justice McCabe shortly to prioritize his needs.</p>
        <p>''Anything that is injurious to the health, safety and welfare of the jurors, lawyers, visitors and court personnel will have a priority,'' she said. ''Aesthetic things like stains on the walls will have to wait because of the fiscal crisis. I know it's an abomination. It is inexcusable for people to work in these conditions.''</p>
        <p>But Justice McCabe said that conditions have so deteriorated that this week he plans to ask the state to cancel the county's maintenance contract and permit him to hire private contractors. He pointed out that the state has similar contracts with the cities of Long Beach and Glen Cove and that the courtrooms there are properly maintained.</p>
        <p>''I don't see any reason why the county can't do the same,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
