<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Twins Who Also Share An Enigmatic Vision</title>
    <meta content="02SCWA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Turner Prize</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Las Vegas (Nev)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tate Gallery (London)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Caesars Palace (Las Vegas)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Desert Inn (Las Vegas)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Louise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwabsky, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada/Las Vegas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D91638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Twins Who Also Share An Enigmatic Vision</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY SCHWABSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwabsky, Barry</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barry Schwabsky reviews Tate Gallery's exhibit of latest video projection by Louise and Jane Wilson, 32-year-old twins who were nominated for 1999 Turner Prize; new work, Las Vegas, Graveyard Time, was filmed at Caesars Palace and Desert Inn casinos; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT a recent exhibition of the work of the neo-Classical architect Sir John Soane at the Royal Academy here, the video artists Jane and Louise Wilson were especially taken by a watercolor of the Bank of England in ruins. Here was a Soane work envisioned as a relic of the past rather than a project for the future.</p>
        <p>Their fascination with this image sheds a revealing light on the work of this team of 32-year-old twin sisters. They are best known for a pair of room-encompassing four-channel video-projection works filmed in abandoned outposts of cold war Europe: the headquarters of the East German secret police in Berlin and the United States missile base at Greenham Common, England. These are projections of a hallucinated architecture, the obsessively patient reconstruction of ruins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT a recent exhibition of the work of the neo-Classical architect Sir John Soane at the Royal Academy here, the video artists Jane and Louise Wilson were especially taken by a watercolor of the Bank of England in ruins. Here was a Soane work envisioned as a relic of the past rather than a project for the future.</p>
        <p>Their fascination with this image sheds a revealing light on the work of this team of 32-year-old twin sisters. They are best known for a pair of room-encompassing four-channel video-projection works filmed in abandoned outposts of cold war Europe: the headquarters of the East German secret police in Berlin and the United States missile base at Greenham Common, England. These are projections of a hallucinated architecture, the obsessively patient reconstruction of ruins.</p>
        <p>By that account, their newest work, ''Las Vegas, Graveyard Time,'' might seem a departure. But the two casinos where much of it was filmed, Caesars Palace and the Desert Inn, are already relics to some extent, their kitsch decor rendered passe by the family-style respectability of newer casinos like the Bellagio.</p>
        <p>''Las Vegas, Graveyard Time'' is currently on view at the Tate Gallery here. It is part of an exhibition of works by the Wilsons, who were nominated for the 1999 Turner Prize, which was won by another video and film artist, Steve McQueen.</p>
        <p>Initiated in 1984 and nominally intended to honor a British artist under 50 for an outstanding exhibition during the preceding year, the Turner has been seen, at least since its award to Damien Hirst in 1995, as conferring something approaching pop-star status. As Jane Wilson remarked not long after the 1998 prize had gone to Chris Ofili: ''I don't know how he can stand it. Sure, it's a great thing that he won, but the Turner Prize puts such a terrible pressure on a young artist.''</p>
        <p>It is hard not to imagine the Wilsons' being disappointed at missing out on the prize (and the $32,000 that goes with it), but they have seen plenty of pressure over the last year anyway.</p>
        <p>At the same time that they were finishing ''Las Vegas, Graveyard Time'' on a rush schedule, to have it ready for the opening of the show at the Tate on Oct. 20, they were also preparing for their first big museum exhibition, at the Serpentine Gallery here in September and October. The Serpentine show included an equally ambitious new work, ''Parliament,'' which was filmed last summer when the Houses of Lords and Commons were in recess.</p>
        <p>''Actually, they're scared out of their minds,'' Lisa Corrin, the curator of the exhibition at the Serpentine, confided as the Wilsons looked after last-minute details the day before the Tate opening. ''They're up to their eyeballs in details. They've even got their mother in from Newcastle to look after them.''</p>
        <p>Jane is the short-haired, outgoing twin, Louise the quieter, longer-haired one. They have cultivated a look that plays down their resemblance, though they clearly know how to use their twinhood for effect: having decided to go to art school in different parts of Britain (Jane in Newcastle, Louise in Dundee), they collaborated on a single work for their senior-thesis shows. They then went on to study together for their master's degree at Goldsmiths College, London, the breeding ground for much of the attention-getting new art that has come out of London in the 90's. Now they live together in the working-class Brixton neighborhood of South London, with a studio in Bermondsey, just below the Thames.</p>
        <p>Unlike Mr. Ofili, whose spirited collage-paintings are reminiscent of folk art and psychedelia, or Tracy Emin, another of this year's Turner nominees, the Wilsons are not part of the ''Sensation'' exhibition of new British art at the Brooklyn Museum, the show that brought Mr. Ofili notoriety for his painting ''The Holy Virgin Mary.'' Along with Mr. McQueen and a number of other young English artists who are drawing increasing attention, like Tacita Dean, one of last year's Turner nominees, they represent a very different strand in current British art, one that is perhaps more European in outlook than specifically English.</p>
        <p>The works in ''Sensation'' were drawn from the collection of Charles Saatchi, London's most prominent and omnivorous art collector. The artists most strongly associated with Mr. Saatchi's taste, among whom Mr. Hirst is the most notorious, use sculpture and painting to convey imagery that demands a visceral response; in this art, the complex critical moment may have more to do with examining one's own reactions to an object than with the object's formal elaboration.</p>
        <p>Artists like the Wilsons, Mr. McQueen and Ms. Dean, by contrast, work primarily with film and video (although all of them avail themselves of sculpture, photography and other media as well) to create work that may be equally concerned with emotionally laden public issues, but that engages them in a slower, subtler, more rigorously formalized way. (Although Mr. Saatchi's collection is otherwise broad, he has not so far shown much interest in video.)</p>
        <p>''Stasi City'' (1997) was the work that marked the Wilsons' arrival as more than just promising. By successfully taking on a site like the former East German secret-police headquarters, the Wilsons announced that they were ready to move on from the quirky, personal subject matter so typical of video work by young artists and engage with capital-H history. But not in a didactic spirit, or in the manner of a documentary. All the fears and anxieties of the cold war are there, certainly, but kept at a distance by a rigorous structure that shows them only in glimpses, like the faceless uniformed figures who occasionally pass through, conspicuous but enigmatic, ''like fading wisps of a dream when one awakens,'' as the critic Peter Schjeldahl writes in the exhibition catalog for the Serpentine.</p>
        <p>Their next work, ''Gamma'' (1999), was a companion piece to ''Stasi City,'' filmed in a Western landmark of the cold war as the earlier piece was in one of its Eastern outposts -- both of them now abandoned. More than that, it perfected the method that ''Stasi City'' had brilliantly adumbrated, with its spooky atmosphere reminiscent of science fiction and horror movies.</p>
        <p>Both works are four-channel, floor-to-ceiling video projections, creating a virtual architecture surrounding the viewer, which means that there is never a position from which all four screens are visible simultaneously. The camera restlessly roves deserted spaces, revealing resonant details without dwelling on them. The relentlessly mobile, anonymous viewpoint becomes as much the works' subject as the places being explored. There is no dialogue or voice-over to frame these details, only eerie sounds of machinery and echoing footsteps, sounds that sometimes make viewers whirl around to catch something that sounds as if it had just happened behind them.</p>
        <p>P HOTOGRAPHS from ''Gamma'' are currently being exhibited at the Carnegie International in Pittsburgh. Other United States exhibitions of the Wilsons' work are scheduled at the 303 Gallery in New York in September and at the List Visual Arts Center at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology next January.</p>
        <p>The new work at the Serpentine, ''Parliament,'' showed a continuation of the Wilsons' interest in working with politically charged spaces. Maybe that's why ''Las Vegas, Graveyard Time'' came as so much of a surprise. But there are similarities between the two works.</p>
        <p>Just as ''Parliament'' fuses parts of two distinct places, Commons and Lords, into a fictional ''third house,'' as Jane calls it, ''Las Vegas'' combines two casinos, along with corridors in the interior of the nearby Hoover Dam, into a single psycho-architectural experience.</p>
        <p>As Jane points out, while the other three works are built around horizontal and vertical camera movements, ''Las Vegas, Graveyard Time'' makes extensive use of circular camera movements. ''There are more pans,'' she says, ''like the motion of the roulette wheel. The whole point of the way the casinos are designed is keeping you there -- creating an enclosed mental space with no outside. It's like hypnotism, which was the subject of one of our earliest videotapes. And like the cinema, too.''</p>
        <p>The Wilsons may be fascinated by cinema's power to hypnotize, to pin its viewers down to a single spot, but the form of their installations is meant to resist it at the same time. ''The four-screen setup implicates you more, makes you less passive,'' Jane says. Louise adds, ''It's more like the way you move around sculpture.''</p>
        <p>Jane continues: ''When cinema first began it was very experimental. A lot of that's been lost, but you can experience things in a much more physical, engaged way.''</p>
        <p>Does that mean the Wilsons see their work (which is shot on film, though displayed as video) as closer to cinema than to art? ''No,'' they both insist at once, but then Louise distinguishes their work from most other video art by adding, ''Our production values are attempting to be as good as cinema.'' Maybe that's why critics who write about their work follow the artists themselves in invoking filmmakers like Andrei Tarkovsky or Dziga Vertov as predecessors, rather than video artists like Bruce Nauman or Joan Jonas.</p>
        <p>''Las Vegas, Graveyard Time'' imposes its own brand of austere, melancholy grandeur on the town least likely to want it. While video installations have become art-world darlings -- thanks to their ability to bring museums closer to the ethos of popular culture, to make them feel more like places of entertainment -- the Wilsons lend the genre something more like the near-abstraction and gravitas of high modernist films like Alain Resnais's ''Last Year at Marienbad.'' But in their work, as in that of Mr. McQueen and Ms. Dean, both strands, cinema and video art, are equally present. And that's part of what gives it its special strength, as well as its blend of accessibility and artistic reflexivity.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Barry Schwabsky is author of ''The Widening Circle: Consequences of Modernism in Contemporary Art.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Barry Schwabsky is author of ''The Widening Circle: Consequences of Modernism in Contemporary Art.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
