<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dean of 'Dadgum' Sets His Sights On a Championship</title>
    <meta content="02BOWD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sugar Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Bobby Bowden</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute &amp; State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowden, Bobby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E0DB1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dean of 'Dadgum' Sets His Sights On a Championship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>TALLAHASSEE, Fla., Jan. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Florida State Coach Bobby Bowden in view of upcoming Sugar Bowl against Virginia Tech for national title; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The coach is looking for soup in his kitchen, something warm to take to the couch while he puts up his feet and watches a nature show and lets his head clear from the cold he always manages to catch around the holidays. For an hour at least, until the wives of his assistant coaches arrive for a gift exchange, Bobby Bowden does not have to be Bobby Bowden, the kindly, homespun icon of Florida State football.</p>
        <p>Instead, he can be tired and 70 years old. He can be free of the meetings and game films and having to put names with the numbers and faces of some 80 kids a half a century younger than he his.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The coach is looking for soup in his kitchen, something warm to take to the couch while he puts up his feet and watches a nature show and lets his head clear from the cold he always manages to catch around the holidays. For an hour at least, until the wives of his assistant coaches arrive for a gift exchange, Bobby Bowden does not have to be Bobby Bowden, the kindly, homespun icon of Florida State football.</p>
        <p>Instead, he can be tired and 70 years old. He can be free of the meetings and game films and having to put names with the numbers and faces of some 80 kids a half a century younger than he his.</p>
        <p>Forty-eight hours ago, Bowden flew to Dallas and back to visit a high school recruit. There have been two crisply paced staff meetings, where the coach consulted his voluminous notes and tersely told his assistants what they needed to do if Florida State was going to win a second national title, if, after 34 years and 303 career victories as a head coach, Bowden was going to complete his first undefeated season by beating Virginia Tech in the Sugar Bowl on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>For four more hours, he has stood alone on a tower above the practice field and scratched more notes for more terse instructions. In between, he has signed dozens of footballs and pictures and answered hundreds of pieces of mail --  even dictating individual letters to members of a flag football team in Bartlett, Ill. He has taken two naps on his office couch and dozed off another time or two while watching game film.</p>
        <p>Now at home, the TV drowns out the Christmas carols his wife, Ann, plays on the compact disc player. The rustle of Bowden's garnet and gold Seminoles sweatsuit precedes him every time he pops his head around the corner to ask Ann whether the salad is for him. How about the ham? And which button turns off the music?</p>
        <p>''We're like most old people,'' says Ann Bowden, who through 50 years, 6 children and 21 grandchildren has been the coach's wife. ''We've got satellites and all this stuff, but if  we push a wrong button we don't know how to get it to work again. We remember things 30 years ago, but forget where we put our keys this morning.''</p>
        <p>The coach, indeed, has made concessions to age. He rides a golf cart to the practice field. He has turned over the play-calling to his offensive coordinator, Mark Richt. More often than he likes, Bowden must greet some of his players with a catch-all ''buddy'' when their names do not immediately find their way to the tip of his tongue.</p>
        <p>But one thing that has not dimmed as Bowden squints his way through the twilight of his coaching career has been his success. For the third time in four years, Florida State (11-0) is playing for a national championship. For the 13th consecutive year, his team will finish in the top four in the national rankings and close out a season with 10 victories or more.</p>
        <p>From Big Brother To Grandfather</p>
        <p>Bowden dawdles in his kitchen and spends too much time on the sofa when he is home. When the man who has tried to return ''dadgum'' to the American lexicon, however, crosses his arms, shuts his eyes and remembers a head coaching career that began in 1955 at South Georgia College, he spits out game scores and players' names that span three seasons of a career.</p>
        <p>''When I first started, I had more a big brother relationship with my team,'' Bowden said. ''Then it evolved into a father-son thing, and now I'm more like a grandfather -- a little more patient and forgiving. Maybe softer.''</p>
        <p>Do not be fooled. Once a 100-yard football field is marked off and 22 players are on the field, Bowden is as hard-nosed and precise as the war generals he spends his off hours reading about.</p>
        <p>Earlier this afternoon, 45 minutes before practice began, the coach motored his golf cart to the practice field and parked all alone as he does every day. It is his sacred quiet time and no one dares to bother him -- not assistants, not players. In fact, when an errant punt bounced in his direction and threatened to disturb his peace, several of those beefy young Seminoles a quarter of his age cringed and tried to will the ball to bounce away from Bowden.</p>
        <p>If the icon has gone soft, it has not affected his sense of order. Though he has cut back his hours and likes to say he now only ''coaches his coaches,'' when Bowden ascends that steel platform at the start of each practice, every Seminole assistant, trainer and player knows who is in command.</p>
        <p>Terrell Buckley, the former Seminole defensive back now playing for the Miami Dolphins, dubbed it the ''Tower Of Power.'' It is where Seminoles who blew a blocking assignment or botched a pass route glance furtively, hoping that Bowden was concentrating on some other part of the field or writing in his notebook. His assistants do not bother looking -- they know Bowden has recorded the errors.</p>
        <p>''You dread getting those notes in the staff meetings in the morning,'' said Dave Van Halanger, the strength and conditioning coach who played for Bowden at West Virginia and has been an assistant at Florida State for 17 years. ''He doesn't miss anything. You know when it's coming.''</p>
        <p>But it is in his office, when a half-chewed cigar is jammed in his mouth, that Bowden most resembles the great military men he so admires. He insists on answering every bit of mail. His longtime assistant, Sue Hall, is constantly taking polite but firm orders over the intercom as he scribbles his name through a four-foot pile of mementos.</p>
        <p>''He's a tough guy to work for,'' Hall said. ''He wants things done his way and wants it done now. You don't run something this big without a certain regiment and pace.''</p>
        <p>By studying Patton, MacArthur and Rommel, Bowden has created something this big -- Florida State football. In the process, he joined Bear Bryant, Pop Warner, Amos Alonzo Stagg and Joe Paterno as the only major-college coaches to win 300 games. He does not care how cliche it sounds to link war and football; they have been his passion since he was bedridden with rheumatic fever as a 13-year-old in Birmingham, Ala.</p>
        <p>For six months, Bowden listened to World War II on the radio, imagining how the great generals' feigns and flanking maneuvers looked on the battle field. He shared the room with his grandfather, Robert Cleckler who was of German descent, so he paid special attention to enemy movements.</p>
        <p>From Rommel, Bowden learned a lesson about strategy. From Patton, MacArthur and the victors, he learned two traits that embody his Florida State program.</p>
        <p>''Rommel was a great tactician -- he knew how to think in surprises,'' Bowden said. ''He could do more with less than any of the great generals. They all demonstrate discipline and that you need reserves so if you're getting annihilated on one front, you can attack somewhere else.''</p>
        <p>The traits that would help Bowden claim his spot in college football history were in place in 1955 when, as a 25-year-old, he took his first head coaching job at South Georgia College. He won 22 games there, but they do not count on his record because at the time it was a two-year school.</p>
        <p>From the start, he showed a knack for recruiting. His team was culled from farm boys and returning veterans. He plucked his assistant and childhood friend, Vince Gibson, from a higher paying job as a high school coach in Florida. ''I took a $900 pay cut and left the beach to make $3,600 a year because Bobby sold me on the power we could build up there,'' says Gibson, who went on to coach Kansas State, Louisville and Tulane. He will play host to a party for Bowden, the South Georgia team and their Birmingham friends in New Orleans before the Sugar Bowl.</p>
        <p>Bowden is tough.</p>
        <p>In his second season, after South Georgia had lost its opener, Bowden addressed his ''boys'' -- it did not matter many were older than Bowden, he was the coach -- about rumors he had heard about their breaking training. He asked them to raise their hands if it was true. Seventeen hands went up -- 17 scholarships were taken away.</p>
        <p>''The thing about Bobby is that he comes off as such a nice, sweet Southern boy that people underestimate him,'' Gibson said. ''He's a tough guy and can be a hard one when he wants.''</p>
        <p>Bowden is loyal.</p>
        <p>Every year since, he has driven to Georgia for the reunion of those teams. ''You go to those reunions,'' Gibson said, ''and you got guys 65 years old who worship Bobby like a father.''</p>
        <p>There were two more head coaching stops that shaped Bowden before he arrived in Tallahassee in 1976. In 1959, he became head coach at his alma mater -- Howard, now Samford University -- in Birmingham. Down the road in Tuscaloosa, Bryant was in his second year of building Alabama into a power. Bowden often made the 50-mile drive to watch and learn. He saw how the military principle of reserves worked in football.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't one of his guys, but he was cordial and helpful,'' Bowden said. ''He knew I could help him out. In those days, Coach Bryant monopolized players because he had so many scholarships. Each spring, he'd have an assistant coach walk me around the field with a list of guys who weren't going to play much. They'd ask me who I wanted and then they'd talk the boys into transferring to us.''</p>
        <p>Learning What Coaching Really Is</p>
        <p>Though Bowden went 31-6 in four years at Samford, he returned to the assistant-coaching ranks -- including a stint at Florida State -- before being named coach of West Virginia in 1970. There, he went 42-26 over six seasons and learned a tough lesson: the game is a business. After finishing 4-7 in 1974, some Mountaineer fans hung him in effigy.</p>
        <p>''I'd probably still be there if that didn't happen,'' Bowden said. ''It taught me people are fickle and you got to do what's best for you.''</p>
        <p>When Florida State called in 1976, Bowden was thinking short term. Both his and Ann's mothers were widows in Birmingham, and Tallahassee was just a six-hour drive. Besides, the coach thought that sooner rather than later, Alabama or Auburn would be ready to bring him home as a head coach.</p>
        <p>''They didn't have facilities and the salary wasn't that great,'' Ann Bowden said. ''Frankly, I thought Bobby was ready to go to a big-time program.''</p>
        <p>Instead Bobby Bowden built one. Warrick Dunn, Deion Sanders and more than 40 other Seminoles are now in the National Football League. In athlete-rich Florida, Bowden found the raw talent to construct his football reserve. He went 5-6 his first season and has not been under .500 since. The Seminoles have gone to bowl games 18 straight years. Bowden has visited housing projects in Miami and farms in the Florida panhandle in pursuit of players. He can tick off recruiting adventures: the stoned grandfather who did not move in his rocking chair, the baby sister who fell asleep in his lap, the pecan pies a mama made in South Georgia.</p>
        <p>''I like people,'' Bowden said of recruiting. ''I like meeting their daddies and grandmas and visiting with them. It's not work at all.''</p>
        <p>And they like him -- so much so that they entrust him with their kids.</p>
        <p>Sermons About Life and Football</p>
        <p>Bowden concedes that his players do not drop into his office just to talk as much as they used to. He attributes it to the distance of generations and perhaps to the Bear-like status he has earned across the South. But just like members of those South Georgia teams, his current players idolize him. Still, when his star wide receiver Peter Warrick was arrested in a shopping mall scam, Bowden suspended him for two games before reinstating him after he pleaded guilty to a misdemeanor. Another wide receiver, Laveranues Coles, was also involved and was kicked off the team.</p>
        <p>''Laveranues had already been in trouble and I had warned him,'' Bowden said. ''It was Peter's first time. I got a lot of letters wondering how I could allow Peter back. I wrote every one of them -- first I don't condone that behavior. Second, if that was your kid and your life wouldn't you want him to have a second chance? And I haven't heard back from any of them.''</p>
        <p>Seminoles tight end Ryan Sprague said that those are the tenets Bowden preaches each Friday night before football games. He said the pregame talks are like church services: Bowden with his note cards is the pastor, the players his congregation. The sermon is about life; the last five minutes  about the truisms of football. Hang on to the ball. Do not arm-tackle.</p>
        <p>Sprague, a junior, was a walk-on for the Seminoles and did not have a conversation with his coach in his first two years. When Bowden acknowledged him one afternoon with a pinch and a ''Hey, buddy,'' Sprague rushed home to call his parents. Even now, on Bowden's Sunday highlight show, the coach misidentifies his starting tight end.</p>
        <p>''He's had me being from St. Augustine and from Savannah,'' said Sprague, who is from Augusta, Ga. ''But when you think about all the players he's had and all the history he's made, we're just a wrinkle in time for him. He is who he is. He is the guy who runs Florida State football and that means a whole lot to a bunch of people.''</p>
        <p>The coach spooning the soup on his sofa recently signed a contract worth $1 million a year through 2004. As much as Bowden likes watching TV, stroking the two cats that roam the house and going to Europe to retrace the campaigns of history's great generals, he likes being a coach more.</p>
        <p>He enjoys signing all those footballs, breaking down films and making all those notes. He is energized on Saturday nights in the winter, when a fire is roaring and pool lights in the backyard are on and he and Ann are having Florida State recruits and their families at their home for dessert.</p>
        <p>''He loves the television, the media, the recruiting the whole package that is college football,'' Ann Bowden said. ''I think it scares him to think this might be over.''</p>
        <p>Bowden will continue to take naps so he can climb the Tower of Power. He will continue to think football strategy all alone on his golf cart on the practice field. He believes he will continue to win. His reason is simple.</p>
        <p>''When you retire, there is just one more big event,'' he said. ''And I ain't ready for that.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
