<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Artist Uses New Kind of Canvas</title>
    <meta content="02MEGA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wozencraft, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aloni, Udi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDD1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Artist Uses New Kind of Canvas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN WOZENCRAFT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wozencraft, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli artist Udi Aloni creates wallscapes that display commercial advertisements on New York City buildings; wallscapes, unlike painted billboards, are printed via disk onto vinyl mesh material and hung flat like posters against sides of buildings; Aloni photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he stands on 42nd Street in Manhattan, Udi Aloni can see his ideas towering over the milling crowds. And with his photo-crisp advertisements for Apple Computer, the Gap, Old Navy and DKNY looming 40 feet high on the faces of skyscrapers, there is no question that Mr. Aloni, a 40-year-old Israeli artist, is making an impression on the Big Apple. From 10th Avenue to Broadway, Mr. Aloni's huge, high-resolution signs, called wallscapes, overlook every intersection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he stands on 42nd Street in Manhattan, Udi Aloni can see his ideas towering over the milling crowds. And with his photo-crisp advertisements for Apple Computer, the Gap, Old Navy and DKNY looming 40 feet high on the faces of skyscrapers, there is no question that Mr. Aloni, a 40-year-old Israeli artist, is making an impression on the Big Apple. From 10th Avenue to Broadway, Mr. Aloni's huge, high-resolution signs, called wallscapes, overlook every intersection.</p>
        <p>''My goal was to alter the urban landscape without having visual pollution,'' Mr. Aloni said. ''Wallscapes are much more organic to the city, and I thought it would be cool if I could hang my work on these buildings.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aloni came to New York in 1994 to focus on his art, not to dream up a new way of displaying commercial advertisements. But when he looked up at New York's massive buildings, he saw a potential canvas. He had already experimented with digital printing in his art -- interactive projects that explore religious themes -- and realized that the same tools could be used for advertising.</p>
        <p>He proposed the idea to NUR Macroprinters, an Israeli company that produces a large-format continuous inkjet press. Unlike painted billboards, wallscapes are printed via disk onto a lightweight vinyl mesh material and hung flat like posters against the sides of buildings. Not only are the images razor-sharp, but they can also be produced faster and removed more quickly and easily than a painted billboard. From that concept, MegaArt was born.</p>
        <p>Companies like MegaArt are sprouting -- and being snatched up by larger companies -- to take advantage of the fast-growing and lucrative large-format digital printing business, which industry analysts expect to grow to about $10 billion from $1.5 billion in the next three years. MegaArt's competitors range from huge billboard companies like Metromedia to small graphic design businesses.</p>
        <p>Familiar names -- the Gap, Apple, DKNY -- are loyal MegaArt clients. Advertisers create the images and send them via CD-ROM to MegaArt, which prints them. MegaArt says that it produces about 85 percent of the wallscapes in New York City, and the company has expanded its work to Israel, Europe and Japan.</p>
        <p>In the beginning, Mr. Aloni often worked with advertisers to translate their ideas to his large canvases, and some still seek his advice.</p>
        <p>MegaArt's sales have soared, to $11 million in 1999 from $1.5 million for the fiscal year that ended Aug. 31, 1997. Profits rose 50 percent in the same period, and the number of employees has increased to 83 from 5. The company expects sales to reach $18 million this fiscal year.</p>
        <p>MegaArt was acquired in September 1998 for $14.4 million by Unidigital, a digital printing and media services company in Manhattan that went public in 1996. Mr. Aloni is now the second-largest shareholder of Unidigital, behind William E. Dye, Unidigital's chairman. In 1998, Unidigital acquired SuperGraphics, a company in Sunnyvale, Calif., that makes vinyl ads that wrap around buses. Mr. Aloni runs MegaArt and SuperGraphics under one division.</p>
        <p>''Udi is a visionary,'' Mr. Dye said. ''His creative insight into new media concepts makes him really unique.''</p>
        <p>MegaArt's workshop, in a 30,000-square-foot renovated warehouse on Pier 40 at West and Houston Streets, is a bustling production center with seven printers that roll out gigantic images on the sturdy vinyl mesh. Although MegaArt's ownership has changed, Mr. Aloni says his mission is the same: to take the company to the next level artistically.</p>
        <p>''I've been freed from the day-to-day numbers and all the things I'm not so interested in,'' he said. ''Now I can concentrate on the creative side, developing concepts for the future. It's what really gives me my passion for this business.''</p>
        <p>Unidigital's strategy is to incorporate entrepreneurs and let them develop their businesses. ''There are so many images grabbing for our attention,'' said Rudolf Hokanson, an analyst who used to cover the company for CIBC Oppenheimer, the investment bank. ''So if you can be a master of digital printing, you have a better chance of being the one who offers a total solution for the customer.''</p>
        <p>Transportation Displays Inc., or T.D.I., was the first large company to give MegaArt its business. Bill Murphy, T.D.I.'s director of operations, said he was impressed with both Mr. Aloni's artistic background and his understanding of digital technology.</p>
        <p>MegaArt usually has about 25 wallscape projects going on at once, charging $20,000 to $400,000. T.D.I. spends $3,000 to $300,000 a year to lease wall space, then sells the space to advertisers for $5,000 to $50,000 a month, Mr. Murphy said.</p>
        <p>''Udi is an artist by trade, so he really appreciates the work we do,'' said Rebecca Weill, a spokeswoman for the Gap. ''He has a really good eye.''</p>
        <p>Since last January, MegaArt has focused on a new concept called ''station domination,'' which means one advertiser buys all the space at one location for one or two months.</p>
        <p>In partnership with T.D.I., which has franchise agreements with several transit authorities, including the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, MegaArt prints the images and displays the work. For example, Pontiac is spending $100,000 a month to display almost 300 images at the Port Authority bus terminal and $200,000 a month for 138 ads at the World Trade Center. In the Bond Street Underground station in London, all the signs were changed to read ''Blonde Street'' for a Clairol ad campaign.</p>
        <p>''They look for ways to service the clients and simplify the process,'' said Brigg Hyland, vice president for special projects at T.D.I. ''That allows the client greater flexibility.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aloni used to feel conflicted about his two roles: artist and entrepreneur. But he said he is over that now. ''My job is to find cool applications for these new digital tools,'' he said. ''I've grown as an artist since I started my business. I bring the same spirit and passion to both parts of my life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
