<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fine Timing By Yeltsin Gave Russia a Breather</title>
    <meta content="02MOSC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smale, Alison</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6DD1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fine Timing By Yeltsin Gave Russia a Breather</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON SMALE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smale, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Jan. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boris N Yeltsin's decision to resign as president of Russia does not spark flurry of public discussion and political sparring that would normally follow such a sensation because he chose to announce it on Jan 31, just as Russians begin celebrating New Year and just 12 days after election of a new Parliament, when rival blocs have yet to solidify (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As always, Boris N. Yeltsin picked his moment.</p>
        <p>By choosing to resign on the last day of the old year, Mr. Yeltsin guaranteed that almost all Russians would be deeply engaged in celebrating the arrival of the new one, traditionally the day of the biggest family feast here. Better than that, he acted at a time of enormous political flux: the start of a protracted break in the political year, and just 12 days after the election of a new Parliament, where rival blocs have yet to solidify.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As always, Boris N. Yeltsin picked his moment.</p>
        <p>By choosing to resign on the last day of the old year, Mr. Yeltsin guaranteed that almost all Russians would be deeply engaged in celebrating the arrival of the new one, traditionally the day of the biggest family feast here. Better than that, he acted at a time of enormous political flux: the start of a protracted break in the political year, and just 12 days after the election of a new Parliament, where rival blocs have yet to solidify.</p>
        <p>The advantage of acting in this political void is that Mr. Yeltsin avoided the usual flurry of public discussion and political sparring that would normally follow such a sensation. His successor, Vladimir V. Putin, meanwhile, was able to dominate such news programs as there were by making his trip to Chechnya.</p>
        <p>Daily newspapers will not appear here for at least another four days, because of the holidays. Television stations are mostly running favorite old Soviet movies, New Year's entertainment programs or concerts. Financial markets are closed. Many of Mr. Yeltsin's political rivals are out of town or abroad.</p>
        <p>Those who have not been heard from since Mr. Yeltsin's announcement that he was stepping down include Grigory A. Yavlinsky, leader of the liberal Yabloko party, and Yevgeny M. Primakov, the former prime minister whose political bloc fared relatively poorly against the supporters of Mr. Putin and other Yeltsin allies in last month's elections.</p>
        <p>Even when political life does shift into something resembling second gear at midweek, many politicians and businessmen will still be out of town. There is, after all, Orthodox Christmas to celebrate on Jan. 7, not to mention, six days later, Old New Year, as it is affectionately known in deference to the calendar that operated before the 1917 revolution.</p>
        <p>Thanks to feast days and weekends, many Russians will not work until Jan. 14. Moscow's streets, jammed with traffic in the pre-New Year's shopping rush, are deserted. One of the two main business dailies, Kommersant, will not even appear until mid-January. Nezavisimaya Gazeta, a widely read daily newspaper, will not publish until Jan. 11.</p>
        <p>All this means that Mr. Yeltsin's sudden and unchallenged transfer of power to Mr. Putin will go mostly undiscussed in the usual political forums for the bulk of the next two weeks. And Russians are free meanwhile to indulge in their most beloved pastimes: gathering around tables and discussing life, raising toasts and philosophizing, walking through the tender winter air, dusted with snowflakes, reveling in nature.</p>
        <p>Around one Moscow table tonight, the very suggestion of having to discuss Mr. Yeltsin and Mr. Putin prompted several guests into loud declamations about their distaste for all politics.</p>
        <p>''We've just been listening to a wonderful toast about how a few troubles are an essential part of life, and that the most important thing is our souls,'' cried Yevgeniya Melkonova, a homemaker. ''It's the first day of the year, and this isn't the day for talking about politics.''</p>
        <p>Yelena Strikovskaya cut in: ''Well, everybody in fact did talk about it when it happened. It was unexpected, but we got used to it quickly. There have already been so many resignations.''</p>
        <p>The talk then turned to Mr. Putin. Like many Russians, Ms. Strikov skaya heatedly criticized Mr. Putin for saying on television last fall that Chechen terrorists should be wiped out, and using an extremely crude slang expression.</p>
        <p>The 20 or so guests at this table nodded in agreement with her, declaiming loudly that mass media, indeed society in general, seem to have little inbred distaste for language considered unutterable in public in the Soviet era, just 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>A glass was raised to the hospitality of the house where the party was taking place. Talk turned back to the stuff of Russian life, the soul.</p>
        <p>''I just can't even hear about politics,'' said one guest, Olga Maslova, 38, who works at a Moscow television station. ''I understand that it's our duty to be interested, that it's our future, for our children, and so on. But I simply don't believe in any of those politicians. I don't believe there's a single good person up there.''</p>
        <p>The view that Russian politicians are unscrupulous and corrupt is widespread. Mr. Putin's first decree, officially exempting Mr. Yeltsin from any future prosecution, is universally seen as an attempt by the ex-president to protect not only himself, but his family and close friends, several of whom amassed considerable wealth and power during his eight years in the Kremlin.</p>
        <p>Around this table, the decree was taken as an unavoidable fact of life, and one that may not guarantee Mr. Yeltsin a future above the law. Besides, one guest noted, the first act of Gerald Ford as president was to pardon Richard M. Nixon, so there was, in his eyes at least, a precedent for Mr. Putin's action.</p>
        <p>Those Russian journalists who were heard from basically reflected the national desire to relax and forget about the daily grind of politics  for a few days. Lena Berezinskaya, writing for the online newspaper Vesti.Ru, noted that Mr. Yeltsin rarely took offense at journalists, simply riding above the many bad things they wrote about him. ''But how journalists hated him for quitting on Dec. 31'' -- either because they had nowhere to air their opinions, or because they had to work.</p>
        <p>Vesti.Ru went out of its way to thank Mr. Yeltsin for at least having the good grace to announce his resignation at noon on Dec. 31, rather than waiting until that night. But then, as Mr. Yeltsin well knew, almost nobody would have paid him any prolonged heed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
