<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World: It's the American Way; Europe Stares at a Future Built by Immigrants</title>
    <meta content="02CROS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165527"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EFDD1338F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World: It's the American Way; Europe Stares at a Future Built by Immigrants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profound demographic change facing Europe with influx of immigrants discussed; photo; traditionally homogeneous peoples may have to tolerate ethnic and racial newcomers in order to survive economically, given downturn in its own population growth (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPEANS, it often seems, spent the last decade building resentments of American fast food, pop culture, corporate callousness and  military might -- when they were not importing or trying to emulate them. They ended the century thinking they had staked out the parameters of Americanization and could now concentrate on erecting barricades around their traditional larders, languages and societies. But some demographers have a big surprise in store.</p>
        <p>Before the new millennium is a few decades old, these demographers say, Europe will be face to face with an American-style phenomenon more profoundly unsettling to many of them than any superficial cultural symbol or business intrusion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPEANS, it often seems, spent the last decade building resentments of American fast food, pop culture, corporate callousness and  military might -- when they were not importing or trying to emulate them. They ended the century thinking they had staked out the parameters of Americanization and could now concentrate on erecting barricades around their traditional larders, languages and societies. But some demographers have a big surprise in store.</p>
        <p>Before the new millennium is a few decades old, these demographers say, Europe will be face to face with an American-style phenomenon more profoundly unsettling to many of them than any superficial cultural symbol or business intrusion.</p>
        <p>The challenge, these experts say, is this: To survive economically and socially, Europe may have to lower its bars to immigration and change its racial and ethnic face through mass migration of labor from around the world. In other words, it may find itself debating moves toward a social structure that looks more like America's.</p>
        <p>It has often been said that however much they share in democratic values, Europeans and Americans still differ on one fundamental: In America, the whole idea of citizenship is that anyone from anywhere can become naturalized. In Europe, on the other hand, the idea of citizenship in most places is still linked to ethnic heritage, or at least to language and culture. True, Americans have restricted immigration and Europeans have invited foreign workers to take jobs in their economies. But large-scale immigration and naturalization is still an American ideal, while Europeans cling to a linguistic and racial basis for citizenship.</p>
        <p>In the coming decades, United Nations experts say, demographics indicate that many European countries (and Japan) will have more older people and fewer babies than ever before. This seems to foretell severely shrunken labor forces and swollen ranks of pensioners. If Europeans want to keep their economies and social services running, they will be tempted to look far afield for qualified workers of all kinds -- not just the semiskilled or unskilled workers who have traditionally been invited to fill gaps in their work forces.</p>
        <p>Joseph Chamie, the director of the United Nations population division, says there is a logical response: what he calls replacement migration. ''These countries in Europe will face the wall,'' he said. ''They either bring in migrants, or they are going to decline in size. The model that the United States has -- and Canada and Australia -- is increasingly becoming attractive to some of the thinkers in those countries.''</p>
        <p>United Nations experts preparing a report to be published this year say that their early projections show that Italy would have to add about 9 million immigrants by 2025 -- about 300,000 a year -- to keep its population at 1995 levels, Germany would need to import 14 million people -- 500,000 a year -- France 2 million and the European Union as a whole about 35 million. If the Europeans wanted to keep their ratio of older people to active workers at the 1995 levels, the union would need 135 million immigrants by 2025.</p>
        <p>Surplus labor, some of it very highly skilled, is waiting in the third world, and the pressure for migration out of overpopulated countries will be growing as the European societies shrink. A group of developing countries is calling for a United Nations conference that would have the freer movement of labor on its agenda. India, for example, has a labor force larger than that of the European Union. A lot of its computer geniuses are already sought by Silicon Valley. Will Europe soon have to compete for them? And will it let them migrate?</p>
        <p>If migration is the answer, and the numbers are large enough, Europe may well find itself under a challenge to make these and other immigrants full citizens in every sense. Today, Germany tolerates Turkish ''guest workers,'' as France allows Algerian migrants, but in both cases these minorities have become lightning rods for nationalist resentments.</p>
        <p>As always when projections are made, there are dissenting voices. Michael Teitelbaum, program director of the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation in New York and the co-author with Jay Winter of ''A Question of Numbers: High Migration, Low Fertility and the Politics of National Identity'' (Hill and Wang, 1998) points out that some European countries are already quite culturally and racially diverse. That aside, he says, he does not believe that large-scale migration is unavoidable.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there is anything inevitable about anything when it comes to demography, and I am a demographer,'' he said. And, he said, European nations may not see the American example as worth emulating.</p>
        <p>''It depends on what your goals are,'' he said. ''If your goals are to maximize your gross domestic product then you probably don't want a labor force that is slowly declining in numbers, even if their productivity is rising fast. If your goal is not G.D.P. but G.D.P. per capita or the equitable distribution of G.D.P. and a kind of equilibrium, a kind of agreeable quality of life in your society, then you may not care as much.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Teitelbaum is saying, in effect, that the challenge may be what Mr. Chamie predicts, but that Europeans may decide the cost of meeting it is too high. He points to European feelings about American-style capitalism.</p>
        <p>''There are many Europeans who hear Americans say how triumphant the American economy is and how wonderful and prosperous it is and they look at it and say, 'Gee, we don't want to be like that,' '' Mr. Teitelbaum said. '' 'It's really two societies with the kind of underclass that's getting worse and worse off, more and more marginalized.' ''</p>
        <p>ALSO, he said, not everybody has the same definition of multiculturalism. ''The French think that what they call the Anglo-Saxon model is a multicultural model of integration in which everybody speaks their own language and doesn't necessarily learn the common language -- and they don't really become British or Canadian or American. They simply live in those countries and the political system sort of stitches together compromises between these groups.''</p>
        <p>''The French image is quite different, but not xenophobic at all,'' he said, recalling the numbers of Poles, Russians and others who have settled over the century. Their model, he said, is ''that anybody of any race, national origin or whatever can become French, but they've got to really become French --  French defined in French terms.'' Germany, with an ethnically based view of citizenship has had a different debate about immigration, he said.</p>
        <p>Policies and programs to overcome hurdles like language barriers are scant in much of Europe because cultural homogeneity has been deeply valued, citizenship has often been defined ethnically or linguistically, and the naturalization process that has made Americans out of millions of foreigners does not exist. For example, while Britain may now be the most racially diverse and integrated nation in Europe, restrictions on immigrants from outside the European Union remain. Skinhead violence against non-Europeans has erupted from Scandinavia into Central and Eastern Europe. In Denmark, a right-wing nationalist leader proposed recently that all Muslims should be rounded up and put in camps.</p>
        <p>''You have European governments that continue to deploy the most sophisticated forms of immigration control,'' said Arthur C. Helton, an international lawyer who is a senior fellow at the Council on Foreign Relations. ''Yet European societies thirst ever more for new blood and labor, which will come from outside of Europe.''</p>
        <p>How to manage that? Mr. Helton said the example of the United States is instructive.  Immigration there ''has not only inspired but enforced a set of ways to manage conflict that Europeans are going to have to either borrow or invent,'' he said. ''There is a profound recognition by most Americans that this is a country more about change than about status. Europeans had better get ready for change.''</p>
        <p>IN Europe, protection of minorities is often seen as enough. ''But people don't want to be beneficiaries of minority rights arrangements,'' Mr. Helton said.  ''So there is a dilemma. Immigrants want to preserve their language and culture but do not wish to be stigmatized as second-class citizens. That's a delicate balance that often is missed, and it leads to intolerance, discrimination, backlash, race riots and the lot.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Teitelbaum says that this is where political leadership comes in, and that is as difficult to predict as anything else. With the combination of low fertility and high immigration, he said, ''you can have everything from prosperous peace and comity to disastrous, disintegrative civil war.''</p>
        <p>''A lot,'' he said, ''depends on the actions of political leaderships, to either exploit fears or to try to deal with them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
