<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Kurt Eissler, b. 1908; Keeper of Freud's Secrets</title>
    <meta content="MB101228" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malcolm, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eissler, Kurt Robert (Dr) (1908-99)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freud, Sigmund (1856-1939)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1D91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Kurt Eissler, b. 1908; Keeper of Freud's Secrets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Janet Malcolm</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Malcolm, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Malcolm article on Kurt Robert Eissler, psychoanalyst and author, who died in 1999; cites his role in preserving Sigmund Freud's work and thinking; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In preparation for writing about the psychoanalyst, writer and scholar Kurt Robert Eissler, who died in February, I went to the library of the New York Psychoanalytic Institute to read the memorial tributes that colleagues traditionally put on record there. Eissler, who was born in Vienna and came to America in 1938 to escape Hitler, had been one of the institute's ornaments. He was the author of 12 books, among them ''Goethe: A Psychoanalytic Study'' and ''Talent and Genius: The Fictitious Case of Tausk Contra Freud.'' In addition to his writing and a full-time psychoanalytic practice, he created, and for many years single-handedly ran, the Sigmund Freud Archives, an enterprise designed to save from oblivion the scattered letters, photographs and papers of Freud, and to preserve the recollections of Freud's living colleagues, relatives and patients through tape-recorded interviews.</p>
        <p>Eissler brought to American psychoanalysis attributes of mind and heart that do not normally flourish in our soil, and that are are immediately recognizable for their alien beauty. Encountering Eissler at a gathering of analysts was like coming upon an orchid in a hayfield. Coupled with his erudition, subtlety of mind and exquisite (perhaps mildly ironic) courtesy was a bracing, sometimes almost abrasive, honesty. He was thorny and passionate. He always spoke his mind. There was nothing smooth and glossy about him. Like all people of superior achievement, he was too intelligent to be satisfied, no less impressed, with himself. He revered genius but did not disdain lesser minds, never appearing to notice the disparity between himself and even the most dull-witted of his interlocutors. His extraordinary kindness was well known, not because he ever spoke of it, but because there were so many beneficiaries of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In preparation for writing about the psychoanalyst, writer and scholar Kurt Robert Eissler, who died in February, I went to the library of the New York Psychoanalytic Institute to read the memorial tributes that colleagues traditionally put on record there. Eissler, who was born in Vienna and came to America in 1938 to escape Hitler, had been one of the institute's ornaments. He was the author of 12 books, among them ''Goethe: A Psychoanalytic Study'' and ''Talent and Genius: The Fictitious Case of Tausk Contra Freud.'' In addition to his writing and a full-time psychoanalytic practice, he created, and for many years single-handedly ran, the Sigmund Freud Archives, an enterprise designed to save from oblivion the scattered letters, photographs and papers of Freud, and to preserve the recollections of Freud's living colleagues, relatives and patients through tape-recorded interviews.</p>
        <p>Eissler brought to American psychoanalysis attributes of mind and heart that do not normally flourish in our soil, and that are are immediately recognizable for their alien beauty. Encountering Eissler at a gathering of analysts was like coming upon an orchid in a hayfield. Coupled with his erudition, subtlety of mind and exquisite (perhaps mildly ironic) courtesy was a bracing, sometimes almost abrasive, honesty. He was thorny and passionate. He always spoke his mind. There was nothing smooth and glossy about him. Like all people of superior achievement, he was too intelligent to be satisfied, no less impressed, with himself. He revered genius but did not disdain lesser minds, never appearing to notice the disparity between himself and even the most dull-witted of his interlocutors. His extraordinary kindness was well known, not because he ever spoke of it, but because there were so many beneficiaries of it.</p>
        <p>His acute sensitivity to suffering is everywhere apparent in ''The Psychiatrist and the Dying Patient,'' perhaps the most accessible of his books. Eissler was incapable of banality, and his writings are sometimes touched with brilliance, but they are flawed by an unruly discursiveness. He did not know how to control the ideas that streamed from his pen like water from a burst pipe. (His study of Goethe is more than 1,500 pages long!) He needed an editor, and perhaps one day he will get one for a volume of selections from his work.</p>
        <p>When I arrived at the institute library and asked to see the memorial tributes, I was surprised (and after a moment's thought, not surprised) to learn that there were none. Eissler had left explicit directions that his death go unnoted by his colleagues. (As I later learned, assurances that his wishes be honored were a condition of his continued membership in the institute.) Eissler had always guarded his privacy; little more was known about his personal life than that he was married to another distinguished analyst, Ruth Eissler, and that he took his analyst's August vacation in Vinalhaven, Me. He and his wife were childless, and he was given to forming fatherly friendships with younger men and women. His final decades were shadowed by the unwelcome publicity that one of these friendships brought down on him. To the world at large, Eissler is known only as the guileless analyst who was betrayed and sued by his protege Jeffrey Masson. To a smaller world, the example of Eissler's remarkable thinking, writing and work with patients remains part of the explanation for the mysterious survival of psychoanalysis in the face of its repeatedly reported demise.</p>
        <p>Janet Malcolm is the author of ''In the Freud Archives,'' ''The Silent Woman: Sylvia Plath and Ted Hughes'' and most recently ''The Crime of Sheila McGough.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Janet Malcolm is the author of ''In the Freud Archives,'' ''The Silent Woman: Sylvia Plath and Ted Hughes'' and most recently ''The Crime of Sheila McGough.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
