<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Evil Empire</title>
    <meta content="02RYANLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ryan, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Courtois, Stephane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Werth, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Panne, Jean-Louis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paczkowski, Andrzej</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nartosek, Karel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Margolin, Jean-Louis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Black Book of Communism, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EEDB1539F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Evil Empire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Ryan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ryan, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Ryan reviews book The Black Book of Communism. Crimes, Terror, Repression by Stephane Courtois, Nicolas Werth, Jean-Louis Panne, Andrzej Paczkowski, Karel Nartosek and Jean-Louis Margolin (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BLACK BOOK</p>
        <p>OF COMMUNISM</p>
        <p>Crimes, Terror, Repression.</p>
        <p>By Stephane Courtois, Nicolas Werth,</p>
        <p>Jean-Louis Panne, Andrzej Paczkowski,</p>
        <p>Karel Bartosek and Jean-Louis Margolin.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 856 pp. Cambridge, Mass.:</p>
        <p>Harvard University Press. $37.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BLACK BOOK</p>
        <p>OF COMMUNISM</p>
        <p>Crimes, Terror, Repression.</p>
        <p>By Stephane Courtois, Nicolas Werth,</p>
        <p>Jean-Louis Panne, Andrzej Paczkowski,</p>
        <p>Karel Bartosek and Jean-Louis Margolin.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 856 pp. Cambridge, Mass.:</p>
        <p>Harvard University Press. $37.50.</p>
        <p>It is impossible to imagine any reader of ''The Black Book of Communism'' sitting down and plowing all the way through this 856-page catalog of the tortures, murders, deportations and deliberately created famines that Communist regimes have inflicted on their subjects during the past 80 years. There is a limit to the human appetite for descriptions of horrible death and hopeless misery. The authors of the several chapters that make up this grim compilation know this and do not wish it otherwise. Their aim is not to dramatize the sufferings of the victims of Communism, or to astonish their readers with new revelations. To the extent that the book has a literary style, it is that of the recording angel; this is the body count of a colossal, wholly failed social, economic, political and psychological experiment. It is a criminal indictment, and it rightly reads like one.</p>
        <p>Nor is it the aim of ''The Black Book of Communism'' to engage in the quarrels over numbers that used to preoccupy Robert Conquest and his critics some 25 years ago. In a sense, the collapse of Communism almost everywhere, and its at least partial transformation in China, has made exactness irrelevant. The famine caused by the Great Leap Forward resulted in the deaths of anywhere from 25 to 40 million Chinese -- nobody has wholly reliable statistics, and there is room for legitimate disagreement about how to count the indirect effects of malnutrition and economic disruption. Given that the economic policies of the Great Leap Forward were utterly disastrous in their own right, they were not worth the sacrifice of one life. Given that they were persisted in with grotesque and extreme brutality long after their flaws were perfectly clear, who is going to suggest that the lower of two appalling death tolls makes any serious moral difference?</p>
        <p>The purpose of ''The Black Book of Communism'' in its original form was highly specific. When the book was first published in France in 1997 (and became a best seller), it indicated the end of an epoch. Disillusioned social democrats had known since 1917, if not earlier, that the old cry of ''no enemies on the left'' was a recipe for disaster, that Communist parties all over the world had subverted their democratic allies whenever it suited them, and had murdered them in every country in which Communism had come to power. French intellectuals had, however, made it a point of honor to stare unflinchingly at the terrorism of successive Soviet regimes and announce that it was the price to be paid for the eventual liberation of the oppressed. Anything else was a concession to bourgeois humanitarianism. This book signified the end of that particular piece of nonsense.</p>
        <p>Its editor, Stephane Courtois, the director of research at the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique in Paris, might demur at the thought that even in France Communism is definitively extinct. He refers in passing to Mao's China and Kim Il Sung's North Korea as among the ''Communist regimes currently in vogue in the West,'' but this is surely an error. Whatever anyone's doubts about the problems caused by the triumph of capitalism on the world stage, nobody suggests China or North Korea as answers to them. Courtois was, perhaps, puzzled by the fact that nobody had commemorated the collapse of the Soviet bloc and the evaporation of the Soviet Union itself by drawing up the kind of criminal accounting he wanted. The answer, surely, is not that anyone still wishes to defend Stalin, Mao or Kim Il Sung, but that nobody knows what more to say.</p>
        <p>As Courtois points out, the observation that you can't make an omelet without broken eggs may be true, but it was long ago destroyed as a justification of the Soviet tyranny by the fact that we had all seen the broken eggs but nobody had ever seen the omelet. As he also notices, the decisive event both in awakening Western intellectuals to the horrors of Stalinism and in setting in train the destruction of the Soviet Union took place long ago. Khrushchev's ''secret speech'' to the 20th Party Congress in 1956 lifted the lid on the lies, murders and stupidities of Stalinist rule, and nothing was ever the same again.</p>
        <p>The next 40 years saw the slow unraveling of the Soviet bloc, but the impact on Western Communist parties was instantaneous. The silence over the horrors of Communism that Courtois complains of is not the silence of people who are morally uncertain, as someone might be in trying to think whether the atomic bombing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki was a hideous act justified by its effectiveness in preventing very much worse things from happening. It is the silence of people who are simply baffled by the spectacle of so much absolutely futile, pointless and inexplicable suffering.</p>
        <p>Courtois spends a good deal of his introduction worrying at a question that few Americans will hesitate to answer for him. In what sense can we describe whole governments as criminal? Narrowly construed, crimes are what particular states define as such, and if Stalin or Mao failed to criminalize the murderous behavior of their secret police, prison guards and militias, how can we call these acts crimes? Ever since the Nuremberg war crimes tribunal, Americans have known the answer: ''crimes against humanity'' are what the conscience of the ordinary, nondepraved human being recognizes as such. It is the answer that Courtois comes to as well. It is hard to know what other answer one might come to.</p>
        <p>There are in the end two large and fascinating questions that the several contributors, along with Martin Malia -- an American historian of Russia and the Soviet Union and the author of a very useful foreword to this translation -- all settle on as decisive. The first indeed gives the book's last chapter its title: Why? This is a somewhat embarrassing question for West Europeans, particularly the British, whose occupation of North America, Australia and parts of Africa involved the near-extermination of their original inhabitants. But the striking difference with the Soviet case is that the Soviet leadership made war on its own people. This was not invasion and colonization but supposedly the work of the ordinary government of a country.</p>
        <p>The short answer is that there is not one answer. The Russian penchant for rule by murder was centuries old by the time Stalin outdid all his predecessors in the sheer numbers he killed. A couple of years after the revolution, Gorky brooded unhappily on the curious Russian taste for inflicting death by the most painful and humiliating means -- and a decade later was proposing that the enemies of the people should be used for medical experiments. China had a violent and troubled history, but not the Russian culture of political murder. What is common to all Communist states, however, is the perversion of utopia.</p>
        <p>The frame of mind that sees society as a sheet of blank paper on which the great leader is to paint the ideal city of the future has often been accompanied by a readiness to imagine that killing off opponents is a necessary first step. But what might be a passing fantasy in the mind even of Sir Thomas More, the author of ''Utopia,'' became something that Lenin and Trotsky could begin to put into practice and Stalin turn into a settled policy.</p>
        <p>Popular though this view is -- nicely summed up in Malia's claim that it takes great ideals to cause great crimes -- I have never been convinced by it. The tyrant's dilemma, explored by thinkers ever since Plato, explains all we need to have explained: each death a tyrant perpetrates gives more people reason to hate him and therefore creates more enemies he has to eliminate. Trotsky and Lenin would probably have understood this and stopped; Stalin was thought by Trotsky to be a paranoid maniac, and may well have been so by the end of his life. But even paranoids have enemies, particularly when everything they do gives so many people reason to hate them.</p>
        <p>All of which brings one to the second great question. What of the relative immorality of Communism and Nazism? Both Malia and Courtois chew over this puzzle at some length; oddly, they do it as though it were not one of the standard subjects of debate back to the 1950's. The body count tips the scales against Communism. If wild utopian disregard for human life is the charge, there is little to choose between the practices of Nazism and Communism. But if the issue is the intrinsic evil of the entire project, it still seems no contest. Nazism was committed in principle to exterminating the Jews. So long as a shred of Marxist intelligence remained to Communist practice, it was not in itself an exterminationist project. Just how and why socialist aspirations came in practice to be so thoroughly betrayed will continue to preoccupy historians well into the next century.</p>
        <p>Alan Ryan is a professor of politics at New College, Oxford.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alan Ryan is a professor of politics at New College, Oxford.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
