<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2000 Draws Rave Reviews After Opening Night Night Jitters</title>
    <meta content="02MILL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE YEAR 2000: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square and 42d Street (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kleinfield, N R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2000 Draws Rave Reviews After Opening Night Night Jitters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By N. R. KLEINFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kleinfield, N R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Yorkers, concerned about Y2K computer problems and possibility of terrorist attack during New Year's Eve elebration in Times Square, awake to city that in year 2000's first hours looks and behaves pretty much way it did in 1999; things work and no terrorists intrude on gaiety; photo of city workers removing garbage in Times Square (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the bleary afterglow of the pulsating mass party in Times Square, New Yorkers awoke yesterday to a city that in the year 2000's first hours of innocent youth looked and behaved pretty much the way it did in 1999. Things worked. The terrorists stayed home.</p>
        <p>Gerard Vitti, a maintenance worker who had to report to his job at Manhattan Plaza at 6 a.m. and thus slept as the 1990's expired, got up and welcomed the 2000's by testing an electrical outlet in his Bronx apartment. Sure enough, it worked. He flicked on the radio. No blackouts. No bombs. Just another workday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the bleary afterglow of the pulsating mass party in Times Square, New Yorkers awoke yesterday to a city that in the year 2000's first hours of innocent youth looked and behaved pretty much the way it did in 1999. Things worked. The terrorists stayed home.</p>
        <p>Gerard Vitti, a maintenance worker who had to report to his job at Manhattan Plaza at 6 a.m. and thus slept as the 1990's expired, got up and welcomed the 2000's by testing an electrical outlet in his Bronx apartment. Sure enough, it worked. He flicked on the radio. No blackouts. No bombs. Just another workday.</p>
        <p>''Everything was fine, so I hopped on the subway,'' he said, noting that it too clacked down the tracks just the way it did all through the 1990's. ''It has turned out to be a normal Saturday morning, more or less.''</p>
        <p>In the wake of a hyperbolic night when so many fidgety people did their cork popping in their own homes, New York stepped into the new year a little sleepier, a little messier, but with any throbbing headaches relieved considerably by the excess of normality.</p>
        <p>Times Square itself, immobilized for a day by celebrators and cheer, was untidy but intact. Police estimates of the turnout of possibly two million people for the elongated extravaganza was quadruple the conventional New Year's Eve crush. And yet the merrymaking, watched carefully by unprecedented might from the city's police force, proceeded with exceptional bonhomie and minimal reports of misconduct. The lights still shone and no terrorists intruded on the gaiety.</p>
        <p>Early yesterday, under dank skies, a new morning shift of people who could not extinguish their celebratory urges continued to wander into the party scene. Steve Delladonna, 26, of Mamaroneck, N.Y., and Tara Berrigan, 25, of Niagara Falls, had reached Times Square around 4:30 p.m. Friday, and there was already no room. Unable to edge close enough to see anything worthwhile, they retreated to their hotel at 7:30 and settled for watching the ball drop on television. At 8 yesterday morning, they finally got to really see Times Square. ''I've never seen so much garbage in my whole life,'' Ms. Berrigan said.</p>
        <p>Two teenagers from Brooklyn, their eyes barely open after an all-night rave party in Sayreville, N.J., wobbled through Midtown awestruck by how unchanged it all was.</p>
        <p>''We thought everything would be burned and barren,'' said Viktor Ryshkov, 17.</p>
        <p>''I guess the timer on the bomb wasn't Y2K compliant,'' said his friend, Gene Sigalov, also 17.</p>
        <p>In a news conference at the Marriott Marquis Hotel in Times Square yesterday morning, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani shoveled praise on New York for being, in effect, very un-New York -- cheerful, well-behaved, polite. Summing up the celebration, the mayor said, ''We feel very happy this morning that we were able to enter the new millennium, celebrate it with the grandest and largest New Year's celebration in the city and do it in a peaceful way and in a way we demonstrate the way in which New York City is every day of the year.''</p>
        <p>Was he describing New York or Sioux Falls?</p>
        <p>The police reported only 14 arrests during the 26-hour Times Square marathon, mostly for disorderly conduct. They handed out 69 summonses, the bulk of them for carrying open containers of alcohol. The authorities received an uncommonly steep 48 bomb threats, including one involving the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge, though the mayor said all of them were bogus. On a typical day, the city gets about 16 bomb threats.</p>
        <p>Around 7:30 yesterday morning, however, a small makeshift explosive device blew out a window of a catering kitchen at 542 West 46th Street. No one was injured.</p>
        <p>In the opening hours of 2000, the police said that there were nine incidents of gunfire, mostly people shooting at one another. No one was killed, though there were several serious injuries. On a rooftop in Harlem, the police confronted two men firing guns into the air. One of the men, who had a shotgun, was shot in the buttocks by the police and was hospitalized.</p>
        <p>In Times Square, the magical moment arrived after a seemingly unending succession of highly choreographed festivities that began at 6 a.m. Friday and marked the hourly expiration of 1999 across the globe with puppets, costumed dancers and carnival performers.</p>
        <p>One minute before midnight, Dr. Mary Ann Hopkins, a surgeon being honored for her work in war-ravaged countries as a volunteer with Doctors Without Borders, pushed the button that sent a half-ton Waterford crystal ball sliding down the flagpole atop One Times Square. The specially composed ''Anthem for the Millennium'' blasted from speakers lining a dozen square blocks.</p>
        <p>As the illuminated globe touched down, that poignant numeral, ''2000,'' beckoned luminously. Fireworks exploded in the chilly sky and three tons of confetti coated the crowd. Thousands of balloons swirled lazily into space. An exultant roar of uncontained joy erupted from the crowd that could be heard in Trenton.</p>
        <p>Of the 14 arrests, two men were arrested in a single incident, and accused of assaulting a police officer. Another man was arrested on a charge of having a pistol.</p>
        <p>Then there was the man from Saranac, Mich. Identified as George James, 29, he was discovered by police officers in a parking garage on West 53rd Street walking around with handcuffs. The officers had stepped into the garage to use the bathroom. When they searched Mr. James's heavily lived-in van, they found a raft of pornographic magazines and a loaded shotgun.</p>
        <p>Mr. James, who works as a repair truck dispatcher for a cable television company, was charged with several counts of illegal possession of a weapon. The police said he told them that the shotgun was for his own defense, and they said there was no evidence that he intended to use it.</p>
        <p>There is always an untidy side to New Year's Eve -- the drunken driving incidents, the barroom brawls -- and while this one was not spared from such blemishes, neither was it inordinately marred by them. Hospital emergency rooms in the city reported that activity there was generally quieter than normal. In New Jersey, fog and iced-over roads did cause a spate of traffic accidents, but nothing exceptional.</p>
        <p>In Times Square, after the $7 million extravaganza finally lapsed at 8 a.m. and the last red-eyed stragglers limped on their way, sanitation crews driving their mechanical brooms whirred down the avenues to scoop up innumerable flattened party hats and noisemakers. The City Sanitation Department estimated that it would end up collecting 35 tons of garbage, double the normal residue, at a cost of $3 million. Save for stray confetti here and there, the department expected to be done tidying up before this morning.</p>
        <p>For the most part, affability reigned throughout the region. The first breath of new life was said to have been taken at Sisters of Charity Medical Center in Staten Island. Rebekah Yi was born one second after midnight, weighing 6 pounds 13 ounces.</p>
        <p>One of the best ways to start a year is with $100 million. Someone did, for there was just one winning ticket in the New York Millennium Million drawing on New Year's Eve. The prize winner was not identified, but the ticket was sold at the Garden Check Cashing Service, six blocks from Times Square.</p>
        <p>Scores of parties, large and small, persisted hours into the beginning of 2000.</p>
        <p>Ted Field, the movie and record producing chairman of Interscope Communications and notable for his trendier than trendy New Year's Eve bashes, resurrected the infamous Studio 54 discotheque for a glittery party of 2,000 of his dearest friends, most of them too young to remember when Studio 54 was Studio 54, rather than a cabaret theater. At midnight, champagne flowed from the rafters as women adorned in silver bikini bottoms and go-go boots gyrated to Prince's ''1999.''</p>
        <p>The party was intended to last until 8 a.m., but by 4:30 it began to wither. That's when Mr. Field left with an entourage of young women.</p>
        <p>It was a time of frantic activity coupled with certain absences of activity. Given the sparse amount of airplanes flying in and out, the three airports serving the city had more the feel of rural terminals. So many people feared menace, whether from terrorism, navigational glitches or whatever apocalyptic unknowns, that most Friday evening flights were canceled. Planes sat on the ground. The skies were quiet.</p>
        <p>Adam Chesler, 31, of South Brunswick, N.J., originally canceled plans to take a train on New Year's Day. Then he felt dumb for getting swept up by the Y2K fever. He took the train yesterday. ''It's not really a big deal,'' he said. ''The first time you see the date abbreviated, you know 01/01/00, it looks a little weird, like someone hit the reset button or something. Other than that, everything feels like normal.''</p>
        <p>THE YEAR 2000: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
