<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>QUICK BITE/Montclair; Eclectic Power</title>
    <meta content="02HI1.0AA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6DC1438F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>QUICK BITE/Montclair; Eclectic Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA HIGBIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SoHo cute, Cafe Eclectic is busiest after the movies let out on weekend nights but rarely is it empty. Its lush yard-sale decor - 20 mismatched tables a hodgepodge of chairs adn a clutch of crushed velvet sofas - keeps this coffeehouse true to its name and entirely comfortable in a ''Sunset Boulevard'' kind of way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SoHo cute, Cafe Eclectic is busiest after the movies let out on weekend nights but rarely is it empty. Its lush yard-sale decor - 20 mismatched tables a hodgepodge of chairs adn a clutch of crushed velvet sofas - keeps this coffeehouse true to its name and entirely comfortable in a ''Sunset Boulevard'' kind of way.</p>
        <p>''I used to hang out in New York cafes a lot, and I always wanted to open a cafe of my own'' says Julio Valentin Jr. 30 the owner who has a fairly eclectic past himself. He grew up in Newark, where he still lives joined the Army after graduating from high school and then the Newark Police Department. ''While I was an officer, I did a lot of reading about business and I researched cafes.''</p>
        <p>It was apparently a thorough education: he bought the cafe two years ago and eight months ago he doubled its size by expanding into the space next door. The drinks, amny invented and named by Mr. Valentin are eclectic too, from the simple but just right cafe au lait to the red eye (coffee with a double shot of espresso), vanilla spiced chai, the Viennese (a double shot of espresso with mandarin orange flavoring, cinnamon and steamed milk) and sludge cup (brewed espresso and steamed water). ''My favorites are the caramel latte and mocha infusion,'' he says. The desserts, featuring cheesecakes, chocolate-chocolate-chip cake, fruit and caramel pies and Oreo mousse, are delivered from bakeries in Manhattan and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>More a bar than a Starbucks, Cafe Eclectic presents lives jazz and folk on Monday and Tuesday nights. Dating games and loud laughter are the order of each evening, and the smoking room - with a waterfall - is the bigger and more luxe of the two areas.</p>
        <p>And the clientele is fittingly eclectic. ''We have everyone here you can imagine'' Mr. Valentin says. ''Teens to college students to senior citizens to punk rockers to yuppies all in one place at same time.''</p>
        <p>Of course, in the relentlessly child-centric Montclair the truly young are always welcome: they get to drink the white hot chocolate.</p>
        <p>ANDREA HIGBIE</p>
        <p>Cafe Eclectic, 444 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair, (973)509-9179. Hours:Mondays, 1 p.m. to midnight; Tuesdays through thursdays, 9 a.m. to midnight; Fridays 9 a.m. to 2 a.m.; Saturdays, noon to 2 a.m.; Sundays, 1 p.m. to midnight. Coffees, $1 to $4.25; desserts, $3.50; white hot chocolate, $2 to $3.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
