<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Shakespeare Tale Whose Time Has Come</title>
    <meta content="02BATE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bate, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hopkins, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taymor, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Titus (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Titus Andronicus (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/William Shakespeare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Julie Taymor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Box Office</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D91638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Shakespeare Tale Whose Time Has Come</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN BATE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bate, Jonathan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Bate report on Julie Taymor's film Titus, starring Anthony Hopkins; photo; Titus Andronicus, bloody but witty play, was young Shakespeare's first box-office smash (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF William Shakespeare were alive today, he would be writing and directing movies. Julie Taymor's ''Titus,'' which opened last week, offers a glimpse of what they might be like: challenging but accessible, tragic and comic, responsive to the past yet relevant to the present.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taymor's favorite scene in the 1998 movie ''Shakespeare in Love'' is the one in which Will encounters a boy outside his theater feeding mice to a cat. The little torturer expresses his admiration for a certain play in which heads are cut off and a daughter mutilated with knives. ''When I write plays,'' he says, ''they will be like 'Titus'.'' Will is pleased. He asks the boy his name: it is John Webster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF William Shakespeare were alive today, he would be writing and directing movies. Julie Taymor's ''Titus,'' which opened last week, offers a glimpse of what they might be like: challenging but accessible, tragic and comic, responsive to the past yet relevant to the present.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taymor's favorite scene in the 1998 movie ''Shakespeare in Love'' is the one in which Will encounters a boy outside his theater feeding mice to a cat. The little torturer expresses his admiration for a certain play in which heads are cut off and a daughter mutilated with knives. ''When I write plays,'' he says, ''they will be like 'Titus'.'' Will is pleased. He asks the boy his name: it is John Webster.</p>
        <p>The real Webster was the most gifted of the generation of playwrights who followed Shakespeare. He excelled in darkly brilliant revenge tragedies that veer between extreme violence and black comedy. Webster was the Quentin Tarantino of his age, but he didn't invent this mixed style of drama. As the scene in ''Shakespeare in Love'' suggests, credit there belongs to Will himself. The bloody but witty ''Titus Andronicus'' was young Shakespeare's first box-office smash, the work that made his name, the first of his plays to appear in print.</p>
        <p>Though enormously successful in its own time, ''Titus'' was an embarrassment to later generations. When the hero confronts the horrific fate of his children, he does not cry or curse. He laughs. Critics in the 18th and 19th centuries could not cope with such incongruity, but it strikes a chord in us. The Elizabethans were not afraid to confront violence in ways that are simultaneously shocking and playful. In this we are like them, and so it is that ''Titus'' is the Shakespeare play for the turn of the millennium.</p>
        <p>Bloody revenge, dismemberment, rape, feigned madness, cannibalism: what more could a movie need? Interviewed in London on the day she won an Evening Standard award for ''The Lion King,'' Julie Taymor said she had had a tough fight with the Motion Picture Association of America to win ''Titus'' an R as opposed to an NC-17 rating. She found herself defending her movie in a telephone call from Venice -- ''I'm in a city,'' she said, ''where the churches have frescoes on the walls showing scenes much more shocking than anything in my film.'' She agreed to cut a handful of shots from her Roman orgy, but what is revealing about her defense is the comparison with Renaissance paintings of the martyred and the damned. It points to two things: the visual quality of Ms. Taymor's imagination, which is everywhere apparent in the movie, and her belief that ''Titus'' is no Shakespearean potboiler but a profound exploration of the darker recesses of humanity, a tour de force that can hold its own with the greatest and most troubling creative works of Western culture.</p>
        <p>The movie was made at the Cinecitta studios in Rome, and such scenes as the orgy inevitably invite comparison with ''Fellini Satyricon,'' especially since Ms. Taymor's production designer, Dante Ferretti, worked with Fellini. There are also touches of Pasolini, a master at dramatizing emotional extremity in harshly lighted landscapes. But the richest influence is Shakespeare's own proto-cinematic imagination. Ms. Taymor has the gift of finding visual equivalents for the dramatist's figurative verse. The two locations at the center of her ''Titus,'' a swamp and a crossroads, are peculiarly haunting. They translate Shakespearean poetry into the language of cinema. At the same time, the film fully respects the original words, reproducing a higher percentage of text than any other recent screen adaptation of Shakespeare with the exception of Kenneth Branagh's over-long ''Hamlet'' in 1996.</p>
        <p>Like Pasolini, Shakespeare believed that ancient myths can speak to modern times. ''Titus Andronicus'' mingles mythology, history and invention. The story is patterned on the tale of Philomel, who was raped by her brother-in-law. He cuts out her tongue so that she cannot reveal his identity, but she finds another way of communicating, enabling her sister to serve up a horrible revenge. Shakespeare took this mythic prototype and retold it through an invented narrative about a fictional Roman general, Titus Andronicus, who returns from successful wars against the Goths only to find himself at odds with the new emperor. Rome collapses into chaos from within.</p>
        <p>T HE play is set simultaneously in timeless myth, imperial Rome and Shakespeare's own Europe. Ms. Taymor, too, creates a stylish interplay of past and present, with chariots one moment and motorcycles the next. She reads ''Titus'' as a compendium of 2,000 years of warfare and violence. The Colosseum scenes were shot in Croatia; proximity to Bosnia and Kosovo was a constant reminder that the atrocities of war are as modern as they are ancient.</p>
        <p>''Titus,'' Ms. Taymor said, is not just about violence; ''it's about how we make entertainment out of violence.'' Hence the movie's opening sequence, adapted from the director's 1994 New York stage production of the play, in which a boy stages a battle of toy soldiers to the accompaniment of television violence. Play becomes reality as war intrudes and the child is catapulted into the ancient Colosseum. The subsequent action is witnessed through his eyes -- which become our eyes.</p>
        <p>The presence of pity in the act of witnessing is one reason Ms. Taymor is right to resist easy parallels with Quentin Tarantino. '' 'Pulp Fiction' is all surface,'' she said, whereas in ''Titus'' both the characters and the audience go on an inward journey in which the human reaction to violence is of more consequence than the violence itself. At the heart of the movie is a scene involving the killing of a fly, in which black comedy momentarily gives way to an exquisite tenderness, delicately rendered by both Ms. Taymor's camera and Anthony Hopkins's performance as Titus.</p>
        <p>Only a great actor at the height of his powers can do justice to the sheer range of feeling within the character. Laurence Olivier achieved it in Peter Brook's 1955 stage production, which redeemed the play from centuries of neglect and disparagement. Now Mr. Hopkins, who began his career under Olivier in the early days of London's National Theater, has achieved it on film. His performance is not without moments of homage to Olivier's grand style, but it is richest when it is quiet rather than loud, especially when the once proud general is reduced to seeking tearful sympathy from the stones in the roadway. Titus' outburst against the injustice of the world is equally memorable: ''If there were reason for these miseries, / Then into limits could I bind my woes.'' Ms. Taymor regards such lines as a match for any in Shakespeare.</p>
        <p>She is equally enthusiastic about the role of Titus' opponent, Tamora, queen of the Goths (Jessica Lange). ''Why do people make such a fuss about Lady Macbeth?'' she said. ''We never learn what her motives are, whereas with Tamora it's understandable from the start: she's a wronged mother.'' Shakespeare's text compares Tamora to a ''ravenous tiger,'' an image Ms. Taymor brings to the screen in one of the film's dreamlike insets. Tamora is fierce because she is protective of her young -- a Tiger Queen out for revenge because Titus has ordered the sacrificial execution of her eldest son.</p>
        <p>Her two younger sons, Chiron and Demetrius, are disturbingly familiar to a late-20th-century audience. Bored young Goths, they go on a killing spree for the sheer fun of it. The movie had wrapped before the massacre at Columbine High, but Ms. Taymor sensed the resonance when it happened. Shakespeare doesn't crudely demonize Tamora's boys. He shows us that peer group pressure and the spirit of competition can lead young men to kill and rape.</p>
        <p>Tamora's sons are egged on by their mother's lover, Aaron the Moor (played by Harry J. Lennix, the one actor in the movie retained from Ms. Taymor's stage version). Aaron is the first great Shakespearean villain, the forerunner of Richard III, Iago and Edmund in ''King Lear.'' But he is also the first great black role in English drama. Ms. Taymor regards the part as more complex than that of Othello. Aaron is motivated by his status as an outsider. At first he seems to be the devil incarnate. But toward the end, there is an astonishing turnaround. ''Zounds, ye whore,'' he says to the nurse who hands him his first-born son with an insult, ''is black so base a hue?'' Black pride and paternal affection undo the ancient racist equation of darkness with evil.</p>
        <p>Shakespeare's text is not explicit about the final fate of Aaron's baby. His survival will depend on the integrity of Lucius, Titus' only surviving son. Will the cycle of blood for blood go on, or is there hope for the future?  Ms. Taymor's stage production was ambiguous, whereas the movie ends on an uplifting note, with a closing image of singular beauty. Though filmed before the release of ''Shakespeare in Love,'' the scene is satisfyingly reminiscent of Gwyneth Paltrow's walk along the shore of the brave New World at the close of that movie. Ms. Taymor insists that she has not bowed to the Hollywood convention of happy endings; the decision was made, she said, when the actor playing Lucius (Angus MacFadyen) persuaded her that his was a character who would keep his word.</p>
        <p>Whatever the merits of this particular production choice, the way in which it was made is symptomatic of the integrity of Ms. Taymor's project. She has respected both an ancient work of art and a modern company of screen actors. Her reward is to have created something very special. Where so many movies impress at the time but fade in the instant you walk out of the theater, ''Titus'' keeps on growing in the imagination.</p>
        <p>FILM Jonathan Bate edited the text of ''Titus Andronicus'' for the Arden Shakespeare series.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jonathan Bate edited the text of ''Titus Andronicus'' for the Arden Shakespeare series.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
