<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Siting a House for Rooms With a View</title>
    <meta content="02COV.$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vermont</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diesenhouse, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Barbara C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Alesia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Donnell, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Donnell, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E3D91738F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Siting a House for Rooms With a View</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN DIESENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diesenhouse, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLOTTE, Vt.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>People building new houses in scenic sections of Vermont are finding imaginative ways to position or design them to showcase spectacular views; to create most view-friendly topography for sitting the houses, inventive owners, architects and builders may sculpt the land to fashion a flat plane or raise up portion of the lot with fill; others devise unusual house designs that aim for beautiful panorama from every room; they may put bedrooms downstairs and living area up, and they may build in towers, turrets or expansive glass elements; new homeowners Barbara C Wilson, Robert and Alesia Barnes and Patricia and Jim O'Donnell comment; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Vermont, where the Green Mountains and Lake Champlain frame hundreds of miles of bucolic vistas, people building new houses are finding imaginative ways to position or design them to showcase the spectacular views.</p>
        <p>To create the most view-friendly topography for siting the houses, inventive owners, architects and builders may sculpt the land to fashion a flat plane or raise up a portion of the lot with fill. Others devise unusual house designs that aim for a beautiful panorama from every room. They may put the bedrooms downstairs and the living area up, and they may build in towers, turrets or expansive glass elements.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Vermont, where the Green Mountains and Lake Champlain frame hundreds of miles of bucolic vistas, people building new houses are finding imaginative ways to position or design them to showcase the spectacular views.</p>
        <p>To create the most view-friendly topography for siting the houses, inventive owners, architects and builders may sculpt the land to fashion a flat plane or raise up a portion of the lot with fill. Others devise unusual house designs that aim for a beautiful panorama from every room. They may put the bedrooms downstairs and the living area up, and they may build in towers, turrets or expansive glass elements.</p>
        <p>Then there are those, like Patricia O'Donnell and her husband, Jim Donovan, who are willing to invest in a premium site that is high enough, or includes enough extra acreage, to ensure that nothing is built to spoil their sight lines. Their almost completed house in this town of 4,300  sits on a ridge overlooking Lake Champlain, and offers majestic vistas.</p>
        <p>From a tower that rises a floor above the corner of the two-story house nearest the lake, the clouds seem to bob below eye level, hanging over a vast expanse of water bordered by mountains on both the Vermont and New York shores. From the house down to the lake yawn 80 acres of open fields, which the couple own and will never develop.</p>
        <p>''The fields protect us from someone blocking our view,'' said Ms. O'Donnell, who, like her husband, is a 47-year-old landscape architect. ''We passed up six other properties in this town until we found one with a view, because it's enriching, calming and puts things in perspective. We can see ourselves as part of a larger creation.''</p>
        <p>The couple had been living for 15 years in Westport, Conn., when they bought their 118 acres, half of it a dairy farm that was going out of business, in 1994. The search for the land took a long time -- two years -- as it often does. And the purchase price, which the buyers declined to disclose, was so high that it took them three years to recoup financially, they said. They designed the house themselves, began construction late in 1997, and moved in last summer. The entire project, they said, cost about $700,000.</p>
        <p>The move also meant a change in lifestyle. Mr. Donovan accepted a pay cut to work for an engineering firm in Burlington, about 15 miles north of here. Ms. O'Donnell, meanwhile, must now commute farther to reach her clients around the country.</p>
        <p>''This choice was about quality of life, not about price or convenience,'' she said. ''We took a risk that if we went for the location we really wanted, the work would follow.''</p>
        <p>Like most people who build largely for a view, this couple undertook an extensive search to find the right property. One would think that a big state like Vermont, with a population of only about 600,000 would have plenty of pretty home sites for sale. But for several reasons, it's difficult to find a buildable site with views in the most popular locations, such as here in greater Burlington, Stowe, or farther south in Woodstock, said Kevin L. Dorn, director of the Homebuilders and Remodelers Association of Northern Vermont.</p>
        <p>One issue is waste disposal. Often, a scenic site cannot accommodate the types of septic systems required by the state. Moreover, some municipalities are not approving  new hookups to their public sewer systems until they expand existing capacity. Neither Shelburne nor Stowe, about 25 miles northeast, are currently adding hookups, but a new treatment plant is under construction in Shelburne and Stowe is expanding its existing facilities.</p>
        <p>Then there is the zoning question. In much of Vermont's open space residential or commercial development is effectively barred by zoning rules intended to preserve agricultural or rural land. Such land cannot be subdivided into house lots of even 5 or 10 acres. Even building one 3,000-square-foot house on 118 acres, as Ms. O'Donnell and Mr. Donovan did in Charlotte, requires a special town permit, Mr. Dorn noted.</p>
        <p>Also, after a decade-long downturn in the residential market here, builders and construction workers are scarce. Those who stayed when the work disappeared now often prefer the certainty of building a few high-priced custom homes a year, rather than doing a larger, more risky speculative project, said Paul Sherwood, a real estate broker with Century 21 in West Dover, near Brattleboro. As a result, labor and materials now cost from $120 to $200 a square foot, up 40 percent since the late 1980's, builders say.</p>
        <p>With a scarcity of labor and buildable sites with views and an increase in the demand for houses, prices have risen dramatically in the last 10 years. For instance, in Charlotte, fast evolving into a commuter suburb of Burlington, the average sale price of a home was $331,000 in 1998, up from $163,906 in 1986. But the number of permits issued fell to 20 last year, from 53 in 1987, according to Kay Gualt, an assistant in the assessor's office.</p>
        <p>Land prices of course vary with location. In towns like Charlotte, near Lake Champlain, or in resort locations such as Stowe, land prices can reach $100,000 an acre. Therefore, once complete, a custom house with a view can have a total development cost of $300 to $500 a square foot, according to owners, brokers, builders and local officials.</p>
        <p>DESPITE the costs, ''the busiest segment of Vermont's new-home market is for the magnificent high-end homes in the woods or on a lake, for consultants who routinely fly in and out from Burlington,'' said Mr. Sherwood, the broker.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Donnell fits that description, as does Robert M. Barnes, 55, a lawyer who is a partner in the Jacksonville, Fla., law firm of Barnes, Barnes and Cohen. Mr. Barnes and his wife Alesia, 38, usually spend several weeks at their newly renovated farmhouse in Stowe, then return to Jacksonville for a few weeks.</p>
        <p>In October 1997, after a one-year cross-country search for a site, they purchased an 1840's farm with 44 acres for $1 million. ''As soon as we walked onto the property, we knew it was the one, and it was all about the views,'' said Ms. Barnes, who as a child lived in upstate New York and Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>The property sits on the side of Edson Hill, overlooking the town of Stowe and affording an unobstructed view of the Worcester Mountain Range and Mount Mansfield. Long known as Peterson Brook Farm, it has two ponds, two brooks, four horse pastures, two barns, a riding rink, a four-bedroom guest house and a two-car garage.</p>
        <p>And it had a simple two-story three-bedroom farmhouse that the new buyers gutted and rebuilt and expanded. To assure a spectacular view from every room in the three-bedroom house and from various outdoor spaces, the couple invested an additional $900,000 to renovate and landscape. Work started a year ago and is just being completed.</p>
        <p>The new two-story house is clad in cream-colored clapboards and has a gray shingled roof. It has dormers, bay windows, window seats and glass French doors all around. Mr. and Mrs. Barnes redesigned and expanded the house by 300 square feet, to 4,100 square feet. They created an open floor plan by demolishing the old staircase and installing a new one that culminates in cupola that  serves as a lookout tower.</p>
        <p>Outside, a mason built stone-walled gardens, slate walkways, patios and a covered front porch. He also installed a new gravel entry and a bridge over a brook. A split-rail fence marks off the property while a rough-sawn entry arch bears the homestead's original name, Peterson Brook Farm. Despite his $2 million investment, Mr. Barnes was compelled by tradition to retain the  property's historic identity. ''We're just custodians here,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In Underhill, about 20 miles east of Burlington, Barbara C. Wilson and Michael F. Luck, a couple in their early 50's, are just completing their new custom-built house.  Entranced by their views of Mount Mansfield and Lake Champlain (when winter withers the leaves), this couple from Wayland, Mass. designed an upside-down house. The master suite and study are on the ground floor. The living areas, including a lookout loft, are upstairs.</p>
        <p>The couple also built a two-story tower filled with windows facing west, giving 180-degree views upstairs and down.</p>
        <p>''This house is an invention because we wanted to frame the views from every angle,'' said Ms. Wilson. ''In a harsh climate like Vermont's, views are so important because they bring the outside in and capture the light.''</p>
        <p>For the builder, Tom Moore, and designer, James Nassau, both of Underhill, siting the house to highlight the views of Mount Mansfield, the South Hill Range and Taylor Notch was not easy. ''It was a struggle between getting the sunlight from the south and framing the panorama,'' Mr. Moore said.</p>
        <p>For the couple, however, this house is a dream come true. Mr. Luck, vice chancellor of the University of Massachusetts, is the great-grandson of Peter Leddy, who built the adjacent Maple Leaf Farm in the 1880's. Mr. Luck started in 1985 trying to buy their five-acre parcel. Finally, in 1995, they closed on the land for $85,000. Since then, they have invested $415,000 more for design, excavation, construction and landscaping.</p>
        <p>WHILE they created an unconventional design in order to take maximum advantage of the views, they clad the exterior in traditional gray clapboard. ''We believe in integrating the spirit of previous generations and bringing it forward,'' Ms. Wilson said. ''Vermont is about community, continuity and respect for the fact that you inherit your little piece of land just for awhile.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wilson and Mr. Luck started construction of their 3,000-square-foot house in 1998. To site it for optimal views, they sculpted the land. Two workers spent two days clearing away trees, and four more days working with a bulldozer to flatten the top of a knoll, build up the sides of the site and put in a driveway. That made room for a wraparound slate patio, grape arbor and vegetable garden. Inside, the ground floor has the master suite, a study and bathroom. Upstairs is the living/dining area, kitchen, family room, bathroom and lookout loft.</p>
        <p>The house has all modern conveniences, including remote controlled heating. But with its large arched windows and elements crafted from antique New England structures, the interior has the feel of a Tuscan villa. A chestnut balcony salvaged from a 200-year-old church in Whitehall, N.Y., supplied the wood from which the owners made shelves and a window seat in the family room, while columns from a 100-year-old home in Brookline, Mass. now frame the circular tower area in the living room.</p>
        <p>Back on the shore of Lake Champlain in the town of Shelburne, just north of here, Ronald VanMynen and his wife Janet, both 62, are building a 6,300-square-foot retirement house on a seven-acre lot with 310 feet of shorefront. Although they had purchased property for future construction on a small North Carolina lake several years ago, they decided last year that the majesty of Vermont was more to their taste. They bought their Vermont property in June, and are trying to sell their property in North Carolina.</p>
        <p>To have the best possible views of the water and mountains, and to make room for a basement and improve drainage on his low-lying land, Mr. VanMynen is having fill hauled in to raise the site about 10 feet. This sculpting also makes future handicapped access possible by creating gentle slopes on the east leading to the main entrance and from the western side of the house down to the water and private dock. Once completed, the site work will have consumed the equivalent of 900 truckloads of soil.</p>
        <p>Also to ensure exceptional views, Mr. VanMynen has sited the four-bedroom, Florida-style home with the long end facing the lake. The house is on one level and has an open floor plan with 12-foot ceilings, nine windows and two sets of glass doors overlooking the water, for a total of 77 linear feet of glass on the side of the house overlooking the lake. There will be a full basement, half of it finished, with a walk-out patio and an eight-car garage. In the garage Mr. VanMynen keeps two antique cars and four modern models that he drives. ''I'm a car nut,'' he said.</p>
        <p>CONSTRUCTION started last June and completion is scheduled for next summer, with the total development cost expected to reach $1.75 million. Throughout the process, soil and rocks are being hauled in, adding about 8 percent to the final cost. At first the aim was merely to raise the house site. Now it is to build the slopes, said the architect, Dan Webster of Weimann Lamphere Architects, of Colchester.</p>
        <p>In Charlotte, the next town south, Ms. O'Donnell and Mr. Donovan spent 18 months designing the house for their property, which also includes a farmhand's house (where they lived temporarily), two barns and a 19th century shed.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to take time to live on the land and understand it,'' Ms. O'Donnell said. They began by renovating the 1,100-square-foot farmhand's house to add a great room that offers a better view of the lake.</p>
        <p>For their new house, ''We didn't want a trophy house strung out across the ridge facing the lake,'' she said. Instead they sited it facing south for passive solar heating. They conceived of it as three modules: the main house, conservatory and office. With its traditional peaked roof, cedar clapboard siding and white-trimmed windows, their house echoes the architectural motifs of the neighboring old farmhouse, barns and silos.</p>
        <p>They used classic post-and-beam construction, and only local, chemical-free materials. But within those parameters, the entire house was designed to maximize the views. For example, the kitchen and dining room, filled with windows, face the lake on the first floor. On the second floor is the master suite, a balcony with an all-glass wall and a sunset room overlooking the water. The entire third floor is an 8-foot by 10-foot tower designed simply for taking in the sights.</p>
        <p>''For us the challenge was to fit in with centuries of natural and human evolution,'' Ms. O'Donnell said, ''and not kill the golden goose that drew us here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
