<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Will New York Be Necessary In the 21st Century?; Some of the City's Bright Lights Ponder the Future of the Metropolis</title>
    <meta content="02FEAT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohatyn, Felix G (Amb)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nieporent, Drew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sante, Luc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butts, Calvin O 3d (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gregorian, Vartan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riggio, Leonard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huxtable, Ada Louise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rupp, George E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levine, Arnold J (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallace, Mike (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caro, Robert A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jamison, Judith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daniele, Graciela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazarus, Shelly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leventhal, Nathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Michaels, Lorne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E4D81438F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Will New York Be Necessary In the 21st Century?; Some of the City's Bright Lights Ponder the Future of the Metropolis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD STAMLER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prominent New Yorkers, past and present, are asked whether city will lose its edge or even become unnecessary in the increasingly technological 21st century or whether it will continue to be a magnet for talent and an incubator of progress; comments from Jane Jacobs, Felix G Rohatyn, Drew Nieporent, Luc Sante, Rev Calvin O Butts 3d, Vartan Gregorian, Jane Friedman, Leonard S Riggio, Ada Louise Huxtable, George E Rupp, Dr Arnold J Levine, the historian Mike Wallace, Robert A Caro, Judith Jamison, Graciala Daniele, Shelly Lazarus, Nathan Leventhal and Lorne Michaels; photos; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK came of age when all that was new seemed to flow from the city, when crowded streets and the world's tallest building were matters of civic pride. Like all great cities in their times, New York thrived in the 20th century because it was a place where the energetic and the talented -- many from distant lands -- gathered to form a critical mass. It was the quintessential modern city, unrivaled in America, if not the world.</p>
        <p>But New York is vastly different from what it was even a decade ago. Shopping-mall culture has expanded from the suburbs into the heart of the city, eliminating many of New York's idiosyncrasies. Newer cities and suburban centers have lured jobs along with innovators. And many have argued that the sweeping technological advances of recent years, from faxes to cell phones and especially the Internet, have undercut the need for a central city in fields like the arts, communications and finance, the very areas in which New York has been pre-eminent. Today, people can opt for lives that are less frantic than those typically led in New York. They can move to the country, or to newer, cleaner towns and cities, while continuing to do business with the click of a mouse or a remote control.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK came of age when all that was new seemed to flow from the city, when crowded streets and the world's tallest building were matters of civic pride. Like all great cities in their times, New York thrived in the 20th century because it was a place where the energetic and the talented -- many from distant lands -- gathered to form a critical mass. It was the quintessential modern city, unrivaled in America, if not the world.</p>
        <p>But New York is vastly different from what it was even a decade ago. Shopping-mall culture has expanded from the suburbs into the heart of the city, eliminating many of New York's idiosyncrasies. Newer cities and suburban centers have lured jobs along with innovators. And many have argued that the sweeping technological advances of recent years, from faxes to cell phones and especially the Internet, have undercut the need for a central city in fields like the arts, communications and finance, the very areas in which New York has been pre-eminent. Today, people can opt for lives that are less frantic than those typically led in New York. They can move to the country, or to newer, cleaner towns and cities, while continuing to do business with the click of a mouse or a remote control.</p>
        <p>And so the question arises: In this new technological era, will New York lose its edge? Will it still be a magnet for talent and an incubator of progress? Will New York be necessary in the 21st century?</p>
        <p>The New York Times asked some prominent New Yorkers, past and present, to explore these issues.</p>
        <p>Jane Jacobs  Author, ''The Death and Life of Great American Cities''</p>
        <p>Cities become necessary because they make themselves necessary. It's not some mysterious bestowal from heaven; it's what they do. And the great service of cities has always been to solve problems as they become acute and provide the wherewithal, especially the knowledge, to other places on how to do them. That's how epidemics have been overcome, to a great extent. It's how drudgery has been removed from lots of tasks. It's how there have been new kinds of housing and new standards of living and new ways of educating people -- these all started in cities, and always have. So that's one service that cities do, and it is a service that New York has provided, and if it continues to be innovative in this practical, essential way, it'll continue to be necessary. If it doesn't, it won't be necessary.</p>
        <p>Another great service is that they enrich civilization and New York has done that. And if it keeps on doing that, it will continue to be necessary.</p>
        <p>But I can't prophesy whether it will continue doing that or not, and neither can anyone else. Cities make themselves up as they go along, just as languages do, and whether they're going to do it in a creative and useful way, or whether they're going to muff it, who can know in advance?</p>
        <p>Felix G. Rohatyn  United States Ambassador to France</p>
        <p>Maybe absence makes the heart grow fonder, but the more I'm away from New York, the more indispensable it appears to me.</p>
        <p>New York is already the 21st-century city because it is the city that encompasses both total cultural diversity and a total commitment to intellectual property, which is what the 21st century is going to be all about. Whether it's publishing, whether it's finance, whether it's fashion, whether it's the arts, whether it's communications, whether it's information technology, or architecture, whether it's being a transport and communications hub, New York is actually going to increase in importance.</p>
        <p>Every time I come back I get this jolt. Paris is beautiful, but Paris doesn't have the electricity of New York. Paris is like Greta Garbo, compared to Michelle Pfeiffer as New York.</p>
        <p>Drew Nieporent  Restaurateur</p>
        <p>Restaurant-wise, nothing beats the variety and the value of New York as a food town, and I don't see that changing. If anything, it's just becoming more vibrant, and there are that many more choices and places than before.</p>
        <p>We used to take concepts from outside, like French and Italian, and we'd do all that food and bring it to New York. But now you have some really talented chefs who are taking the craft they developed in New York and bringing that to other places, and there are markets that really appreciate a New York product, not the same French extract or Italian extract. New York is developing its own cuisine culture that's past matzoh ball soup and corned beef sandwiches.</p>
        <p>Luc Sante  Author, ''Low Life: Lures and Snares of Old New York''</p>
        <p>New York is not necessary for me. After living here 27 years, I am within a few months of moving out, probably to the country. For me, the things that I loved about New York are gone. They may come back at some point, if New York goes through another spin cycle, but right now they're not in existence. New York was the magnet for the members of the worldwide fringe, the eccentrics, the unemployables, the visionaries, the whatevers back in the days when you could still kind of live marginally here, which is to say until sometime in the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>But now that it's so expensive to live in New York, it seems to have only one face. The city has always been about money, of course, but it had that other aspect, it had more than one face. At one time it was a seemingly endless labyrinth I could wander around forever. But now I have no desire to walk down streets of condo conversions.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Calvin O. Butts 3d  Pastor, Abyssinian Baptist Church, Harlem</p>
        <p>If there wasn't a place on this planet called New York, God would have to create it. It is the best experiment in democracy that the world knows. The most diverse city in the world, it has a great mixture of the heavy, secular greed that is necessary for this kind of place to exist, but also the kind of balance provided by the deep spiritual nature of the people who live here and the institutions that represent that spirit.</p>
        <p>If you are looking for a real attempt to get to one world, a real example of what the new millennium will look like, New York is it. And so we need New York as an example of how we can get along and work together.</p>
        <p>Vartan Gregorian  President, Carnegie Corporation of New York</p>
        <p>New York is still going to be the center of the world, more so than it is now. There are several factors: No. 1, the entire culture is becoming urban culture, worldwide, and New York is the epitome of that. Second, this is the most international city anywhere in the world, and I include London, Paris, Berlin -- name it. New York is also the ethnic capital of the world. It's a vibrant city, the perpetual revolving door for immigrants where one wave displaces the other. New York is not just an actuality, it's a potentiality.</p>
        <p>As for the idea that people will never leave their homes because of the Internet, well, I'll tell you, I heard about that a long time ago, that videos were going to displace movie houses. People still need people. They like to feel the vibration. They like to walk on Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>Jane Friedman  Chief executive, HarperCollins</p>
        <p>The center of publishing in America has been New York City for eons and I think that that will absolutely continue. I think there is talent coming from everywhere entering the publishing world, but I think that the publishing companies themselves -- the editorial staffs, the marketing staffs, the promotions staffs, the advertising staffs -- will almost definitely be located in what will still be seen as the center, which is Manhattan.</p>
        <p>I believe wholeheartedly in the Internet, and we are looking forward to the expansion of the Internet Age, but I still believe that just as people still want to go into a bookstore and touch the product, I believe that proximity to human beings is very important. So someplace is going to be necessary in the 21st century, and in my opinion, New York is the best of those someplaces.</p>
        <p>Leonard S. Riggio  Chief executive, Barnes &amp; Noble</p>
        <p>As long as it's still here, New York will still be necessary. And the Internet and e-commerce are not changing that. On the contrary, New York City is on the way to becoming -- is -- the world's greatest shopping center. Retail space is gone, retail rents are at all-time highs, and moving up every day. If anything, the city is threatened with being run over by retailers. The thing we need in our New York City stores now are wall-stretchers.</p>
        <p>To me, the Internet is delivering, and it will only get better. Some people and some companies and even some cities may become victims, but New York sure as hell isn't one of them.</p>
        <p>Ada Louise Huxtable  Architecture critic</p>
        <p>I think New York will be absolutely necessary, and I don't think it depends on the architecture. I think it depends on the creative energy of this place; it's not just an economic center, it's an arts center, a place where everybody comes to do creative work, as well as to make a lot of money. And that makes New York unique, and absolutely irreplaceable.</p>
        <p>So that if that's the way life is still going to be going in the next century, then it's still going to be necessary.</p>
        <p>George E. Rupp  President, Columbia University</p>
        <p>I am convinced that New York City will be even more essential in the 21st century. Globalization, in the end, enhances the eminence of world cities. Global cities will continue to be irreplaceable as centers for face-to-face interaction, intergovernmental deliberations and international finance and as the indispensable locus for global media and world-class arts and performance. That will only be more the case as the world becomes more interconnected.</p>
        <p>Dr. Arnold J. Levine  President, Rockefeller University</p>
        <p>There's a study at the Institute of Medicine that I haven't seen in detail, but I've looked at it a little bit, and it actually projects a very rapid growth rise in science here in New York. Universities like Mount Sinai Medical School, Cornell Medical School, Rockefeller University are planning expansions in the biological and medical sciences. There will literally be thousands of new scientists who will be coming into the New York City environment over the next 10 years and who are going to be working in brand new laboratories that are being built.</p>
        <p>Mike Wallace  Historian, co-author, ''Gotham: A History of New York City to 1898''</p>
        <p>From a planetary perspective, New York has for centuries been a crucial node in the global circulation of capital, labor, information, commodities and cultures. After World War II, we emerged as the center of the capitalist world system, and though we now must share the global spotlight with other world cities, so long as the United States remains the world's dominant economic and military power, New York's status -- and hence, ''necessity'' -- is not likely to change fundamentally. Still, given the vigorous competition, sustaining our position will require public and private initiatives as smart and bold as our forebears' digging of the Erie Canal.</p>
        <p>From a national perspective, the city's ''necessity'' -- which had waxed steadily from the 1790's -- began to wane after the 1930's, a consequence of the growth of the Federal state, the rise of sunbelt/gunbelt competitors, the loss of manufacturing and commercial pre-eminence, the erosion of hegemony over cultural production. Yet if political competition and disaggregative economic forces have seriously undermined our former national supremacy, we remain a major hub of commerce, finance, business services, fashion, arts, media, specialized manufacturing and tourism. We are well positioned to maintain this status quo, but only if we keep moving, keep building on inherited advantages and seizing upon new possibilities.</p>
        <p>From a third, local perspective, New York will continue to be ''necessary'' for the millions of us who live here. Indeed the city has long thrived in part by generating -- and meeting -- its own vast demand for food, transport, shelter and entertainment. Happily, many of the interventions we should make to maintain and enhance our quality of life will also improve our standing in global and national arenas.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Caro  Author, ''The Power Broker: Robert Moses and the Fall of New York''</p>
        <p>Of course New York will be necessary -- for the same reasons it has always been necessary. New York is the melting pot, the great cauldron of the planet. Into it are thrown all of the diverse peoples and cultures of the entire world, and in New York those cultures mix and churn and swirl together. Each of them retains its identity, but somehow out of all of this churning and swirling comes something greater than all of them put together.</p>
        <p>The reasons New York fulfills this function have to do, in part, with density and a concentration of peoples. Because there are so many people here, and they live so closely side by side, there are enough of them and enough interactions between them to reach a critical mass that produces a unique vitality, energy, creativity -- an explosion of vitality and creativity, really.</p>
        <p>Judith Jamison  Artistic director, Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater</p>
        <p>If great artists still come here, this will still be the place. This is where the world discovers great artists, everybody knows that: New York is for the arts. All those old cliches about how you can play anywhere if you can play New York, they're all true. That won't change.</p>
        <p>Anybody who is creative will tell you that they can do it in the dark, in the closet -- wherever they are, they're going to shine. But if you're going to have this brilliance be delivered in Technicolor and in three dimensions, then you have to come to New York.</p>
        <p>Graciela Daniele  Theater director and choreographer</p>
        <p>I don't know whether New York will be necessary -- is any city really necessary? Great cities throughout history, in great cultures -- as great, or many greater than America -- disappeared, and the world continued and new communities were formed some place else. So, taking the big picture, I don't know if the word is necessary.</p>
        <p>If nothing catastrophic happens to New York, or to America or to the world, I think New York would always be the point in the world where people will come, like bees in search of pollen.</p>
        <p>It is something that appeals to artists from all over the world, and in that sense, I believe it doesn't matter what happens -- corporations coming into the theater, or Disney taking over -- it will always be the place people come to, not for the myth of Broadway, but because it's a very extraordinary cultural island.</p>
        <p>Shelly Lazarus  Chief executive, Ogilvy &amp; Mather</p>
        <p>In advertising, you have to go where people want to live, and creative people love living in New York. There are other places, of course, London, Singapore, for example; Johannesburg and Cape Town are also wonderful sources of talent. But New York is absolutely key for what we deliver to clients. This is a business of ideas, and for ideas you need some stimulation. And if you're looking for stimulation, New York is still the place to be.</p>
        <p>Nathan Leventhal  President, Lincoln Center</p>
        <p>I think New York has always been irreplaceable as the cultural capital of the world. Look around this country today and show me a city that has one-tenth the number of theaters and performance spaces New York has, or even a twentieth. That has not changed in the whole course of the 20th century, nobody has seriously challenged New York in the area of live performance either in this country or around the world, and I suspect that will continue well into the next millennium.</p>
        <p>Basically, life everywhere else is a tryout for New York.</p>
        <p>Lorne Michaels  Executive producer, ''Saturday Night Live''</p>
        <p>New York is kind of a mythic city, a place where just about anything can happen, and where almost nothing is shocking -- both the worst and the best.</p>
        <p>Will it still be necessary in the future? It depends on whether you think frustration is good for people.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
