<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends: Reconsidering Cannibalism; If You Are What You Eat, Mind if I Move to Another Table?</title>
    <meta content="02WADE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cannibalism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turner, Christy G (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Nicholas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cannibalism</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1DD1338F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends: Reconsidering Cannibalism; If You Are What You Eat, Mind if I Move to Another Table?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Nicholas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>History and lurid lore about cannibalism discussed; photo of Prof Christy G Turner with human remains from New Mexico that he belives were cannibalized (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DO you eat human flesh?</p>
        <p>No, it is not a very polite question. But perhaps the horror it arouses reflects a guilty desire, some dark instinct buried in the atavistic limbo of the mind, to crush one's enemy, savor his flesh and absorb his qualities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DO you eat human flesh?</p>
        <p>No, it is not a very polite question. But perhaps the horror it arouses reflects a guilty desire, some dark instinct buried in the atavistic limbo of the mind, to crush one's enemy, savor his flesh and absorb his qualities.</p>
        <p>Cannibalism has been in the news as rival experts try to get this bizarre but revealing topic into focus. The issue is whether cannibalism was once a routine part of human social behavior or is merely a myth designed to justify advanced nations' domination over primitive and allegedly anthropophagous peoples.</p>
        <p>Of course the survivors of desperate expeditions  will sometimes resort to eating their companions if no other food is available. The companions, one hopes, died of natural causes, though this cannot always be assumed. ''Oh, I am a cook and a captain bold, And the mate of the Nancy brig, And a bo'sun tight, and a midshipmite, And the crew of the captain's gig,'' the sole survivor laments of his consumed shipmates in W. S. Gilbert's ''Yarn of the Nancy Bell.''</p>
        <p>This consumption in extremis is known as survival cannibalism, a practice that is not in doubt. The debate concerns the practice of ritual cannibalism, like the headhunting of enemies, the Aztecs' sacrifice of war captives or the eating of dead relatives as part of beliefs about recycling and regeneration.</p>
        <p>Human myth and folklore are shot through with man-eating ogres and Cyclopses. The central sacrament of Christianity is the symbolic eating of transubstantiated flesh and blood. It is hard not to suspect a lot of anthropophagy in the closet of the human past. But the modern reporting of cannibalism has been beset by a bout of extreme revisionism.</p>
        <p>In a 1979 book, ''The Man-Eating Myth: Anthropology and Anthropophagy,'' William Arens of the State University of New York at Stony Brook dismissed as circumstantial and unconvincing all reports of ritual cannibalism. Dr. Arens even challenged the widely accepted finding that kuru, a human form of mad cow disease seen among the Fore people of Papua New Guinea, was spread by the eating of human brains.</p>
        <p>Dr. Arens's position has influenced anthropologists who believe primitive peoples were often maligned by missionaries and others intent upon their moral improvement. ''There is no reliable evidence to support the claim that Australian Aboriginal societies engaged in institutionalized cannibalism,'' writes Michael Pickering, of the Museum of Victoria in Australia, in ''The Anthropology of Cannibalism'' (Bergin &amp; Garvey, 1999).</p>
        <p>This tide of skepticism doubtless washed away many fanciful accounts but has been dismaying for archaeologists who found their evidence for cannibal feasts summarily dismissed. Cracked and burned human bones have been turned up for decades in Anasazi ruins in the American Southwest. Despite suggestions first made a century ago that these might represent cannibalism or ritual sacrifice, the remains were delicately referred to as ''mass burials.''</p>
        <p>The leading advocate of Anasazi cannibalism is Dr. Christy G. Turner of Arizona State University. He met only disbelief when he proposed in 1970 that the cut, burned and defleshed bones of 30 American Indians in Polacca Wash in Arizona were the remains of an ancient cannibal repast. ''In the 1960's, the new paradigm about Indians was that they were all peaceful and happy. So, to find something like this was the antithesis of the new way we were supposed to be thinking about Indians,'' Dr. Turner told Science magazine in 1997.</p>
        <p>Critics attributed the cuts on grisly remains like these to animal scavengers, funerary practices, the roof falling in -- anything but anthropophagy. After 30 years of work and the study of 15,000 skeletons, Dr. Turner is now convinced that cannibalism was practiced by the Anasazi as a method of social control. The cannibals' base of operations seems to have been the great house in Chaco Canyon, N.M., from which they terrorized people within a 100-mile radius between 900 and 1700 A.D.</p>
        <p>Dr. Turner's findings have been supported by a paleoanthropologist, Dr. Tim D. White of the University of California at Berkeley, who from human bones at an Anasazi site dated to 1150 A.D. noted the macabre phenomenon of ''pot polish.'' The tips of the bones had shiny patches, as if rubbed smooth against the walls of a cooking pot. Dr. White showed that deer bones cooked in an Anasazi pot acquired the same polish marks.</p>
        <p>Cannibalism is sometimes said to be a phenomenon of the agricultural revolution of 10,000 years ago, after which human populations first became quite numerous. But a clear case of cannibalism was reported last October among Neanderthals who lived 100,000 years ago by the Rhone river in southern France.</p>
        <p>From a cave, French archaeologists recovered 78 pieces of bone that seemed to belong to about six people. Cuts on the skulls show the chewing muscles were stripped off and, in one case, the tongue cut out. The leg bones were broken to remove the marrow.</p>
        <p>Even now, this horrid propensity for human flesh lies not so deep beneath the surface. After World War II a Japanese nurse was found guilty of having participated in eating the liver of an American airman executed at Kyushu University, the historian John Dower notes in his new book ''Embracing Defeat.'' The Emperor Jean-Bedel Bokassa I of the Central African Republic possessed an oversized refrigerator and oven, which his accusers said were used for the culinary preparation of his countrymen. And Americans have Jeffrey Dahmer.</p>
        <p>Even in Western Europe, that cradle of civilization, consider the strange use of food names for former adversaries. The French, for example, call the English les bifteks (beefsteaks), while the English sometimes refer to the French as frogs (for frog legs) and the Germans as krauts (cabbage). These jocular epithets are doubtless anthropophagous echoes of a forbidden taste from our Paleolithic heritage.</p>
        <p>Do you eat human flesh? Of course not. But not so long ago, your ancestors did.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
