<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Countdown Worth the Wait vs. a Big Ho-Hum</title>
    <meta content="02HYPE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE YEAR 2000: THE HYPERBOLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reservations (Airlines, Hotels, Etc)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square and 42d Street (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Marriott Marquis Hotel (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woodyard, Edward L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reservations (Airlines, Hotels, Etc)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7DB1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Countdown Worth the Wait vs. a Big Ho-Hum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward L Woodyard of Armonk, NY, who celebrated New Year's Eve 1999 with relatives at Marriott Marquis in Times Square, made his reservations in 1983, when hotel was half-finished; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before the countdown, the cork-popping, the confetti and the computer worries -- indeed, long before most people had personal computers -- there was the anticipation. And no one did more anticipating than Edward L. Woodyard, who spent 16 percent of the 1900's anticipating the arrival of 2000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woodyard, a screenwriter from Armonk, N.Y., had so much time to spend ruminating on 2000 because he made his reservations for New Year's Eve 1999 back in 1983, when the hotel in Times Square where he finally did his celebrating on Friday night was a half-finished skeleton of steel and concrete.</p>
        <p>''I decided if other people were thinking like I was, I'd better get my reservations in because when the time comes, it was going to be a mob scene,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before the countdown, the cork-popping, the confetti and the computer worries -- indeed, long before most people had personal computers -- there was the anticipation. And no one did more anticipating than Edward L. Woodyard, who spent 16 percent of the 1900's anticipating the arrival of 2000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woodyard, a screenwriter from Armonk, N.Y., had so much time to spend ruminating on 2000 because he made his reservations for New Year's Eve 1999 back in 1983, when the hotel in Times Square where he finally did his celebrating on Friday night was a half-finished skeleton of steel and concrete.</p>
        <p>''I decided if other people were thinking like I was, I'd better get my reservations in because when the time comes, it was going to be a mob scene,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As predictions go, that was a safe one -- Times Square was, in fact, a mob scene. He was above it, looking down on Times Square from the 44th floor of the Marriott Marquis. It seemed the perfect place to consider whether the arrival of 2000 lived up to its billing.</p>
        <p>People could easily argue about that for the next thousand years -- or at least the next thousand hours, which turns out to be 41  2/3 days. As litmus-test questions go, this one could prove as complicated as the kind that try to elicit whatever it is that separates liberals from conservatives, Martians from Venusians or Maria Callas fans from Renata Tebaldi aficionadoes. In other words, was the Champagne flute half full or half empty?</p>
        <p>''It's way overhyped, but that's the modern world,'' said the restaurateur Warner LeRoy, putting himself in the second category and suggesting that New Year's Eve brought the first backlash of the 21st century (or the last backlash of 20th): ''Most of the people I know stayed home.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, some promoters canceled their pricey New Year's celebrations for lack of paying customers; One television network canceled its daylong special for lack of stations to broadcast it. And some thought that much too much had been made of possible problems as 1999 rolled over to 2000.</p>
        <p>''It was overhyped, definitely,'' said Alan Gross of Brooklyn, who spent New Year's Eve at home. ''I was hoping my computer wouldn't work because I'd have an excuse to buy a new one.'' He booted up after midnight and was disappointed by the lack of drama. ''It was working just fine,'' he said. ''Unfortunately.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Woodyard's answer, on the other hand, was affirmative if a bit inarticulate; after a lot of partying, even screenwriters find themselves fumbling for nouns and adjectives, as well as hoarse from shouting ''10, 9, 8, 7'' and so on.</p>
        <p>But yes, he said, 2000 was worth the wait. ''I was almost speechless. I don't have words for it.'' He tried four: ''Spectacular. Phenomenal. Overpowering. Wow.''</p>
        <p>Then there were the naysayers, who may or may not also be doomsayers, but that is another story.</p>
        <p>''Pity the poor millennium: It never had a chance to get off the ground,'' said Mark Mitten, who registered the word ''billennium'' as a trademark because, he said, 2000 was the beginning of the second millennium. He also has a trademark on something called the ''millennium hype-o-meter'' on his World Wide Web site, www.millenniumhell.com.</p>
        <p>''Overburdened by Y2K fears, over-the-top parties and marketing hype, it seemed to have lost any of the potential it had to be a noble occasion, worthy of waiting a thousand years for,'' said Mr. Mitten. ''With all the overkill, it was hard to know if it had any significance at all.''</p>
        <p>And so the arrival of 2000 brought a kind of seesawing. There were those who thought it was the greatest thing in the last thousand years, or at least in the last four. Waterford crystal, which made the ball that slid down the pole on 1 Times Square at midnight, credited it with a 30 percent increase in sales last year, double the company's annual growth rate since 1996. Waterford, in fact, sold out of seven millennium-related keepsakes that cost as much as $200.</p>
        <p>The buildup included warnings that there would be no corks to pop: that there would be a Champagne shortage. But late last week, some stores were cutting prices they had raised back when they thought they would be at a different point on the supply-and-demand curve. Still, Korbel considered 2000 a manufacturer's dream: It had nothing left to ship to stores by the time Dec. 31 dawned. ''With this being the most active week for Champagne sales,'' said Andrew Varga, the Korbel Champagne brand general manager, ''we knew we're going to be wiped out.''</p>
        <p>But were people hyped out?</p>
        <p>Not Jeffrey Katz, an owner of 1 Times Square. ''People didn't understand, including myself, how you could do this all day long and not get tiresome,'' he said, ''but it was a thrill.''</p>
        <p>Not Peter Coleman, a vice president of the Times Square Business Improvement District, the semigovernmental organization that was one of the organizers of the celebration in Times Square. ''We didn't hype this,'' he said. ''We were trying to fulfill people's dreams.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Woodyard certainly seemed close to fulfillment.</p>
        <p>His New Year's Eve plans began in October 1983. ''My wife was pregnant, and I was talking to my brother-in-law,'' he said. ''We were trying to figure out when this baby would graduate from high school. I went, 'Holy cow, I know the millennium doesn't start till 2001, Arthur C. Clarke and all that, but the party is when all those zeros turn over, so let's have a big blowout when the zeroes turn over.' And then I said, 'The only place to be in the world is Times Square.' ''</p>
        <p>In 1983, he said, the only hotels in Times Square were the kind that charged hourly rates. But he knew that Marriott was building one on Broadway.</p>
        <p>''I called up the reservations clerk on the 800 number,'' he said. ''I said, 'You may think that I'm out of my mind, but I want to make a reservation for 16 years from now in your hotel that isn't built yet.' There was this long pause, and the woman said, 'You'll have to speak to my supervisor,' and I did. And that person said I'd have to talk to her supervisor. Finally, they patched me all the way into the executive headquarters in Washington, and the executive vice president said, 'Sure, we'll take the reservation.' ''</p>
        <p>Lucy Bossert, a spokeswoman for the hotel, said that its cylindrical core was about half finished when Mr. Woodyard called in 1983. Eventually Marriott offered Mr. Woodyard a suite with two adjoining bedrooms free, and he checked in with a group of relatives that included cousins from Minnesota and Virginia and his son, Christopher, whose birth led to the reservation-making in the first place. (The hotel did not rent other suites for New Year's Eve; it charged $2,000 for a four-night package for regular rooms.) And Mr. Woodyard started considering the where-were-you-when question.</p>
        <p>''Our generation remembers where we were when Kennedy was assassinated and our parents remember V-E Day, when that happened,'' said Mr. Woodyard , who remembered going to Times Square as a child for New Year's Eve in 1958. ''This was one of those things: where were you at the beginning of the millennium, when all those zeros turned over. I remember what fun I had as a kid, and I think this was 50 times that. What was 1958 in comparison with 2000? The Edsel is long gone. Do we remember the Edsel? No. Well, we remember it with some trepidation. I don't think we'll be forgetting the millennium.''</p>
        <p>Some wish may that they could. Kenneth H. Walker, a onetime architect who holds the registered trademark for the numerals 01-01-00, said his licensing and merchandising efforts had generated more than $100 million in sales, only about half what he had expected -- ''a good double,'' he called it, not the home run he had been counting on in 1998.</p>
        <p>''The reality is, the millennium never materialized into being the event of the last 1,000 years that I think a lot of people thought it would be,'' he said. ''The hype and all the articles you read about the hype were indeed true: It was overhyped. Most of what you read about with the hype was the New Year's Eve celebration greed, the hotels, the cruise ships charging ridiculous amounts of money for participation. I think that took away from things like ours.''</p>
        <p>THE YEAR 2000: THE HYPERBOLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
