<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lott, Disenchanted, Is Weighing a Union Challenge to Upshaw</title>
    <meta content="02NFLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Football League Players' Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lott, Ronnie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Upshaw, Gene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E5D91138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lott, Disenchanted, Is Weighing a Union Challenge to Upshaw</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>lott, disenchanted, is weighing a union challenge</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ronnie Lott spent nine years with the San Francisco 49ers and earned a reputation as one of the best safeties ever to play the game. No one was more fearless as a player, or more respected by his peers. Quite simply, he helped change the fortunes of the franchise, earning five Super Bowl rings.</p>
        <p>Now, Lott says he is hoping to change the way the National Football League Players Association does business and is strongly considering a run to replace its longtime executive director, Gene Upshaw.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ronnie Lott spent nine years with the San Francisco 49ers and earned a reputation as one of the best safeties ever to play the game. No one was more fearless as a player, or more respected by his peers. Quite simply, he helped change the fortunes of the franchise, earning five Super Bowl rings.</p>
        <p>Now, Lott says he is hoping to change the way the National Football League Players Association does business and is strongly considering a run to replace its longtime executive director, Gene Upshaw.</p>
        <p>If Lott does run, it will represent the first significant challenge Upshaw has faced, because Lott is held in such high esteem by many players. Before Lott agreed to be interviewed last week, a small number of players from various teams were asked if they would vote for him if he became a candidate. All said his reputation for honesty alone would merit serious consideration.</p>
        <p>Four Giants said they would strongly consider voting for Lott, a future Hall of Famer. When asked why, one veteran said: ''The times I've spoken to him, he has been nothing but a straight-up guy. He's a legend. He's very honest.''</p>
        <p>And, most likely, in a lot of locker rooms.</p>
        <p>Lott, now a pro football analyst for Fox, has flirted with the idea of running for head of the union before, but decided against it, feeling the time was not right. He is more serious about running now, he said, because of his rising anger over what he perceives to be the union's lack of dedication to nonstar players.</p>
        <p>''That is supposed to be the main part of the job, looking out for the interests of all players, not just star players,'' Lott said. ''Whether it is Michael Irvin catching passes in Dallas, or Olindo Mare kicking field goals in Miami, or Victor Green with the Jets, everyone should have a say. The way it is now, that is not the case.</p>
        <p>''I think players are kept in the dark about issues on purpose. That way the status quo is maintained. Gene and the N.F.L. owners are pretty comfortable with each other. I think owners like it that way, because if the union is comfortable with the N.F.L., then the union will never really push the league hard.''</p>
        <p>The union's offices were closed last week. An N.F.L.P.A. spokesman did not return phone calls.</p>
        <p>Lott is clearly not a fan of Upshaw and other leaders of the union. In 1997 he filed a lawsuit against union leaders, arguing that Players Inc., the N.F.L.P.A.'s marketing arm, stole the idea of the Super Bowl players' party from him and the former Oakland running back Marcus Allen, who joined Lott in the suit. The case is set for trial in May. The N.F.L.P.A. has denied the claims.</p>
        <p>Should Lott win the case and also beat Upshaw in an election, he would be expected to donate any monetary judgments to charity in order to avoid a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>Lott is exploring the exact procedure he would face in mounting a challenge to Upshaw. For one thing, he would very likely need a certain number of signatures from rank-and-file players on a petition.</p>
        <p>Upshaw has presided over the largest growth ever in N.F.L. player salaries, the average player now earning about $1 million a year. Medical and pension benefits have also increased. Pro football has also enjoyed labor peace for more than a decade, and thus there are many players who think Upshaw is doing a good job.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Lott said, the union's executive committee, the small group of N.F.L.P.A. officials who are instrumental in many key decisions, needs reform. There should be term limits for executive board members ''because the league is constantly changing,'' Lott said. ''There is a tremendous amount of turnover among players. I think you always need to have fresh faces on the executive committee who bring fresh ideas.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I've had players say to me, 'How can we get some of those people out of the union?' And I always say, 'You can't the way the system is set up.' The system needs to be changed so people aren't on the executive board five years or 10 years or longer. The same should go for the executive director.''</p>
        <p>Another complaint Lott said he had heard from players was the general lack of guaranteed salaries. Football lags behind other professional sports in that if a player signs for a four-year, $4 million salary, the entire amount is usually not guaranteed.</p>
        <p>For lower-tier players the situation is worse, Lott said. Not only are most of their base salaries not guaranteed, but their signing bonuses are usually low, making these players expendable.</p>
        <p>If Lott does attempt to become executive director, he will, in the words of one veteran player, be a formidable opponent, and, if he wins, a good leader. ''Ronnie is Ronnie,'' the player said. ''He's tough, and he would give Gene a good fight.''</p>
        <p>Complementary Weapons</p>
        <p>Indianapolis quarterback Peyton Manning is having an outstanding season, but there is no question he is benefiting from the success of running back Edgerrin James and wide receiver Marvin Harrison. James and Harrison have combined for 3,672 yards, the second-highest total in the 1990's by a running back/wide receiver duo. James and Harrison may yet pass running back Emmitt Smith and wide receiver Michael Irvin of Dallas, who combined for 3,751 yards in 1995.</p>
        <p>Right behind James and Harrison is the St. Louis duo of Marshall Faulk and Isaac Bruce. They have 3,520 yards this season.</p>
        <p>Blue in the Bayou</p>
        <p>This has been a miserable season for the rookie running back Ricky Williams. His New Orleans team has won three games. Coach Mike Ditka has said Williams needs to improve his conditioning and has even called him weird because he wears his helmet while doing interviews.</p>
        <p>Williams may have reason to be grouchy. His base salary for this season, because of a highly questionable contract he signed after becoming the No. 1 player in the draft, is just $175,000. He had the chance to earn more than $3 million in incentives, but will get only $50,000 because of his poor rushing numbers and the terrible season the Saints have had.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ditka believes he will be back as coach next season. If he does return, the owner Tom Benson may ask for major changes in his staff.</p>
        <p>Around the League</p>
        <p>San Diego Coach Mike Riley called the Pro Bowl snub of Chargers linebacker Junior Seau a travesty. . . . The Jets' defensive coordinator, Bill Belichick, remains the No. 1 candidate to replace Coach Pete Carroll in New England. Coach Bill Parcells, meanwhile, has already completed his book on the 1999 season. The manuscript contains no hints about his future plans. . . . With one Sunday left in the regular season, 21 players have broken the 1,000-yard receiving mark, the second-largest group ever. Eight players are within 100 yards of 1,000. In 1995, 23 players had 1,000-yard receiving seasons. . . . The Baltimore Ravens recently added a minority investor, Stephen Bisciotti, who also has an option to buy the remaining 51 percent of the franchise from the principal owner, Art Modell, in 2004. Yet Modell said, ''I plan on being in the N.F.L. for a long time.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
