<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Jim Jensen, b. 1926; Authority Figure</title>
    <meta content="MB100049" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rich, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jensen, Jim (1926-99)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Frank Rich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2D91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Jim Jensen, b. 1926; Authority Figure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Rich</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Ric</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The two most famous fictional TV news anchormen of the 1970's -- Ted Baxter of ''The Mary Tyler Moore Show'' and Howard Beale of ''Network'' -- may not have been directly inspired by Jim Jensen, but they could have been. Jensen, who worked at WCBS from 1964 to 1995, was the very model of a modern local newsman. With his deep Midwestern baritone, rangy good looks and a humorless, macho manner that suggested he could reach out of the tube and slug someone, he laid down the news with the authority of -- well, if not God, then at least Charlton Heston at full Old Testament throttle.</p>
        <p>Was Jensen actually an old-school journalist like Howard Beale, or was he, like Ted Baxter, merely an empty suit behaving like a stuffed shirt? Did he have any knowledge or insights to back up the headlines and wisdom he dispensed? It mattered not. Arriving at his desk in the era defined by network anchors like Chet Huntley, David Brinkley and Walter Cronkite, Jensen was cast perfectly as News Patriarch. He ruled absolutely, his unsmiling visage brooking no nonsense from either his on-air colleagues or the mass audience readying itself for dinner or bed. If Jensen wanted to rebel against TV's growing commercialism like the mad-as-hell Beale, he never let on. But neither did he ever make idiotic gaffes on air, like vacuous Ted. In TV news, Jensen was a shining light of the Golden Age of Testosterone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The two most famous fictional TV news anchormen of the 1970's -- Ted Baxter of ''The Mary Tyler Moore Show'' and Howard Beale of ''Network'' -- may not have been directly inspired by Jim Jensen, but they could have been. Jensen, who worked at WCBS from 1964 to 1995, was the very model of a modern local newsman. With his deep Midwestern baritone, rangy good looks and a humorless, macho manner that suggested he could reach out of the tube and slug someone, he laid down the news with the authority of -- well, if not God, then at least Charlton Heston at full Old Testament throttle.</p>
        <p>Was Jensen actually an old-school journalist like Howard Beale, or was he, like Ted Baxter, merely an empty suit behaving like a stuffed shirt? Did he have any knowledge or insights to back up the headlines and wisdom he dispensed? It mattered not. Arriving at his desk in the era defined by network anchors like Chet Huntley, David Brinkley and Walter Cronkite, Jensen was cast perfectly as News Patriarch. He ruled absolutely, his unsmiling visage brooking no nonsense from either his on-air colleagues or the mass audience readying itself for dinner or bed. If Jensen wanted to rebel against TV's growing commercialism like the mad-as-hell Beale, he never let on. But neither did he ever make idiotic gaffes on air, like vacuous Ted. In TV news, Jensen was a shining light of the Golden Age of Testosterone.</p>
        <p>''You can't rely on gimmickry or you don't last long, he once said. ''You just do your job.'' The job, beyond reading from a teleprompter and taking occasional glamorous forays into the field, was somewhere between public oracle and high-school principal, and perhaps it was best dramatized by an incident late in his career. Anchoring coverage of the 1993 terrorist bombing at the World Trade Center, Jensen fielded a call on the air from a man trapped on the 107th floor who described the panicking fellow captives around him. ''Tell them to calm down,'' commanded Jensen. ''We're going to try to get help to you.'' They calmed down; help arrived; end of story.</p>
        <p>In private life, Jensen had his demons. He turned his bouts with alcohol and Valium into public-service broadcasts. But what really did him in was the changing world of local TV news. The 70's brought the proliferation of Eyewitness News -- happy-talk broadcasts devised by consultants like Frank Magid Associates. In the new local news, there was no Top Dog but an egalitarian ''team,'' assembled to win over the full diversity of Nielsen demographics. There were jokes and casual repartee, to flatter viewers into thinking they were part of the TV family. There were no authority figures, no stentorian voices. On the new news, no one even pretended that journalism was a required skill. Putting Jim Jensen in such an environment would have been tantamount to making Judge Judy a regular on ''The View.''</p>
        <p>When Jensen left the air a few years before his death, his departure was barely noticed, so completely transformed was the kingdom he once ruled; only on the dying network evening-news broadcasts do authoritarian white men still hold sway. It would be hard to argue that the passing of his era was a great loss for journalism; it was just a typical turnover of fashion in a show-biz simulation of journalism. But as we look at Jim Jensen's successors, with their designer eyeglasses and slap-happy banter, it's hard not to feel nostalgia for the day when our anchors devoted heart and soul to upholding the reassuring pretense that they were not as vacuous as we feared.</p>
        <p>Frank Rich is a Times Op-Ed columnist and a senior writer for The Times Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Frank Rich is a Times Op-Ed columnist and a senior writer for The Times Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
