<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That's All, Folks!</title>
    <meta content="02KENNEDT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Twentieth Century</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, J M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Twentieth Century (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDB1539F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That's All, Folks!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul Kennedy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Kennedy reviews book Twentieth Century. The History of the World, 1901 to 2000 by J M Roberts; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twentieth Century</p>
        <p>The History of the World, 1901 to 2000.</p>
        <p>By J. M. Roberts.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 906 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $39.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Twentieth Century</p>
        <p>The History of the World, 1901 to 2000.</p>
        <p>By J. M. Roberts.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 906 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $39.95.</p>
        <p>ONE hundred years ago, as our forefathers hurtled breathlessly into the 20th century, the novelist and futurist H. G. Wells warned that humankind was engaged in a race between ''education and catastrophe.'' That phrase might be interpreted in many ways, but it is clear to any student of Wells's writing what that gifted seer meant. An explosion in knowledge, generated by the Enlightenment, and an explosion in new devices and machines, generated by the scientific and industrial revolutions, had combined to give Homo sapiens the capacity to transform his environment. The steam engine and the factory system meant that goods could be produced, and in far larger numbers, 24 hours a day. People could move 100 miles in one afternoon, by rail or by the newfangled motor cars. Ships could pound their way against contrary winds and currents because they were powered by coal and oil and no longer dependent on sail. Why, some young Americans had just built a flying machine! Were there no physical and technical limits to humankind's reach? Was not the future bright with promise?</p>
        <p>Yet Wells was uneasy, sensing that catastrophe might still outweigh education. Since time immemorial, malevolent humans had contrived to use new tools and structures to conquer, kill and destroy. Those primal drives had not gone away; they were simply being channeled in more modern times into an intense state-centered patriotism and xenophobia. Military men were already testing ways whereby the Wright brothers' invention could be adapted to drop bombs on intended enemies. Automobiles were being converted into armored cars. The flourishing steel, chemical and electrical industries were being harnessed to make guns, tanks and warships. Industrial society had an unprecendented capacity to create prosperity and comfort but also contained undeniable new powers to harm, to victimize and to control, as Wells and later writers like George Orwell fully recognized.</p>
        <p>Does not this dichotomy between creativity and destructiveness, crude though it may be, capture the essence of the century just ending? The world's population has risen almost fourfold in these 100 years, but more people than ever before in history have been slaughtered, starved and driven into exile. Our collective wealth has risen astronomically, but the distinction between rich and poor countries, and rich and poor individuals, seems as skewed in the year 2000 as it was in 1901 -- and this after generations of efforts to create equity. The social comforts that any reasonably prosperous middle-class family enjoys today would astound Queen Victoria, but about two billion people worldwide live in grinding poverty. Many humans exhibit deep reverence for nature, for old churches and paintings and other artifacts, and for the preservation of all that we have inherited; but even more (usually poorer) folks are engaged in slash-and-burn forestry, polluting the atmosphere, discarding industrial waste and wiping out plant and animal species. We can create frost-free plants and conquer polio, but we can also produce H-bombs that, if exploded, would devastate a vast swath of the earth. In sum, our abilities to affect our destiny, for good or bad, are now so much greater than a century ago.</p>
        <p>How is one to capture all these changes, both for our own understanding of the momentous 20th century and, more especially, for a younger generation that will live the greater part of its life in the 21st century? There are now very few people living who remember World War I. Within a few decades, there will be nobody alive when the Holocaust occurred, when the first jet flew, when oral contraceptives became broadly available or when women did not have the vote. How will we teach this e-mail generation?</p>
        <p>One answer is to search for an unusually wide-ranging, curious and learned scholar who might make sense of the convoluted and kaleidoscopic events of the past 100 years, and hammer them into a certain shape. It would be a shape much influenced by that scholar's own background -- by nationality, sex , age, politics and ideology -- and no other writer would compose exactly the same account or focus on exactly the same things. Nevertheless, any and all attempts at such a synthesis deserve our initial welcome and empathy.</p>
        <p>This is certainly true of J. M. Roberts's remarkably astute and balanced work, ''Twentieth Century: The History of the World, 1901 to 2000.'' This distinguished British historian and former warden of Merton College, Oxford, is the author of many well-known surveys, including ''A History of Europe'' and the truly impressive ''History of the World.'' The author is one of the great synthesizers of our time.</p>
        <p>But what does that mean exactly, in terms of the end product? Perhaps the key quality here is balance -- that is, the judicious selection of events and themes that encapsulate as much of the historical reality as is humanly possible. This is easier said than done. A mere recording of thousands of facts about the past century would be antiquarianism. But the imposition of a single theme -- say, arranging the entire history around the rise and fall of the welfare state, or North-South relations -- would be arbitrary and Procrustean.</p>
        <p>The best three measures of historical balance are, I would think, chronology, geography and genre, and in all those respects Roberts passes the test. Achieving a chronological balance is, of course, the easiest to do: he simply allocated about half the book (in this case, approximately 15 chapters and some 400 pages) to the period before the cold war, and the other half (about 14 chapters and another 400 pages) to world events since the late 1940's. Still, the results of this balancing act are eye-opening, especially to those brought up in the more traditional ways of describing the 20th century. Thus, World War I (Chapter 8, and 30 succinct pages) claims the same amount of space as the various movements to challenge authority in the 1960's (Chapter 20, and also 30 pages). Also eye-opening and, frankly, a little disturbing to those readers who think that history is the study of the past is the recentness of the later parts of Roberts's narrative. The conflict in Kosovo, the creation of the euro, convulsions in Indonesia, the electoral defeat of Helmut Kohl, the Monica Lewinsky scandal and China's criticism of American ''hegemonism'' close his tale, just as the Boer War and the Boxer Rebellion open it.</p>
        <p>More interesting and demanding still is the requirement for geographic balance. Can a privileged Oxford don, composing this ''Twentieth Century'' in a quiet cottage in Somerset, England, really be fair to all parts of the globe? Can this history avoid a predictable ''Western'' or ''Northern'' slant? Of course not. An Eskimo, a Botswanan and a Jamaican will not find much on their specific countries, even if the general social and cultural changes that the author delineates will seem more familiar. Still, the physical range here is dauntingly broad, and a welcome antidote to writings that, both in history and more particularly across the social sciences, seem to be getting narrower and narrower in topic. For example, the fifth large section of Roberts's work (he calls it ''A New World'') ranges across the post-1945 landscape. All the familiar features of that terrain are there, from the Marshall Plan to the Korean War; but so, too, are regions and stories less familiar to Western readers, like the emergence of Indonesia, the early years of Japan's recovery, the white supremacist movement in Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe), the coming of settled democracy to India. This does not mean that one could assemble from this tour d'horizon a composite history of, say, Latin America in the 20th century: such regions sort of meander in and out of the story, depending upon their pertinence to Roberts's more general themes and arguments. Nevertheless, this is a genuine and, on the whole, successful effort at a global history, which always has to acknowledge that most of the impulses for change originated and were grappled with first in the North, and yet not ignore the story of what was going on in the South, especially as its peoples, too, encountered the new ideas, technologies and forces for social transformation.</p>
        <p>But it is in the third dimension -- that of balancing the different genres of history and of comprehending its seamless web -- that Roberts is at his best. Perhaps this is because he deliberately starts the book by creating a very large framework -- almost as if he were describing the features of the planet Earth to a set of extraterrestrial tourists who were completely ignorant of this new world on their intergalactic journey. Thus, the first elements that are drawn attention to are ''Human numbers -- The world's wealth -- Commerce -- States and governments,'' etc., all in a chapter entitled ''Structures.'' Moreover, the author is quick to let the reader know that this is not a static portrait, like a Baedeker guide detailing York Minster or the Pyramids. Another chapter, ''Shapes of Things to Come,'' introduces us to the various transformations that human society is experiencing at the start of the 20th century -- its own demographic growth, the spread of industrialization, the changes in daily lives due to new machines or improvements in medical science, the advent of mass communications and the emergence of new mindsets.</p>
        <p>Having ensured that the focus of ''Twentieth Century'' really is ''what is happening to all humankind?'' Roberts thus finds it easier to order and interpret the flow of events than someone who began, say, with a narrowly political description of a Western, male, partly democratic, late-Victorian world system. His antennas are sensitive to all manner of ways that people lived through this century. He is particularly good, it seems to me, on the transformations in the lives of women over the past 100 years: thus the coming of electricity brought labor-saving machines that took away a great deal of the hard, daily work (cleaning the family's clothes in a tub by churning them or hitting them with a stick, for example, as was done overwhelmingly by women for centuries -- and is still done by hundreds of millions of women today in societies that lack electricity). In the same vein, his discussion of the coming of ''the Pill'' in the 1960's, and of the social and behavioral changes that flowed from its ever widening use, make this a work of great breadth, insight and, yes, historical empathy.</p>
        <p>One final aspect of Roberts's book completes this reviewer's satisfaction at his marvelous distillation: it is the sure and firm way that he brackets this complicated story with both a fine introduction that poses large questions of how to write such a history in any case (there is a really good, small section on ''The Different Pasts of 1901'') and a complementary retrospective chapter on the meaning of the 20th century. All told, this is a book that deserves the widest reading because it is about one of the most important historical stories of all -- namely, what happened in the most dynamic and recent century of humankind's journey through time.</p>
        <p>Paul Kennedy is the Dilworth professor of history at Yale University and the academic editor of ''The Global Century,'' a forthcoming multivolume series.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul Kennedy is the Dilworth professor of history at Yale University and the academic editor of ''The Global Century,'' a forthcoming multivolume series.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
