<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gardens Now Public at a du Pont Estate in Delaware</title>
    <meta content="02FOC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wilmington (Del)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milford, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Du Pont Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharp Family</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Delaware/Wilmington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7D81E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gardens Now Public at a du Pont Estate in Delaware</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN MILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Milford, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WILMINGTON, Del.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gibraltar, former mansion owned by du Pont family in Wilmington, Del, is about to be converted into small inn and gardens were recently opened for public use; when project is completed in early 2001, total cost should be $5 million; estate is owned by Sharp branch of the du Ponts; estate's history detailed; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Colleen Schuetz is alone in the gardens of Gibraltar, a former du Pont estate here, the horticulturist sometimes imagines long-dead women from the family descending the sweeping outdoor staircase during summer parties.</p>
        <p>''There's just this aura about the place -- this sense of being transported to another lifetime -- it's very powerful,'' said Miss Schuetz of the six-acre estate on Pennsylvania Avenue at the Wilmington city limits.</p>
        <p>Miss Schuetz, 23, is not the only one who feels that way. When the estate, known as Gibraltar, was in danger of being torn down and developed for upscale housing in the mid-1990's, the community felt it was losing a piece of its heritage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Colleen Schuetz is alone in the gardens of Gibraltar, a former du Pont estate here, the horticulturist sometimes imagines long-dead women from the family descending the sweeping outdoor staircase during summer parties.</p>
        <p>''There's just this aura about the place -- this sense of being transported to another lifetime -- it's very powerful,'' said Miss Schuetz of the six-acre estate on Pennsylvania Avenue at the Wilmington city limits.</p>
        <p>Miss Schuetz, 23, is not the only one who feels that way. When the estate, known as Gibraltar, was in danger of being torn down and developed for upscale housing in the mid-1990's, the community felt it was losing a piece of its heritage.</p>
        <p>Besides the imposing hulk of a house made of locally quarried Brandywine blue stone, Gibraltar was noted for its formal gardens, designed by Marian Cruger Coffin. A pioneer female landscape architect, Miss Coffin designed more than 130 gardens on the East Coast in the first half of the 20th century, including many for the du Ponts.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, Gibraltar's owners -- the Sharp branch of the du Ponts -- were willing to consider alternatives to demolition. While none of the descendants of the original owners, the late H. Rodney and Isabella du Pont Sharp, wanted to take on the costly job of renovating the house and gardens for their own use, they did not want a development that would be incompatible with the area.</p>
        <p>Now, after nearly five years of complex deal-making by the Sharps, the state and a historic preservation group, the mansion is about to be converted to a small inn and the gardens were recently opened for public use. When the project is completed in early 2001, the total cost should be $5 million.</p>
        <p>Under the arrangement, the Sharps, who had been asking $2 million for the property, deeded the house to Preservation Delaware Inc., a nonprofit group that seeks to save the structures and landscapes that give the state its unusual character.</p>
        <p>In return, the Sharps received $750,000 for development rights to Gibraltar from the Delaware Open Space Program, a state land-preservation initiative. A conversion easement was then placed on the property, permitting development of the hotel with some limited expansion and opening of the gardens to the public.</p>
        <p>''I think it was a win, win, win,'' said Ron Vickers, chief of the land preservation office of the State Division of Parks and Recreation. ''It allows for the protection of the historic building, the preservation of the gardens and the preservation of the character of the neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>To handle conversion of the house into a 31-room hotel, Preservation Delaware has signed an agreement with Someplace(s) Different in Exeter, N.H., a company that operates 24 historic hotels from Quebec City to Orlando.</p>
        <p>Work on the house is expected to begin early next year, with completion in the first quarter of 2001. A restaurant is planned for greenhouses above the garages.</p>
        <p>Wilmingtonians have already begun to see changes at the estate. In September, the $1 million restoration of the gardens was completed. Altogether, Preservation Delaware has raised $2.1 million for the gardens, of which half will be used as an endowment for maintaining the grounds.</p>
        <p>While the house, now listed on the National Register of Historic Places, has been  empty except for caretakers for nearly 10 years, the gardens have already been the scene of two weddings. Though neglected, the gardens have essentially been unaltered from the days after Miss Coffin created them for the Sharps in 1919.</p>
        <p>The late Mr. Sharp shared a love of horticulture with his brother-in-law, Pierre S. du Pont. Mr. du Pont -- one of three du Pont cousins who took over the family's gunpowder business in 1902 and transformed it into a modern chemical business -- helped make his relatives fabulously rich within two decades. Mr. du Pont created Longwood Gardens, a world-renowned horticultural destination in nearby Kennett Square, Pa., as a du Pont family legacy. Indeed, Miss Schuetz came to Gibraltar after an internship at Longwood.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharp was an important preservationist in the state, saving more than a half-dozen historic homes in the former port town of Odessa, south of Wilmington. He also worked with Pierre du Pont on the design and construction of the buildings and campus at the University of Delaware in Newark.</p>
        <p>For his home, Mr. Sharp settled on what was then a country estate a little more than a mile from the center of Wilmington. A large saltbox house had been built in 1844 by John Rodney Brinckle, a Wilmington cotton merchant and descendant of the Delaware patriot Caesar Rodney. After buying the house in 1909, the Sharps tripled its size over several decades.</p>
        <p>As with many du Pont estates, the house was less important than the gardens. Indeed, when Eleuthere Irenee du Pont , founder of the gunpowder company, landed in Newport, R.I., on New Year's Day in 1800 en route from France, he listed his profession as botanist.</p>
        <p>Dr. David Ames, director of the Center for Historic Architecture and Design at the University of Delaware, calls Gibraltar's gardens an outstanding example of urban landscape architecture from the early decades of the century. The house, with an Italianate core and Colonial Revival modifications, is less interesting, Dr. Ames said.</p>
        <p>''The du Ponts have been called the first family of horticulture,'' Dr. Ames said. Miss Coffin, whose family was socially connected to the parents of Henry Francis du Pont of Winterthur, Del., formed a lifelong friendship with him while she was studying at Massachusetts Institute of Technology and he was at Harvard. At M.I.T., Miss Coffin came under the influence of Guy Lowell, who designed the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston and wrote about the renewed taste for Renaissance gardens in the early part of the century.</p>
        <p>Later, Mr. du Pont hired Miss Coffin to do work at Winterthur, which has since become the nation's premier museum of American decorative arts.</p>
        <p>For Gibraltar, Miss Coffin divided the property into two sections. The section in front of the house was to resemble an English park, while the east side of the property that faces downtown Wilmington was designed as an elegant Beaux-Arts garden. A steep slope was carved into a series of interconnecting terraces and retaining walls. Stone steps curve gracefully down to a reflecting pool that was used for swimming by the family.</p>
        <p>Benches are tucked into nooks, with classical statues and decorative wrought iron gates to give the feeling of outdoor rooms. On the lowest level is a flowered border garden that moves to an allee of bald cypress trees and smoke bushes. The allee ends at a Belvedere Temple.</p>
        <p>Descendants of the Sharps have fond memories of the gardens and holidays in the house when the Christmas tree would be cut on the family property. But they were reluctant to undertake renovation of the house themselves.</p>
        <p>H. Rodney Sharp III, grandson of the original owners and president of the Longwood Foundation, said the restoration would not only cost millions but also require a full staff to maintain, which he called an irresponsible use of resources.</p>
        <p>''You would have to be a real aficionado of that kind of living,'' he said. ''There's better things to spend your money on than living in a house with a huge staff.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, many du Ponts today have chosen not to keep houses built during the years when the family ran the chemical company on a daily basis. The du Ponts are known in Delaware for their understated, old-money lifestyle, and it doesn't seem to bother them to see those houses open for public use. ''Its not strange for me,'' Mr. Sharp said. ''I'm looking forward to being able to eat and spend the night there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
