<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Footloose and Luggage-Free</title>
    <meta content="02PRAC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVLER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Luggage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Betsy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Luggage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4DB1E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Footloose and Luggage-Free</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETSY WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Betsy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Practical Traveler column on shipping luggage and skis, as alternative to lugging them through airports (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN you are hauling luggage and skis through airports, onto rental-car shuttles and into the snow, you swear you would pay anything to turn the task over to someone else.</p>
        <p>There are such people. Longtime package companies like United Parcel Service and Federal Express, and a newcomer, are doing some heavy lifting so vacationers can travel with carry-ons only. For a price.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN you are hauling luggage and skis through airports, onto rental-car shuttles and into the snow, you swear you would pay anything to turn the task over to someone else.</p>
        <p>There are such people. Longtime package companies like United Parcel Service and Federal Express, and a newcomer, are doing some heavy lifting so vacationers can travel with carry-ons only. For a price.</p>
        <p>The new company, Travelite, in suburban Chicago, after shipping materials to conventions for 14 years, has expanded into baggage. It picks up and, for a fee based on weight and distance, delivers luggage to a hotel in the United States at roughly the time its owners arrive. The company's Virtual Bellhop program uses messenger services and express companies, providing the same coverage for loss that the airlines have been providing domestically, $1,250 per passenger now, but rising this month to $2,500.</p>
        <p>Although spokesmen for United Parcel and Federal Express sound cool about handling baggage, saying that their focus remains business-to-business shipping, they have been accommodating travelers just the same.</p>
        <p>Shunning the luggage carousel is not cheap; it may be as much as another airline ticket. But many consider it worthwhile: Carolyn Tancotti, the front desk manager for the Thunderbird Lodge and Chalets in Taos, N.M., said that U.P.S. regularly comes to the door with luggage and skis for arriving guests. Her estimate was that 10 to 20 percent of lodge guests now ship their stuff ahead.</p>
        <p>2 Scenarios, 3 Options</p>
        <p>The biggest hurdle in shipping is being sure the hotel has a catcher's mitt. It is no fun to crawl through cartons in storerooms desperately seeking material sent too far in advance. Travelite's president, William F. Cippola, says that his shipping companies hold the baggage until the day the travelers arrive.</p>
        <p>This is an evolving area. Anyone who wants to try it should first call the hotel to be sure it can receive bags without owners attached. Travelers should know that air shipments are subject to the same rules as checked luggage; pressurized hair sprays and other hazardous materials, for example, should not be included.</p>
        <p>To get ball-park estimates, we created two scenarios, one a shipment of a family's skis from Manhattan to the Thunderbird Lodge in Taos, and the other to get four suitcases from Minneapolis to a cruise ship pier in Fort Lauderdale, Fla.</p>
        <p>The comparisons are complex because United Parcel wants the items put into containers; Federal Express has a plastic sleeve to go over ski bags and will accept suitcases as is or in cartons. Travelite does the packaging.</p>
        <p>Ski areas have their heads up for such plans. Deer Valley, Utah, near Park City, for example, in a program with FedEx, will accept skis and poles and stash them near the lift for $45. Skiers aiming at Deer Valley or Park City should call ahead, (800) 558-3337, to get this rate. Jess Bunn, a spokesman for FedEx, said that the company was negotiating with resorts in Colorado on this sort of plan, so when reservations are made it is worth asking what is feasible.</p>
        <p>The cruise venture is trickier. Carnival, the biggest in the field, says it has no provision for bags shipped ahead. But Silversea in Fort Lauderdale and Crystal in Los Angeles and Cunard-Seabourn, with longer and more expensive cruises, say they can arrange with ground operators to handle bags that come ahead, and get them into suites in time for embarkation.</p>
        <p>''We have never said no to a guest,'' Jennifer Lawrence Schott of Silversea said.</p>
        <p>Liz Jakeway of Celebrity Cruises said it was looking into the idea.</p>
        <p>Sending Skis to Taos</p>
        <p>The comparisons show that planning reduces prices: get the skis off a week ahead and save major dollars. And comparison shopping for each trip is advisable.</p>
        <p>Virtual Bellhop service will pick up and package two pairs of adult skis and two pairs of children's skis from Manhattan's West Side and ship them to the lodge in Taos for a third-day delivery for $210. Second-day delivery costs $245 and next-day air $262. Third day means articles picked up on Monday will be delivered Thursday.</p>
        <p>United Parcel requires the sender to package the skis. Sporting goods shops sell telescoping hard plastic containers called SporTubes for one or two pairs of skis; at Paragon in New York they cost $100 or $150.</p>
        <p>Using specifications for these containers, Kenneth E. Shapero, a spokesman for United Parcel, said that two such containers if picked up at home and sent ''second-day air'' would cost $141.25, cheaper than Virtual Bellhop, but one must buy containers. If picked up for next-day delivery, the cost would be $194. Automatic coverage is $100 in value per package; additional coverage costs 35 cents per $100.</p>
        <p>FedEx refers inquiries about its service to its Web site, www.fedex  .com. People who enjoy this sort of thing can enter ZIP codes, weights and dimensions to learn what a cost will be; Mr. Bunn says that FedEx uses the higher of the costs from a weight chart or a dimension chart. Using dimensions, two ski containers, each with two pairs inside, if picked up at home (the pickup adds $3 per package) and delivered on the third business day -- a day later than United Parcel's ''second-day air'' --  would cost $110.20. Picked up for second-day delivery, the cost would come to $119.50. For next-day delivery, $171.50.</p>
        <p>If no extra value is declared on a FedEx package, it is set at $100; for a payment of $2.50, coverage goes to $500, and the cost is 50 cents for each $100 thereafter.</p>
        <p>Cruise Passenger Options</p>
        <p>As for getting four suitcases to a pier, Virtual Bellhop prices the Minneapolis-Fort Lauderdale venture at $121 for third-day delivery, $130 for second-day and $165 for next-day. Mr. Cippola says that his company estimates that four suitcases will weigh 100 pounds total.</p>
        <p>United Parcel wants the suitcases put into cartons, and estimates each suitcase's weight at 40 pounds. The prices with pickup at home are close to the drop-off prices because, Mr. Shapero says, the company wants to encourage pickups. For fourth-day delivery, the cost for the four pieces, if picked up, would be $101.48. With pickup for second-day delivery, the cost is $279. For overnight, pickup included again, it comes to $387.</p>
        <p>The FedEx Web site shows the cost for 100 pounds of suitcase, whether one or four, at $149 if picked up for delivery on the fourth day; for second-day, $162, and for next-day delivery, $238.</p>
        <p>Virtual Bellhop, (877) 235-5467,  can provide estimates once it is given details. The Web site is www  .virtualbellhop.com; the address is 31632 North Ellis Drive, Suite 304, Volo, Ill. 60073.</p>
        <p>United Parcel Service can be reached at (800) 742-5877; www.ups .com.</p>
        <p>Federal Express can be called for pickup at (800) 463-3339; www .fedex.com.</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVLER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
