<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking the Time to Repair or Replace a Balustrade</title>
    <meta content="LICLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE2DB1538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking the Time to Repair or Replace a Balustrade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A WELL-CONSTRUCTED staircase is made of many components: treads, risers and stringers that fit together like a fine cabinet. Some staircases are enclosed between two walls, but most are usually built against one wall with the opposite side being open. For safety reasons, the open side should be enclosed with a balustrade. The balustrade is a series of vertical posts, called balusters. These support the handrail. One end of the handrail is usually anchored to a wall or a railing at the top of the stairs. At the other end of the balustrade, at the foot of the stairs, is the newel post. It supports the handrail and anchors the balustrade.</p>
        <p>All this may seem complicated, but the balustrade is basically a very simple and sturdy structure. Occasionally, problems develop if the joints between the parts loosen or if a baluster cracks or breaks. Balusters generally work loose at the top where they support the handrail. They can be tightened with glue and wooden shims.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A WELL-CONSTRUCTED staircase is made of many components: treads, risers and stringers that fit together like a fine cabinet. Some staircases are enclosed between two walls, but most are usually built against one wall with the opposite side being open. For safety reasons, the open side should be enclosed with a balustrade. The balustrade is a series of vertical posts, called balusters. These support the handrail. One end of the handrail is usually anchored to a wall or a railing at the top of the stairs. At the other end of the balustrade, at the foot of the stairs, is the newel post. It supports the handrail and anchors the balustrade.</p>
        <p>All this may seem complicated, but the balustrade is basically a very simple and sturdy structure. Occasionally, problems develop if the joints between the parts loosen or if a baluster cracks or breaks. Balusters generally work loose at the top where they support the handrail. They can be tightened with glue and wooden shims.</p>
        <p>To tighten a loose baluster, cut a thin shim from a piece of hardwood and coat it with glue. Use a small mallet and a wooden block to drive the shim into the gap between the rail and baluster top. Ideally, you should make this repair at night when the stairs will not be used. In this way the glue can set for 12 hours without being disturbed. When the glue is dry, use a utility knife to trim the shim so it is flush with the baluster.</p>
        <p>You can also use a long wood screw to secure a loose baluster. Drill a pilot hole at an angle through the side of the baluster up into the rail. Next, countersink the hole so the screw head will be hidden below the surface of the wood. Driving the screw through the hole should pull the rail and baluster securely together.</p>
        <p>Replacing a broken baluster is more difficult because the piece is usually doweled or dovetailed into the tread and it may be hard to remove. It is usually easier to saw the baluster in half, then pull the top part out from the rail. In some cases, the top of the baluster may be fitted in a rectangular groove in the handrail and secured in place between fillet blocks (rectangular pieces of wood that fit in the rail groove between each baluster). Before you can pull out the sawed baluster, you may have to chisel out one of the fillets.</p>
        <p>The bottom part of the baluster may have a doweled end set with glue into a hole in the tread, or it may have a base that is dovetailed into slots in the tread. To loosen and remove a doweled baluster base, grip it with an adjustable wrench and twist it. This should break the glue bond so you can pull the piece free. If you cannot loosen the baluster with a wrench, you will have to drill it out. First, saw the baluster so it is flush with the tread, then use a spade bit the same diameter as the dowel to bore out the hole.</p>
        <p>Balusters with dovetails are concealed behind a piece of decorative molding mounted on the edge of the tread. Before you can remove the baluster, you must pry away the molding to reveal the dovetail joints. With the molding removed, you can tap the baluster with a mallet to force it from the tread slot. If that doesn't work, saw it flush with the tread then chisel the remaining piece from the slot.</p>
        <p>If your staircase was built within the last 25 years, it was probably constructed with standard mass-produced parts, and you should be able to find replacement balusters at the local lumberyard or building supply store. These dealers usually carry a variety of standard balusters that match contemporary designs. If you cannot find a matching piece in stock, you will have to have one made to order by an experienced cabinetmaker.</p>
        <p>Installing the replacement baluster is a matter of angling it between the rail and tread, then gently tapping it into a vertical position. Before doing this, coat the dowel hole or dovetail slot in the tread with glue.</p>
        <p>Newel posts are sturdy, so they rarely need to be replaced. They do, however, loosen over time and need to be tightened. Tightening a newel post depends upon its construction. One type has a base extension that extends through the floor and is bolted to a joist. Firm up the post by tightening the nut on the extension. The other type of newel post is hollow with a vertical threaded rod running through the core of the post. Tightening the nut on the end of the rod will firm up the post. To gain access to the rod, remove the decorative finial cap on top of the post.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
