<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="02FSUM$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DA1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-12</p>
        <p>Russian Starts Tenure With Chechnya Visit  Vladimir V. Putin, on his first day as Russia's new acting president, left before dawn to visit with Russian troops fighting in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>The sprawling capital city of Chechnya has turned out to be, once again, a deadly killing zone in the Russian war with the breakaway republic. Russian soldiers have made inroads, but still do not control the center of the capital, Grozny, while the casualties continue to rise.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-12</p>
        <p>Russian Starts Tenure With Chechnya Visit  Vladimir V. Putin, on his first day as Russia's new acting president, left before dawn to visit with Russian troops fighting in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>The sprawling capital city of Chechnya has turned out to be, once again, a deadly killing zone in the Russian war with the breakaway republic. Russian soldiers have made inroads, but still do not control the center of the capital, Grozny, while the casualties continue to rise.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Hostages Recount Experiences  The experience of being trapped in a hijacked Indian Airlines jet for eight days has left many of the hostages feeling deeply traumatized. In interviews, they described days of tedium punctuated by moments of terror.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Pakistani Confesses Killings  The frantic monthlong hunt for a man who said he killed 100 youths in Pakistan out of vengeance ended when the wealthy, tormented man surrendered by entering the office of a newspaper to offer his story.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>13-24</p>
        <p>A Sophisticated Campaign Against the War on Drugs  A small coalition of libertarians, liberals and humanitarians has mounted a sophisticated campaign to end the nation's war on drugs. Using polls, focus groups and advertising, the coalition has selected and promoted causes that might arouse sympathy among Americans.</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Unlikely Architecture Showcase  Columbus, Ind., is close to winning National Landmark status as a showcase for the leading lights of modern architecture. The city boasts a collection of about 65 buildings by nationally known architects.</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>The Primary Races as a Dash  The chairmen of the Republican and Democratic parties say they are bracing for a presidential primary season so unexpectedly competitive that they have to reach back to 1960 for a comparison. Yet the state of the campaigns is such that the entire exercise may be over soon after the public begins to pay attention.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>THE YEAR 2000</p>
        <p>12-14, 30-32</p>
        <p>A Day Later, a Look Back At All the Hoopla  One man started planning his New Year's Eve 2000 celebration 16 years ago, and says it was definitely worth the wait. Others said they weren't so sure.</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>New Computer Question  Now that the Year 2000 has arrived around the world without significant disruptions of power, transportation, commerce and other activities dependent on computers, the question arises: Was the threat of technology failure overstated, or did spending hundreds of billions of dollars to fix things avert a catastrophe?</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Just Another Day  In the wake of a hyperbolic night, New Yorkers awoke to a city that in the first hours of the year 2000 looked and acted pretty much the way it did in 1999. Things worked. The terrorists stayed home. No blackouts. No bombs.</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Cuba's Different Drummer  Cuba did not have a millennial celebration. It takes the position that because the Christian calendar began with the Year One, the new millennium actually starts next year. Families celebrated in their traditional way while they watched tourists celebrate lavishly.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>British Warm Up to Dome  The 10,500 guests to the strictly-by-invitation New Year's Eve extravaganza at the custom-built Millennium Dome in Greenwich, England, could not help but be swept up in the grand scale and euphoria of the occasion although most waited for more than two unheated hours before the show.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>Anticlimax in Cyberspace  By the time midnight struck in Hawaii, even the Internet's most dedicated harbingers of millennium doom had to concede that things had turned out better than they had expected.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>27-33</p>
        <p>Environmentalists Criticize Plan to Buy Diesel Buses  A plan by the Metropolitan Transportation Authority to order hundreds of diesel-powered buses for New York City is drawing resistance from environmentalists and legislators, who say it will increase smog and health problems. The authority is focusing its efforts on an experimental hybrid engine that runs on both diesel fuel and electricity.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Speculating on an Archbishop  Since Cardinal John O'Connor, the archbishop of New York, is likely to retire soon, speculation and hope are swirling within church circles about whom Pope John Paul II will appoint to this powerful post.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>NEEDIEST CASES</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>35</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>TV Update</p>
        <p>34</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
