<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Celebrating the Past By Looking at Present</title>
    <meta content="02ART.$19" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, Helen A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4DA1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1282" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Celebrating the Past By Looking at Present</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Helen A. Harrison</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harrison, Helen A</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Helen A Harrison reviews fin-de-siecle art shows at Graphic Eye Gallery in Port Washington and at Omni Gallery in Uniondale; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'A Quarter Century of the Graphic Eye Meets the Millennium'</p>
        <p>Graphic Eye Gallery, 301 Main Street, Port Washington. Through Jan. 30. (516) 883-9668.  Shelter Rock Art Gallery, 48 Shelter Rock Road, Manhasset. Through Jan. 26. (516) 627-6560.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'A Quarter Century of the Graphic Eye Meets the Millennium'</p>
        <p>Graphic Eye Gallery, 301 Main Street, Port Washington. Through Jan. 30. (516) 883-9668.  Shelter Rock Art Gallery, 48 Shelter Rock Road, Manhasset. Through Jan. 26. (516) 627-6560.</p>
        <p>To celebrate the 25th anniversary of Long Island's oldest surviving artists' cooperative, the Graphic Eye has mounted a group exhibition in two locations: its own gallery in Port Washington, and the gallery of the Unitarian Universalist Congregation in Manhasset. The two venues allow for a more in-depth selection of works by the co-op's roster of 24 artists, but one cannot help feeling that an opportunity has been missed.  In spite of its commemorative title, the show functions almost exclusively in the present tense.</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding the glut of century-summarizing, millennium-celebrating exhibitions, it seems appropriate for the Graphic Eye to mark its silver anniversary by including evidence of its origins and past achievements. With the amount of space available in the two galleries, there would be ample room for pieces from the co-op's early days by its founders and initial members, some of whom are now deceased, as well as recent work by current members. Such a combination of historical and contemporary material would also show how the organization's focus has changed since its inception in 1974 as a printmakers' cooperative spawned by Ruth Leaf's graphics atelier.</p>
        <p>Strangely, the earliest works on view are neither prints nor products of the co-op's first years. They are two gouaches by Toby Sullivan -- one a nightmarish Ku Klux Klan scene reminiscent of New Deal era socially conscious art, the other a charmingly naive Central Park landscape -- both painted nearly 30 years before the Graphic Eye was founded.  Although at first their inclusion seems inappropriate, on reflection one can make a case for it. Since the organization has undergone the sea change from one exclusively for printmakers to a general artists' group, what better way to illustrate its eclecticism? Ms. Sullivan is also represented by ''The Dream,'' a recent monotype that is light years away from her gouaches, both technically and aesthetically, and, paradoxically, closer to the co-op's original focus. Her style now is Baroque modernism, like Matisse in his Moroccan phase, and her handling of pigment is loose and gestural, in contrast to the tightly controlled brushwork of the early pieces. As Ms. Sullivan's selections indicate, current members may show whatever they like.</p>
        <p>The other artists tend to be more consistent, showing related works in both galleries. For example, Susan Kornblum's ''Comix I'' collage painting is on view in Manhasset, and its mate, ''Comix II,'' is featured in Port Washington. Both canvases consist of panels cut from comic strips, attached to the paintings' chalky surfaces and partly obliterated by erasing, scratching and overpainting.  The effect is of a Mondrian-like grid structure, somewhat dissolved but nevertheless a symbol of artistic purism, playing a witty counterpoint to the pop-culture appeal of the cartoons, which in turn are partly obscured. The juxtaposition seems to emphasize the fact that the grid and the cartoon are opposite extremes; both are forms of visual abstraction, the one often criticized as elitist while the other is considered vulgar.  By blending them so cleverly and allowing them subtly to play off against each other, Ms. Kornblum has reconciled their differences.</p>
        <p>Similarities are the theme of Stephanie Bloom's pair of ''Class 2000'' photomontages, which use repeated images of white, middle-class schoolchildren to comment on the dangers of social conformism. Each group of clones represents the successful imposition of an arbitrary norm -- a false homogeneity that breeds narrow-mindedness, discourages tolerance and stifles creativity.  From a distance, however, these institutional images look quite ordinary. Indeed, most of us posed with our own classmates for very similar pictures. On closer inspection, however, the familiarity is replaced by a feeling of alienation, and the implications of cookie-cutter sameness make the innocent smiles seem oddly sinister.</p>
        <p>Raisy Derzie also repeats her figures, but with very different intent.  Her monotypes, both titled ''Then What?'', are successive pulls of the same plate, each yielding forms and colors that are less distinct. In one print, apparently the first run through the press, the image is vivid, emphasizing the emotional intensity of a scene with theatrical overtones.  In the second print, the plate has been used twice on the same sheet, the top impression mirroring the bottom one to produce a playing-card effect. The format's allusion to gambling enhances the impression of a morality tale, with its theme of a casual sexual encounter followed by remorse, and repetition as a reminder that misdeeds are often compulsively serial.</p>
        <p>''In the Presence Of,'' three photoetchings by Ellen Brous, use the repeated motif of hands raised in  greeting, homage or, perhaps, benediction. Emerging from the velvety darkness that surrounds it, a shadowy figure makes its gesture of acknowledgment, which in turn becomes a disembodied echo of the initial salute. When the figure disappears, the hands remain to form their own supporting structure, and they also acquire an independent meaning, like pictographs based on human and animal characters.</p>
        <p>'Twentieth-Century Traditions'</p>
        <p>Omni Gallery, 333 Earle Ovington Boulevard, Uniondale. Through Jan. 21. (516) 396- 0031.</p>
        <p>In another fin-de-siecle show, this one based on the premise that all art is a product of evolution, five artists look back to the 20th-century forebears whose influence they feel most strongly. Written statements accompanying the installations acknowledge the artists' sources and explain their impact on works in which the references to specific precedents are often veiled or oblique.</p>
        <p>Looking at Tati Herrera's mixed-media collages, with photographic details and painted acetate overlays assembled in a uniform grid pattern, one would not immediately think of Kurt Schwitters as a progenitor, but that is whom Ms. Herrera cites.  Schwitters's ability to recast random discards into meaningful documents of experience appears less relevant than his gift for bringing structure to formless fragments. The body parts that combine and recombine as thematic variations in ''Boomerang Echoes'' and ''Late Blight'' are divorced from their original anatomical context, just as Schwitters's eggshells, envelopes and bus tickets transcend their mundane origins.</p>
        <p>Greg Card has developed a hybrid art beholden to sources as diverse as Frank Stella's French-curve reliefs, Donald Judd's slick finishes and vehicle pinstriping, with a dash of Picasso for spice. Some of these references are rather deeply buried, but no one will mistake the nods to Stella's often garish filigrees and the elaborate linear symmetries of custom-car decoration. Rick Miller's avatars include a long line of street photographers, like Paul Strand, Helen Levitt and Gary Winogrand, whose documentary black-and-white technique he emulates. He is a sympathetic observer, without an obvious social agenda but closely attuned to the body language of social interaction.</p>
        <p>Eleanor Honig blends brushwork indebted to Willem de Kooning with the spatial ideas of Hans Hofmann to produce energetic abstractions that allude to nature. More graffiti-like than painterly, her compositions use line to evoke the forces of growth and the elements. Gloria Cunnick (who is coincidentally included in the Graphic Eye exhibitions) became interested in the encaustic medium through her admiration for Jasper Johns.  Her waxy panels also owe a debt to Mark Rothko's use of luminous color, but the results, with their recollections of ancient wall paint and plaster, are distinctively her own.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
