<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Fiction's Final Frontier; Perhaps</title>
    <meta content="02COVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sci-Fi Channel</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elias, Justine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E3D91138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1328" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Fiction's Final Frontier; Perhaps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUSTINE ELIAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elias, Justine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>science fiction's final frontier, perhaps*</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even if humankind hasn't traveled beyond Earth's moon, our television transmissions have. And somewhere in the far reaches of the galaxy some alien race may be settling down in front of a viewing module getting ready to enjoy the adventures of the Starship Enterprise, only to find -- to their green-skinned horror -- that ''Star Trek'' or some other favorite science-fiction series has been unceremoniously canceled because of low ratings.</p>
        <p>Avid fans of science fiction, no matter what planet they call home, are all too familiar with the cycle of excitement, confusion and despair that seems to  occur whenever a new science fiction series begins. First there's the promise of an intriguing, risk-taking show. The viewers quickly become puzzled when the fledgling series, having failed to gain a mass audience, is shuttled through various time slots, pre-empted, postponed or tossed into the black hole known as ''permanent hiatus.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even if humankind hasn't traveled beyond Earth's moon, our television transmissions have. And somewhere in the far reaches of the galaxy some alien race may be settling down in front of a viewing module getting ready to enjoy the adventures of the Starship Enterprise, only to find -- to their green-skinned horror -- that ''Star Trek'' or some other favorite science-fiction series has been unceremoniously canceled because of low ratings.</p>
        <p>Avid fans of science fiction, no matter what planet they call home, are all too familiar with the cycle of excitement, confusion and despair that seems to  occur whenever a new science fiction series begins. First there's the promise of an intriguing, risk-taking show. The viewers quickly become puzzled when the fledgling series, having failed to gain a mass audience, is shuttled through various time slots, pre-empted, postponed or tossed into the black hole known as ''permanent hiatus.''</p>
        <p>But one cable network is challenging the notion that the science fiction and fantasy genres are too expensive and  specialized to attract more than a niche audience. The SCI FI channel, after nearly a decade of showing classic and not-quite-classic fantasy films, resurrecting old science fiction series and rescuing shows from other networks, is developing its own series and films.</p>
        <p>Though its most popular programs draw no more viewers than the lowest-rated shows on broadcast networks do, SCI FI is becoming more attractive to advertisers. According to network estimates, SCI FI is seen in 60 million households and has the highest concentration of prime-time viewers aged 18 to 49 ( the audience most desired by advertisers) and the highest concentration of male viewers in that age group ( something the network would like to change by attracting more women).</p>
        <p>January is often a quiet month in terms of new programming, but SCI FI has been aggressively promoting itself as the definitive home of all things futuristic and fantastic. Bonnie Hammer, the network's executive vice president and general manager, said the audience for science fiction was broader than ever. ''The growth of SCI FI, as a channel, has a lot to do with the changes in society at large,'' said Ms. Hammer, who came to SCI FI 18 months ago after eight years at its sister network, USA. ''Who would have thought 5 or 10 years ago that so many of us would be communicating instantly, via cyberspace, cellular phones, even fax machines in our cars? In so many ways, we are leading science-fiction lives.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hammer also points to the popularity of stories that mix science and speculation, like ''Jurassic Park,'' and supernatural-theme films like ''The Sixth Sense'' as evidence that the mass audience does embrace science fiction  even if most people don't consider themselves hard-core fans.</p>
        <p>''We don't subscribe to the old school of marketing that says that Sci Fi is a male vehicle,'' said Ms. Hammer, whose favorite television shows while she was growing up were the original ''Star Trek'' and ''The Twilight Zone.'' It is no coincidence that many of the network's new offerings feature strong female characters and heroes who are more complex than the genre's stereotypically invulnerable action heroes.</p>
        <p>This month Sci Fi is promoting the second seasons of ''Farscape'' and ''First Wave,'' two original series that  take disparate looks at the near future. It will also revive ''Prey,'' a suspense series about a species that is more highly evolved and far more brutal than Homo sapiens. ''Prey,'' which features the ''Will and Grace'' star Debra Messing as a resourceful scientist, was canceled by ABC in 1998 before all 13 of its episodes were shown.</p>
        <p>This month will also bring the debut of a psychic talk show, with the host John Edward, who is billed as a specialist in after-death communication, and ''Lexx,'' a Canadian-British-German production that might be described as a cross between ''Star Trek'' and ''Monty Python's Flying Circus.'' Unlike the crew members of the Starship Enterprise, who tended to improve conditions on the planets they visited, the crew members of the Lexx -- including a dead but reanimated assassin and a sexually voracious female explorer -- manage to bring about the total annihilation of every planet on which they set foot.</p>
        <p>Sci Fi is also producing two mini-series. The first is a version of Frank Herbert's seminal fantasy novel ''Dune,'' which was made, some would say disastrously, into a 1984 movie. ''Frank Herbert's 'Dune,' '' now being filmed in Prague, will be shown later this year. Then there is ''Taken,'' a 20-hour mini-series about alien abductions,  produced by Sci Fi and Steven Spielberg's DreamWorks Television.</p>
        <p>''First Wave,'' produced in British Columbia by Francis Ford Coppola's television company, is midway through its three-season commitment. Thus far, its hero, Cade Foster, played by Sebastian Spence, has staved off an alien invasion of Earth using the prophecies of Nostradamus.</p>
        <p>Chris Brancato, the creator of ''First Wave,'' compares its aliens to the early United States military advisers in Vietnam: ''They're an advance team, and some of them are not sure they are going to win.'' And while the show has apocalyptic overtones, he said, it is not pessimistic. ''The premise is a way to comment on the human character, and the way we live.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, despite the urgency of its main story, ''First Wave,'' like ''The X-Files,'' finds room for entertaining detours. One humorous installment follows the hero's paranoid friend to his high school reunion, which has been infiltrated by aliens, while another allows Foster, who has been grieving for his dead wife, to fall for a woman he has taken hostage.</p>
        <p>Though First Wave was bought with a three-season commitment, it is ''Farscape'' that has turned out to be the network's most highly rated original series. Filmed in Australia and produced by Jim Henson's company and Hallmark Pictures, ''Farscape'' takes a contemporary man, an astronaut and scientist named John Crichton (Ben Browder), and sends him through a wormhole to the far side of the universe. His companions aboard a living starship include a blue-skinned priestess (Virginia Hey), a fierce soldier (Claudia Black) and a tiny, arrogant aristocrat, Rygel, portrayed by a puppet. The show's creator, Rockne S. O'Bannon, calls the show's hero the ''stranger in a strange land.'' ''Crichton's an educated, accomplished, adventurous guy, but out there he's the alien,'' he said. ''And they're not all that impressed by him.''</p>
        <p>Lowly as Crichton may seem to the alien beings, Mr. O'Bannon said, he is brave, adaptable and endlessly improvisational, all of which help him to survive. The show may turn out to be as mutable as its hero. ''Steven Chao, the president of USA, didn't actually buy this show; it was bought before he came in, and I was nervous,'' Mr. O'Bannon said. ''But his marching orders were, and I quote, 'I want this show to be as outrageous as possible.' '' One of Mr. O'Bannon's previous series was ''Sea Quest DSV,'' which ran for three seasons on NBC before being rerun on SCI FI.</p>
        <p>If ''First Wave'' and ''Farscape'' gain an even larger audience, SCI FI's schedule may eventually lean toward largely original programming. ''Our mission in some ways should be to move forward, not just to repeat things that are rich and wonderful from the past,'' Ms. Hammer said. ''Science fiction has always projected images and concepts of what's coming next, what life, government, morals, sexuality, politics will be like as we move ahead into a complicated world and a complicated future.''</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
