<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living In/Clinton Hill, Brooklyn; Historic, Diverse and on the Rise</title>
    <meta content="02LIVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Clinton Hill (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Joyce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE7D81E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living In/Clinton Hill, Brooklyn; Historic, Diverse and on the Rise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>If You're Thinking of Living In column on Clinton Hill section of Brooklyn; table of geographic data; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH little commercial activity and only one subway line to Manhattan, Clinton Hill has long been a place that turns in early for the night.</p>
        <p>Now, though, this low-profile Brooklyn neighborhood is getting attention from people priced out of other parts of the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH little commercial activity and only one subway line to Manhattan, Clinton Hill has long been a place that turns in early for the night.</p>
        <p>Now, though, this low-profile Brooklyn neighborhood is getting attention from people priced out of other parts of the city.</p>
        <p>Like its sister neighborhood, Fort Greene, with which it is often compared, Clinton Hill is primarily one big historic district. The streetscape is open and varied, with row upon row of brownstones mixed with carriage houses, frame structures, brick mid-rises and even a Georgian mansion or two.</p>
        <p>The landmarked Royal Castle apartment building looms in a florid Beaux-Arts style. The Roman Catholic Queen of All Saints Church resembles a diminutive Gothic cathedral. The sunshine-yellow Steele-Skinner House, circa 1812, sports a cupola.</p>
        <p>Then there is the hulking Graham Home for Old Ladies, founded in 1851 as the ''Brooklyn Society for the Relief of Respectable, Aged, Indigent Females.'' Plans to turn the brick monolith into lofts fell through, and it is currently on the market for $2.6 million.</p>
        <p>''There's a certain quietness and gentleness to life in Clinton Hill,'' said Bob Evans, chairman of Community Board 2, who lives in Fort Greene but attends the landmarked Emmanuel Baptist Church in Clinton Hill. ''It's phenomenal in terms of its diversity -- ethnically, racially and economically.''</p>
        <p>Real-estate agents say that prices are lower in Clinton Hill than next door in Fort Greene and that people get more space for their money there than in comparable parts of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''Cheap real estate brought me here,'' said Douglas Clubok, a computer programmer who bought a two-bedroom co-op in 1985 in one of Clinton Hill's mid-rise apartment houses. ''And I was charmed by the physical appearance of the neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>Currently, typical four-story houses in the historic district sell for $600,000 to $650,000, said Naida McSherry, owner of Naida McSherry Realty. Prices are higher for very large houses with ''exceptionally beautiful detail,'' she said. They are lower for houses that need extensive renovation or are at the edges of the landmarked area or beyond -- on the blocks north of Myrtle Avenue, sometimes known as Wallabout, or near the Fulton Street/Classon Avenue intersection, adjacent to Bedford-Stuyvesant.</p>
        <p>Prices, which started climbing three to four years ago, have been rising at 20 percent a year, said Kathryn Lilly, who owns Realty on the Greene.</p>
        <p>People unfamiliar with the area initially prefer Fort Greene ''because it's closer to the subway line and Fort Greene Park,'' she said. ''But when they're here, they see Clinton Hill has much more diverse architecture and the population density is a little lower,'' she added.</p>
        <p>The price range is wide, Ms. Lilly said, adding, ''We've got a little one-family house that needs a gut rehab for $150,000 and we have things listed for $700,000.'' Desirable houses can sell in a week, she said.</p>
        <p>MUCH of the housing is in original condition because ''Clinton Hill was landmarked [in 1981] before anybody wanted to live here,'' said Sandra Shepard, an agent at William B. May Company whose family moved last year into a double carriage house in Clinton Hill. She said that prices for a few high-end homes, like triplexes with garden rentals were heading into the $800,000 range.</p>
        <p>''Multifamily houses go for less,'' she said. ''Houses that are chopped up are harder sells. You would have to reconfigure the house to get the living space you need.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shepard credited the introduction of the MetroCard with changing the perception that Clinton Hill is out of the way. The C train, a local, is the only one that goes to Manhattan. Now, with free bus-subway transfers, people are taking a 15-minute bus ride to downtown Brooklyn, with its large choice of subway lines. Those with cars report little trouble finding on-street parking.</p>
        <p>The area's several high-rise co-op complexes include the Clinton Hill Co-operative Apartments, built in 1938 for workers at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. The 1,221-unit complex, with 12 buildings of 12 to 15 stories, was converted in 1982.</p>
        <p>''The north side housed the enlisted men and the south side the officers,'' said the sales director, Jacqueline Henriquez. ''It was less dense on the officers' side.'' One-bedrooms sell for around $90,000, two-bedrooms for $120,000 and the few studios for $70,000.</p>
        <p>Often, rentals are within owner-occupied brownstones. Within the historic district, a one-bedroom rents for $1,200 to $1,400, said Suzanne DeBrango, an agent at the Aguayo &amp; Huebener Realty Group. A two-bedroom rents for $1,600 to $1,800, three-bedrooms for $2,000 and up. One went recently for $3,200, Ms. DeBrango said.</p>
        <p>Rental prices tend to be substantially lower east of Cambridge Place, where the blocks are more rundown. Nearby Fulton Street has several boarded-up storefronts. The intersections of Fulton Street and Classon Avenue, and of Grand and Putnam Avenues, do have ''some congregating on the corner'' and ''some disorder,'' said Capt. James Guida, commanding officer of the 88th Precinct.</p>
        <p>In the last several years, the precinct has seen some of the city's most dramatic drops in crime. Recently, however, grand larceny has been on the rise, said Captain Guida. ''Last year was a tough year to beat,'' he said. ''The crime that has risen most significantly is property crime'' --like theft of equipment from offices and from unattended vehicles.</p>
        <p>Clinton Hill lacks major shopping areas, though there are scattered grocery stores, coin laundries and pizza places. Myrtle Avenue, near Wallabout, includes thrift shops, gas stations and fast-food restaurants. Several merchants' groups are currently mobilizing to beautify the street and attract more businesses.</p>
        <p>One neighborhood favorite is Mike's Coffee Shop on DeKalb Avenue, a fixture for 60 years.</p>
        <p>A fresh food market and bakery should be opening on Vanderbilt Avenue in the spring, said Ms. DeBrango, who also handles commercial rentals.</p>
        <p>ONCE farmland, Clinton Hill got its start in 1832, when the main boulevard was laid out. It was named for De Witt Clinton, who had been both mayor and governor.</p>
        <p>In 1874, Charles Pratt, an oil magnate and a partner of John D. Rockefeller, built himself a mansion at 232 Clinton Avenue, then built four more as wedding presents for his sons. Three remain. The leafy promenade gained a reputation as the Fifth Avenue of Brooklyn, or Millionaire's Row.</p>
        <p>Early in the last century, apartment buildings replaced some of the grand houses, and brownstones were divided into rooming houses.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Hill Society nurtures the landmark district by raising funds for preservation, running house and garden tours, and painting over graffiti that mars the streets.</p>
        <p>In the 1960's and 1970's, Clinton Hill was beset by poverty, said Kurt Wohlfeil, the society's president. ''Brownstones were converted to floor-throughs and just sat there, whereas at other places people were taking out the banisters, woodwork and mirrors,'' he added. ''Now, people are restoring these gems.''</p>
        <p>Neighborhood volunteers are also active in publishing a free quarterly newspaper, The Hill: Journal of Clinton Hill, Fort Greene &amp; Wallabout.</p>
        <p>A mainstay of the area is the Pratt Institute. The art, design and architecture school was founded by Charles Pratt in 1887 with one drawing class and a dozen students. Today it has more than 4,000 students. Pratt's 25-acre campus includes several demapped streets, four landmarked buildings and three residence halls. Last summer, 26 large sculptures were installed on the grounds.</p>
        <p>PART of Clinton Avenue is occupied by St. Joseph's College, a 1,300-student commuter school that focuses on business and health management. St. Joseph's also runs the highly regarded Dillon Child Study Center for preschoolers.</p>
        <p>The neighborhood's most respected public elementary schools, both pre-k-6, are P.S. 11, the 800-pupil Purvis J. Behan School on Waverly Avenue, and P.S. 20, the 1,000-pupil Clinton Hill School on Adelphi Street, two blocks into Fort Greene. Both schools offer programs for instrumental music, art and academic enrichment. There is also plenty of ''meaningful parent involvement,'' said Lester W. Young, superintendent of Community School District 13.</p>
        <p>For the seventh and eighth grades, many students move on to I.S. 113, the 700-student Ronald Edmonds Learning Center on Carlton Avenue in Fort Greene. It also includes two sixth-grade classes -- one for performing arts and one for the academically advanced.</p>
        <p>District 13 has its own high school, the Benjamin Banneker Academy for Community Development. By next fall, the 600-student school will offer three majors -- pre-engineering, medical science and math, science and technology. There were nearly 500 first-choice applications for 160 seats, Dr. Young said.</p>
        <p>Religious education is offered by the parochial k-8, 253-student Queen of All Saints School. Annual tuition is $2,250 for both parishioners and nonparishioners.</p>
        <p>Graduates often head up the block to Bishop Loughlin Memorial High School, where annual tuition is $4,500. About 80 percent of the 900 boys and girls come from Brooklyn, as did a member of the class of 1961, Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
