<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Death in Atlanta</title>
    <meta content="02BIRKERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Birkerts, Sven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bambara, Toni Cade</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Those Bones Are Not My Child (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E0DB1539F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Death in Atlanta</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sven Birkerts</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Birkerts, Sven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sven Birkerts reviews book Those Bones Are Not My Child by Toni Cade Bambara (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOSE BONES</p>
        <p>ARE NOT MY CHILD</p>
        <p>By Toni Cade Bambara.</p>
        <p>676 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $27.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOSE BONES</p>
        <p>ARE NOT MY CHILD</p>
        <p>By Toni Cade Bambara.</p>
        <p>676 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $27.50.</p>
        <p>When Toni Cade Bambara died in 1995, she left behind a massive, nearly completed novel, which her longtime friend and editor, Toni Morrison, has now prepared for publication. Morrison's contribution, unlike that of John F. Callahan, who worked with Ralph Ellison's myriad drafts to effectively create the novel ''Juneteenth,'' seems to have been mainly one of editorial condensation. Bambara's manuscript, reportedly some 1,800 pages long, was shaped down to a relatively less unwieldy work in which the author's intentions are clearly on view.</p>
        <p>Or so one supposes, for ''Those Bones Are Not My Child'' moves with an almost monomaniacal intensity along a strictly chronological track, the main narrative progressing in a series of dated sections from July 20, 1980, to July 11, 1982. The setting is Atlanta during the period when more than 40 black children were abducted and murdered. Between these dates unfolds a drama that is at once harrowingly private and revealingly public at every level.</p>
        <p>On that first day, Zala Spencer, separated mother of three children, awaits the return of her eldest, Sonny, from a Boys' Club outing. As the hours pass and her irritation changes slowly to anxiety, Zala finds herself obeying the universal parental reflex, testing and rejecting scenarios: ''Sonny hit by a truck. Sonny hitching a ride with a lunatic. Sonny ducking in an abandoned building . . . crazy junkies jumping him.'' What she is fending off, of course, is the worst fear -- that her boy may have become the latest in some deranged killer's string of victims.</p>
        <p>Over the days that follow, through the lens of Zala's now rapidly escalating panic, we start to make out the contours of her life. Estranged from Spence, a Vietnam veteran and sometime limo driver, Zala takes in sewing at home and watches over her children. Though now it seems to be her two youngest, Kofi and Kenti, who must watch over her, frightened and confused, as friends and neighbors parade through their house and police officers make their preliminary inquiries. Slowly, carefully, with a sense of intensifying implication, Bambara begins to enlarge the scale of her plot, bringing into view not just the dynamics of Zala's own circle of family and acquaintances but the complex political structure of Mayor Maynard Jackson's Atlanta, the self-styled ''City Too Busy to Hate'' -- a telling counterpoint to the Atlanta that appeared in Tom Wolfe's novel ''A Man in Full.''</p>
        <p>Zala's Sonny is not the first child to have disappeared. A growing number of people in Atlanta's black community are convinced that some cult or conspiracy is at work, and that the motive for the killings may well be racial. In an atmosphere of mounting collective suspicion, Zala and Spence reconnect, helping to mobilize a grass-roots search, independently investigating leads, correlating patterns of data, publicizing what they have discovered and putting as much pressure as they can on what often appear to be deliberately obstructive moves on the part of the official investigators.</p>
        <p>Bambara builds up a racking suspense through the opening sections of the book. Zala, impelled by what feels like an almost visionary paranoia -- she seeks and sees connections everywhere -- devotes herself utterly to the case. Yet although this is psychologically plausible, it leads the author into what becomes a narrative morass. The novel's long middle section -- much of its real heft -- is given over to dense and somewhat confusing documentary accounts, all relating to the collective search for clues about the killings. The reader must either become a fellow obsessive or fall by the wayside. What makes matters more difficult is the fact that the Spencer family, whose travails impart dramatic character to this horrifying chaos of evidence and speculation, all but disappears from view. Was this, we wonder, where the editor did her most judicious pruning? Could Morrison have trimmed even more without sacrificing any artistically essential material?</p>
        <p>Fortunately, just when the novel threatens to disappear under the weight of all this reportage, the plot is retrieved. News comes about a ''John Doe Jr. in observation in Pediatrics, found wandering in a daze on the highway, barefoot, in khaki shorts and a ragged child's undershirt four sizes too small,'' a child ''so badly battered, it was difficult to isolate one area of damage from another.'' Utterly traumatized, he will not talk about what has happened to him. Nor does he reveal anything much when, a short time later, a young black man named Wayne Williams is charged with some of the murders.</p>
        <p>Events that might, in a less subtle author's hands, be treated in climactic ways are here subjected to a different sort of pressure. Unwilling to push for the ease of closure, Bambara creates a persuasive psychological ambiguity. The novel's last long section is a tour de force in which the full intensity and complication of family life emerge. Bambara, much praised for the shaded depth of her characterizations -- in the stories of ''Gorilla, My Love'' and other works -- rarely builds a scene toward a simple explosion. She relishes, instead, the power of accumulation, the visceral immersion that deepens as life's difficulties are compounded and carried forward. ''Those Bones Are Not My Child'' moves toward its conclusion via episodes of tense disequilibrium. The reader feels buffeted by the lives that rear up on all sides.</p>
        <p>On the larger, public level, the charging of Williams in a number of the killings does not set matters to rest. The divided city continues to roil -- politically, racially. Contrary to the logic of pop psychology, neither communities nor cities, let alone families, return to the status quo after a catastrophe like this. The damage is permanent, and all concerned can only hope to make the worst of the hurt endurable.</p>
        <p>Of course, few people ever believed that ''Case Closed'' could be stamped on the mountains of files in Atlanta Police Headquarters. Until the whole truth -- the complete system of interlinked facts -- is known, a terrible ache must remain. When people are still missing, or their murders remain unsolved, true grieving is not possible. Bambara's achievement -- in this masterly if not yet fully balanced work -- is to voice this sense of loss, to give full human dimension to events that for too many of us flashed by like billboards at highway speed.</p>
        <p>Sven Birkerts is the author of five books of essays, most recently ''Readings.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Sven Birkerts is the author of five books of essays, most recently ''Readings.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
