<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Charles Pierce, b. 1926; Crossing</title>
    <meta content="MB103204" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mallon, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pierce, Charles (1926-99)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0D91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Charles Pierce, b. 1926; Crossing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas Mallon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallon, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>crossing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Of course I'm too much! If I were too little, I wouldn't be up here!''</p>
        <p>He'd shout this in the Bette Davis portion of the act -- usually wearing his ''All About Eve'' dress -- but you had no doubt that Charles Pierce was, at that moment, allowing himself a bit of triumphal self-reference. I used to go see him down at the Ballroom in the late 80's, shortly before he ''abdicated'' -- his word -- from show business. In his 60's by then, he had already retired the strenuous bit where he would fly out over the audience on a swing, dressed up as Jeanette MacDonald and singing ''San Francisco.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Of course I'm too much! If I were too little, I wouldn't be up here!''</p>
        <p>He'd shout this in the Bette Davis portion of the act -- usually wearing his ''All About Eve'' dress -- but you had no doubt that Charles Pierce was, at that moment, allowing himself a bit of triumphal self-reference. I used to go see him down at the Ballroom in the late 80's, shortly before he ''abdicated'' -- his word -- from show business. In his 60's by then, he had already retired the strenuous bit where he would fly out over the audience on a swing, dressed up as Jeanette MacDonald and singing ''San Francisco.''</p>
        <p>Where drag was concerned, it took Pierce a while to get into the closet. He'd begun his act in a tuxedo, with just a box of props; in the 1950's, local ordinances in places like Miami Beach made him go light on the makeup and wear trousers under the gowns. By his post-Stonewall peak, Pierce's Mae West was so dolled up she'd come onstage saying, ''I couldn't decide what to wear, so I wore everything.''</p>
        <p>But even then, the outfits were never the main point. Connoisseurs of comedy realized that under the clothes was a man trying to get out, and that the man was Jack Benny, whose timing Pierce revered and eventually matched. ''Just because I'm dressed like this,'' he'd say, ''doesn't mean I can't do a man.'' Momentary silence. The twitch of an eyebrow. Delayed audience recognition. Howls.</p>
        <p>The outsize women he did -- like West and Tallulah Bankhead -- were, he realized, ''almost female impersonators themselves,'' but toward these subjects he never showed any of the envy or hostility that can be the dark trim of drag. Without the female stars who made him a ''male actress,'' he conceded, he'd still be a department-store Santa Claus in Pasadena or doing the character roles he performed at that city's Playhouse before opening at Club La Vie in Altadena in 1954. Pierce said he never wanted stardom, but he must have had some hankering for it, crossing over as he did into a world where there are no supporting parts, only divas and queens.</p>
        <p>His gay fans had only about a decade to enjoy him in complete relaxation -- that between-time when there were no more vice-squad raids and not yet any AIDS to empty the chairs. But drag itself has proved resilient, even mainstream: Lypsinka performs in clubs as Charles Pierce's most accomplished heir, kids tune in to RuPaul on TV and politicians hustle for votes at Wigstock. Watching today's drag allows straights -- those stiffed men and backlashed women -- to relax inside their sexual roles, to accept the gender divide as a joke instead of a cultural obsession.</p>
        <p>Pierce himself claimed never to have anything but fun in mind, professing amusement over how ''serious about their drag'' some performers are these days. His own ashes now reside at Forest Lawn -- a short distance from Bette Davis's remains -- and his spirit is strutting, as he liked to put it, ''one high-heeled step beyond.''</p>
        <p>Thomas Mallon is the author of the novel ''Two Moons,'' which will be published in February.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Thomas Mallon is the author of the novel ''Two Moons,'' which will be published in February.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
