<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial Property/Long Island; On Old A &amp; S Hempstead Site, a New Retail Center</title>
    <meta content="02COMM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hempstead (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Home Depot Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Old Navy Clothing Stores</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Shoprite Supermarkets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaman, Diana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spiritis, Glen L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garner, James A (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E6D71738F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial Property/Long Island; On Old A &amp; S Hempstead Site, a New Retail Center</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA SHAMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shaman, Diana</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Construction is under way for $65-million retail development at site of old Abraham &amp; Straus department store in Hempstead, LI; stores are expected to be open by summer, including Home Depot, Old Navy and Shop Rite supermarket; Glen L Spiritis, Hempstead's commissioner of community development, and Mayor James A Garner comment; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR the moment, all that can be seen of the Hub retail center, under construction here on Fulton Avenue at the former location of an Abraham &amp; Straus department store, are huge mounds of earth and the start of some foundations.</p>
        <p>But the site is already a symbol of revival in Hempstead after years of decline, which turned the village from a vibrant shopping destination into a downtown filled with vacant storefronts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR the moment, all that can be seen of the Hub retail center, under construction here on Fulton Avenue at the former location of an Abraham &amp; Straus department store, are huge mounds of earth and the start of some foundations.</p>
        <p>But the site is already a symbol of revival in Hempstead after years of decline, which turned the village from a vibrant shopping destination into a downtown filled with vacant storefronts.</p>
        <p>The $65-million development, which will occupy 42 acres in the heart of downtown, has been approved for 410,000 square feet of space. Construction of the first phase, with 250,000 square feet of space plus open parking, is already under way on 30 acres. All except 5,000 square feet has already been rented. Stores are expected to open by summer, among them a 135,000-square-foot Home Depot, a 25,000-square-foot Old Navy department store and a 65,000-square-foot Shop Rite supermarket. There will be parking for 1,262 cars.</p>
        <p>''National tenants are coming back to Hempstead because we can offer them something of substance and size to do business in,'' said Wilbur F. Breslin, president of Breslin Realty Development Corporation of Garden City, which is building the complex in partnership with a Westport, Conn., developer, Starwood-Ceruzzi. If land parcels are added, the Hub could grow to occupy one million square feet within five years, Mr. Breslin said.</p>
        <p>The 30-acre site, bordered by Fulton, Front Street, Cathedral Avenue and High Street, once held a 520,000-square-foot A &amp; S store, which closed in 1992 and moved to the Roosevelt Field shopping mall in Garden City.</p>
        <p>In that year, Federated Department Stores, the parent company of A &amp; S, had just emerged from bankruptcy protection. Under a reorganization plan it had begun selling some of its properties, including the Hempstead store.</p>
        <p>Breslin Realty wanted to redevelop the site in 1994, but lost its anchor tenant, Bradlees, when the department store chain declared bankruptcy in 1995. A subsequent deal with Federated, negotiated by a partnership of RD Management of Manhattan and Basser-Kaufman of Lawrence, also fell through when its anchor tenant, Lowe's Companies, of North Wilkesboro, N.C., pulled out. Breslin Realty came back to the table, this time with Starwood-Ceruzzi as its partner, and bought the site in 1998, demolishing the vacant department store building last year.</p>
        <p>By naming the shopping center the Hub, the developers adopted the term used for the village itself, which is a terminus for 31 bus lines, including three interstate lines, and has a Long Island Rail Road station. At one time, major retailers clustered in Hempstead included Sears, Arnold Constable, Lane Bryant, Florsheim Shoes and TSS-Seedman, a department store. Smaller retailers thrived on the crowds that the large stores brought in.</p>
        <p>''You couldn't walk down the sidewalks because they were so crowded,'' said R. Alvina Gray, a longtime village resident and deputy commissioner of the village's Community Development Agency.</p>
        <p>But with the arrival in the 1960's of Roosevelt Field and the Green Acres Mall in Valley Stream, with their ample parking and indoor amenities, Hempstead lost its appeal to shoppers. Retailers began moving out.</p>
        <p>''In 1989 everyone wanted to jump ship because they saw nothing going for the village,'' said Mayor James A. Garner. ''But we took an aggressive approach and put together a master plan to show us where we came from and where we were going.''</p>
        <p>Completed in 1993 by Saccardi &amp; Schiff, land planners in White Plains, the master plan has served as the road map for the revitalization that is now taking place, the mayor said.</p>
        <p>THE Metropolitan Suburban Bus Authority, since renamed Long Island Bus, built an $8-million 22-bay terminal between Jackson and Columbia Streets in 1993, and now a new Long Island Rail Road station is being built beside it at a cost of $22 million. The old bus terminal, which is owned by Nassau County, has been renovated to house offices and stores.</p>
        <p>Office developers have also begun seeing opportunities in Hempstead. ''We now own the two largest buildings in Hempstead,'' said Joel Hoffman, who, with a partner, Mitchell Wolff, bought the 130,000-square-foot building at 50 Clinton Street and another at 175 Fulton Avenue, which has 200,000 square feet of space, in the early 90's. They invested $3 million in the two properties, which were both rundown and almost 40 percent empty. They are now fully occupied, Mr. Hoffman said. Tenants include the State Workers' Compensation Board and the State Department of Taxation and Finance. Government agencies now represent the village's main employment base, providing jobs for about half of the 150,000 commuters who arrive daily.</p>
        <p>The original 21-acre A &amp; S site has grown through the addition of parcels bought by private parties and properties acquired by the village under its powers of eminent domain and resold to the developers. The village also donated about two acres of land.</p>
        <p>''Rather than compete with malls, we've brought the mall to downtown Hempstead,'' said Glen L. Spiritis, the village's Commissioner of Community Development.</p>
        <p>Another new shopping strip, called Hempstead Commons, opened on Peninsula Boulevard two blocks east of the Hub site last March. It was built by the RD Management and Basser-Kaufman partnership.</p>
        <p>That nine-acre property had also lain fallow for years following the closing in 1989 of the 250,000-square-foot TSS-Seedman store. The 110,000-square-foot shopping strip contains a Staples office supply store and a Pep Boys automotive center, among other retailers.</p>
        <p>''The new stores are doing unbelievably well,'' said Marc Kemp, one of the Basser-Kaufman principals.</p>
        <p>The arrival of the Hub will only enhance Hempstead Commons, he added, because it will bring new retail tenants to the area, ''and that will be our best advertisement that Hempstead is a good place to do business in.''</p>
        <p>The village has moved revitalization forward by being ''developer-friendly,'' expediting approvals so that projects can get started within a few months, Mr. Spiritis said.</p>
        <p>Since 1990, $170 million in federal and state loans and grants have been allocated to various development projects, he added.  The public funds have been leveraged by $76 million in private investment. A $20 million federal loan, for example, is being used by the Hub developers for acquisition and construction costs.</p>
        <p>Most important, retailers say they are once again viewing Hempstead, with its central location, large population of 50,000 and public transportation network, as a desirable place to be.</p>
        <p>''The Hempstead demographics are very good,'' said Pat Smith, real estate manager for Home Depot, ''and it's a market we're not serving right now.'' He added that the company's two stores closest to Hempstead, in East Meadow and Elmont, ''are extremely busy, and we wanted to take some of the pressure off those.'' The Hempstead store is expected to employ up to 300 people full and part time.</p>
        <p>Home Depot, the Atlanta-based home improvement store, already has 13 stores on Long Island. The Hempstead store will be its sixth in Nassau, not counting an Expo design center in Westbury.</p>
        <p>James A. Toopes, vice chairman of Big V Supermarkets of Florida, N.Y., which will operate the Shop Rite at the Hub, was equally enthusiastic.</p>
        <p>''It is an outstanding site,'' Mr. Toopes said, ''and I feel that the developer has put together a very powerful combination of retail tenants. This center should bring people back into the area and help resurrect Hempstead's reputation of years past.''</p>
        <p>The Hempstead store will be Big V's first on Long Island. Shop Rite, a trademarked name, is operated by different entities. In addition to traditional delicatessen, bakery and grocery items, the store will have general department store merchandise like electronics, Mr. Toopes said.</p>
        <p>Emboldened by what it perceives to be a thriving future, and with huge sales tax revenue at stake once the Hub opens for business, the 357-year-old village is moving forward with plans to incorporate as a city. Legislation is being drafted for submission to the State Legislature in March. It must pass both houses and be signed by Gov. George E. Pataki. Then the measure will be placed on the ballot for a local voter referendum.</p>
        <p>At the moment, all sales tax revenue goes to the town of Hempstead. If the village of Hempstead were a city, its share of sales taxes could reach $10 million a year, Mr. Spiritis said, further enhancing the growing tax base.</p>
        <p>''Hempstead will never be what it was,'' he added, ''because it's going to be a lot better.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
