<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Beat Poet Behind the Candy Counter</title>
    <meta content="02BAYO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POETRY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsberg, Allen (1926-97)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silverman, Herschel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nash, Margo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EEDF1438F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Beat Poet Behind the Candy Counter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO NASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nash, Margo</byline>
      <dateline>BAYONNE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Herschel Silverman, native of Bayonne, NJ, who owns local candy store and writes poetry; was member of Beat Generation and friend of Allen Ginsberg; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oh Bayonne, you will shine once again as  with diamonds.  from ''O, Bayonne on Approaching the Millennium'' by Herschel Silverman</p>
        <p>IN November, an anthology called ''The Outlaw Bible of American Poetry'' was published by Thunder's Mouth Press. It includes Allen Ginsberg, Diane diPrima, Bob Dylan, Woody Guthrie, Amiri Baraka, William Carlos Williams and Herschel Silverman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oh Bayonne, you will shine once again as  with diamonds.  from ''O, Bayonne on Approaching the Millennium'' by Herschel Silverman</p>
        <p>IN November, an anthology called ''The Outlaw Bible of American Poetry'' was published by Thunder's Mouth Press. It includes Allen Ginsberg, Diane diPrima, Bob Dylan, Woody Guthrie, Amiri Baraka, William Carlos Williams and Herschel Silverman.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Silverman is less known than the others, he has been long known in his native Bayonne. In 1957, as the owner of a candy store here, Mr. Silverman wrote to  Allen Ginsberg inviting him to come over, drink malteds and talk about poetry. Mr. Silverman, who also wrote poetry, had been stirred by reports of poets with knapsacks abroad in the land. He longed to be among them, but had a wife and two children to support. Ginsberg wrote back saying he was leaving for Europe but would drop by if he had time. He kept his promise 22 years later. In the meantime the two men became friends.</p>
        <p>They corresponded while Ginsberg was in Europe, and Mr. Silverman sent along of his poems and Mr. Ginsberg gave him some pointers. Writing from Paris in 1958 the poet remonstrated:</p>
        <p>Silverman Silverman, what are you writing</p>
        <p>me mad letters full of extravagant neon</p>
        <p>imagery in long versicles like hiccups</p>
        <p>In another letter Ginsberg berated him for ''Beatnick Schmaltz'' but also praised him for ''soulful perception of life.'' And in a lyric poem of his own, ''Television Was a Baby Crawling Toward That Death Chamber,'' Ginsberg called Mr. Silverman ''a candy store emperor who dreams of telling the truth.''</p>
        <p>The candy store, across the street from Bayonne High School, was called Hersch's Beehive. All the students would come over, including the athletes and cheerleaders. Mr. Silverman in blue apron would give pep talks, go to games and post game schedules and scores in the store. He counseled students and turned them onto the jazz that was always on his radio.</p>
        <p>He wrote about one of students, Stanley Kopcinski, in a poem, ''I'll Weep for You.''  ''He was a student in the high school who used to come in my store,'' Mr. Silverman said. ''One time he was going to his high school prom and came in all dressed up in his tuxedo. Not long after, he went into the marines and was the first Bayonne guy who got killed in the war.''</p>
        <p>Ginsberg, after he returned from Europe, introduced Mr. Silverman to the poets in his circle. Mr. Silverman was dazzled: ''These must be Giant Creative Spirits moved into man here, moving man to shine, come out of moon to revel, unwind mind,'' Mr. Silverman wrote in a prose poem called ''High on the Beats.''</p>
        <p>Back in Bayonne at night the candy store owner would write hundreds of poems.  Soon they were being published and would eventually fill up 20 collections. Mr. Silverman also got a grant from the New Jersey State Council on the Arts to put together a book of the letters he and Ginsberg had exchanged. In 1986, after 34 years at the Beehive, Mr. Silverman retired.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silverman's wife, Laura, died in 1988. After that he lived the poet's life full time, traveling around the country for poetry readings, editing literary journals and helping others publish their poetry. In 1998 he was asked to read a poem at the inauguration of the Bayonne mayor, Joseph V. Doria Jr.</p>
        <p>These days Mr. Silverman, 73, is still reading, writing and publishing.</p>
        <p>Dan Shot, the Hoboken-based poet and publisher of Long Shot, an arts and literacy magazine, said of Mr. Silverman: ''I think of Hersch as the godfather of Hudson County poetry because there are few poets from this part of New Jersey whose lives Hersch hasn't touched. Hersch has been a role model for me. He spent most of his life just working, getting up at 5:30 in the morning to open up his candy store, to make money to support his family. but he never lost sight of what he wanted, which is to be a poet.''</p>
        <p>In the new poetry anthology is Mr. Silverman's account of how he met Mr. Ginsberg and other Beat poets. Next to his piece is one by Mr. Ginsberg called ''Homage to Hersch.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ginsberg wrote: ''his sincerity &amp; the pleasure his life's taken in the poetry world encourages us all to realize that poetry does serve humankind well in giving pleasure &amp; empowerment to people of sensitive spirit, domestic folk.''</p>
        <p>POETRY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
