<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>13,000 Hellos So Far, Only 987,000 to Go</title>
    <meta content="02HELL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greetings</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dashow, Carrie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roe, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DB1538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>13,000 Hellos So Far, Only 987,000 to Go</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM ROE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roe, Tom</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carrie Dashow, video artist who lives in Brooklyn, is 13,000 greetings into a project to greet 1 million people, which should take her at least another 70 years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On any given day in New York City, it's possible to say ''hello'' to hundreds of people, or none at all. Carrie Dashow is one New Yorker who knows exactly how many people she greets each day.</p>
        <p>Since last January, Ms. Dashow,  28, a video artist who lives in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, has clicked a small counter more than 13,000 times, once for each person she has greeted. ''People spend more time'' with images on television and in the movies ''than with real people,'' she said. ''I wanted to counteract those 'experiences' with actual two-way communication.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On any given day in New York City, it's possible to say ''hello'' to hundreds of people, or none at all. Carrie Dashow is one New Yorker who knows exactly how many people she greets each day.</p>
        <p>Since last January, Ms. Dashow,  28, a video artist who lives in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, has clicked a small counter more than 13,000 times, once for each person she has greeted. ''People spend more time'' with images on television and in the movies ''than with real people,'' she said. ''I wanted to counteract those 'experiences' with actual two-way communication.''</p>
        <p>Her goal is greeting one million people, and at the rate she's going it will take at least 70 more years. She's finding more efficient ways to initiate contact with strangers, though, as she continues. As an invited greeter at the Limelight one evening this fall, she said hello to 700 clubgoers. On another day, she hailed 2,200 commuters at Penn Station in just 45 minutes. During the photography session for this article, she greeted more than 400 people in Times Square one morning.</p>
        <p>Mostly, though, she attempts to make eye contact with passers-by on  the street, so she can say hello during her everyday life. ''It's a barrier that I don't see too many other people crossing that often,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dashow says that on days when she tries to say ''hi'' to people,  many of them greet her first, perhaps, she suspects, because she radiates receptivity. She has  discovered that she is  less approachable in black. Light colors and pink lipstick work best.  When she travels, she finds that Southern hospitality still exists and that San Francisco is a very friendly town. And in New York, she has  been asked out on several dates.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dashow, a curator of a roving experimental video series  called Video Lounge who teaches video in after-school programs in the city, says she picked her arbitrary goal partly because ''you have to go on television to reach a million people'' all at once.  Instead, she's trying to reach a million people one at a time.</p>
        <p>''I have no idea what meeting a million people feels like,'' she says of the task she has set up for herself.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sashow, who is Jewish, says she has tried to relate that million-person figure to the six million who died in the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>One person she greeted was Seth Kramer, another 28-year-old video artist who is engaged in a similar project and has also been thinking about the Holocaust as he counts. Since 1994, Mr. Kramer has counted more than 2.6 million grains of rice, each of which he then saves. His goal is six million, one for each Holocaust victim. At top speed, Mr. Kramer can count 1,000 grains in 10 minutes, much faster than Ms. Dashow's under-50-a-day pace. Of course, saying hello to people takes a lot longer than counting rice. If he were to devote two hours a day to counting, Mr. Kramer would reach his goal in less than a year, while he believes Ms. Dashow can never reach hers.</p>
        <p>''There's no way she could ever count six million people,'' he said.  ''She'd have to live to be 600 years old.''</p>
        <p>TOM ROE</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
