<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Willie Morris, b. 1934; Southern Manners</title>
    <meta content="MB104357" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="45" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Willie (1934-99)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFD91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Willie Morris, b. 1934; Southern Manners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Ford</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ford, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Ford article recalls dinner with writer Willie Morris, who died in 1999; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Back in 1968, when I was a kid writer and Willie Morris was the famous author of ''North Toward Home'' and the highly public editor of Harper's Magazine, I sent him short stories. We were Mississippians, though not acquainted. And my stories would always bounce back with a typed note: this or that was ''interesting''; ''clearly'' I possessed a writerly ''talent.'' This one wasn't ''right for'' Harper's but ''definitely'' would be publishable elsewhere. A good quarterly maybe. ''Do try us again. . . . '' Sincerely, Willie Morris.</p>
        <p>Not long after 1968, Willie left Harper's via a noisy turmoil. For a while he stayed up North, kicked around New York and the Hamptons, continued writing provoking books -- Yazoo,'' ''Good Old Boy,'' ''The Last of the Southern Girls.'' Eventually, in 1980, he removed to Mississippi, to teach journalism at Ole Miss, and established himself not merely as the prodigal son come home, but as a very good son: a deep Southerner who adored Mississippi, who was consummately literate, kept up with the buzz from New York, liked to drink and smoke and carry on all night, who would be nice to your grandmother -- was perhaps even related to your grandmother -- yet who had his head on straight about race, the past, about what was worth preserving in the state's troubled character and how it and we fitted into the larger Republic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Back in 1968, when I was a kid writer and Willie Morris was the famous author of ''North Toward Home'' and the highly public editor of Harper's Magazine, I sent him short stories. We were Mississippians, though not acquainted. And my stories would always bounce back with a typed note: this or that was ''interesting''; ''clearly'' I possessed a writerly ''talent.'' This one wasn't ''right for'' Harper's but ''definitely'' would be publishable elsewhere. A good quarterly maybe. ''Do try us again. . . . '' Sincerely, Willie Morris.</p>
        <p>Not long after 1968, Willie left Harper's via a noisy turmoil. For a while he stayed up North, kicked around New York and the Hamptons, continued writing provoking books -- Yazoo,'' ''Good Old Boy,'' ''The Last of the Southern Girls.'' Eventually, in 1980, he removed to Mississippi, to teach journalism at Ole Miss, and established himself not merely as the prodigal son come home, but as a very good son: a deep Southerner who adored Mississippi, who was consummately literate, kept up with the buzz from New York, liked to drink and smoke and carry on all night, who would be nice to your grandmother -- was perhaps even related to your grandmother -- yet who had his head on straight about race, the past, about what was worth preserving in the state's troubled character and how it and we fitted into the larger Republic.</p>
        <p>In 1985, my wife and I were living near Clarksdale, Miss., in an old plantation headquarters I had rashly purchased. We called Willie, whom we really only barely knew, and asked him if he'd like to drive over and eat dinner with us and our friend the editor Pat Towers.</p>
        <p>Willie, reachable at home by a coded phone ring, and only after 5 p.m. (when he arose), surprisingly accepted. And in a week he arrived at our house alone and looking a way I would often afterward see him: he looked feverish, as if his mind were athrum. He was dressed in standard Southerner get-up: rumpled chinos, scuffed loafers, an oxford-cloth shirt with some kind of striped tie and a slightly wrinkled tweedy jacket. It was May and already ridiculously humid. We were all sweating. But Willie seemed to endure it even less well than the rest of us. There was a good deal of Willie, and his clothes seemed somehow to rest heavy upon him.</p>
        <p>And of course he was completely charming, completely at ease, completely voluble. He knew that Governor Alcorn had built my house for his son Milton; knew what General Forrest had done in the neighborhood in 1863; knew that Nazi prisoners had poured our concrete swimming pool back in the 40's. He talked about William Styron, Robert Lowell, James Jones, Norman Mailer, noted that he'd bought his shoes in Charlie Conerly's shoe store in Clarksdale. We were very happy he was there. He was a celebrity, and in some way his large presence authenticated us.</p>
        <p>When it was time for dinner, we sat down with a view of the evening cotton fields, and I had by then taken the trouble to spread all of my nearly 20-year-old rejection notices onto Willie's empty plate. I knew he did not associate me then with me back then. But Willie was a famous joke-meister and putter-onner, and I meant by drawing a connection between the two of us then and now to amuse him. It was another authenticating gesture. Southerners are preoccupied by them.</p>
        <p>Willie, I think, understood all of this small complexity. In any case, he knew what to do. He read the notices -- aloud, at the table, with a high, theatrical judiciousness: ''Ah, yes,'' he intoned, his eyes scanning the small type, holding the letter delicately up like a rare document. ''I remember this story. Great mistake not taking it. The magazine has yet to recover. Hmm. Here, astonishingly, is another one I let slip through my fingers. Genius. And at such an early age. It's actually a moment in history that we can all be eating dinner here tonight in the Mississippi Delta. . . . '' He quickly did two more, each with faultless timing, then put the subject away for good, and we ate dinner.</p>
        <p>But in its lenience and sweet ardor it was a characteristic gesture. Willie Morris was a man who knew how to act -- a dying art in our day. Doing so required him not only to look for the good in others but also to search for it diligently in himself, and to put both into play. He did it among near strangers that evening, and he did it as long as I knew him. He was a smart, decent, mirthful, valuable man, and in Mississippi, he was larger than life, though, persuasively, never better than life. For us, he was a public man in the best sense, for he was almost precisely as he purported to be, while being just as you hoped he would be. At his funeral in the Methodist church in Yazoo City last August, when it came the moment of closing, the Rev. Will Campbell asked us all to stand up, and for just this once not to sing a hymn or speak a prayer, but to give Willie a great round of applause. And because we knew Willie deserved it, we did.</p>
        <p>Richard Ford is a novelist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard Ford is a novelist.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
