<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Newcomer That Offers Lots to Celebrate</title>
    <meta content="02DINE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blake's (Woodmere, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDC1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Newcomer That Offers Lots to Celebrate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Blake's, restaurant in Woodmere, LI; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RESIDENTS of Woodmere have an added reason to celebrate this new year:  Blake's has opened in their town. As tablemates from nearby Lawrence remarked, ''The Five Towns have nothing like this.''</p>
        <p>Blake's is the baby of Blake Verity, one of the Island's most talented chefs. He was chief toque at Panama Hatties for seven years, when that superior restaurant was rising to culinary fame. He is now fulfilling the dream of many a chef: he has a place of his own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RESIDENTS of Woodmere have an added reason to celebrate this new year:  Blake's has opened in their town. As tablemates from nearby Lawrence remarked, ''The Five Towns have nothing like this.''</p>
        <p>Blake's is the baby of Blake Verity, one of the Island's most talented chefs. He was chief toque at Panama Hatties for seven years, when that superior restaurant was rising to culinary fame. He is now fulfilling the dream of many a chef: he has a place of his own.</p>
        <p>The sign in the window proclaims Blake's Bistro and much of the food, like the roast chicken and the braised short ribs, is squarely in the casual bistro mold. The decor, however, is a bit more formal. The small room is carpeted and the walls are sage green. Those walls hold a pleasing assembly of pictures, votive candles, vines and wrought iron. Expect cafe curtains and varied seating: wicker basket chairs, straight black metal ones and a wraparound, overstuffed banquette in the front window.</p>
        <p>Service was a bit shaky on my first visit. There was no host or hostess at the reservations desk, and the harried waiters seemed to be rushing in other directions. That night, Mrs. Verity arrived in the middle of the evening, carrying her young baby.  After one look at the crowded room, she deposited the child with a sitter and pitched headlong into the dining room, seating guests and helping serve.</p>
        <p>On return visits on very busy weekend nights, the restaurant was ready for the crowds and handled them beautifully.</p>
        <p>Blake's is about food, good food.  One peek at the bread basket confirms it. The charming metal container, decorated with fresh thyme and slim baby carrots, also holds wonderful homemade rolls. The assortment varies from night to night and might include raisin-studded scones, corn bread, focaccia, cinnamon-raisin rolls, biscuits and spiral dinner rolls.</p>
        <p>On slack nights, the chef may send out a complimentary tidbit: a dab of meltingly soft lamb shank crowned with baby greens one evening, a paper-thin serving of buffalo atop a slice of tomato another.</p>
        <p>My favorite appetizer is the seared diver scallop Napoleon, a layering of the luscious seafood with marinated portobello mushrooms and crisp triangles made from won-ton wrappers. The dish resonated with the ginger-sesame tastes of Asia. Another prime pick is the exemplary jumbo crab cake, which has little filler and lots of flavor. It arrives on a warm endive salad with a topper of mache.</p>
        <p>Speaking of salad, the baby field greens in a sparkling lemon-herb vinaigrette are simple and delicious.  The Caesar also made points with its eye-catching, crisp rye toast molded into a towering basket.</p>
        <p>Be sure to try the ravioli filled with roasted artichokes white beans and crowned with a half lobster tail. The pasta pockets are sauced with a melange of finely minced vegetables.  Two also-rans were the garlic-crusted shrimp accompanied by sweet potato gnocchi, which were a tad heavy, and smoked salmon, which was sliced a bit too thickly.</p>
        <p>One other minor quibble: the Long Island bouillabaisse harbored a few chewy clams in an otherwise fine seafood medley. The saffron-tomato-fennel broth was terrific, as was the luscious toast spread with aioli.</p>
        <p>Nearly every main course is top of the line; take your pick. The fall-away-tender short ribs braised in red wine got high marks, as did the moist roast chicken, the flavorful filet mignon, the double-cut pork chop mated with red cabbage and the cooked-to-order rack of lamb artfully crisscrossed on an autumn vegetable ratatouille and crisp polenta-goat cheese cake.</p>
        <p>Two fish that scored were the halibut set atop Israeli couscous in a shiitake mushroom-ginger-kaffer lime nage, and beautifully flaky salmon in a Pommery mustard sauce.</p>
        <p>Mr. Verity serves as his own pastry chef, and his creations are spectacularly plated treats. All were crowd pleasers, but my favorites were the intense lemon tartlette (lemon cake topped with an airy lemon souffle) and the double chocolate-raspberry bombe. The latter starred chocolate mousse robed in dark chocolate and laced with raspberry jam.</p>
        <p>Blake's  1066 Broadway, Woodmere, (516) 569-2259.  Excellent</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE Storefront bistro with country charm.</p>
        <p>SERVICE A bit shaky at first. Improved with every visit.</p>
        <p>SOUND LEVEL A tad loud when restaurant is full.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES Scallop Napoleon, crab cake, Caesar salad, ravioli, field green salad, short ribs, roast chicken, pork chop, filet mignon, rack of lamb, halibut, salmon, all desserts.</p>
        <p>WINE LIST A small number of familiar names, mainly from popular, commercial, mass-producing West Coast vineyards.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE Appetizers $6 to $10; entrees $17 to $22; desserts $8.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS All the majors.</p>
        <p>HOURS 5:30 to 10 p.m. Tuesday through Sunday.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS A must.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY One step at entrance.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
