<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At-Home Fathers Step Out To Find They Are Not Alone</title>
    <meta content="02DADS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newsletters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marin, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newsletters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DF1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At-Home Fathers Step Out To Find They Are Not Alone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK MARIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marin, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>DES PLAINES, Ill.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>At-Home Dads Convention in Des Plaines, Ill, draws about 85 men from 20 states who by choice or economic necessity are normally home changing diapers while their wives act as breadwinners; stay-at-home fathers are growing in number and gaining acceptance, even approval, but they still suffer from isolation, which manifests itself in loneliness, depression, stir-craziness and weight gain; convention, as well as Web sites, newsletters and play groups catering to men whose wives work, seek to break down that isolation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a gray lecture hall in the Oakton Community College, a group of middle-aged men were shouting affirmations.</p>
        <p>''Who ARE you?'' their cheerleader, Hogan Hilling, demanded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a gray lecture hall in the Oakton Community College, a group of middle-aged men were shouting affirmations.</p>
        <p>''Who ARE you?'' their cheerleader, Hogan Hilling, demanded.</p>
        <p>''Proud dads!'' they replied.</p>
        <p>''What time is it?''</p>
        <p>''It's DAD time!''</p>
        <p>To further raise the room's esteem, Mr. Hilling instructed the men to raise one hand in the air, then bring it down into a clenched fist with a rousing ''Yes!''</p>
        <p>The ''Yes!'' fist pump was the support-group chant of choice at the recent At-Home Dads Convention in this Chicago suburb. A day of seminars on topics like ''At-Home Daddying . . . What Are Our Issues?'' and ''The Anatomy of a Working Mom's Brain'' drew about 85 men from 20 states. Many of the attendees, a small group with a broad constituency, run Web sites, newsletters and play groups that cater to men whose wives bring home the reduced-fat bacon.</p>
        <p>No longer the butt of demeaning ''Mr. Mom'' jokes, these men have become familiar figures at playgrounds and P.T.A. meetings. They have ''come out of the pantry,'' some of them like to say, with a newly emboldened attitude. Their nascent men's movement comes with a new idea of masculinity: Ironing John. But they still have issues.</p>
        <p>Dozens of virtual sweatlodges or kaffeeklatsches have sprung up for the men who by choice or economic necessity find themselves on the daddy track. Among them are MrMomz.com, Athomedad.com and the Parent Soup section of America Online. Here they can discuss everything from diaper disasters to feelings of isolation. On Slowlane.com, the slickest and most complete of the sites, the slogan is, ''You are not alone.''</p>
        <p>At the convention, men who had known each other only by e-mail met  for the first time. Attendance has increased from 35 in the group's first year in 1996 and is down from 100 in 1998. Christopher Coby, 35, said connecting with other fathers like him through the Internet had pulled him out of his version of postpartum funk.</p>
        <p>''I had two kids in diapers at once and I was fried!'' said Mr. Coby, who lives in Wake Forest, N.C. ''I was online and I kind of came out out of lurk mode and got on a couple of lists.''</p>
        <p>That saved him, he said: ''I came here to meet the guys face to face and just say thanks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coby is 6-foot-2, weighs 215 pounds and is a former tank commander in the Army reserves. He quit teaching elementary school after his son was born because his wife, who works for a consulting firm, had a higher salary and better benefits.</p>
        <p>He proudly wears an apron that his wife gave him last Father's Day that says, ''Women want me. Martha Stewart fears me.''</p>
        <p>How many Chris Cobys are out there is unclear. The Census Bureau's last survey on the subject, in 1993, reported that 1.9 million unemployed men were the primary caregivers of children up to 14 years old -- down from a recession high of more than 2 million in 1991. A Bureau of Labor Statistics study released in September showed that, from 1991 to 1996, unemployed men ages 25 to 54 who chose not to look for work because of ''home responsibilities'' rose to 8.4 percent from 4.6 percent.</p>
        <p>That change is significant, experts say, because men have traditionally been unwilling to admit household duties as the reason for their unemployment.</p>
        <p>James Levine, director of the Fatherhood Project at the Families and Work Institute in New York, said, ''The number of men at home taking care of their kids is the best-kept secret in American child care.'' Many of them, he said, are blue collar: ''cops and firemen working night shifts while their wives work days.'' Such men are not unemployed and may not consider themselves stay-at-home fathers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levine believes there has been a ''quantum leap'' in the numbers of stay-at-home fathers since he researched his book, ''Who Will Raise the Children? New Options for Fathers and Mothers,'' 25 years ago. ''They were really few and far between then,'' he said. ''It was considered nuts.''</p>
        <p>Still far from the norm, stay-at-home fathers are gaining acceptance. Even approval. In his new book, ''Fatherneed'' (Free Press), Dr. Kyle Pruett, a clinical professor of psychology at the Yale Child Studies Center, found slightly above-average intellectual, social and emotional development among a small group of children reared by stay-at-home fathers. He followed the families for 10 years.</p>
        <p>Among the pop-cultural barometers of shifting breadwinner roles is  a pilot to be shot this month for a mid-season sitcom called ''Daddio,'' produced by Disney for NBC, about one such man. Matt Berry, an executive producer of the show, stayed home with his children during his 15 years working nights as a stand-up comedian. He said he and his writing partner had pitched the idea to networks before, unsuccessfully because the reaction was always, ''but people won't respect him as a man,'' he said. ''And we were like, 'Why is that a tainted concept? Why can't he be a man because he decided to stay home full time with his kids?' ''</p>
        <p>Despite their growing ranks, men who stay home still face a problem well-known to women in the same position: isolation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert Frank, a psychologist who has organized these conventions for the last four years, conducted a study in 1996 of 371 fathers who identified themselves as their children's ''primary caregivers.'' Of those, 63 percent said they felt isolated, versus 37 percent of mothers in the same position.</p>
        <p>The isolation manifests itself in many ways. Loneliness, depression, stir-craziness that some men described as ''bouncing off the walls.'' And the familiar corollary of all these problems: weight gain.</p>
        <p>In a small discussion group, Vince Gratton, a former prosecutor from Pueblo, Colo., with three girls (one 9 and 3-year-old twins) said he had started working out. ''I've been weight-training for four months,'' he said. ''I can bench 265 and squat 400 and I'm going to crush the next guy who says, 'What do you do?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gratton, 56, said he had to go all the way to Chicago to find another stay-at-home dad from his hometown. ''Now I got this big guy here, who's sensitive and loving,'' Mr. Gratton said gruffly, motioning to another burly man in an aviator jacket. But no one else, he said. ''I live in a steel town where manly men do manly things.''</p>
        <p>The tables in the classroom were pushed together to encourage intimacy. Experiences of a so-called ''glass wall'' separating mothers from fathers in parks and schoolyards echoed around the room. Edward Howard, 54, said, ''I go to the playground with my son and I'm tired of being looked at as some kind of sexual pervert.''</p>
        <p>Equally frustrating as feeling frozen out for these men is being condescended to. Jim DiCenzo said the principal of his child's school in San Diego told him, ''I think it's so cute that you stay home with your kids.'' His reaction: ''I could have strangled her.''</p>
        <p>Still, some of them said, better to drive to a distant Burger King for a play date with another stay-at-home father than endure the awkwardness or boredom of the company of women. One man, who asked not to be named, said, ''I don't want to sit around and talk for an hour about shopping or listening to them complain about their husbands.''</p>
        <p>The occasional retrograde comment aside, most of the convention's attendees regard themselves as fully evolved males, in touch with their nurturing sides.</p>
        <p>After screening his 22-minute documentary film ''Homedaddy,'' Kent Ayyildiz told his rapt audience, ''The gains women have made in the workplace should be balanced by men making the same gains in the house.'' As the closing credits rolled, the audience whooped its approval and gave the ponytailed Mr. Ayyildiz a standing ovation. They cheered again when he said he no longer identified himself as a filmmaker who also happens to stay home with his child, but as a ''homedaddy'' who also happens to make films.</p>
        <p>Even so, Mr. Ayyildiz admitted to a certain ambivalance about putting child rearing first. ''These are the growing years of my career,'' he said. ''At the same time, I get one chance with my son.''</p>
        <p>Family finances compelled most of these men to stay home. Discovering that they enjoy it has kept many of them there in flusher economic times.</p>
        <p>Chris Cooper, who in 1998 published a compendium of essays called ''The At-Home Dad Handbook,'' said he was working at Athlete's Foot in Atlanta and his wife at United Parcel Service when they had their first child.</p>
        <p>''We didn't want to go the day care route and with her having the better salary potential, we decided I'd quit work and stay home,'' said Mr. Cooper, who now has two children, ages 6 and 5, and lives in St. Paul. In 1997, he started a group called Dad-to-Dad, which has 30 chapters nationwide.</p>
        <p>''Now that I can be home with the kids, I look at things differently from when I was single or just married,'' he said. ''Then I was career-driven and work meant pretty much everything to me. Now my kids are my life and raising them is what I consider my 'career.' ''</p>
        <p>Ed Steffek, a former math teacher, said he had listed ''homemaker'' as his profession on his daughter's birth certificate.</p>
        <p>The commitment to being a good parent outweighed other forms of housework for many men at the convention. Peter Baylies, publisher of the At-Home Dad newsletter and Web site, recalled the adjustment when he and his wife traded places.</p>
        <p>''After a couple of months she said, 'When are you gonna clean the bathroom?' I was humiliated. I didn't care if the bathroom was clean. It didn't make any difference to me.''</p>
        <p>Peter Hoh, husband of a nurse in St. Paul, expressed a similar attitude toward what used to be called women's work. ''People say, 'Your wife works. You stay home. Who cleans the house?' And the answer, when people open the door, is clearly, 'Nobody!' ''</p>
        <p>The cleaning issue came up in Joanne Massey's seminar, ''The Anatomy of a Working Woman's Mom.'' Her husband, Jay Massey, runs Slowlane.com and a Web site design company from their house in Pensacola, Fla. That makes him a ''work-at-home dad,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Massey, the only woman participating in the convention, told the audience that her husband's work day begins when hers ends. As a result, ''Mom has to clean up when I come home,'' she said. ''That was hard to adjust to.''</p>
        <p>She also said when she had asked their 5-year-old son what he wanted to be when he grows up, he said, ''I want to be an at-home dad.'' That got a big, fist-pumping ''Yes!''</p>
        <p>In defense of their lifestyle choice, the at-home fathers often point out that before the industrial revolution, children were accustomed to having their fathers around, on the farm or in the blacksmith shop.</p>
        <p>''Ten years ago, it was considered freakish,'' said Mr. Baylies, looking around at the clusters of conventioneers gathered for a low-cal lunch of pasta and salad. ''You'll know that stay-at-home dads are totally accepted when we don't have to do this.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
