<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dried Beans Provide Hearty Cold-Weather Dishes</title>
    <meta content="WCFOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabricant, Florence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DB1538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dried Beans Provide Hearty Cold-Weather Dishes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabricant, Florence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Food column offers recipes using beans (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is time to get back to basics. Hearty cold-weather dishes can now replace the elegant tidbits or rarefied luxuries that dressed up dining over the last few celebratory weeks.</p>
        <p>For millennia, long before the last one, dried beans have been a cold-weather staple to nourish people the world over. Here are three recipes that suit the season. One is a sturdy soup, another a variation on macaroni and cheese, and the third is a meat and bean sauce for pasta.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is time to get back to basics. Hearty cold-weather dishes can now replace the elegant tidbits or rarefied luxuries that dressed up dining over the last few celebratory weeks.</p>
        <p>For millennia, long before the last one, dried beans have been a cold-weather staple to nourish people the world over. Here are three recipes that suit the season. One is a sturdy soup, another a variation on macaroni and cheese, and the third is a meat and bean sauce for pasta.</p>
        <p>If the dried beans you buy are reliably fresh, that is, they have not been gathering dust on the grocery shelf -- or in your pantry -- for the last year, presoaking for at least four hours or overnight before cooking is not necessary.</p>
        <p>And for a real shortcut, to cut at least an hour from the preparation time, drained canned limas, white beans or kidney beans can be substituted. Use triple the amount of canned beans to replace the dried and add them when the cooked beans are to be combined with the other ingredients.</p>
        <p>Smoked Trout And Lima Bean Chowder  Total time: 1 1/2 hours plus soaking if desired</p>
        <p>2/3 cup dried lima beans, soaked if desired</p>
        <p>1 ounce slab bacon, diced</p>
        <p>2 leeks, rinsed, trimmed and finely chopped (white part only)</p>
        <p>1 pound boiling potatoes, peeled and diced</p>
        <p>3 1/2 cups low-fat milk</p>
        <p>6 ounces skinless, boneless smoked trout</p>
        <p>1/3 cup heavy cream</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons minced chives.</p>
        <p>1. Put beans in saucepan, add water to depth of two inches and simmer, partly covered, about an hour, until nearly tender. Skim surface as needed. Drain beans and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Cook bacon in a heavy saucepan until fat starts to render. Add leeks. Continue cooking until leeks are tender and turn golden. Add potatoes and two cups milk. Simmer about 30 minutes, until the potatoes are tender. Roughly mash with a fork, leaving some pieces. Add remaining milk and drained beans and simmer 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Break trout in chunks and add it, along with cream. Bring to a simmer and season to taste with salt and pepper. Serve with a sprinkling of chives on each portion.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Macaroni and Beans  Total time: 2 hours plus soaking if desired</p>
        <p>3/4 cup Great Northern beans, soaked if desired</p>
        <p>3/4 cup elbow macaroni</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon butter</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons dry bread crumbs</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>1/2 cup chopped onion</p>
        <p>1 jalapeno pepper, seeded and finely minced</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon ground cumin</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>2 eggs, beaten</p>
        <p>1 1/2 cups half-and-half</p>
        <p>1/3 cup shredded Monterey Jack cheese.</p>
        <p>1. Put beans in saucepan, cover with water to depth of two inches and simmer partially covered, until beans are tender, about 50 minutes if soaked, an hour and 15 minutes if unsoaked. Skim any foam from the surface. Drain beans.</p>
        <p>2. While beans are cooking, bring another saucepan of salted water to a boil, add macaroni and cook until al dente, about eight minutes. Drain well.</p>
        <p>3. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Use half the butter to grease a six-cup baking dish. Dust dish with half the bread crumbs.</p>
        <p>4. Heat oil in a skillet and saute onion and jalapeno until soft but not brown. Stir in cooked beans, macaroni and cumin. Season to taste with salt and pepper and transfer to baking dish.</p>
        <p>5. Mix the eggs and half-and-half and pour over beans and macaroni in baking dish. Sprinkle with cheese and remaining bread crumbs and dot with remaining butter.</p>
        <p>6. Put in oven and bake 40 minutes, until set and lightly browned on top. Serve hot or at room temperature.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 side-dish servings.</p>
        <p>Kidney Bean Ragu With Penne  Total Time: 2 hours plus soaking if desired</p>
        <p>1/2 cup dried kidney beans, soaked if desired</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>1 large onion, finely chopped</p>
        <p>4 large cloves garlic, minced</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon fennel seeds</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon crushed black pepper corns</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon dried oregano</p>
        <p>1/2 pound ground beef</p>
        <p>1/2 cup dry red wine</p>
        <p>2 cups finely chopped, drained canned plum tomatoes</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>1 pound penne</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons chopped flat-leaf parsley</p>
        <p>Freshly grated Parmesan.</p>
        <p>1. Put dried beans in saucepan, add water to a depth of two inches, bring to a simmer and cook, partly covered, about an hour and a half. Drain.</p>
        <p>2. Meanwhile, heat oil in a heavy saucepan. Add onion and garlic and cook over low heat until very soft but not brown. Stir in fennel seeds, peppercorns, oregano and ground beef and cook, stirring, until beef has lost pinkness and is finely broken up. Increase heat to medium and continue cooking another 10 minutes or so, until beef and onions start to brown. Stir in wine. Cook a few minutes longer, until wine has mostly evaporated. Add tomatoes, cover and cook over medium heat about 30 minutes. Season to taste with salt and pepper. Set aside.</p>
        <p>3. When beans are nearly tender, bring a large pot of salted water to a boil for penne. Add penne to pot and cook 10 to 12 minutes, until al dente.</p>
        <p>4. Fold beans into meat sauce. Bring to a slow simmer.</p>
        <p>5. Drain penne and add to sauce. Heat briefly, season to taste with salt and pepper, fold in parsley and serve, with cheese on the side.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
