<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dale Bellisfield and Noel Nowicki</title>
    <meta content="02VOWS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOWICKI, NOEL (NOEL BELLISFIELD)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BELLISFIELD, DALE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellisfield, Dale</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nowicki, Noel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brady, Lois Smith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E2D91538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dale Bellisfield and Noel Nowicki</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOIS SMITH BRADY</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vows column on wedding of Dale Bellisfield and Noel Nowicki; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DALE BELLISFIELD, a clinical herbalist, greets visitors to her home as if they are patients. ''How are you?'' she says with apparent deep concern, as if she wants to know everything from your blood pressure to your astrological sign. She offers several herbal tea concoctions asking, ''Is there any mood you'd like to encourage or change?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bellisfield, who is 51 and the herbal consultant at Hackensack Hospital in Hackensack, N.J., lives in a Tudor-style house in nearby Fair Lawn with wind chimes on the porch and cats drifting around like tumbleweed. She recently started an herbal tea and skin care business, the Fertile Hand, based in her home. She creates brews and lotions to treat everything from bee stings to bad dreams to backaches, poor circulation and broken hearts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DALE BELLISFIELD, a clinical herbalist, greets visitors to her home as if they are patients. ''How are you?'' she says with apparent deep concern, as if she wants to know everything from your blood pressure to your astrological sign. She offers several herbal tea concoctions asking, ''Is there any mood you'd like to encourage or change?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bellisfield, who is 51 and the herbal consultant at Hackensack Hospital in Hackensack, N.J., lives in a Tudor-style house in nearby Fair Lawn with wind chimes on the porch and cats drifting around like tumbleweed. She recently started an herbal tea and skin care business, the Fertile Hand, based in her home. She creates brews and lotions to treat everything from bee stings to bad dreams to backaches, poor circulation and broken hearts.</p>
        <p>She created many of her teas and cures for herself as she went through two divorces and raised her daughter, Samantha, now 12. Describing her experiences as a divorced mom, Ms. Bellisfield said: ''It's been hard, exciting, fun, complicated. I took a lot of Siberian ginseng to keep me in balance.''</p>
        <p>She says her daughter is not interested in alternative medicine. ''She doesn't do herbs,'' she said. ''Mostly she does makeup.''</p>
        <p>In the spring of 1997, a friend introduced Ms. Bellisfield to Dr. Noel Nowicki, an internist turned acupuncturist with a private practice at the Kessler Institute for Rehabilitation in East Orange, N.J. For their first date, she brought a homemade picnic including roasted chicken, pickled beets and herb cookies to his house in Upper Montclair, N.J. Even though he hates beets, the date lasted eight hours.</p>
        <p>''I thought he was really interesting, complex, extremely smart, very funny,'' Ms. Bellisfield said. ''At the end of the day, he said he was interested in me and wanted to go out. He's not shy. I said I was seeing somebody.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Nowicki, who has been divorced once and has longish hair and piercing eyes, remembered: ''Dale said she was seeing several suitors at the time. She does this ''Glass Menagerie,'' Southern-speak sometimes.''</p>
        <p>Over the next several months, he assiduously courted her. He called often; he began serving her teas to patients in his waiting room, and he even went to her house one night to help her with housework, bringing his own iron. That won her heart. ''He saw that I was overburdened with work, and he came to lighten my load, literally and figuratively,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Soon, the couple began participating in various spiritual workshops together -- they meditated, fasted, explored their dark sides and studied herbs. Dr. Nowicki and his cats began spending a lot of time at Ms. Bellisfield's house, a place he said was both neater and more artfully decorated than his. ''Her bedside table is like a tableau from Macy's windows,'' he said. ''There's Ukrainian dried eggs, her grandfather's watch, a lamp, a statue of Siva.''</p>
        <p>In January 1998, while they were at a New Year's healing workshop, he informally proposed after a day of meditation. ''Noel ended our silence by dancing around the room playing very off-key notes on this little pearly-red accordion,'' Ms. Bellisfield said. ''It was his idea of a love presentation.''</p>
        <p>Last year, he proposed more formally with Samantha present. ''That was really brave,'' Ms. Bellisfield said. ''My daughter could very easily have said, 'No way, Jose.' '' Instead, she replied, ''That would be nice.''</p>
        <p>The couple were married on Wednesday -- Dr. Nowicki's 50th birthday -- in a Cherokee wedding ceremony at the Grenville Hotel in Bay Head, N.J. In Cherokee tradition, the couple fed each other four sacred foods (berries, corn, meat and water); promised to share blankets forever and were given a long hickory stick. ''Birth, death, sadnesses and happinesses all get carved into the stick,'' said David Winston, a Cherokee medicine priest, who officiated. ''As long as the stick is intact, the marriage is intact.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
