<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Makeup That Says: Night and Day, You Are the One</title>
    <meta content="02COUN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTERINTELLIGENCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Witchel, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EED81538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1378" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Makeup That Says: Night and Day, You Are the One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Witchel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Witchel, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alex Witchel report on evening makeup that is supposed to make women look like movie stars filmed through gauzy filters (M</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SITTING near the Prescriptives counter at Bergdorf Goodman, I eyed the glowing white liquid suspiciously. ''Is this Magic?'' I asked Darac, the illusionist (read makeup artist) who goes by one name only.</p>
        <p>He nodded. ''Magic alters the reality of what you see,'' he said. ''It plays with light so it's all illusion. It's very Lucille Ball in 'Mame.' Every time she had a close-up she looked very soft, no fine lines or discoloration. Think of Magic as soft surgery. It's for people who say, 'Should I have something done?' and shouldn't, but do, and then come out looking like Mrs. Phantom of the Opera. Which we don't enjoy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SITTING near the Prescriptives counter at Bergdorf Goodman, I eyed the glowing white liquid suspiciously. ''Is this Magic?'' I asked Darac, the illusionist (read makeup artist) who goes by one name only.</p>
        <p>He nodded. ''Magic alters the reality of what you see,'' he said. ''It plays with light so it's all illusion. It's very Lucille Ball in 'Mame.' Every time she had a close-up she looked very soft, no fine lines or discoloration. Think of Magic as soft surgery. It's for people who say, 'Should I have something done?' and shouldn't, but do, and then come out looking like Mrs. Phantom of the Opera. Which we don't enjoy.''</p>
        <p>Prescriptives is just one of the major cosmetics companies that have been introducing products that are supposed to play with light so that women of a certain age (over 30) can welcome in 2000 looking like movie stars shot through cheesecloth. Estee Lauder recently introduced Spotlight, a lotion ''whose trick lies in the special way light is reflected by 'micro-prisms,' '' its promotional literature claims.</p>
        <p>Revlon's Age Defying Makeup and Concealer Compact features ''unique moisturizer-wrapped color particles,'' which ''float above skin lines, making them look less noticeable.'' And Christian Dior takes playing with light one step further with its new Lumiere Noire, a makeup line that is transparent in daylight and can be seen only in the black light of nightclubs (and is sold only at Sephora).</p>
        <p>Anne Carullo, the vice president of marketing and product development worldwide for Prescriptives, who came up with the concept for Magic, said: ''I always figured maybe I could trick light a little bit. If we optically alter what light sees, we alter the way we are seen.''</p>
        <p>In fact, in formulating Magic, Prescriptives worked with Trisha Sawyer, a makeup artist for Julia Roberts and Sharon Stone, on translating the principles of movie makeup into one for the masses -- meaning that if you use a base coat underneath your foundation, one that is filled with tiny glittering particles, it will somehow influence the way light hits your face (gently, thank you).</p>
        <p>At least, this is how I could best decipher the corporate gobbledygook describing Magic's Illuminating Liquid Potion as ''a holographic liquid, an oil-free, water-in-silicone emulsion with three-dimensional pigments made of spherical, multilayered particles that changes the way skin reflects light.''</p>
        <p>For those who speak English, this means that Magic will make you look as dewy and brimming with estrogen as you did the day of your junior prom. Which sounded good to me.</p>
        <p>During the last week, I tried all four of the new makeup lines in the hope that I, too, would wake up this weekend and greet the millennium with Julia Roberts's face -- and salary. Here's what happened instead.</p>
        <p>PRESCRIPTIVES -- Darac was the key to this experience (I'm sure the other companies' illusionists are equally good, though I tried those products at home). His sessions at Bergdorf's are free, though you must book well in advance. What is not free are the products: the Illuminating Liquid Potion is $30, the custom-blended foundation Darac made for me (''the difference between ordinary and extraordinary,'' he insisted) was $55, and the custom-made lipstick was $30, though all he did was copy the color of the $11.50 Clinique lipstick I usually buy.</p>
        <p>No matter. Darac's floor show is worth the extra charge, as was the discovery of my new favorite Prescriptives product, the Cooling Globe, which looks like a small light bulb. You keep it in the freezer and roll it over your puffy eyes when you get up in the morning.</p>
        <p>''This will rescue you,'' Darac proclaimed, applying it to my eyelids. Heaven. ''Also here, after a few martinis,'' he went on, pressing it behind my neck. ''And sinuses,'' he added, holding it on my cheeks. ''It's an Altoid for the eye,'' he said, albeit a $30 Altoid. How did I ever live without it?</p>
        <p>He did a fabulous job on my makeup, and indeed, shadows, red marks and all unevenness were obliterated without it looking like I was wearing makeup at all. Unlike other makeup applications, the result of this one was that my skin looked genuinely more lush than usual (though if I looked extra close I could see the little glitters; I simply resolved not to look.)</p>
        <p>Alas, hours later, when I checked myself again, the sparkles had sputtered and my skin had way more creases than usual, which is what happens when there is too much makeup on my face, even when expertly applied. ''Old pumpkin,'' a friend calls the effect.</p>
        <p>When I used the products on my own a few days later, I avoided this look, but I also avoided the cheesecloth glow. I had bypassed ethereal completely, leaving me to believe the magic may have been Darac's. Does he do hair, too? I had asked. He drew himself up. ''We are only cosmetic,'' he proclaimed. ''One man, one art: Aristotle.''</p>
        <p>CHRISTIAN DIOR -- I wasn't quite sure what to make of Lumiere Noire, a novelty makeup for the club-hopping set, which remains invisible to the naked eye until you encounter it under the black lights of a club. I never saw much point in clubs, even when I was younger, but now that my stepchildren are old enough, or almost old enough, to go instead, I sat them down for an after-dinner demonstration.</p>
        <p>They loved it, drawing a stick figure on my cheek and a tick-tack-toe board on my forehead, applying a stencil to the inside of my arm, coloring it in, then writing their names underneath. I looked totally normal until I held up a black light, revealing the designs in vivid ice blue. Fantastic! It occurred to me that you could write any kind of heinous message right across your forehead, go to work and smile at your bosses, and all the while they would have no idea what they were looking at. It definitely beats lingerie for that ''only you know'' sort of thrill.</p>
        <p>The drawback? After washing my face three times with soap and water, the blue remained. Blurred and faded, but still glowing. That was strange, but even so, I'd recommend it to anyone with time (and kids) on their hands, whether they go to clubs or not. It's fun, and it makes you feel young -- without the glitter.</p>
        <p>ESTEE LAUDER -- I found Spotlight to be quite similar to Magic, though it was definitely shinier, or more ''radiant,'' as the adjective in its packaging promised. Either way, my forehead looked like a headlight.</p>
        <p>While the makeup had the same glittery particles that Magic did, Spotlight gave my skin a reddish cast, which is actually meant to offset the green undertones of fluorescent office lights. Had it not been Christmas Eve, I would have found the red alarming, as my nose was glowing a la Rudolph. Luckily, when I applied my own Georgette Klinger foundation over it, the excessive rosiness disappeared and the overall effect came closest to Darac's application of Prescriptives. As he would say, I enjoyed.</p>
        <p>REVLON -- This was my briefest experiment. The Age Defying All Day Lifting Foundation felt like thick grandma makeup on my skin, seeming only to enhance the size of my pores. And the accompanying concealer compact felt oily to the touch and did not work as well as the Benefits concealer I normally use.</p>
        <p>The result of all this applying and removing different combinations from my face was an increase in the very same unsightly marks and blotches that these makeups were formulated to conceal, not to mention patches of dryness (especially on the site of the stick-figure man).</p>
        <p>Well, so much for movie stardom. Makeup is only makeup, after all. Though Ms. Carullo of Prescriptives promises that in May the company will introduce its second group of products that play with light. ''Maybe a putty to build cheekbones with,'' she mused, ''a serum that pulls the face back.''</p>
        <p>Sounds interesting. We would enjoy.</p>
        <p>COUNTERINTELLIGENCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
