<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dayne Lifts The Badgers To a Repeat In Pasadena</title>
    <meta content="02ROSE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rose Bowl (Football Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bowl Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Wisconsin</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stanford University</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowl Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4D91138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dayne Lifts The Badgers To a Repeat In Pasadena</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN GURNICK</byline>
      <dateline>PASADENA, Calif., Jan 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>dayne lifts the badgers to</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 86th Rose Bowl was billed as a potential offensive shootout, but it turned into a defensive battle decided in large part by injuries and by the kicking game.</p>
        <p>And, ultimately, by Ron Dayne.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 86th Rose Bowl was billed as a potential offensive shootout, but it turned into a defensive battle decided in large part by injuries and by the kicking game.</p>
        <p>And, ultimately, by Ron Dayne.</p>
        <p>Dayne, the National Collegiate Athletic Association's career rushing leader, gained 200 yards today on 34 carries, set a Rose Bowl career scoring record with a touchdown and captured the most valuable player honor for the second consecutive year as Wisconsin wore down and defeated outmanned but stubborn Stanford, 17-9, in the lowest-scoring Rose Bowl in 23 years.</p>
        <p>Dayne ran for 154 yards in the second half. He finished his career with 728 yards in bowl games and 6,397 in the regular season -- a total of 7,125. He set up his 4-yard touchdown run with a 64-yard rumble up the middle on the second play of the third quarter that put the Badgers ahead for good at 10-9.</p>
        <p>The Cardinal, inspired by the play of the injured stars Troy Walters and Willie Howard, was victimized by a first-half ankle injury to its long snapper, Jon Sande. Two errant snaps by his replacement, Anthony Gabriel, resulted in a missed extra point and a blocked field goal, the only turnover of the game.</p>
        <p>Stanford led by 9-3 at halftime. But Wisconsin held the Cardinal, the Pacific-10 champion, to minus-5 yards rushing over all and was able to contain its big-play offense throughout the second half. Stanford averaged 467 yards during the season, but was held to 264 yards by Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>The Badgers' redshirt freshman quarterback, Brooks Bollinger, completed two critical passes to tight end John Sigmund late in the game, leading to Bollinger's 1-yard touchdown sneak with 7 minutes 22 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Stanford (8-4) was making its first Rose Bowl appearance in 28 years and had a last-gasp chance to tie the score, but its drive was snuffed out with 1:11 left when quarterback Todd Husak slipped and fell with Ben Herbert bearing down on him on fourth-and-12 from his 46-yard line.</p>
        <p>Wisconsin (10-2), which beat U.C.L.A. last year, became the first Big Ten school to win consecutive Rose Bowl games (the conference had a no-repeat rule from 1946-60). The Big Ten has won seven of the last eight Rose Bowl games.</p>
        <p>''When we found out we had a chance to make history, it became one of the goals I addressed with the team,'' said Wisconsin Coach Barry Alvarez, who had knee replacement surgery earlier this season and manned the sideline with a cane. ''There's nothing like doing something no one else has done.''</p>
        <p>It was an equally historic game for Dayne, the Heisman Trophy winner, who was held to 46 yards in the first half. Dayne had four touchdowns last year, and his total of 30 points is a Rose Bowl record.</p>
        <p>''We had a nice talk at halftime and everybody got motivated,'' said Dayne, who ran for 246 yards against U.C.L.A. in last year's Rose Bowl. ''On the long run, I saw the hole and I just ran through it. It really gave us momentum and we carried it on. It would have been nice if we could have kept scoring so we wouldn't have had to bite our nails to the end.''</p>
        <p>Stanford opened the game with a disregard for injury reports. It started Walters, its all-American receiver, despite a dislocated wrist; Howard, the mainstay defensive lineman, despite a torn knee ligament; and center Mike McLaughlin despite a knee injury. McLaughlin lasted only one play, but Walters and Howard were key elements in a surprisingly effective game plan.</p>
        <p>During the regular season, Wisconsin's offense averaged 35.6 points a game and Stanford averaged 37.2. So the two teams looked as if they were impostors during a scoreless first quarter that had punters Sean Tolpinrud of Stanford and Kevin Stemke of Wisconsin vying for most valuable player honors.</p>
        <p>The Cardinal defense, ranked 110th in the nation, swarmed around Dayne and sniffed out every rollout pass by Bollinger, limiting Wisconsin to 12 yards in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>''We hadn't played since early November and we didn't have our rhythm,'' Alvarez said. ''They had a very good scheme and they did a great job with our tendencies, anticipating what we would call.''</p>
        <p>But late in the first quarter with Stanford backed up against its goal line, Husak got breathing room when he hit Howard with a play-action 28-yard completion.</p>
        <p>Kerry Carter scored Stanford's only touchdown on a 1-yard run in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
