<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Find a New Killer Attack, Try Renovating an Old One</title>
    <meta content="02CHES$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Chess Congress</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Byrne, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benjamin, Joel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldin, Aleksandr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shabalov, Alexander</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ivanov, Alexander</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EED61038F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Find a New Killer Attack, Try Renovating an Old One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Byrne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Byrne, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Byrne column notes that National Chess Congress, held in Philadephia from Nov 22 to 28, finished with four-grandmaster tie for first place; says Joel Benjamin, Aleksandr Goldin, Alexander Shabalov and Alexander Ivanov were each awarded $1,425; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Chess Congress, held in Philadelphia from Nov. 22 to 28, finished with a four-grandmaster tie for first place. Joel Benjamin of Manhattan, Aleksandr Goldin of Russia, Alexander Ivanov of Brookline, Mass., and Alexander Shabalov of Pittsburgh each scored 5-1 in the 84-entrant, Swiss-system event and each was awarded a prize of $1,425. No tiebreak coefficients were used. The tournament, run by the Continental Chess Association, was held at the Adam's Mark Hotel.</p>
        <p>The gem of the first round -- and possibly of the entire tourney -- was the encounter between Goldin and Dean Ippolito of Boontown, N.J. The Russian sharpened up a recently resuscitated attack and won impressively.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Chess Congress, held in Philadelphia from Nov. 22 to 28, finished with a four-grandmaster tie for first place. Joel Benjamin of Manhattan, Aleksandr Goldin of Russia, Alexander Ivanov of Brookline, Mass., and Alexander Shabalov of Pittsburgh each scored 5-1 in the 84-entrant, Swiss-system event and each was awarded a prize of $1,425. No tiebreak coefficients were used. The tournament, run by the Continental Chess Association, was held at the Adam's Mark Hotel.</p>
        <p>The gem of the first round -- and possibly of the entire tourney -- was the encounter between Goldin and Dean Ippolito of Boontown, N.J. The Russian sharpened up a recently resuscitated attack and won impressively.</p>
        <p>After 5 . . . h6 in the Semi-Slav Variation, the once discredited gambit with 6 Bh4! is currently a hot item. For many years now, the positional 6 Bf6 Qf6 has held the field, but in a Ruck-Szuhanek game in Zalakaros, Hungary, 7 e3 Nd7 8 Bd3 Qd8 9 0-0 Be7 10 a3 0-0 11 Qc2 b6!? 12 cd ed 13 b4 Bb7 14 Qb3 Nf6 15 Rfe1 Rb8!? 16 Ne5 Bd6 17 f4 c5 18 bc bc 19 Qa4 a6 worked well for Black.</p>
        <p>After 6 . . . dc 7 e4 g5 8 Bg3 b5 9 Be2, defense with 9 . . . Bb7 has failed against 10 h4 g4 11 Ne5 b4?! 12 Na4 Ne4 13 Bc4 h5 14 Qe2 Ng3 15 fg Rh6 16 O-O f5 17 d5! Qa5 18 Rf5!, with an annihilating attack in a Stohl-Pavasovic game in Portoroz, Yugoslavia, in June.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the alternative with 9  . . . Nbd7 has not held up against 10 d5! For instance, 10 . . . b4 11 de bc 12 ed Bd7 13 bc Ne4 14 Qd4 Ng3 15 hg Rg8 16 Qc4 has stuck Black with problems defending his king, as in a Belyavsky-Atalik game in Vrnjacka Banja, Yugoslavia, in October. So Ippolito tried to keep a more compact formation with 9 . . . Bb4.</p>
        <p>After 10 Qc2 g4 11 Ne5 Qd4 12 O-O Bc3 13 bc Qe4, Ippolito was three pawns ahead, but Goldin was about to renovate an old, nearly forgotten onslaught.</p>
        <p>After 14 . . . Nbd7, Max Euwe suggested 33 years ago that White would get a dangerous attack with 15 Rad1, which was probably anticipated by Ippolito, but now Goldin steps up the attack another notch with 15 f3!, after which 15 . . . Qd5 16 Qf4 Ne5 17 Qe5 Qe5 18 Be5 Ke7 19 fg will cost Black a piece.</p>
        <p>Ippolito avoided that with 16 . . . Rg8, but after 17 Nd7 Nd7 18 fg e5 19 Qh6, Goldin was only a pawn down, for which he had an overwhelming attack.</p>
        <p>After 24 . . . Kc7, Goldin scored with 25 Rd7! Rd7 26 Qe5 Kd8 (or 26  . . . Rd6 27 Bc5 Rg8 28 Rf6) 27 Bg4 f5 28 Bf5 Qg7 29 Qb8 Bc8 (or 29 . . . Ke7 30 Bc5 Kf7 31 Bd7) 30 Bd7. If 30 . . . Qd7, then 31 Bd4 Re8 32 Bf6 Re7 33 Re1. Ippolito gave up.</p>
        <p>CHESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
