<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Retirement Road, 65 Is Still Their Limit</title>
    <meta content="02SENI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SENIORITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brock, Fred</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Seniority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EFDE1238F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Retirement Road, 65 Is Still Their Limit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED BROCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brock, Fred</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chances of retiring at age 65 are slipping away, at least as Social Security is concerned; changes made by Congress in 1983 are ratcheting up retirement age for people born after 1937; while this may not be problem for some people, it is not being greeted well by people whose jobs are physically demanding, such as construction workers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE next time some policy strategist or ivory-tower academic suggests raising the retirement age to 70 for collecting full Social Security benefits, I wish he would get up from his ergonomically designed chair, go to Bloomfield, N.J., and spend a day with William Gelenites or John Cuffari.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gelenites, 35, a carpenter, and Mr. Cuffari, 37, a laborer, work among the rising girders of an office building. Their jobs are physically difficult, especially during the winter cold. And in their circle of workers,  the idea of staying on the job until 70 is not exactly catching fire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE next time some policy strategist or ivory-tower academic suggests raising the retirement age to 70 for collecting full Social Security benefits, I wish he would get up from his ergonomically designed chair, go to Bloomfield, N.J., and spend a day with William Gelenites or John Cuffari.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gelenites, 35, a carpenter, and Mr. Cuffari, 37, a laborer, work among the rising girders of an office building. Their jobs are physically difficult, especially during the winter cold. And in their circle of workers,  the idea of staying on the job until 70 is not exactly catching fire.</p>
        <p>''By the time you reach 55 or 60 in the heavy construction business, most contractors don't want you,'' Mr. Gelenites said. ''You just can't do the hard work after years of getting banged around.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuffari pointed to a huge supermarket nearby.</p>
        <p>''The blocks they used to build that with weigh 105 pounds each,'' he said. ''I lifted 90 percent of them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gelenites said there was pressure from contractors to keep working hard all day. ''I've been on jobs where they get mad if you take too many drinks of water,'' he said. ''It's go, go, go. If you don't feel good and slack off, that's no excuse.''</p>
        <p>They work, often outside, in rain or snow. And they get paid only if they work. ''There are no paid holidays, no vacation, no sick days,'' Mr. Gelenites said.</p>
        <p>THE two men, who are union members, also cite safety as an especially acute issue for older construction workers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuffari should know. In 1991, when he was 29, a scaffold on which he was working collapsed, sending him crashing 20 feet to a concrete floor. He suffered head injuries, his back was broken in three places and his collarbone was fractured.</p>
        <p>''If I'd been 66 or 67, I'd have been done for,'' he said.</p>
        <p>You don't have to spend much time talking with people who build our buildings, pave our roads, clean our office toilets or tote our garbage to see clearly the contrast between them and people who work in comfortably heated and air-conditioned offices. And guess where those who make the retirement-policy decisions work.</p>
        <p>The notion of retiring at 65 is already slipping away, at least as far as Social Security is concerned.</p>
        <p>Changes made by Congress in 1983 are ratcheting up the retirement age for people born after 1937. For instance, workers born in 1942 must wait until they are 65 and 10 months to get full benefits. Those born in 1960 or later must wait until they are 67. Workers can still take early retirement at 62, but benefits are reduced by 20 to 30 percent, depending on the year of birth.</p>
        <p>The Social Security Administration has a Web site (www.ssa.gov) that lets you plug in the year you were born and find out when you can retire under current law. I clicked on the year I was born, 1944, and discovered that I cannot get full retirement benefits until I'm 66. Well, O.K., I guess I can roll myself up to my keyboard for a year longer than I had planned. But if I were operating a jackhammer for a living . . . .</p>
        <p>There is talk, of course, of raising the full retirement age to 70 -- a move that is always presented as necessary for ''saving'' Social Security, whether it needs it or not.</p>
        <p>Mark Weisbrot is one of a growing number of economists who thinks it does not. He is the co-director of the Center for Economic and Policy Research in Washington and co-author, with Dean Baker, of a new book, ''Social Security: The Phony Crisis'' (University of Chicago Press). They argue that even with economic growth projections for the next 75 years that are only half the last 75 years' average annual rate of 3 percent, the system will experience only a small shortfall. That gap won't appear until 35 years from now, they say, and can be bridged with only minor changes. At a growth rate of 3 percent, they contend, there will be virtually no shortfalls.</p>
        <p>''Many people believe Social Security is in trouble because they have been told so by politicians in search of issues and by right-wing ideologues who have opposed the whole notion of social insurance since the New Deal and are looking for excuses to make cuts,'' Dr. Weisbrot said.</p>
        <p>''Plus, a big part of the push to increase the retirement age to 70 is simply that the policy crowd doesn't work at jobs in which they're spent by the time they're 65.''</p>
        <p>So the next time you hear people calling for raising the retirement age to 70, ask them what they do for a living.</p>
        <p>SENIORITY Fred Brock is an editor at The Times. His column on the approach and arrival of retirement appears the first Sunday of each month.  E-mail: fbrock@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Fred Brock is an editor at The Times. His column on the approach and arrival of retirement appears the first Sunday of each month.
&lt;br&gt;E-mail: fbrock@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
