<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Undressed, Trees Reveal Their Splendor</title>
    <meta content="WCGARDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faust, Joan Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E1DB1538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Undressed, Trees Reveal Their Splendor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Faust, Joan Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gardening column on looking at trees in winter (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BUNDLE up in a warm coat, scarf, hat and gloves because this is a perfect time for a tree walk. This may seem like an odd time to look at trees, without the leaves. Yet, they are in one of their most grand stages.</p>
        <p>Shorn of their leafy canopies, the full skeleton or architectural pattern is laid bare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BUNDLE up in a warm coat, scarf, hat and gloves because this is a perfect time for a tree walk. This may seem like an odd time to look at trees, without the leaves. Yet, they are in one of their most grand stages.</p>
        <p>Shorn of their leafy canopies, the full skeleton or architectural pattern is laid bare.</p>
        <p>I like to call this scaffolding the deciduous tree's magnificence. At this time of year, their splendid strength and form shows through. No wonder these excellent treasures have in many ways, gained new respect. Possibly the easiest way to go out and see trees is to learn who they are.</p>
        <p>There are all sorts of means of identification that provide practical clues to the identity of a species. The first place to start is with the bark. In some cases, this sorting is easy, particularly with the paper birch and its glistening clean white bark.</p>
        <p>During the early history of this country is was best known to the Indian tribes as the canoe birch. It was this tree from which they stripped off the bark to make canoes or even tent walls. For the homeowner, the paper birch tree has often been used as a landscape feature, especially when it is placed near evergreens to show off the bark. One less appealing factor is that the trunks of this species are all too often subject to high wind damager.</p>
        <p>The shagbark hickory is one of the easiest trees to recognize. Its bark is  so shaggy that flakes of the bark can  be easily pulled off.</p>
        <p>Then there is the tree with the showiest bark, the sycamore. Sometimes these trees can grow to tremendous heights and width, especially along rivers, their favorite haunts. The bark flakes off to show a somewhat mottled effect. Some call it a piebald bark for it has many colors: green, white, tan to deeper brown. This is the tree that is often confused with the European London Plane tree, a common street tree, which is a hybrid between the American species and an Oriental species.</p>
        <p>As to the magnificent scaffolding of a tree, probably the most wonderful is the wide and broad spread of the white oak. This is a marvelous specimen if the tree has the proper room to grow, such as in a park.</p>
        <p>Two other oaks, that are easy to identify are the pin oak and the scarlet oak. The pin oak, another frequently planted street tree, has its limbs hanging, as if carrying them on a slow-paced walk. The branches of the scarlet oak, by contrast, are held upright as if in praise. This sort of structure has to be seen from a distance to get the full sense of the tree.</p>
        <p>Of course, the weeping trees are easy to identify. The weeping willow should be known to all for its thin willowy twigs and branches that bow ever so easily in the slightest breeze.</p>
        <p>Not as easy to pick out are the weeping structures of the great beeches, which have become somewhat of a rarity these days.</p>
        <p>The tulip tree is also easy to identify for its trunk goes straight up to the sky. This stately giant was a favorite of shipbuilders who used the trunks for their masts. Usually the flowers of this tree are so high up, you have to look for the fallen ones during the summer months. To many eyes, they resemble tulips, hence the name.</p>
        <p>For those who really want to get intimate with trees, looking at the buds can be challenging fun. The flower buds of the dogwood stand upright on the twigs like so many fat turbans. If there are plenty of these turbanlike buds on the trees now, a sure Maytime splendor is guaranteed.</p>
        <p>Several trees have long skinny buds. One in particular is the shadbush, one of the first trees to flower in the spring, when the shad are running -- thus, the name. This tree's buds are long and pointed almost like sharp pencil points. Beech tree buds are long and skinny as well. So are those of the birch trees.</p>
        <p>The fattest buds of all belong to the horse chestnut. This particular bud is covered with a shiny wax protectant.</p>
        <p>These are but a few of the explorations that can be made outdoors now. It is a splendid way to get close to nature and become acquainted with the local surroundings. For those who really want to get serious about identifying woody plants, there is a  paperback to guide the learning process. ''The Tree Identification Book'' (William Morrow &amp; Company, $17.95) by George Wellington Dillingham Symonds is a big help. The black and white photographs are ideal to aid identification.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
