<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dining Out; Critic's Choice: Where Service Counts</title>
    <meta content="02DINE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EFDA1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dining Out; Critic's Choice: Where Service Counts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed recommends restaurants in Westchester County with good food and hospitable service (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE bull market may rage on, but dining opportunities in Westchester are turning decidedly bearish. That is not to say there are no fabulous restaurants that would repeatedly draw us back for occasions ranging from a casual repast with a peckish friend to a formal bash celebrating one of life's great events. There are, and they are listed below.  But observant readers will notice that this year's choice picks number fewer than those in the past. And the primary cause for these cuts is ungracious or inattentive service.</p>
        <p>When dining out, the consumer rents, for a few hours, a certain ambience: the kitchen and its skills, the dining room, chairs, lighting, decor, linens and other appointments and service. This last should include not only table service but also a warm welcome and a few words of gratitude at departure. The higher the tab, the more punctilious an establishment should be. Yet, it is interesting that many letters we receive complain of abuse by management, and at high-priced restaurants at that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE bull market may rage on, but dining opportunities in Westchester are turning decidedly bearish. That is not to say there are no fabulous restaurants that would repeatedly draw us back for occasions ranging from a casual repast with a peckish friend to a formal bash celebrating one of life's great events. There are, and they are listed below.  But observant readers will notice that this year's choice picks number fewer than those in the past. And the primary cause for these cuts is ungracious or inattentive service.</p>
        <p>When dining out, the consumer rents, for a few hours, a certain ambience: the kitchen and its skills, the dining room, chairs, lighting, decor, linens and other appointments and service. This last should include not only table service but also a warm welcome and a few words of gratitude at departure. The higher the tab, the more punctilious an establishment should be. Yet, it is interesting that many letters we receive complain of abuse by management, and at high-priced restaurants at that.</p>
        <p>As we dine anonymously, we, too, have received rude, shoddy service. It is amazing how many restaurants allow diners to stand, ignored, at the entrance or to depart without farewell and sincere hopes that they were pleased and that they will return.</p>
        <p>The telephone manners of some places could also use honing. Especially in high season, instead of announcing curtly that they are fully booked for the evenings in question, restaurants might thank the caller for thinking of them and suggest trying again.</p>
        <p>This list is a personal one of places where we have enjoyed tempting, carefully prepared dishes and where we have been treated hospitably. They are mentioned randomly. Reservations are essential on weekends and advisable even on week nights.</p>
        <p>American</p>
        <p>The distinction among cuisines has become increasingly fuzzy. Ethnic categories in many cases seem arbitrary, particularly when it comes to appellations like American, Italian and French. These days such restaurants are borrowing internationally, and the result is new and tempting combinations that flesh out the vision of creative chefs. Nowhere is this trend more splendidly seen than at Peter Xaviar Kelly's four stunning establishments, where Mr. Kelly's inspirations become delicious reality: Xaviar's in both Piermont (359-7007) and, on weekends only, in Garrison (424- 4228), Restaurant X and Bully Boy Bar (268-6555) in Congers, and, sharing the kitchen with Xaviar's in Piermont, Freelance Cafe &amp; Wine Bar (365-3250). Service is first rate.</p>
        <p>Seamless service and a fresh approach in the kitchen mark Crabtree's Kittle House (666-8044) in Chappaqua. Gregory Gilbert turns out superb, beautifully balanced dishes. Order at will. Anibal Romero's desserts are equally divine.</p>
        <p>New at Bistro Twenty-Two (234-7333) in Bedford Village is Brian Galvin, well schooled in balancing textures and savory tastes into delicious equations. Also new and welcome at Peter Pratt's Inn (962-4090) in Yorktown is Daniel Laughran, who has infused the offerings here with plenty of spark and wit, although service can be dicey and the cellar dining room at times airless.</p>
        <p>Mark Filippo continues to produce uncommonly appealing dishes at Cafe Meze (428-2400) in Hartsdale, making what sounds old, harmoniously new again. Fresh seasonal vegetables turn the trick.</p>
        <p>In White Plains on the border of Hartsdale, Mighty Joe Young's (428-6868) depends on its wood-fired grills and huge stone ovens for flavor. Steaks, octopus, ostrich -- all are imbued with a delicious smokiness from the fire. The safari motif in decor is kitschy and fun.</p>
        <p>Manhattan comes to Nyack in the form of stylish Lu Shane's (358-5556). The restaurant is a beauty; the service, attentive; the food, impressive enough to make being here a pleasure.</p>
        <p>For impeccably fresh, nicely prepared seafare, one cannot do better than the Fish Cellar (666-4448) in Mount Kisco. The oysters at the popular raw bar slip down easily, and soups and grilled fish, as well as a full seafood menu, are available in the dining rooms beyond.</p>
        <p>Dudley's (941-8674) in the small landmark purple house in Ossining is one of those dining spots where management could take a few lessons in customer appreciation. But dishes are interesting and skillfully prepared by the chef and co-owner Takaii Minamoto, and the music from Thursday through Saturday nights is engaging. Diners looking for new tastes will find game meats beautifully prepared and presented.</p>
        <p>And although service can be painfully amateurish at Iron Horse Grill in Pleasantville (741-0717), Philip McGrath, the chef and owner, balances flavors expertly, with attention lavished on appetizers and desserts. This restaurant now occupies the tastefully renovated waiting room of the drafty Pleasantville train station. When the winter wind is up, diners would do well to don sweaters and warm socks.</p>
        <p>Hardly fine dining, but for something entirely different and extremely casual, try hilarious, sprawling Hogwash BBQ &amp; Grill (698-5802) in Mamaroneck. The Disney World Old West atmosphere is great fun and the dripping Texas barbecue, tasty.  Go with a group, and wear washable clothing. Live music begins late on weekends. Cover charges may apply. Under the same ownership but in much tighter quarters in the Fleetwood section of Mount Vernon, the Bayou (668-2634) fills its tiny stage with similar musical fare, from blues to zydeco. Spiritual readings and voodoo nights continue the New Orleans theme here as does the menu of Cajun-Creole food, from Jazzy Jumpin' Jambalaya to po'boys. Call either spot for monthly entertainment schedules, which list special events and any charges.</p>
        <p>Chinese</p>
        <p>Considering the number of restaurants serving Chinese food, it is remarkable how little dishes vary from place to place. A few notable exceptions, however, eschew thick, gloppy sauces, employing soy sauce, corn starch and oil to a minimum, if at all. K. Fung's (472-3838) in Hartsdale is a delightful one of these. Rounding out an extensive familiar menu are complex salads, vegetarian dishes and a handful of delicious specials.  Daily specials are posted at Jade Palace (472-8888), and they, also, deserve consideration. This Scarsdale restaurant always seems to have an unusual ingredient in the kitchen, perhaps safflower, sea moss, white and flower leeks or pea shoots and fresh seafood -- all ready to add zip to the bill of fare. And for tasty, straightforward mix-and-match ingredients, in a tiny Larchmont storefront Ray's (833-2551) allows diners to choose the combination that suits mood and diet. Fresh vegetables, rice or noodles, fish and duck stand at the ready.</p>
        <p>French</p>
        <p>Jackie's Bistro (337-8447)in Eastchester serves French food the way we knew it in the 50's, only better.  Careful cooking and not nostalgia alone make dishes here memorable: onion soup, garlicky escargots, duck a l'orange, moules mariniere. Jackie's gossamer cheesecake is a knockout.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, so-called French restaurants, like many so-called American restaurants, have incorporated international techniques and ingredients into their Gallic vision. Nowhere is the alchemy more magnificent than at the splendid Arch (279-5011) in Brewster. Chef and owner, George Seitz, and his team also see to it that gracious service and seamless pacing add to the gustatory pleasures.</p>
        <p>La Panetiere (967-8140) in Rye seems more elegant with every passing year, appropriate ambience for the fine food served here. Supplementing the beautifully appointed main dining room, an upstairs room with a greenhouse wall gives the effect of dining atop trees. The aerie location of Auberge Argenteuil (948-0597) in Hartsdale has a similar view. The pretty dining areas here may be tight, but the welcome is big and heart felt.</p>
        <p>Indian</p>
        <p>With Chinese cuisine at a creative standstill, the mellow spicing of Indian food is all the more welcome, and the variety of dishes from all the regions of this vast subcontinent promise to please every taste.</p>
        <p>Bengal Tiger (948-5191) in White Plains and India House (736-0005) in Montrose remain among the first and the best in the county. In the same family India Cafe &amp; Grill (273-7081) in Armonk lives up to the standard.</p>
        <p>As brilliant and sunny as the cuisine, the decor at spacious Tandoori Taste of India (235-8390) in New Rochelle is an exciting eyeful, just as the kitchen produces a tempting mouthful. The smaller and less extravagant sister restaurant of the same name in Port Chester (937-2727) has a similar menu and a kitchen that blends spices a tad more aggressively but just as deliciously.</p>
        <p>Italian</p>
        <p>Most diners will find the food at upbeat Cinema Ristorante (693-9200) in Ardsley worth the trouble of finding a parking space in the narrow cul de sac in front. With any luck a valet will appear to solve any problems.  Dishes here are inventive, yet decidedly Italian, from savory antipasti to creamy zecchino.</p>
        <p>Cheerful Valentino's (776-6731) in Yonkers was the county's first dining spot to serve food in basins to be passed around a table family style. Although a handful of restaurants have copied the form, Valentino's remains the best. Clearly, food is prepared in quantity, but expect no mushy pasta or overcooked seafood here. The place is usually packed with groups, especially those celebrating a birthday when everyone seems to join in the singing.</p>
        <p>Japanese</p>
        <p>Japanese food, particularly sushi, has become so popular that quite a few Chinese restaurants have installed sushi counters. Good as these may be, we tend to favor those spots that concentrate on serving only Japanese dishes. Diners who have found menu listings unenlightening in these restaurants will be pleased to know that more and more places are producing picturebook menus or adding extensive descriptions of dishes.</p>
        <p>Not all Japanese restaurants are able to produce both superb sushi and accomplished cooked dishes. In Scarsdale Gyosai (725-3730) manages to excel in both. Sushi is creative and pristine, and cooked dishes are delectable.</p>
        <p>Depend on inventive rolls (maki-zushi) as well as nicely cooked dishes at Hanada (769-0638) in Pleasantville. And at Ichi Riki (592-2220) in Elmsford and in Nyack (358-7977), the stuffed trout is particularly inspired.</p>
        <p>Warm up at Sushi Raku (332-8687) in Sleepy Hollow with a bowl of hot nabemono. Sushi combinations are straightforward and fresh.</p>
        <p>Azuma Sushi (725-0660) in Hartsdale specializes in raw fish. Diners crowd in for the sushi and sashimi, the only items on the menu.</p>
        <p>Portuguese</p>
        <p>In Tarrytown the informal Caravela (631-1863) is one of several restaurants serving hearty Portuguese-Brazilian dishes, and it is the smallest, a feature that, to our mind, makes it the best. No sprawling party rooms to put an unexpected strain on kitchen and service here. Quality and preparation are consistent, the food fresh, richly flavored and generously portioned. A few pieces of handsome Portuguese ceramics state the theme. Diners wanting a refreshing aperitif might try delicious, lime-based caipirinha.</p>
        <p>Spanish</p>
        <p>Conveniently situated on the far side of the train station in Irvington, Solera on Hudson (591-2233) offers a wine and tapas bar, comfortable dining areas and some exciting Spanish dishes. Casserole of clams, zarzuela, octopus, mussels and daily fish specials are only a few of the accomplishments. End the meal with an assortment of Spanish cheeses.</p>
        <p>Turkish</p>
        <p>Unless one lives nearby in Mamaroneck, going to Turquoise (381-3693) without a reservation would be a mistake. This dining room is almost always filled with diners enjoying zesty, satisfying cuisine based on myriad variations of vegetables and char-grilled meats and fish. Rice or warm pita soaks up the delicious juices and sauces. For dessert, frangible Middle Eastern pastries and, of course, Turkish coffee.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
