<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Next Wave? 3-D Could Bring On a Sea Change</title>
    <meta content="02GURE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Three-Dimensional Devices</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurewitsch, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Three-Dimensional Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3D91638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Next Wave? 3-D Could Bring On a Sea Change</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW GUREWITSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gurewitsch, Matthew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matthew Gurewitsch on new film technologies, including large-format 3-D that may be wave of cinematic future; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS we reset the Great Clock, new technologies are appearing by the minute. Some filmmakers who have worked in the medium believe that large-format 3-D is the wave of the cinematic future -- ''the next click,'' in the words of Brett Leonard, director of ''T-Rex: Back to the Cretaceous,'' a 1998 film that has become the most popular large-format title to date.</p>
        <p>From this viewer's perspective, however, large-format 3-D looks to be something more interesting than that, as distinct from conventional cinema as symphonies from opera or poetry from prose fiction, with a potential for greatness all its own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS we reset the Great Clock, new technologies are appearing by the minute. Some filmmakers who have worked in the medium believe that large-format 3-D is the wave of the cinematic future -- ''the next click,'' in the words of Brett Leonard, director of ''T-Rex: Back to the Cretaceous,'' a 1998 film that has become the most popular large-format title to date.</p>
        <p>From this viewer's perspective, however, large-format 3-D looks to be something more interesting than that, as distinct from conventional cinema as symphonies from opera or poetry from prose fiction, with a potential for greatness all its own.</p>
        <p>Beginning with ''We Are Born Stars,'' an 11-minute history of the universe created for the Fujitsu Pavilion at Expo '85 in Japan, the large-format 3-D catalog now numbers 16 main attractions. Apart from Christine Edzard's ''Imax Nutcracker'' (1997), a non-singing, non-dancing holiday treat to rival Madame Tussaud's (based on the same E. T. A. Hoffmann tale that inspired Tchaikovsky), each of them springs surprises inconceivable in any other form .</p>
        <p>Runaway blobs of paint caroming through space (Roman Kroitor and Peter Stephenson's lighter-than-air cartoon ''Paint Misbehavin','' 1997). A sky that hangs overhead not like a dome but like the lid of an azure box, painted with clouds (Mr. Leonard's ''Siegfried &amp; Roy: The Magic Box,'' 1999). Spherical holograms and luminous technical displays that glow in midair (Allan Kroeker's ''L5: First City in Space,''1996). Beyond image or point of view, what gives these moments their charge is the sensation of physical presence.</p>
        <p>Stereoscopic photography, the technical heart of the medium, supplies two slightly shifted ''flat'' perspectives of each image, one for each eye. Still or moving, it has a long history. But the large-format cinematic variety takes a quantum leap. Associated with the Imax Corporation, a Toronto-based company that developed all aspects of the system from cameras and sound to its proprietary projectors and theater design, large-format 3-D has been picked up by producers including Sony Pictures Classics, L-Squared Entertainment and Mandalay Media Arts.</p>
        <p>''It's not your parents' 3-D!'' trumpets the trailer for Ben Stassen's ''Encounter in the Third Dimension,'' which opened last year. Beneath the cloak of zany escapism, the film incorporates a casual survey of 3-D from its tentative beginnings to the present day. We see the very first, very brief three-dimensional film clip, ''L'Arrivee du Train,'' shot by the Lumiere brothers in black and white in Paris in 1903. For original audiences, we are told, the illusion of an oncoming train was so potent that they ran panic-stricken from the theater. The chronicle continues with stereoscopic images -- wittily including people in exotic dress and far-off lands gazing through stereoscopes at other stereoscopic images. Vintage horror hokum from midcentury gets an airing, too.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stassen's original material features a dizzy supporting cast of gadgets with a life of their own, a mad scientist and Elvira, the bouncy Morticia Addams-type cult personality, who is imprisoned in two dimensions. For those who miss the point, her little song and dance about a haunted house is frozen in midphrase, someone gives her a push and she falls over -- a cardboard cutout.</p>
        <p>Thus Mr. Stassen makes a joke of a glitch attentive viewers may occasionally be troubled by elsewhere in the large-format 3-D canon: the illusion of depth without the illusion of roundness and solidity. Ghosting can be a problem too, not to mention the spacey phenomenon of bodies that look round but empty, like soap bubbles. As Mr. Stassen shows, a flaw consciously exploited ceases to be a flaw. In what may be his wildest flourish of drop-dead bravura, he presents a pre-title sequence ''behind'' the movie screen, which hangs there like a dusty windshield. Then the words of the title appear, blasting through one flying letter at a time, shattering the ''screen'' and leaving the view crystal-clear.</p>
        <p>O.K., the Imax variety isn't your parents' 3-D. What is it? Some technical data may be in order. Your parents' 3-D -- Hitchcock's ''Dial M for Murder'' and George Sidney's ''Kiss Me, Kate'' from the 50's and Andy Warhol's retro ''Flesh for Frankenstein'' from the 70's, among the more ambitious titles; Andre de Toth's ''House of Wax,'' starring Vincent Price, Arthur Hilton's ''Cat Women of the Moon'' and ''It Came From Outer Space'' and ''Creature From the Black Lagoon,'' both directed by Jack Arnold, among the more representative -- was shot on film stock of standard size, shown on screens of standard size and viewed through special glasses that were flimsy and fit poorly over regular glasses, with splitting headaches the frequent result. The scripts (seldom top-drawer) were conventional movie scripts. In short, your parents' 3-D was ordinary movies plus an illusion of depth.</p>
        <p>And the Imax variety? The stock measures 15 by 70 millimeters per frame, 10 times the size of the 35-millimeter films shown in the conventional multiplex, but delivering a brighter and clearer image over a vastly larger area. How much brighter? The light from a xenon bulb in an Imax projector is so powerful that we could see it with the naked eye from the surface of the new moon. The screen size varies widely. ''We like to say to eight stories high and even wider'' is the official word from an Imax spokesman, who gives the dimensions for the screen at Sony Theaters Lincoln Square, the first Imax theater in a multiplex, as 75.6 feet high by 97.6 feet. The format provides a ''natural'' field of vision that effectively has no edge or frame. Eyewear comes in two styles, both designed to fit comfortably over corrective glasses. The heavier, interplanetary-looking type has a built-in personal stereo system, for spatially enhanced sound effects. Partly for economic reasons, films in Imax 3-D are short. But eyestrain is a factor, too. By the end of a feature, many viewers are starting to experience discomfort. The longest of them clock in at 50 minutes, some at only 20.</p>
        <p>''Historically,'' says Richard L. Gelfond, co-chairman and co-chief executive of the Imax Corporation, ''Imax made its mark by taking people where they couldn't go themselves. To the top of Everest or the bottom of the ocean.'' A large-format cinematic answer to National Geographic, in other words, a spectacular notch or two above ''Nova.'' Just the ticket for museums of natural history.</p>
        <p>That market segment still exists. But since 1987, the number of Imax theaters has jumped from the original one in Vancouver to 77 worldwide (36 of them in the United States). Another 85 are in development (about half of them in the United States).</p>
        <p>Some of the new facilities are free-standing; others are like the Sony Imax in Manhattan, tucked into a multiplex. Filling the seats will take more than kelp forests and frolicking seals, perennial favorites though such things are. In the expanding Imax universe, picturesque travelogues -- ''Across the Sea of Time'' (1995), for instance, which stars New York City past and present, or ''Mark Twain's America'' (1998), both by Stephen Low -- now compete with old-school scientific documentaries.</p>
        <p>IT is possible, of course, to combine delight with instruction, as in John Weiley's ''Imagine,'' produced for Expo '93 in Taejon, Korea. Between segments on depth perception came inspired set pieces illustrating the educational points. One, a speedboat ride down a gorge, was shot so as to simulate what we would see if our eyes were spaced more widely than they are. Apart from the promised optical effect, the scene confuses our perception: not only does the colossal landscape look tiny, as if we were viewing it through the wrong end of a telescope, but it also seems strangely fake, like a meticulous scale model.</p>
        <p>In another set piece, Mr. Weiley showed how minimal movement in an object allows the eye to ''construct'' the object's contours even if they cannot be directly seen. From a flat white field irregularly dotted with black spots emerged a spinning disc, a rotating cube and a real, live elephant, waving its trunk close enough for a viewer to tickle. For an encore, Mr. Weiley presented an aquatic ballet by the modern-dance troupe Momix, involving sylphs and ladders and a human salamander whose tail was longer than his legs. It was projected upside down, so the performers seemed to dive up through a wavy floor of silver. I forget Mr. Weiley's theoretical point, if there was one, but the sequence was sheer bliss.</p>
        <p>Prophetic, too. Entertainment pure and simple is shaping up as a dominant mode for the large-format 3-D of the future. For other prototypes, look at ''T-Rex: Back to the Cretaceous'' and ''Siegfried &amp; Roy: The Magic Box,'' both by Brett Leonard. Cirque du Soleil's ''Journey of Man,'' a sort of New Age ''Wizard of Oz'' punctuated with glamorous circus acts filmed in gorgeous surroundings, is coming soon (and probably would be coming sooner if, as of Jan. 1, Disney had not pre-empted many Imax flagships for four months of ''Fantasia/2000,'' which is definitely 2-D). Beyond that, we are promised 3-D versions of ''Gulliver's Travels'' and Stephen King's ''Sun Dog'' (featuring a diabolical Polaroid camera) -- not to mention Homer Simpson. ''Cyberworld,''  a ''Fantasia''-style potpourri of phantasmagoric high-tech animation, is also in the pipeline. As currently available technologies get cheaper, a prospect Imax executives assure me is no fantasy, original classics like ''2001: A Space Odyssey'' and the ''Star Wars'' series will reappear in new editions, computer-enhanced for 3-D.</p>
        <p>The artistic touchstone of large-format 3-D, meanwhile, and likely to remain so, is Stephen Low's ''Last Buffalo,'' created for the Suntory Pavilion at Expo '90 in Osaka, Japan. Mr. Leonard calls it ''a visual poem.'' Or rather a symphony? Its message, told without a word of text, is easy to intuit, yet hard to paraphrase.</p>
        <p>This is what we see. In alternating segments, Mr. Low shows wildlife of the Canadian wilderness and a sculptor at his forge, pouring and pounding sheets and rods of metal into a life-size buffalo. Under the open sky, clouds and shadows of a day wash over canyons in a moment. Looming before us, gigantically larger than life, a mother buffalo licks clean her newborn calf. Mountain lion, buffalo and rattlesnake wage their ancient warfare.</p>
        <p>Wading birds, filmed from below the water, pick the surface, sending circles rippling where we suspected only air. Indoors, rivers of molten metal threaten to flow into our laps, sparks spray at our faces and wheels whir in air, the spokes dissolved through rotation, like those of the spinning wheel in the Velazquez allegory ''The Fable of Arachne.'' At the close, we pass one last time through the studio. A desolate metal menagerie hangs in the wind, and the sculptor is gone, replaced by himself in effigy, a metal shell in welder's goggles. Outside, on a lonely bluff, a bleached buffalo skull sinks into the blowing sands. In these images, nature and art speak to us, and life and death, time and eternity, linked in ways that are as lucid as they are mysterious.</p>
        <p>The beauties of ''The Last Buffalo'' are by no means lost on Bradley J. Wechsler, Imax's co-chairman and co-chief executive with Mr. Gelfond. But his sights are set on the future. ''Rather than think of the successes to date, I think of the potential,'' he says. ''We're looking for a rhetoric, a grammar of the medium, for directors who will do something special.'' (One top director who has reportedly expressed an interest is James Cameron, though his three-hours-plus ''Titanic'' suggests he might find the built-in time constraints rather hard to cope with.)</p>
        <p>Whatever developments may lie ahead, the grammar of the medium is already in place. Any resemblance it bears to the grammar of traditional movies is purely accidental.</p>
        <p>Of the countless streams that feed the ocean of the traditional cinema, none is mightier than the age-old river of storytelling. Traditional movies were born from the union of the proscenium theater and the photograph. The true subject of Imax 3-D is solid geometry: the drama of pure form in pure space.</p>
        <p>Up versus down, round versus flat, shallow versus deep, horizontal versus vertical, hollow versus solid, open versus enclosed: these abstractions (more precisely, the illusion of these abstractions) are the stuff large-format 3-D is made of, as music is made of sounds.</p>
        <p>These are realities to which neither filmmakers nor critics are necessarily in any hurry to awaken. By the standards of ''real'' movies, the celebratory, gauzy saints'-life treatment accorded the entertainers Siegfried and Roy seems overblown, to be sure. But the momentous scale and depth and the exquisite artifice of the imagery are their own reward. By way of illustration, the recurrent motif of a magic clockwork must suffice, at its most impressive at the periphery of one's vision, steering destinies tick by tock by tick.</p>
        <p>Conventional storytelling is less impossible than immaterial, a point driven home by the failure of the Academy Award winner Jean-Jacques Annaud's ''Wings of Courage'' (1995), a true yarn about early attempts -- heroic or foolhardy? -- to fly mail across the Andes. Billed as ''the first dramatic motion picture filmed in Imax 3-D,'' it fielded a solid script and a solid cast of respected Hollywood names, including Tom Hulce, Val Kilmer, Elizabeth McGovern and Craig Sheffer. What anyone who saw the film remembers is a prancing dog, 3-D to the max.</p>
        <p>Similarly, what captured viewers in ''L5: First City in Space'' was not the slender intergalactic rescue tale but the handful of special effects. The preview blew the cover on all of them, a more devastating move than giving away the ending of any story, for there was nothing else, really, to see. And if ''T-Rex'' rules at the box office, the explanation has nothing to do with its toothless sub-''Jurassic Park'' fantasy, but with its king-size in-your-face raptors.</p>
        <p>It is only fair to add that Stephen Low (''The Last Buffalo'') believes that as the costs of filming in large-format 3-D fall, 2-D will go the way of the dinosaurs, silents and black-and-white. ''I believe 3-D is absolutely the cinema of the future,'' he said recently, between dives for his Imax 3-D documentary on undreamt-of life forms that flourish in volcanic vents 14,000 feet below the sea. ''Because we have two eyeballs. Hollywood guys tell me, 'What's really important is the script, not the 3-D.' But the two things have nothing to do with each other. Any script is better in 3-D. It's more like what God gave us. Humans will never be satisfied with flat screens. The pictures aren't real enough.''</p>
        <p>By this reasoning, sculpture would be an inherently superior medium to painting -- not a tenable proposition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Low has an answer to that objection: ''One of the struggles of the great painters in the history of painting has been to make 2-D three-dimensional. The object has been to make the painting come alive. First they had to learn perspective. Then they came up against other barriers. The eye doesn't see everything in focus, so they developed Impressionism to get around that. In every period, artists made the best of their technical limitations. If painters could do it, they would make their paintings 3-D.''</p>
        <p>With respect, I believe the greatest artist in his medium has it wrong. As time goes on, 2-D and 3-D will grow further apart, not closer. The flat screen -- like the stage, like the novel -- is a canvas for storytellers. And large format 3-D -- like architecture, like dance, like absolute music -- is a vehicle for visionaries. Will the medium stay true to itself in the face of commercial necessities? Only time will tell.</p>
        <p>FILM Matthew Gurewitsch writes about the arts for The Wall Street Journal and other publications.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Matthew Gurewitsch writes about the arts for The Wall Street Journal and other publications.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
