<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Artistic Directors Who Ended A Theatrical Brownout</title>
    <meta content="02CRIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Shakespeare Festival</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mccarter Theater (Princeton, NJ)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">George Street Playhouse (New Brunswick, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monte, Bonnie J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mann, Emily</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saint, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Critic's Notebooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3DD1438F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Artistic Directors Who Ended A Theatrical Brownout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein's Critic's Notebook column on successful efforts of artistic directors Bonnie J Monte, Emily Mann and David Saint in breathing new life, respectively, into New Jersey Shakespeare Festival, McCarter Theater in Princeton and George Street Playhouse in New Brunswick; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHY is everything brown?''</p>
        <p>Another Shakespeare, another Coward -- to one of my theatergoing companions in the 80's, the sets always looked brown. The question she posed was as much a legitimate critical comment as an inarguable observation of visual hell. Usually, after Act One, she would take off, to a mall, to visit a friend nearby or just to drive, once in a downpour. Anything was preferable to all that brown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHY is everything brown?''</p>
        <p>Another Shakespeare, another Coward -- to one of my theatergoing companions in the 80's, the sets always looked brown. The question she posed was as much a legitimate critical comment as an inarguable observation of visual hell. Usually, after Act One, she would take off, to a mall, to visit a friend nearby or just to drive, once in a downpour. Anything was preferable to all that brown.</p>
        <p>Then there were other takers of a critic's second ticket, most of them  first-acters as well. ''I'll just wait in the car,'' said one friend during intermission, reducing one who could not ethically walk out in midperformance to echoing the punchline of that old joke about the bad actor  playing ''Hamlet,'' shouting above the audience's boos: ''Look, I didn't write this . . . stuff.''</p>
        <p>Those were the bad old days of the New Jersey Shakespeare Festival. It took the long overdue arrival of the sunny Bonnie J. Monte to bring color and vision and light to a cramped, impossible space. That is what an artistic director can do: effect change in a comatose theater and a deadened audience. And because Ms. Monte was good, patient and passionate, she was rewarded with a renovated theater and a possible dream.</p>
        <p>Emily Mann did it too, and how.  Both in their 10th seasons, Ms. Monte in Madison and Ms. Mann at the McCarter in Princeton wasted no time transforming ailing theaters with a display of theatrical tough love. Now the McCarter is the state's most prestigious theater, infusing classics (including Shakespeare and Coward ) with renewed life, and on a makeshift second stage, imparting immediacy, adventure and love of language with such gripping plays as ''An Almost Holy Picture'' and ''Portia Coughlin.'' Ms. Mann will have a real second stage in a real theater in two more years or so.</p>
        <p>Most recently, another theater came to life. In New Brunswick, the George Street Playhouse suffered onstage mediocrity and, it is no secret, offstage shenanigans of a silly so-called artistic director whose first production was, tellingly, ''Little Shop of Horrors,'' an appalling staging of a musical that once had charm.</p>
        <p>Now in his second season, David Saint has made it eminently clear that the theater he runs is not about  ''enhancement money'' from producers for the purpose of moving them on to a commercial theater, which seemed to be the priority for new play selection for a mostly lamentable nine years. George Street has fast become an art- as opposed to  agenda-driven regional theater, no purse strings attached. And so a 25-year leap from the commonplace to the rare: a first-ever Chekhov (Mark  Nelson's fine ''Seagull,'') a momentous visit by Uta Hagen, a giddy send-up of ''A Christmas Carol,'' with a top- of-the-line ensemble -- all in Mr. Saint's first season. While failures come, forgivably, with the territory, regional theater audiences subscribe to the sensibility of an artistic director and to a body of defining work, not just to single plays.</p>
        <p>On the flip side, the Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn has had no  change in direction since the theater reopened grandly in 1982, the year it should have made a dent as a serious force in musical theater. Yet, it continues to cater to outmoded, dubious tastes, with no spark at the top, instead of enlightening or elevating audiences who are stuck in a time warp. This season's reworked ''Rags'' was a worthy attempt to get real, with an intelligent investigation of the past. As musical theater falters dangerously, here is the very model of a theatre designed, if not destined, to be a far-reaching nonprofit musical theater center. That  recent departures from Paper Mill's pedestrian, limited norm -- ''Follies,'' ''Gypsy,'' ''Rags'' -- failed to take off beyond Millburn, makes one wonder, with regret, the extent to which the officially designated State Theater of New Jersey really matters to the world.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
