<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First the Revolution, Now the Battle for Respect</title>
    <meta content="02MAP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE MAP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Revolutionary War, American (1775-83)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffin, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Demasters, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E1DD1438F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First the Revolution, Now the Battle for Respect</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Karen DeMasters</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Demasters, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Robert Griffin, chairman of New Jersey's Historic New Bridge Landing Park Commission and president of Bergen County Historical Society; he comments on efforts to give site near New Bridge Landing, where pivotal battle of American Revolutionary war took place, recognition it deserves; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More Revolutionary War battles and skirmishes took place on New Jersey soil than anywhere else, and much of that action was in Bergen County near New Bridge Landing, where a pivotal battle took place.</p>
        <p>The house where George Washington issued orders to his fleeing troops is still standing near the wooden bridge, which was  rebuilt with iron in 1889. Yet the site receives little recognition. The Historic New Bridge Landing Park Commission has been formed to seek state and federal funds to preserve artifacts collected by the Bergen County Historical Society and to get the recognition the park commission believes the site deserves. Robert Griffin, park commission chairman and Bergen County Historical Society president, recently talked about the area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More Revolutionary War battles and skirmishes took place on New Jersey soil than anywhere else, and much of that action was in Bergen County near New Bridge Landing, where a pivotal battle took place.</p>
        <p>The house where George Washington issued orders to his fleeing troops is still standing near the wooden bridge, which was  rebuilt with iron in 1889. Yet the site receives little recognition. The Historic New Bridge Landing Park Commission has been formed to seek state and federal funds to preserve artifacts collected by the Bergen County Historical Society and to get the recognition the park commission believes the site deserves. Robert Griffin, park commission chairman and Bergen County Historical Society president, recently talked about the area.</p>
        <p>Q. Why is this site important?</p>
        <p>A. Other Revolutionary War sites in the state were the scene of one battle. New Bridge Landing played a part in the entire Revolution. For six years, this house, now known as the Steuben House, and the land around it changed hands and served as headquarters for both sides. In New Jersey, the Revolutionary War was a civil war that divided families. The house was originally owned by Loyalists who fled when Washington's troops approached.</p>
        <p>The battle that took place on Nov. 20, 1776, was decisive because Washington took command of the colonial army and began a retreat as the British scaled the palisades. If he had not done that, the colonial army would have been captured and that could have been the end of the Revolution.</p>
        <p>Washington's troops escaped over this bridge, which is at the narrowest point of the Hackensack River and was the only land crossing to reach the west in this area. He issued orders standing on this front porch. Thomas Paine was standing on this porch when he was inspired to write the most famous words ever written about the Revolution: ''These are the times that try men's souls.''</p>
        <p>Q. What other significance does the area have?</p>
        <p>A. This same spot has been a commercial hub since Europeans settled here. Schooners left from here loaded with bricks made in New Jersey that were used in the paving of New York City. This house is an example of a unique Jersey Dutch Colonial architecture that developed in this area. And even before that, this was the dividing line between two branches of the Lenapi Indians. So you have history here that goes back, not to the Revolution, but hundreds of years before that.</p>
        <p>Q. Why has it not received more recognition?</p>
        <p>A. For one thing this was the beginning of the Long Retreat, in which Washington led troops across New Jersey into Pennsylvania, so some people may not want to remember that. The British followed the bloody footprints in the snow to track the colonists, many of whom were barefoot.</p>
        <p>Also, in this one area you have land and buildings owned by the state, Bergen County, the historical society and a private foundation. Part of the land is in River Edge, part in New Milford and part in Teaneck. So there was no coordinated effort to do anything, which is why we created the park commission to try to develop the area and preserve what is here.</p>
        <p>Q. What does the commission want to do with the site?</p>
        <p>A. All of this is in danger of being lost. The Steuben house regularly floods. All of the artifacts should be preserved in heat- and humidity-controlled rooms, not just lying around here. These things should be displayed so that visitors can see the stories they tell. We have 16 parking spaces, a one-person staff and no public restrooms.</p>
        <p>KAREN DeMASTERS</p>
        <p>ON THE MAP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
