<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A NIGHT OUT WITH -- A Hangover Therapist; The Evening After</title>
    <meta content="02NITE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Massage</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leptak, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yazigi, Monique P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/A Night Out With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Massage</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E0D71538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A NIGHT OUT WITH -- A Hangover Therapist; The Evening After</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONIQUE P. YAZIGI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yazigi, Monique P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Leptak, graduate student by day, moonlights as masseur who makes house calls in evening hours to stresed-out New Yorkers; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''MAKE it better,'' moaned Dianne Rosenfeld, a 30-something beauty salon entrepreneur, lying on a table in her Upper East Side apartment on a recent evening.</p>
        <p>A bottle of Beaujolais Nouveau she had downed with a friend earlier that day had left her head pounding. Her body ached from working out too much. She was getting over the flu. And she had had a very intense day of shopping. She was in a bad way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''MAKE it better,'' moaned Dianne Rosenfeld, a 30-something beauty salon entrepreneur, lying on a table in her Upper East Side apartment on a recent evening.</p>
        <p>A bottle of Beaujolais Nouveau she had downed with a friend earlier that day had left her head pounding. Her body ached from working out too much. She was getting over the flu. And she had had a very intense day of shopping. She was in a bad way.</p>
        <p>But such complaints are music to the ears of Michael Lepak, a masseur who makes house calls.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lepak, 34, a quiet blond with a strapping physique, works the late shift for Healing Hands, a Manhattan-based company that dispatches its 50 massage therapists for everything from jet lag (a massage while the client inhales beads of eucalyptus) to a breakup (gentle touching and hours of listening). One of his specialties is hangovers.</p>
        <p>A graduate student in social work by day at Fordham University, Mr. Lepak moonlights five nights a week for $130 an hour, plus tip, from about 4 p.m. on. He has been asked to cure headaches and backaches, to help clients feel awake (peppermint scents) and to help them fall asleep (lilac scents).</p>
        <p>He also gets the occasional 2 a.m. call from the Four Seasons Hotel for someone who just flew into town and is suffering from jet lag.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lepak arrived at Ms. Rosenfeld's at 8 p.m. with his green leather massage table, multicolored oils and extra-supple hands. He began setting up her apartment for the hangover cure by dimming the lights, firing up the lilac candles, putting some New Age guitar on the CD player and pouring oil over her body.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ms. Rosenfeld's friend Harry Redlich, who was visiting from Los Angeles, sat on the couch, sipping wine and watching, claiming he had nothing better to do.</p>
        <p>''We must get the toxins to flow out of your body,'' Mr. Lepak said in a soft voice, as his patient lay limp on the table covered with a towel and a black bikini brief. Kneading her left calf, he said: ''We must push around the blood and fluid. We must push all the poison back into the liver and kidney, where it can be purified.''</p>
        <p>That sounded good to Ms. Rosenfeld, whose usual hangover cure is ''getting a cheeseburger and fries.''</p>
        <p>''No, no,'' Mr. Lepak chided. ''After a hangover you must keep the circulation moving. You must drink lots of water. Flush out the system.''</p>
        <p>''This is just decadent New York life,'' pointed out Mr. Redlich, an advertising writer. Indeed, what could be more decadent than having someone ease your ''indulgence stress,'' as Ms. Rosenfeld called it.</p>
        <p>Twirling her toes, Ms. Rosenfeld called out, ''My feet, my feet!'' Mr. Lepak applied lotion to her soles and rubbed her arches. Ms. Rosenfeld, who gets these treatments several times a month, knows feet are the window to the throbbing head.</p>
        <p>Silently he moved from the calves to the neck, never losing his focus, despite the chatter about Prada sales and the loud funk music Mr. Redlich had turned on.</p>
        <p>Finally, Mr. Lepak tapped his client on the back, signaling that she was ready for her eucalyptus bath.</p>
        <p>''Does Michael draw the bath?'' Mr. Redlich asked.</p>
        <p>''No,'' Mr. Lepak said, already packing up his oils and table for his next call. He had to meet a masseuse on the Upper West Side to administer a double good-night massage to a husband and wife.</p>
        <p>At 10:30, he left Ms. Rosenfeld,  who, after the two-hour session, decided she felt revived enough to skip the bath and instead go with her friend for dinner -- and more wine. ''I'll see you again,'' Mr. Lepak called out, his table in tow.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
