<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="02GUID$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD91738F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eleanor Charles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Talking About AIDS</p>
        <p>When Mpule Kwelagobe of Botswana was crowned Miss Universe of 1999, the Miss Universe Organization formed an alliance with the Harvard University AIDS Institute to overcome ignorance of the disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Talking About AIDS</p>
        <p>When Mpule Kwelagobe of Botswana was crowned Miss Universe of 1999, the Miss Universe Organization formed an alliance with the Harvard University AIDS Institute to overcome ignorance of the disease.</p>
        <p>The 19-year-old Ms. Kwelagobe is on a worldwide tour, and she is expected to appear at Real Art Ways in Hartford on Thursday around 3 p.m. during a public reception. The gallery is currently featuring ''Bodies of Resistance,'' an international AIDS awareness exhibition that will travel to South Africa this summer in conjunction with the 13th International AIDS Conference. Later this year the Mpule Kwelagobe Children's Village is to be dedicated in Botswana as a home for 400 children with AIDS.</p>
        <p>Real Art Ways is at 56 Arbor Street. The number to call for more information is (860) 232-1006.</p>
        <p>Mark Twain and Resolutions</p>
        <p>New Year's resolutions were not Mark Twain's forte. ''Every time I reform in one direction, I go overboard in another,'' he wrote in 1866. His foibles are the theme of a scavenger hunt in which children and adults will look for evidence of Twain's bad habits in the writer's home in Hartford. The family program is scheduled on Saturday at 11 to 12:45, and again at 1 to 2:45. Perhaps there will be some of the contraptions on view that would-be inventors brought to him and which he agreed to finance with disastrous results.</p>
        <p>The sessions will begin with readings from Twain's journals and those of his daughters, about their unsuccessful efforts at self-improvement. Tours of the 19-room mansion will then be given, refreshments will be served, and scrapbooks (in which to record the highs and lows of the new year) will be made to take home. .</p>
        <p>The landmark house, at 351 Farmington Avenue, can be reached by following the signs from Exit 46, Sisson Avenue, off Interstate 84 East or West. The number to call for more information is (860) 247-0998, extension 26.</p>
        <p>Woodworking Revealed</p>
        <p>Women in particular are invited to classes in ''Woodworking for Absolute Beginners,'' to be held at the Woodworkers' Club, 215 Westport Avenue (Route 1) in Norwalk on Tuesdays and Thursdays from 7 to 9:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Students who completed the first course last September made deck chairs, the December project was side tables and on Tuesday and Thursday of this week and next week, everyone will make a bookcase.</p>
        <p>The classes, which tend to sell out quickly, are conducted by Aime Fraser, who has spent the last 25 years teaching woodworking, writing articles for woodworking periodicals, and for a time running the boat shop at the Maritime Aquarium in South Norwalk.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fraser is a hands-on instructor, providing the whys as well as the hows, guiding students through the techniques of using cordless drills, screwdrivers, chopsaws and clamps, and explaining how to read plans and buy lumber.</p>
        <p>The fee is $150 and the number for more information or registration is (203) 847-9663. The February-March project is a chair and the fee will be $200.</p>
        <p>Musicians From Belfast</p>
        <p>Craobh Rua (pronounced Creeve Ru-ah) is a traditional Irish band that will perform on Friday at 8 p.m. at the Pequot Library in Southport.</p>
        <p>The four musicians who make up the group are from Belfast, except that Aaron Jones, who lives there and whose family came from there, was born in Scotland and received his music degree from the Royal College in Edinburgh.</p>
        <p>Brian Connolly, who founded Craobh Rua some 15 years ago, learned to play the mandolin at his grandfather's knee. Now he plays the banjo, and, like his colleagues in the group, switches off from such contemporary instruments to the old ones, including the uilleann pipes (Irish bagpipes), tin whistle, fiddle, and bodhran.</p>
        <p>Michael Cassidy has been a fiddler since he was 12, and in the 70's he recorded for Radio Na Gaeltacht. Patrick Davey, former All-Ireland uilleann pipes champion, is also an expert on the flute and whistle. He was classically trained at Queen's University in Belfast, where he earned a bachelor of music degree, and a master's in performance, specializing in 18th-century Baroque music. Tickets are $10, children $5, and may be reserved by calling (203) 256-8453. The library is at 720 Pequot Avenue.</p>
        <p>Creatures of the Sea</p>
        <p>Over the past decade a growing number of harbor seals have been migrating into Long Island Sound each winter from Canada and the Gulf of Maine.</p>
        <p>Along with gray seals and harp seals, as many as 50 to 60 of the various species have been seen at low tide, sunning themselves or resting on the rocks and shoals off Norwalk and Darien.</p>
        <p>As a result, the Maritime Aquarium's Winter Creature Cruises, departing from the aquarium's dock at 10 North Water Street in South Norwalk, have jumped in popularity. For two and a half hours passengers aboard the research vessel Oceanic are regaled with lore and natural history of the seals as well as having such wintering waterfowl as old squaw, buffleheads and mergansers pointed out.</p>
        <p>Dates and times vary with the tide and the weather from now through March, but the general schedule for January is today, 2:30; Jan. 15 and 29, noon; Jan. 16 and 30, 1 p.m. Tickets are $17.50 a person, and since seal watching is done on the open deck, plenty of warm clothing is required. The number to call for reservations or more information is (203) 852-0700, extension 206.</p>
        <p>Notes, Names and Phrases</p>
        <p>Joseph Grigely has an exhibition called ''The Pleasure of Conversing'' on view at the Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford through April 9. And on Thursday at 6 p.m. he will give an informal lecture in the Hartford Courant Room of the museum and be present at the reception to follow.</p>
        <p>His raw materials as an artist are the scraps of paper that people have written to him -- notes, names, phrases -- in order to converse with him. He was deafened as the result of an accident when he was 11 years old. His inscribed conversations are juxtaposed with paintings, glassworks, sculpture and porcelains that he has selected from the Atheneum's collections.</p>
        <p>His work has attracted the attention of several prestigious art institutions. Currently, he has a solo exhibition at the Cranbrook Museum of Art in Bloomfield Hills, Mich., through March 26, and upcoming shows in San Francisco and Bregenz, Germany. Mr. Grigely, who was educated at the National Technical Institute for the Deaf in Rochester, New England College in Arundel, England, and at Oxford University, Mr. Grigely teaches art and art history at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor. He is also the author of ''Textualterity: Art, Theory, and Textual Criticism,'' published by the University of Michigan Press in 1995.</p>
        <p>museum admission is $7, $5 for students and people 62 and older, $3 for children 6 through 17. Admission is free on Thursdays, and until noon on Saturdays. The museum, at 600 Main Street in downtown Hartford, is open Tuesday through Sunday from 11 to 5. (860) 278-2670.</p>
        <p>ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
