<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aiming for an Inclusive Bull Run</title>
    <meta content="02PROF$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRIVATE SECTOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Jesse L Jr (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Jesse L (Rev)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">It's About the Money (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5DB1238F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aiming for an Inclusive Bull Run</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jesse L Jackson Jr, congressman and son of Rev Jessie L Jackson, is promoting his cause to get African Americans into Wall Street and compelete passage from sharecropper to shareholder; toward this end, he and his father have written book, It's About the Money, which is a how-to manual on investing and personal financial management aimed primarily at minority Americans who Jacksons says have largely missed out on one of greatest bull markets in history; photo of Jacksons (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JESSE L. JACKSON JR., the 34-year-old congressman and son of the Rev. Jesse L. Jackson, is not talking politics this morning, nor is he talking civil rights.</p>
        <p>Instead, the topic is investing, and he is talking about 401(k) retirement plans and mutual funds, describing the benefits of dollar cost averaging and explaining how African-Americans are finally going to reach Wall Street, fulfilling what he and his father call a long journey from sharecropper to shareholder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JESSE L. JACKSON JR., the 34-year-old congressman and son of the Rev. Jesse L. Jackson, is not talking politics this morning, nor is he talking civil rights.</p>
        <p>Instead, the topic is investing, and he is talking about 401(k) retirement plans and mutual funds, describing the benefits of dollar cost averaging and explaining how African-Americans are finally going to reach Wall Street, fulfilling what he and his father call a long journey from sharecropper to shareholder.</p>
        <p>''I would like to spread the message of financial independence to African-Americans,'' the congressman says  over a breakfast of eggs Benedict at the Swiss Hotel. ''I want to market these concepts, these time-honored traditions of how to build wealth in America.''</p>
        <p>He is doing this in a new book he has written  with his father, ''It's About the Money'' (Times Business, $23).</p>
        <p>The book, published last month, is a how-to manual on investing and personal financial management aimed primarily at minority Americans, who the Jacksons say have largely missed out on one of the greatest bull markets in history.</p>
        <p>Ask Representative Jackson why he and his father have ventured into a field populated by so many Wall Street wizards, and you'll get a funny look, a stare. The reply: Why not?</p>
        <p>Representative Jackson has an undergraduate degree in business from North Carolina A &amp; T and says he taught seminars in financial management when he worked at Rainbow/PUSH Coalition, his father's civil rights organization in Chicago. And the elder Mr. Jackson, who has made ''economic justice'' a pillar of his activism, is now heading up the Wall Street Project, a campaign to lobby big business and Wall Street financiers to share their wealth and expand minority business-people's access to capital.</p>
        <p>Representative Jackson, a husky man who, like his father, was once a high school football star, calls the book the shared vision of father and son. The lessons are simple: the Jacksons discourage the use of credit cards, warn about investment scams and predatory lenders and encourage readers to make disciplined financial choices and to squirrel away money for retirement. Perhaps most emphatically, they recommend investing in the financial markets.</p>
        <p>''We've attempted to do this in our own home,'' Representative Jackson said, ''and this is our opportunity to show how others can become responsible with their own finances.''</p>
        <p>For too long, he said, his target audience has been wasting money on things like lottery tickets. His father likes to say that blacks have ''more confidence in a bear lotto than a bull market.''  Representative Jackson says their book faces the dual challenge of trying to reach an audience that  neither reads much nor trusts the stock market -- an audience that would rather spend than save.</p>
        <p>''We're talking about breaking some century-old habits,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The book provides few clues about the Jacksons' own experiences in the world of finance, beyond the elder Mr. Jackson's anecdotes about his mother struggling to make ends meet.</p>
        <p>Instead, it reads like so many other personal finance guides. Written with the help of Mary Gotschall, a financial journalist, it includes a fair amount of reference material like telephone numbers for various agencies and anodyne tips like ''always write out a check in ink'' or ''if anyone says you can receive a high return without risk, be suspicious.''</p>
        <p>(The authors are unlikely to get rich from the book; according to the congressman, his father and Ms. Gotschall split a $60,000 advance; Representative Jackson will draw the first $60,000 in royalties, with any remainder to be shared by the three writers.)</p>
        <p>Representative Jackson's introduction to the world of investing came while he was in law school at the University of Illinois in 1991. He saw an infomercial for an investment seminar being led by Charles J. Givens, the author of ''Wealth Without Risk.'' He bought the book and attended one of Mr. Givens's seminars. ''I learned more about personal finance in an hour-and-a-half seminar than I had in three years in business school,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He and his wife, Sandi, noticed, though, that they were the only blacks in an audience of about 800 people. Now he is trying to remedy that imbalance.</p>
        <p>Representative Jackson wants low-wage workers to jump in, too. ''There are some things that people who earn $30,000 can do to significantly change the quality of their lives,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''But I want to offer one caveat,'' he added. ''In no way am I suggesting that 'It's About the Money' is the answer to solving poverty in America. I believe the only way to solve poverty in America is to have a comprehensive full-employment program.'' He went on for a few more minutes before realizing that he was no longer talking the investing talk.</p>
        <p>But he is walking the walk, he said. He is following his own advice, putting money away now, because his wife, a lawyer, is seven months pregnant. With his daughter due soon, he said it's important ''to invest $50 or $100 a month for her to go to the college of her choice.''</p>
        <p>Before he entered Congress in 1995, he said, he was an ''aggressive'' investor. Now, a financial adviser handles all of his investments.</p>
        <p>Still, he says he's always looking for a good investment. As he walks onto the sidewalk after breakfast, he greets a group of men who shout out things like ''say hello to the Reverend for me.'' Then he puts his cellular telephone earplug in place and walks away, only to trot back.</p>
        <p>''Wait,'' he calls out. ''One more thing. Invest in antiques! That was something I learned from my mother.''</p>
        <p>PRIVATE SECTOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
