<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From/New Haven; A Tribute to the Quinnipiac Indians Who Served as Guides and Teachers</title>
    <meta content="02VIEW$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Quinnipiac Indians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Townshend, Harry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Townshend, Deb</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oliver, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Libby, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E7DE1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From/New Haven; A Tribute to the Quinnipiac Indians Who Served as Guides and Teachers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM LIBBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Libby, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Monument to Quinnipiac Indians, New Haven's first settlers, is planned for Fort Wooster Park in city's East Shore section; Quinnipiac Memorial Monument Projectto raise $27,000for monument has been formed by Patricia Oliver and Deb and Harry Townshend; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST as the settlers of Plymouth, Mass., would have died without the help of the Wampanouag Indians, New Haven's first settlers would have perished during their first winter in 1638 without the help of the Quinnipiac Indians.</p>
        <p>The name Quinnipiac, which means People of the Long Water Land, is still found throughout the state -- on the river that flows through New Haven, on a college and on several businesses. There is no monument dedicated to the tribe, however, and  Priscilla Oliver, Deb and Harry Townshend, whose grandfather was an early historian of the tribe, are trying to change that. They have formed the Quinnipiac Memorial Monument Project to raise $27,000 to place a monument in the city. So far, they've raised about $18,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST as the settlers of Plymouth, Mass., would have died without the help of the Wampanouag Indians, New Haven's first settlers would have perished during their first winter in 1638 without the help of the Quinnipiac Indians.</p>
        <p>The name Quinnipiac, which means People of the Long Water Land, is still found throughout the state -- on the river that flows through New Haven, on a college and on several businesses. There is no monument dedicated to the tribe, however, and  Priscilla Oliver, Deb and Harry Townshend, whose grandfather was an early historian of the tribe, are trying to change that. They have formed the Quinnipiac Memorial Monument Project to raise $27,000 to place a monument in the city. So far, they've raised about $18,000.</p>
        <p>''At present there are no monuments for any American Indians anywhere in New Haven,'' said John DeStefano, the New Haven mayor. ''It's good that this is being corrected, and it's only fitting that the first monument to American Indians is for the Quinnipiac. It should be remembered that the Quinnipiac and the assistance they gave to the first English settlers made the establishment of this city, this 'new' haven possible. The monument will remind us that this city is built on the contributions of many different cultures.''</p>
        <p>The city has given permission for the monument to be placed in Fort Wooster Park in the East Shore section, where the tribe once had its 1,200-acre reservation. The monument, which is expected to be erected by the summer, will be a 6-foot-by-10 foot piece of black granite. Peter Horbrick, a local sculptor, will etch the design, which Mr. Townshend said will depict a Quinnipiac family, walking down the trail that is now Townsend Avenue to greet the first English settlers who arrived on April 24, 1638.</p>
        <p>Efforts to reconsecrate the tribe's burial ground and sites that the tribe considered sacred in the East Shore section will be continued as part of the memorial project.  So will efforts to trace living descendants of the tribe, which genealogists have so far been unable to do. ''The Quinnipiac weren't ferocious warriors,'' said Harry Townshend, whose ancestors have lived in East Shore since the 1600's. ''They were peaceful people who mostly farmed and collected shellfish, and pretty much got along with everybody.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Townshend's grandfather, Capt. Charles Hervey Townshend, who lived from 1833 to 1900, was a historian who wrote about the Quinnipiacs. He told of the epidemics that decimated the tribe in the early 1600's, when they made first contact with Dutch fur traders and other Europeans. When the English arrived, the population continued to fall. The Quinnipiac sold land and food that was no longer needed by their rapidly declining population.</p>
        <p>''During the early years of New Haven,'' writes the historian, John Menta, ''the Quinnipiacs traded deer meat to the colonists, who were unskilled in hunting. In imitation of the Indians, the English built weirs to catch fish.</p>
        <p>''The Quinnipiac served as guides, messengers, traded canoes, killed wolves that preyed on livestock, and taught the whites how to fish and clam.</p>
        <p>''By the mid 19th-century, the tribe had dwindled, migrated, and disintegrated,'' Mr. Menta writes. The few individuals who remained worked for the farmers who had bought the tribe's reservation lands.</p>
        <p>''The Quinnipiacs were here until the 1860's,'' said Mr. Townshend. ''The intent of the monument is to note that they were here, that they developed and lived in a sophisticated and unique culture. Were it not for the Quinnipiac, the English settlers would not have survived. And that this was their last stronghold.'' Among the artifacts of the Quinnipiac found in the East Shore section is a six-pound spear head made of the mineral jasper.</p>
        <p>''The closest place where you could find this type of jasper is in Montana,'' he said. ''It probably was only used for ceremonial purposes. And it shows how extensive the trade routes were.''</p>
        <p>Inspired by the artifacts, Mr. Townshend has learned the techniques by which the Quinnipiac chipped quartz, flint, granite and obsidian to make tools and weapons.</p>
        <p>''Thanksgiving Rock,'' a boulder on the north side of the East Shore section is where the tribe had its harvest celebration and where offerings were burnt to the creator, whom the Quinnipiacs called Catontawit, said Ms. Townshend. The Townshends are seeking a state historic designation for the rock.</p>
        <p>The University of Pennsylvania at Philadelphia has a skull that is labeled as a Mohegan/Quinnipiac, Ms. Townshend said. The Mohegan Tribe's Cultural Resources Department has been contacted in the hope that the federally recognized tribe will assist in reburying the remains and reconsecrating the Quinnipiac's burial ground in Fort Wooster Park, she said.</p>
        <p>Also on the monument will be the totems, or signature marks, of the principal Quinnipiacs who signed the first treaties with the English. On the reverse side of the black granite memorial, which will be about two foot thick, will be the names of the Quinnipiac's historians, Capt. Townshend, Mr. Menta, and Lyent W. Russell.</p>
        <p>''It's important that the Quinnipiacs' role in our history is recognized and acknowledged,'' said Nicholas Bellantoni, the Connecticut state archeologist. ''We live in a future-oriented society, which tends to lose its past very quickly,'' he added. ''If it weren't for the memorial monument and the historic researchers which the monument will also recognize, memory of the Quinnipiac and their contribution could so easily be lost.</p>
        <p>''The Quinnipiac helped the English make the most vital physical adaptions to this place.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
