<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witness</title>
    <meta content="02CARROLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carroll, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wiesel, Elie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wiesel, Marion</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">And the Sea Is Never Full (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DC1E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Carroll</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carroll, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Carroll reviews book And the Sea Is Never Full: Memoirs, 1969- by Elie Wiesel; translated by Marion Wiesel; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AND THE SEA</p>
        <p>IS NEVER FULL</p>
        <p>Memoirs, 1969- .</p>
        <p>By Elie Wiesel.</p>
        <p>Translated by Marion Wiesel.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 429 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AND THE SEA</p>
        <p>IS NEVER FULL</p>
        <p>Memoirs, 1969- .</p>
        <p>By Elie Wiesel.</p>
        <p>Translated by Marion Wiesel.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 429 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
        <p>''In 1970,'' Elie Wiesel tells us in this memoir, ''I spoke of my intention to end my testimony.'' He had just published his ninth book, ''One Generation After''; in this new book he quotes from it: ''And now, teller of tales, turn the page. Speak to us of other things.'' But Wiesel did not stop speaking of the Holocaust. Instead, his became an even more passionate and, to some, problematic voice, obsessed with the subject. Ubiquitous in print and before microphones, he has insisted both that ''the Holocaust defies language and art'' and that language and art ''are necessary to tell the history that must be told.'' Silence, as it turned out, was no option.</p>
        <p>He was 16 when American soldiers found him among the living dead of Buchenwald. In his new book, he writes of the understanding he and his fellow inmates had come to: ''The one among us who would survive would testify for all of us. He would speak and demand justice on our behalf; as our spokesman he would make certain that our memory would penetrate that of humanity. He would do nothing else.'' The young Wiesel, as a writer and teacher, came to embody, for non-Jews as for Jews, the Holocaust's penetration of Western consciousness, if not conscience.</p>
        <p>Since 1970, Wiesel has published 24 works, sometimes with co-authors. The first volume of his memoirs, ''All Rivers Run to the Sea,'' the story of his life up to 1969, was published in 1995. ''And the Sea Is Never Full'' -- the two titles complete a verse from Ecclesiastes -- picks up the story. A simple listing of events that serve as the story's pegs partly indicates why Wiesel found it impossible to end his testimony: the Yom Kippur war in 1973, the television mini-series ''Holocaust,'' the Lebanon war, Ronald Reagan's visit to the Bitburg cemetery, the controversy over Kurt Waldheim, the intifada, the apparent suicide of Primo Levi, the end of the Soviet Union, the opening of the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum in Washington, ''Schindler's List,'' the Balkans. These events revealed the ways in which the Nazi genocide has become a point of moral, political and cultural reference in America.</p>
        <p>In ''The Holocaust in American Life,'' the historian Peter Novick said of Wiesel, ''The relationship between his eminence and the rise of Holocaust consciousness is clearly circular, with no way of distinguishing cause from effect.'' Wiesel's status as the avatar of remembrance was confirmed when he was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1986; it was then, too, that he joined the small circle of world celebrity, becoming the intimate of presidents and the figurehead of numerous high-minded movements.</p>
        <p>The significance of all of this for Jews, non-Jews and Wiesel himself has been profoundly ambiguous. Wiesel has been at the center of arguments about the proper place of the Holocaust in our overly commercialized culture, and about victimization as a defining note of Judaism. He has been rebuked for being too attached to Israel and for not living there (an American citizen, he has made his home in the United States since 1956). His insistence on the uniqueness of the Holocaust has been taken to denigrate the suffering of others, like the millions of Ukrainian victims of Stalin's terror-famine. Many believers, especially among Christians, resent his insistence that the perpetrators can never be forgiven, and others reject the clear implication of his work that even this evil can be redeemed by memory and prayer. His writing has been neglected by critics even as his fame has been exploited by the self-interested.</p>
        <p>''And the Sea Is Never Full'' is a gift to readers who ask the question, where in all this is the man who grew from that 16-year-old boy. The book draws often from Wiesel's contemporaneous journals, but his first observations serve as later occasions of shrewd analysis. His pointed descriptions of encounters with major figures of the age -- Carter, Reagan, Walesa, Gorbachev, Cardinal Lustiger of Paris, Mitterrand, Milosevic, Clinton -- show his constant struggle to align properly the use of his fame with the advancement of his cause. These meetings often verged on the confrontational, and the image of Wiesel that emerged from press reports tended to be that of a self-anointed prophet. Wiesel's own account lays bare his doubts, fears and readiness to outdo his critics in rebuking himself. But in almost every instance, Wiesel's rendition makes clear that he kept faith with himself and with those he left behind in the death camps. His written and spoken interventions in their behalf add up to an exercise of moral authority that stands alone.</p>
        <p>''And the Sea Is Never Full'' is an intimate book that suggests how all of this came to be possible. For one thing, Wiesel carries the memory of his father everywhere -- his father who was, as he says, ''humiliated before my eyes'': ''I see myself once again on the last day of his life. . . . He called me. . . . His cries tore me apart; they tear me apart still. In spite of the danger, I should have gone to him. . . . I would have been killed. I was afraid then. And I am afraid now.'' The capacity to acknowledge this remorse and fear, rooted in the past, provides half the structure of Wiesel's moral center. The other half comes from the future, for Wiesel is also never far, affectively, from his son. When Wiesel received the Nobel Prize in 1986, his son Elisha was with him on the podium. Elisha, born in 1972, was by then nearly the age Wiesel was when the Nazis took him, and when Wiesel did not respond to his own father's cries.</p>
        <p>Elie Wiesel writes in French. His English translator is his wife, Marion Wiesel. Her presence in ''And the Sea Is Never Full,'' as in Wiesel's life, is steady and bracing. And her presence is not unrelated to the question with which we began: Why was Wiesel unable to fall silent in 1970? He and Marion married in 1969. Wiesel has spoken of his failure to rescue his father. He adds here that the whole world failed, which ''long made me fear having a child. . . . It was Marion who persuaded me otherwise. It was wrong to give the killers one more victory.''</p>
        <p>James Carroll's most recent book is his memoir, ''An American Requiem: God, My Father and the War That Came Between Us.'' He is at work on a history of conflict between Christians and Jews.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Carroll's most recent book is his memoir, ''An American Requiem: God, My Father and the War That Came Between Us.'' He is at work on a history of conflict between Christians and Jews.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
