<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dec. 26 - Jan. 1; A Rough Night on the Town</title>
    <meta content="02BOXA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE1DD1338F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="352" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dec. 26 - Jan. 1; A Rough Night on the Town</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sean (Puffy) Combs has the indisputable ability to attract attention. The rap impresario throws lavish parties, drapes himself in furs and jewelry, dates the movie star Jennifer Lopez and all but begs people to look his way. Some say this is a job requirement for a hip-hop star; others find it a tad excessive.</p>
        <p>Last week Mr. Combs, 30, attracted more attention -- the unwanted kind -- when he was arrested after an early-morning shootout in a Manhattan nightclub. The arrest led to inevitable newspaper photographs depicting Mr. Combs skulking away from a police station.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sean (Puffy) Combs has the indisputable ability to attract attention. The rap impresario throws lavish parties, drapes himself in furs and jewelry, dates the movie star Jennifer Lopez and all but begs people to look his way. Some say this is a job requirement for a hip-hop star; others find it a tad excessive.</p>
        <p>Last week Mr. Combs, 30, attracted more attention -- the unwanted kind -- when he was arrested after an early-morning shootout in a Manhattan nightclub. The arrest led to inevitable newspaper photographs depicting Mr. Combs skulking away from a police station.</p>
        <p>The police say a club patron taunted Mr. Combs by throwing a wad of money at the multimillionaire. Mr. Combs and a young protege pulled out guns, they say, but only the protege pulled his trigger. Three bystanders were shot and wounded in the confusion that ensued, while Mr. Combs and Ms. Lopez fled in a sports-utility vehicle that ran 11 red lights before being pulled over.</p>
        <p>Police say they found a gun in the car that had not been fired, but it was loaded -- and stolen. Mr. Combs, his driver and his bodyguard were charged with criminal possession of a weapon, while his protege was charged with attempted murder. Mr. Combs later held a news conference to strongly deny having anything to do with the shootout or with guns.</p>
        <p>Still, the episode resurrected doubts about the rap star's judgment. In April, for example, Mr. Combs and two associates beat up a record executive who had angered him; he later pleaded guilty to a violation. The arrest also comes at a time when record sales for his Bad Boy Entertainment empire have slipped.</p>
        <p>As for questions about Mr. Combs's performance as a role model, his friend and business colleague Andre Harrell said, ''When you judge Sean against his peers, he's not doing such a bad job.''</p>
        <p>DAN BARRY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
