<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Never Just Black Or White</title>
    <meta content="02CONT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE CONTRARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Insurance Information Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Akst, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldstein, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Contrary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EEDE1238F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Never Just Black Or White</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL AKST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Akst, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Akst (On the Contrary) article, noting controversy over racial profiling of motorists by police, says some businesses conduct their own forms of profiling with evident impunity; says among them is practice by insurance companies of charging young men higher premiums for automobile insurance; Steven Goldstein, spokesman for Insurance Information Institute, says there are no statistics that show one race is more likely to have more accidents than the other (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ads are stark. Created by the American Civil Liberties Union in its battle against racial profiling by the police, they show a white face and a black one, side by side, followed by a question: ''Which man looks guilty?''</p>
        <p>To the insurance industry, the answer is both of them. While the police practice of stopping minority motorists solely on account of their race has rightly been condemned, some businesses conduct their own forms of profiling with evident impunity. Among them is the practice of charging young men higher premiums for automobile insurance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ads are stark. Created by the American Civil Liberties Union in its battle against racial profiling by the police, they show a white face and a black one, side by side, followed by a question: ''Which man looks guilty?''</p>
        <p>To the insurance industry, the answer is both of them. While the police practice of stopping minority motorists solely on account of their race has rightly been condemned, some businesses conduct their own forms of profiling with evident impunity. Among them is the practice of charging young men higher premiums for automobile insurance.</p>
        <p>For years, men up to age 25 or even 30 have been guilty until proven older. They are automatically hit with higher insurance rates because, as a group, they have more accidents -- a rationale that sounds suspiciously like the police practice, widely denied and just as widely criticized, of stopping young black and Hispanic men because, as a group, they are more likely to commit crimes.</p>
        <p>As a former payer of high auto rates based not only on my age but also on my unmarried status at the time, it always struck me as strange that the insurance industry didn't go further. Isn't it possible that left-handed drivers, in a world made for righties, may be more accident-prone? Or that short people, perhaps less able to see the road, may also be riskier risks? For that matter, do we know for sure that different races and religious groups don't have differing claims experiences?</p>
        <p>The insurance industry maintains that it charges different premiums for different people based only on strong evidence of different loss levels. But insurance companies don't seem to be trying very hard to find out, say, whether left-handed Zoroastrians or short white people make good or bad drivers.</p>
        <p>''There are no statistics that show that one race is likely to have more accidents than the other,'' said Steven Goldstein, a spokesman for the Insurance Information Institute, a trade group in New York. ''That's something that has not been studied by the insurance industry and I don't think it will be studied. People would find such a study unacceptable.''</p>
        <p>And, Mr. Goldstein noted, the insurance industry isn't the only one that penalizes the young and presumably reckless. Just look at the rental car industry, he suggested. Indeed, a spokeswoman for Hertz said that, except in New York State, where such policies are forbidden, her company and its major competitors turn away customers of both sexes who are under 25.</p>
        <p>But the rental car companies at least act without regard to whether a customer is a man or woman. How is it that the insurance companies, like the police, are allowed to make judgments about groups based on sex and age but not race?</p>
        <p>One reason may be that this kind of pricing is taken for granted. And it may even be defended as appropriate -- auto insurers and car rental companies have a plausible rationale for treating young people differently, for instance.</p>
        <p>But what possible justification, then, can there be for that granddaddy of discriminatory pricing, the senior citizen discount? These discounts amount to a tax on youth. They also are racially discriminatory: as a group, white women live substantially longer than black men, who are therefore less likely to get the discount.</p>
        <p>Though senior discounts are apparently sacred, other forms of pricing bias are under attack. Several cities and states, for example, have considered or adopted legislation aimed at preventing dry cleaners and hairdressers from charging women more than men, even though businesses in these fields say that women's blouses and heads are more costly to work on.</p>
        <p>As for auto insurance, the industry shows no signs of charging on the basis of height, hair color or especially ethnicity, but the industry is getting more creative in rating the risks posed by its customers. Some insurers, for example, have begun taking a driver's credit rating into account when figuring premiums, because statistically, people with bad credit have more accidents.</p>
        <p>In American life, race remains the great taboo, and gender profiling will fly when racial profiling won't. Just ask the American Civil Liberties Union. Its ads show the faces of two men, after all, not women. Like the police, the A.C.L.U. assumes that if somebody's guilty, it has to be a he.</p>
        <p>ON THE CONTRARY Daniel Akst is a novelist and financial journalist. His column tilting at conventional business wisdom appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daniel Akst is a novelist and financial journalist. His column tilting at conventional business wisdom appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
