<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bikers Leap Into the Heart of Woodbury</title>
    <meta content="02BIKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Woodbury (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sommer, Mimi G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EED91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1208" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bikers Leap Into the Heart of Woodbury</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIMI G. SOMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sommer, Mimi G</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on new biking trail for teenage stunt bikers in Woodbury, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WOODBURY, a southeastern Litchfield County town known for antiquing, colonial charm and preserving open land within its borders, has decided that teenage stunt bikers deserve a place of their own.</p>
        <p>Last August, after a yearlong lobbying campaign by the teenagers themselves, town officials agreed to establish a biking area on five acres in Orenaug Park; the site is at the edge of the 90-acre park, just up the road from the Woodbury Public Library, the Woodbury Police Headquarters and near town office buildings and schools. The central location affords the bikers privacy and access to community support services, should they need assistance as they put their BMX (which stands for bicycle motocross) bikes through their paces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WOODBURY, a southeastern Litchfield County town known for antiquing, colonial charm and preserving open land within its borders, has decided that teenage stunt bikers deserve a place of their own.</p>
        <p>Last August, after a yearlong lobbying campaign by the teenagers themselves, town officials agreed to establish a biking area on five acres in Orenaug Park; the site is at the edge of the 90-acre park, just up the road from the Woodbury Public Library, the Woodbury Police Headquarters and near town office buildings and schools. The central location affords the bikers privacy and access to community support services, should they need assistance as they put their BMX (which stands for bicycle motocross) bikes through their paces.</p>
        <p>The biking area is being transformed into a landscape of adventure by the students themselves, who are out at the park most days after school shoveling and packing soil into mounds and banks of varying heights and shapes. They hope to be done with the work by August. The area has a natural slope that propels bikers downward on their course and allows them the speed to ''get air'' as they say, when they leap over small hills.</p>
        <p>Recently at the park, Real Sprague, a 15-year-old 10th grader at Nonnewaug High School, and a skillful BMX biker said: ''It takes a lot of hard work and dedication to get these obstacles formed, and to keep them the way they are. We planned it in our head. We discussed what we wanted. After school, whenever we have a chance, mid-spring to late fall, we ride the trails.''</p>
        <p>The need for a site stemmed from the students' passion for the sport, and from difficulties encountered by them and the community when the biking posed obvious risks for pedestrians and traffic on school and town property. Stunt biking is considered an extreme sport, though not in the same league with sky diving or bungee jumping.</p>
        <p>The bikers are mostly boys age 12 to 18 who have watched the BMX biking events shown on ESPN and gone to bike camps.</p>
        <p>Jay Paparazzo, a 16-year-old 11th grader, who was a spokesman for the bikers' course over a yearlong lobbying process that began in August 1998, described the site as ''a formed-out track of jumps and berms'' and the BMX bike, he said, is ''made out of harder steels, so that the bike will stand the pressure of jumps. There are no speeds on the bike. You go as fast as you can pedal.''</p>
        <p>Bikes range in price from $200 to about $800. Often students buy a frame and add expensive parts to it.</p>
        <p>Erma Miller, the national field director of the National Bicycle League in Hilliard, Ohio, said BMX biking started in the early 1970's in California with a handful of teenagers who were imitating motorcyclists who raced on dirt trails. It wasn't long before it began to be an organized sport, she said. Ms. Miller said the the combined membership for the two sanctioning bodies of BMX racing, the National Bicycle League and the American Bicycle League, is 100,000-plus.</p>
        <p>The Woodbury BMX bikers, who total about 30, said they prefer non-competitive biking.</p>
        <p>''We built the trails with everyone's level of ability in mind, so we could all have fun,'' said Aaron Vroom, a 12th-grader and experienced rider.</p>
        <p>Monique Shay, mother of Woodbury Middle School seventh-grader Ryan Shay, spearheaded the process that led to the course.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot in towns for elementary school children and pre-schoolers. There's not a lot for the 12- to 18-year-olds, unless you go to organized sports, but not all kids want to play soccer or baseball or travel to play.  It's not just the activity, it's the friendships that evolve, the healthy outdoor atmosphere that binds them, building the bikes, building the trails, fixing the bikes, maintaining the tools. It's like a passage to manhood.''</p>
        <p>She brought her concerns to Dr. Linda Demikat, the Woodbury Middle School's principal, who agreed something should be done for the bikers.  Dr. Demikat called Woodbury's First Selectman Richard Crane, who was receptive to the bikers' quest.</p>
        <p>The Woodbury Parks and Recreation Department investigated potential biking sites and held meetings at which the bikers laid out their plans. Jay Paparzzo, who spoke for the teenagers, said: ''We wanted some land and dirt and shovels to build our track. We had a new sport we wanted to introduce.''</p>
        <p>Kay Paoli, a Parks and Recreation commissioner, accompanied several bikers on rounds of the neighborhood adjacent to the planned biker's track before the town approved the trails. Any fears that neighbors had were allayed when the students invited them to see the trails.</p>
        <p>One neighbor, Richard Burmeister, lives two properties away from where the trails are. He said he was approached by two students and Ms. Paoli to ease any concerns he might have.</p>
        <p>''The kids were polite, respectful and explained what they were doing,'' Mr. Burmeister said. ''And I had no ojections.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Paoli said the students were determined. ''They wanted something,'' she said. ''They used the proper channels to get it, and now they're responsible for it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shay applied for funds for bikers' tools and equipment from Woodbury Middle School's Youth Leadership Program. Kay Wester, the school social worker and director of the youth program, had received a three-year grant of $6,000 annually for positive youth programs from the Waterbury Foundation, a nonprofit organization designed to improve the lives of Connecticut's northwestern citizens. The bikers were granted $1,300 from that fund to purchase tools and equipment, such as shovels and helmets. In the future the bikers can reapply to the youth leadership program for funds and raise money with events such as bikers' exhibitions.</p>
        <p>O &amp; G Industries of Southbury and Woodbury donated the soil for the bikers' course and the Woodbury Public Works Department delivered the material to the park.</p>
        <p>Mark Blanchard, Parks and Recreation Department director, acts as a consultant to the bikers, helping them plan trails that do not require the removal of existing trees, which keeps the operation environmentally friendly. The use of the land is contingent upon the bikers' adherence to Parks and Recreation Department rules, which include respecting park hours, wearing helmets, abstaining from alcohol and maintaining a clean park.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crane, the town's first selectman, said that though there have been two biking injuries near and in the park since August, the park's insurance premiums have not increased since the bikers' arrival, and that there is minimal risk.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crane said: ''We wanted the kids to have a sense of ownership.  This is what they wanted to do.  They'll have to be their own policemen. The core responsibility for this project goes to the young bikers.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
