<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>You Must Remember This</title>
    <meta content="02ORAN0AB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSPECTIVE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4D91138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>You Must Remember This</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carl Nelson</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE SPORTS WORLD OF THE 20TH CENTURY embraced everyone form Babe Ruth to Kobe Bryant. It was crammed with thrills and disappointments and was punctuated by the fantastic finishes that left millions of sports fans holding their breaths, always believing that it's not over till it's over and that somehow their heroes would win. Here are some snapshots of moments that brought tears of joy and despair.</p>
        <p>BY CARL NELSON</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE SPORTS WORLD OF THE 20TH CENTURY embraced everyone form Babe Ruth to Kobe Bryant. It was crammed with thrills and disappointments and was punctuated by the fantastic finishes that left millions of sports fans holding their breaths, always believing that it's not over till it's over and that somehow their heroes would win. Here are some snapshots of moments that brought tears of joy and despair.</p>
        <p>BY CARL NELSON</p>
        <p>JORDAN RULES</p>
        <p>In his last game, Michael Jordan sinking an 18-foot jumper over Utah's Bryon Russell that gave the Bulls their sixth world title of the 1990's. (June 14, 1998)</p>
        <p>MIRACLE ON ICE  The United States Olympicd hockey team, a collection of unheralded amateurs led by goal-tender Jim craig and captain Mike Eruzione, stunned the Soviet Union, 4-3 in a medal-round game. The U.S. then won the gold medal by defeating Finland, 4-2. (Feb. 22, 1980)</p>
        <p>THE SHOT HEARD ROUND THE WORLD  Bobby Thomson hitting a three-run homer off the Dodgers' Ralph Branca in the bottom of the ninth inning to vault the Giants into the World Series. (Oct. 3, 1951)</p>
        <p>RUMBLE IN THE JUNGLE  Muhammad Ali used an unusual tactic, the rope-a-dope, to score an eighth-round knockout of the defending champion George Foreman in Zaire. It was Ali's second of three world heavyweight championships. (Oct. 30, 1974)</p>
        <p>HOMETOWN HERO  Bill Mazeroski of Pittsburgh being greeted after hitting a leadoff ninth-inning home run off the Yankees' Ralph Terry. it was the first time a World Series ended with a home run. (Oct. 13 1960)</p>
        <p>THE KICK  The Saints' Tom Dempsey, born without a right hand and part of his right foot, booming a record 63-yard field goal to feat the Lions. (Nov. 8, 1970)</p>
        <p>NEVER GIVE UP  Coach Jim Valvano celebrating North carolina State's national title after Lorenzo Charles dunked Dereck Whittenburg's 35-foot air ball, ending the 26-gaming winning streak of Houston, a.k.a. Phi Slama Jama. (April 4, 1983)</p>
        <p>ICE BOWL  On the frozen tundra of Lambeau Field (wind chill -46 degrees) Bart Starr's quarterback sneak gave Green Bay its third consecutive N.F.L. title. Two weeks later, the Packers defeated Oakland in Super Bowl II. (Dec. 31, 1967)</p>
        <p>THE WAVE  Carlton Fisk coaxing leadoff fly ball that ricocheted off the foul pole, giving Boston a 7-6 12-inning victory over Cincinnati in Game 6 of World Series. the Reds won Game 7, 4-3. (Oct. 22, 1975)</p>
        <p>THE CATCH  Dwight Clark making a fingertip grab from Joe Montana that propelled the 49ers into their first Super Bowl. They would go on to win five Super Bowls. (Jan. 10 1982)</p>
        <p>THE PASS  Gerard Phelan awaiting 48-yard touchdown pass from roommate Doug Flutie that gave Boston College at 47-45 victory over the defending national champion Miami Hurricanes. (Nov. 23 1984)</p>
        <p>THE CURSE  The Red Sox were one strike away from their first World Series title since 1918 when the Mets tied the score on a wild pitch. Mookie Wilson's grounder then went through Bill Buckner's legs to give the Mets the Game 6 victory. The rest is history. (Oct. 25, 1986)</p>
        <p>IMMACULATE RECEPTION  The Steelers' Franco Harris eluding the Raiders' Jimmy Warren for the game-winning touchdown in an A.F.C. playoff game. Harris snared a pass that had ricocheted near his shoetops. (Dec. 23 1972)</p>
        <p>DYNASTY IS BORN  A jubilant BobbyNystrom and Lorne Henning after Nystrom's overtime goal gave the Islanders their first of four consecutive StanleyCups. (May 24 1980)</p>
        <p>THE GOAL  Brandi Chastain's penalty kick enabled the United States to defeat China in the World Cup final before 90, 185 at the Rose Bowl, the largest crowd to watch women's sporting event. (July 10, 1999)</p>
        <p>THE PLAY  Kevin Moen's touchdown at the end of a five-lateral kickoff return through the Stanford band lifted California to a 25-30 victory on the final play of the Big Game. (Nov. 20, 1982)</p>
        <p>PERSPECTIVE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
