<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hostages Recall Times of Terror Amid Boredom</title>
    <meta content="02HOST$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indian Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dugger, Celia W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7DC1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hostages Recall Times of Terror Amid Boredom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA W. DUGGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dugger, Celia W</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Jan. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Passengers and crew kept hostage for eight days aboard a hijacked Indian Airlines jetliner describe days of tedium and moments of terror; talk of living with stench of overflowing toilets and of deciding to stop eating solid foods in an effort to avoid the dreaded bathrooms; some admit to strange bond they formed with one hijacker, who was the most sympathetic and solicitous until the day he told them that they would all be killed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hostages called the hijacker dressed all in black by his nickname, Burger, and within days of commandeering an Indian Airlines jet, he had the 178 passengers and 11 crew members joining in for singing games and joke-athons.</p>
        <p>The grown-ups listened to him recite Urdu poetry. The children called him uncle. And a newlywed wife who had a birthday in captivity was grateful when he bought a shawl from a Nepali hostage who dealt in them and presented it to her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The hostages called the hijacker dressed all in black by his nickname, Burger, and within days of commandeering an Indian Airlines jet, he had the 178 passengers and 11 crew members joining in for singing games and joke-athons.</p>
        <p>The grown-ups listened to him recite Urdu poetry. The children called him uncle. And a newlywed wife who had a birthday in captivity was grateful when he bought a shawl from a Nepali hostage who dealt in them and presented it to her.</p>
        <p>He was the most sympathetic of the five hijackers, and when he walked the aisles holding a gun, he would pause solicitously to chat with passengers, who needed permission to use the bathroom.</p>
        <p>''He was very friendly with everybody,'' said Ipseeta Menon, 25, who once asked him if he got his nickname because he liked eating hamburgers. (He did not, and the name remained a mystery.)</p>
        <p>Cut off as the hostages were, with even the sunlight shut out by the drawn window covers, they thought the masked Burger was a nice guy -- that is until Thursday morning, when he told them that they would all be killed one by one because the Indian government had refused to meet the hijackers' demands.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, the story had a happy ending. On Friday the hostages were released after India freed three militants who, like the hijackers, oppose Indian rule of the Himalayan territory of Kashmir.</p>
        <p>But the experience of being trapped on an Airbus for eight days has left many of the hostages feeling deeply traumatized. In interviews, they describe days of tedium and moments of terror. They talk of living with the stench of overflowing toilets and of deciding to stop eating solid foods in an effort to avoid the dreaded bathrooms.</p>
        <p>And some admit to the strange bond they formed with Burger, the tall, muscular hijacker who was good cop and bad cop all rolled into one.</p>
        <p>''He could change from a very sweet person to one who could shoot you within seconds,'' said Ravi Kollatt, a former merchant marine from Cochin. ''I could see it in his eyes. They were smiling eyes, but then suddenly they would become small.''</p>
        <p>The hostages' journey began on Christmas Eve. Flight 814 was late, but there was a festive air in Katmandu as the passengers waited to board the plane that would carry them on a hop to New Delhi. Among them were eight newlywed couples returning from honeymoons in Nepal. Married in arranged matches, they had only begun to get to know each other -- but would soon find themselves tested in ways they had never imagined.</p>
        <p>Several passengers said they thought it was a joke when men with guns yelled that they were hijackers. One described a steward pushing a drink cart down the aisle who kept moving when one of the hijackers waved a gun at him. Weren't those pistols and the grenade just fake weapons, like in the movies?</p>
        <p>But reality quickly set in. ''When my husband raised his head, they shoved it down roughly,'' said Suchana Goel, of Bhopal, one of the newlyweds. ''We were terrified.''</p>
        <p>For the first two days the hijackers were jumpy and brusque, hostages said. The plane kept taking off and landing -- the passengers had no idea where. As they jumped from Amritsar, India, to Lahore, Pakistan, to Dubai in the United Arab Emirates and finally, on Christmas morning, to Kandahar, Afghanistan, they were bewildered. Many were blindfolded.</p>
        <p>On the harrowing first night, before the plane landed in Dubai, the hijackers picked out a group of strong-looking men and took them into the executive-class compartment, whose occupants had all been moved to economy. Ripen Katyal, 25, a newlywed, was among them.</p>
        <p>''Right in front of us they slashed his throat,'' said K. Keshav Kannan, who was in Nepal on business for his company, Pepsi. ''They wanted to make an example.''</p>
        <p>Only a few knew what had happened. Mr. Katyal's new wife, Rachna, sitting in economy, had not heard a thing. In Dubai, the hijackers released a group of 27 women and children and unloaded Mr. Katyal's body. When her husband did not return, Mrs. Katyal got scared.</p>
        <p>''Poor thing, she was crying for two days,'' said Mrs. Menon, herself one of the newlyweds. ''They were avoiding her. Then on the third day, Burger said to her: 'I'm like your elder brother. Your husband has been released in Dubai. You should be happy he is safe and sound.' Rachna never knew he was killed.''</p>
        <p>Unaware that the hijackers had murdered Mr. Katyal, many passengers became chummy with Burger once the plane settled in Kandahar. Though cameras for CNN and the BBC were constantly trained on the jet and television stations in India broadcast news of little else, the passengers themselves might as well have been on the moon.</p>
        <p>One day Burger started a round of joke-telling. He began it with the one about the man in the helicopter who feels cold, asks why the fan is on, stops the propeller and dies. There was weak laughter. Then the captain of the jet picked up the thread and told one, too.</p>
        <p>Burger also got them to participate in a singing competition called antakshri. One passenger would sing part of a song, then the next would have to start a song with the last word in the previous song. There was merriment as young people sang Hindi movie tunes.</p>
        <p>It was only on the fourth day of captivity that the Indian government began negotiating with the hijackers -- and many of the passengers felt abandoned. If there had been a minister or V.I.P. on board, they told one another, they would already be free.</p>
        <p>''We were not getting any information from the Indian government,'' said Mrs. Menon. ''And the hijackers were being very friendly to us, very genuine,'' she continued -- at least, so it seemed in their ignorance of Mr. Katyal's death.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the sixth day, the hijackers told the hostages that 35 of them would be exchanged for one militant. Women, children and the elderly were selected for the swap. One woman refused to leave her grandchildren.</p>
        <p>Many of those left behind sobbed, fearing they would be more vulnerable now that many of the weaker people were gone.</p>
        <p>But the next morning brought what all the hostages said was the most terrifying moment. Something had gone badly wrong in the negotiations. The deal had apparently fallen through. And Burger was furious.</p>
        <p>People were still asleep, but he wanted to wake them. First he threw open the doors of the jet, and the cold wind swept down the aisles. Then he turned on the lights. Finally he got on the intercom.</p>
        <p>He told them all to pray to their gods because in half an hour he and his fellow hijackers would begin shooting them. And if anyone so much as moved, he warned, he or she would be killed. He ordered all to put down their heads.</p>
        <p>For hours Mrs. Menon, a dentist, said there was pin-drop silence except for the sound of people weeping. She held onto her husband's hand for comfort. ''At that time, we came to know these people were not to be trusted,'' she said. ''We thought the end had come.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kollatt, a father of three who was traveling alone, found himself wondering who would be picked first. ''I started weighing every person. Is it you or you? Will they ask for volunteers? Will I volunteer?''</p>
        <p>But that same afternoon, the hostages said, the hijackers came to tell them that they had made a new deal to free all of them. And the next day, New Year's Eve, when the moment of liberation finally arrived, it was the hijackers who left the plane first.</p>
        <p>Before climbing down the ladder, Burger turned to the hostages and apologized for what they had done. ''We'll meet again,'' he said, waving.</p>
        <p>In his final moments with his captives, several of them joked with him. ''If you see us in an airport lounge and you are on a similar mission, will you tip us off so we can stay off the flight?'' one asked.</p>
        <p>He promised he would. And then he was gone, down a ladder to a waiting car that whisked him away on a vanishing mission.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
