<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Effects of Aging, Viewed Unblinkingly</title>
    <meta content="02GOLD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coplans, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yamanaka, Manabu</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Vicki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6D81638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Effects of Aging, Viewed Unblinkingly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VICKI GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Vicki</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vicki Goldberg reviews photographs by John Coplans and Manabu Yamanaka on subject of aging; shows are at Andrea Rosen and Stephan Stux galleries; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE demographics of nudity in the arts have never quite matched the demographics of whatever population the arts were playing in. In ancient Greece, young men displayed their every charm in stone for a couple of centuries before naked young women were allowed to join them. In late-18th-century neo-Classicism, warriors tended to doff all their clothes while their wives or the women they had brought to grief, both of whom probably outnumbered them by war's end, generally remained covered.</p>
        <p>''Nude'' commonly signifies young women with exquisite curves. In photography, the number of male nudes has increased in recent years but is still disproportionately small. Nude children, too. And elderly nudes have remained almost nonexistent, even as the number of elderly and their life span increased. However, there are signs of change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE demographics of nudity in the arts have never quite matched the demographics of whatever population the arts were playing in. In ancient Greece, young men displayed their every charm in stone for a couple of centuries before naked young women were allowed to join them. In late-18th-century neo-Classicism, warriors tended to doff all their clothes while their wives or the women they had brought to grief, both of whom probably outnumbered them by war's end, generally remained covered.</p>
        <p>''Nude'' commonly signifies young women with exquisite curves. In photography, the number of male nudes has increased in recent years but is still disproportionately small. Nude children, too. And elderly nudes have remained almost nonexistent, even as the number of elderly and their life span increased. However, there are signs of change.</p>
        <p>Two current shows in Chelsea, ''John Coplans'' (17 photographs) at Andrea Rosen Gallery and Manabu Yamanaka's ''Gyahtei: Age'' (16 photographs) at Stephan Stux Gallery (both through Jan. 22) expose the effects of aging on the flesh without blinking, hesitation or pity -- and too explicitly to publish in a family newspaper. No doubt some people will be uncomfortable in the presence of these photographs, particularly Mr. Yamanaka's. The discomfort goes to the core of our culturally determined being.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coplans presents five large, full-frontal images of his own torso from chest to shins, with his hands on his knees, each body divided in two horizontally with a white space between the two sections. One of the images is apparently a union of two slightly different poses: a body divided against itself. The pose insistently puts the genitals smack at the center of attention, while the halo of hairs along the arms and legs fuzzes the body's outlines and activates the surface. Mottled skin, fine lines along the wrists and hands, and gray pubic hair betray the subject's age, and the black-and-white medium turns the flesh entirely to gray.</p>
        <p>The rest of the pictures are of fingers only, usually two of them pointing straight down. These finger exercises struck me as amusingly anthropomorphic games. Positioned at a slight angle, two fingers could be striding legs beneath a pompous belly (actually the lower part of the hand). Two fingers bent, with the thumb sticking out between them, look like the lower half of a naked old woman sitting astride a protuberance that happens to have a thumbnail.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coplans, born in 1920, was a respected art critic, editor and curator before he started photographing. In 1979 he threw over his previous career, and in 1984 he began a series of portraits of himself that he has continued to this day. Well, not exactly his self, but his body. Dare one equate the body with the self in a time when both body and self have become so malleable? In any event, Mr. Coplans never includes his face, so that identifying him by any of a number of intimate anatomical details could only occur if you happened to run across him in the nude.</p>
        <p>By the current standards promulgated by advertising theology and health-club dogma, Mr. Coplans's body is both heretical and slipshod. Among other deviations from the latest book of bodily etiquette, his abs long ago went into hiding, just about every available surface of his skin has sprouted an untidy crop of hair and, worst of all, he is too old. When these pictures were first shown, it was not uncommon to hear people, some of whom knew the photographer, remark that it was really a bit too much to show off at his age, and who wanted to look at it?</p>
        <p>The assumption, which I confess I shared, was that only perfect bodies should be displayed. And perhaps outrageous ones. The body had already become a template for photographic revelation, agitation and disparagement. Robert Mapplethorpe was exposing homosexual practices, Joel-Peter Witkin concentrating on obese figures and amputees, Jeffrey Silverthorne photographing in the morgue. Mr. Coplans's body was probably sufficiently aged to inspire a degree of unease in those who were planning to stay young forever, but it could not match the voltage of the shocking discoveries that were then current.</p>
        <p>Still, he presented a calm alternative to the artificial perfection that blares at us from every billboard, and he has since proved several times that age and imperfection can be stirring vehicles for photography, most notably in the friezes of his twisting body exhibited at P.S. 1 in 1997.</p>
        <p>His ceaseless investigation of his own body, split into pieces and often enlarged to monumental size, has actually been a serial investigation of form, the kind of artistic endeavor he wrote about in his days as a critic. Not that the pictures were abstract, though a few poses were hard to read, and a picture of his feet gigantically filling the space could transform them into a kind of symbol for humankind and its ability to stand on a mere two. The body photographs stubbornly remained images of his aging flesh, and looking at them became a kind of back-and-forth between the artistic, partly theoretical intent and the literally bare facts of a body going to pot.</p>
        <p>The work was, and is, so formal that some of the natural and some of the socially decreed reactions to bodies and to age are damped down, and by now his anatomy is so familiar that whatever shock value it did have is vitiated, but it is still a body, and there is no way to turn off every response to flesh. The pictures inevitably invite voyeuristic curiosity, a whiff of exhibitionism, a nagging awareness of the human condition.</p>
        <p>MR. YAMANAKA'S subjects are much older, and his full-frontal photographs of the entire figures of nude Japanese women isolated on a white ground are even more revealing and more aggressively naked. They have already proved too disturbing for some viewers, possibly because the female nude has traditionally been closely associated with youthful sexuality. These women, all between the ages of 90 and 100, are stooped and bony, with virtually hairless bodies, and the skin from beneath the breasts to the pelvis hangs in loose folds as if it were crepe. They look directly at the camera, and thus at us, with remarkably varied expressions: two present great open-mouthed, toothless smiles, one purses her lips and raises her brows, one looks pained.</p>
        <p>The Japanese respect age more than Americans do; indeed, families in Japan have always cared for their elderly and are far less likely to send a relative to a nursing home. But many Japanese women now work and are no longer available, so older people sometimes advertise for caretakers. Mr. Yamanaka, who is in his 40's, answered several of these ads and for five years worked as a volunteer helping aged people. He photographed women rather than men because he found them beautiful. Some told him that he was only the second man who had ever seen their bodies, the first being their husbands.</p>
        <p>It is probably easier to find these women beautiful if you have a personal attachment to them. Even without that, there is something admirable, if puzzling, in their willingness to be looked at so directly. Why were they willing to pose, to be seen by strangers when they had so seldom been seen before? Gratitude to Mr. Yamanaka? Acceptance of their bodies and their fate? Women who frequent a gym could tell you that dangerously overweight or shriveled-up older women are perfectly comfortable padding about in their skins with strangers of the same sex; I would hope men are the same. It comes as a great relief to think that in this anorexia-bulimia, diet-fad, plastic-surgery society, women whose bodies have given way before the onslaught of age might say at last, ''That's who I am, and it's O.K.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Yamanaka's pictures are unnerving, which they may well be at first, that is in part an index to attitudes about age and the fact that even diet and exercise cannot stave it off forever. Partly it is because few people have seen bodies that ancient, that ineluctably set on the road to death, a highway that frightens nearly everyone. Viewers may also identify in some obscure fashion: will I look like that some day? Only if I live that long. Until science discovers the fountain of youth, age will exact a price and bring fear and sorrow to those not yet in its embrace. As the poet Gerard Manley Hopkins wrote to a child named Margaret who cried when the leaves fell in autumn, ''It is the blight man was born for/ It is Margaret you mourn for.''</p>
        <p>In a time obsessed with bodies, as baby boomers work hard to outfox time with step machines and scalpels, an older population is becoming increasingly difficult to deny or ignore. Film, television and advertisers have been forced for commercial reasons to recognize the extended life span. The older body was one of the last body taboos, a taboo that was bound to be broken in the age of show-and-tell everything.</p>
        <p>So it has been. In the 1970's Imogen Cunningham took pictures of the elderly, including a few nudes, and Anne Noggle began photographing the aging process, including that of her own naked body. More recently, Joyce Tenneson saw older male and female nudes as beautiful, sorrowful and immensely dignified. Donigan Cumming photographed a woman of advanced age in the nude for several years as she declined, as well as some older men in staged situations. Miyako Isiuchi's book ''1906'' is a pictorial study of a naked, elderly Butoh master, vastly wrinkled, hugely spotted, but portrayed with the utmost reverence.</p>
        <p>Yes, the old can be looked upon as beautiful, a word that needs to be revised and updated repeatedly. The press, and Viagra, have begun spreading the news that senior citizens can even be sexy. In Paris this November, Erwin Olaf's photographs of une femme d'une certaine age in cheesecake poses -- in a tub, for instance, with a few soapsuds at strategic points -- is reported to have caused a stir but not delight.  But, hey, do you think that if a construction worker whistled at a gray-haired woman he would get an angry feminist response?</p>
        <p>The generation that warned people not to trust anyone over 30 believed old bodies, like old cars, should be traded in for newer models or sent to the junk heap. Yet age is coming out of the closet -- even onto gallery walls -- because the old have reversed the natural course of things and are multiplying. Will attitudes to old bodies change when more people find themselves wearing them? Stay tuned; the answer's on its way.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
