<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Virtual Lighthouse Museum</title>
    <meta content="02ONLI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK ON LINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lighthouses and Lightships</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York Harbor</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Lighthouse Center and Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Grady, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DB1038F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Virtual Lighthouse Museum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM O'GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Grady, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Web site of National Lighthouse Center and Museum on Staten Island serves as guide to American lighthouses, with an emphasis on the 23 varied specimens in and around New York Harbor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>National Lighthouse Center and Museum  www.lighthousemuseum.org</p>
        <p>People are fascinated by lighthouses for many reasons, says Henry Stephenson, the project director of the National Lighthouse Center and Museum on Staten Island. Some have forebears who worked on ships and relied on lighthouses as a guide to safe harbor. Others view lighthouses as symbols of close-knit communities, or simply appreciate the powerful lenses that split the fog and darkness with a miles-long beam of light.</p>
        <p>The museum, through its Web site, has been contacted by aficionados from as far away as Australia and New Zealand, Mr. Stephenson said. And so many people inquire, via e-mail, about the Jeffrey's Hook Lighthouse beneath the George Washington Bridge -- the Little Red Lighthouse of children's book fame -- that he has a prepared response, including visiting hours and directions, ready to send out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>National Lighthouse Center and Museum  www.lighthousemuseum.org</p>
        <p>People are fascinated by lighthouses for many reasons, says Henry Stephenson, the project director of the National Lighthouse Center and Museum on Staten Island. Some have forebears who worked on ships and relied on lighthouses as a guide to safe harbor. Others view lighthouses as symbols of close-knit communities, or simply appreciate the powerful lenses that split the fog and darkness with a miles-long beam of light.</p>
        <p>The museum, through its Web site, has been contacted by aficionados from as far away as Australia and New Zealand, Mr. Stephenson said. And so many people inquire, via e-mail, about the Jeffrey's Hook Lighthouse beneath the George Washington Bridge -- the Little Red Lighthouse of children's book fame -- that he has a prepared response, including visiting hours and directions, ready to send out.</p>
        <p>While the virtual museum is up and running, the building itself, in the St. George section of Staten Island on a site that once housed the United States Lighthouse Service Depot, isn't scheduled to open until July 4, 2001. In the meantime, the Web site serves as a guide to American lighthouses, with an emphasis on the 23 varied specimens in and around New York Harbor.</p>
        <p>WHAT YOU SEE -- The home page contains a sepia-toned photo of the handsome Romer Shoal lighthouse, which sat at the old depot until 1898, when it was moved to a lonely spot at the mouth of lower New York Bay. Mr. Stephenson said the museum is raising money to have it moved back to St. George.</p>
        <p>The site's highlight is a section called NY Lights, where you can learn lighthouse lore, including stories of the tenders. There was Kate Walker, for example, a German immigrant and former waitress who with her son Jacob and daughter Mamie tended the Robbin's Reef Lighthouse from 1883 to 1919. (Her husband John died in 1886 saying, ''Mind the light, Kate.'')</p>
        <p>''She rescued as many as 50 people by her own count, and at least one dog (a Scottie),'' the site says. ''She once rescued a young man and his sweetheart from a sinking rowboat and then helped to arrange a wedding for them on Staten Island, so that their reputations would not be ruined by their night out.'' The lighthouse, about two miles southwest of the Statue of Liberty, can be seen from the Staten Island ferry.</p>
        <p>Then there is the Throgs Neck Lighthouse in the Bronx, established in 1827, whose earliest keepers are said to have run a bar, serving local anglers and hunters. ''It became a favorite watering hole for those in the area,'' the site says, hastening to point out that ''this type of business was in violation of the U.S. Lighthouse Service rigorous standards and most definitely would have been cause for dismissal, if known.''</p>
        <p>LINKS -- Many. You can click on Lighthouse Links for a tour of lighthouses around the country, and the world.</p>
        <p>WHAT YOU GET -- A fascinating window on an aspect of New York's maritime past, designed by people who carry a torch, so to speak, for that rugged era.</p>
        <p>JIM O'GRADY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK ON LINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
