<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Group Offers Seminars for Single Women</title>
    <meta content="02REAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siderow, Sheila</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Singer, Penny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDA1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Group Offers Seminars for Single Women</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENNY SINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Singer, Penny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Westchester real estate broker Sheila Siderow discusses Woman-to-Woman Network seminars she helped establish as place for women to discuss divorce issues; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN first confronted with the prospect of a divorce, whom do many women call? ''They call their mothers or best friends, then they call their real estate broker,'' said Sheila Siderow, a principal of Siderow Kennedy Real Estate in Chappaqua, adding that she often  receives frantic calls from former customers, women on the verge of separation or divorce.</p>
        <p>''These are not naive, unsophisticated women,'' she said. ''I've had calls from physicians, lawyers, teachers, even an investment banker, all of them scared. They want me to help them sort out their worries about losing their homes, their children and their finances.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN first confronted with the prospect of a divorce, whom do many women call? ''They call their mothers or best friends, then they call their real estate broker,'' said Sheila Siderow, a principal of Siderow Kennedy Real Estate in Chappaqua, adding that she often  receives frantic calls from former customers, women on the verge of separation or divorce.</p>
        <p>''These are not naive, unsophisticated women,'' she said. ''I've had calls from physicians, lawyers, teachers, even an investment banker, all of them scared. They want me to help them sort out their worries about losing their homes, their children and their finances.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Siderow said she offered them advice about their homes and arranged for appraisals, even had them to her house for dinner, but when it came to questions about property division, financial negotiations or child support, she was at a loss.</p>
        <p>''What they needed was a place where they could get guidance and answers to their questions, which would help them gain control over their lives,'' she said.</p>
        <p>And when she discussed with other real estate brokers the possibility of starting a workshop for separated and divorced women, she was surprised to learn that each had had experiences with clients similar to those of her own.</p>
        <p>''They too, were frequently being asked for information on matters they knew very little about,'' she said.</p>
        <p>As a result of the discussions, Ms. Siderow got in touch with three professional acquaintances, one a matrimonial lawyer, another a financial consultant and the third a psychologist, who together in July formed the Woman-to-Woman Network. It conducts seminars as round table discussions. Participants are given a chance to interact with panel members and discuss various topics.</p>
        <p>The three professionals conduct workshops at various locations around the county at 10-week intervals. The first was offered in October, and the second, which attracted 30 women, was held on Nov. 30.  ''There is no charge for the Woman-to-Woman Network seminars,'' Ms. Siderow said. ''All of us are donating our time as a service to the community, but this isn't group therapy. Our aim is practical: to help people get on with their lives.''</p>
        <p>Marilyn Faust, a lawyer in White Plains with more than 14 years' experience in matrimonial and family law, is one of the members who formed the network.</p>
        <p>''I've had clients who have been married as little as six months and as long as 45 years,'' Ms. Faust said. ''An educated client is my best client, and yet I am amazed at how many of my clients are totally in the dark when it comes to financial matters.''</p>
        <p>Getting a divorce may feel emotional, but mostly it is about economics, Ms. Faust emphasized. ''The more informed a woman is about her family's finances, the easier it is for her lawyer to help her get the best possible settlement.''</p>
        <p>At the first seminar, held at the Mount Kisco Library, participants ranged in age from women in their early 30's to those in their 60's. Ms. Faust described all of them as capable, successful and intelligent women who felt absolutely lost. They included women like a 49-year-old social worker who was married for 28 years and enjoyed the good life, which included a home in Pleasantville, two children and plenty of social activities. Then, out of the blue, the woman related at the workshop, her husband asked for a divorce.</p>
        <p>''It was a total nightmare,'' she recalled. ''Unreal. I felt as though I was watching a made-for-TV movie that I wanted to turn off.''</p>
        <p>Her husband, claiming a mid-life crisis, moved out.</p>
        <p>''The truth was, He met someone on the Internet that he fell for,'' the Pleasantville woman said. ''I wondered why he was spending so much time on line, but I never suspected anything so outrageous. The woman is as old as he is, and she has four grandchildren.''</p>
        <p>She worried that she would not be able to keep her house.</p>
        <p>''It will be very hard for us to live on my salary,'' she said. ''I feel working women are getting a raw deal today.''</p>
        <p>A special projects teacher from Yonkers agreed. ''The courts couldn't care less today,'' she told participants at the workshop. ''It doesn't matter who does the leaving. My husband had me looking at new houses while he was getting ready to leave, and I didn't have a clue. And I put my career on hold when I helped him advance his.''</p>
        <p>She said she attended the workshop to get information. ''I don't like those husband-bashing groups,'' she said. ''I need to learn. My husband, who is an accountant, took care of all our finances. Money is already a problem. Our house is up for sale, and my daughter and I are living with my mother.''</p>
        <p>Sheila L. Spicehandler, one of the founders of the network and a financial consultant with Salomon Smith Barney in Greenwich, who frequently counsels women on ways to develop a financial plan, said: ''If there is one thing the workshops hope to accomplish, it is to help newly single women regain a sense of control over their lives. My job is to give them the necessary tools to take control of their finances. I'm helping some of the participants draw up financial profiles.''</p>
        <p>Emotions also have to be dealt with, Marianna Lawrence Cayten, the psychologist on the panel, said.  ''Women have a tendency to put their own emotional needs low on the priority list. Yet they have to work through feelings of fear, sadness and anger to deal with the practical issues of divorce and help their children cope.'' Practical issues include  obtaining the names of experienced  plumbers, reliable painters and  handymen.</p>
        <p>''These are very important resources for women who are suddenly single,'' Ms. Siderow said. ''We're going to pool our sources and come up with a directory.''</p>
        <p>Those who attended the first seminar gave it high marks.</p>
        <p>''Fabulous,''  one woman said. ''I just wish it could have gone on and on.'' Another woman said: ''I see things more clearly now. I want to make my life better.''</p>
        <p>The third workshop will be held on  Jan. 25 from 6 to 8:30 p.m. at the Mount Pleasant Public Library in Pleasantville. The panel will discuss topics like How to Cope in an Emotional Crisis, How to Protect Your Legal Rights and How to Preserve Your Financial Picture. Reference materials will be provided, and there is no fee.</p>
        <p>Eugenia M. Vecchio, a lawyer with offices in Harrison, joined the group in early November. Ms. Vecchio's practice focuses exclusively on estate and trust planning, a topic of great importance to single women.</p>
        <p>Ms. Siderow said, ''Our hope is that those who are divorced and widowed will leave our meetings feeling confident in their ability to survive and thrive on their way to building a new and better life.''</p>
        <p>For more information about the Woman-to-Woman Network, the number to call is 242-8427.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
