<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.Y.I.</title>
    <meta content="02FYI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DB1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.Y.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Zoological Racism</p>
        <p>Q.  Is it true that an African pygmy was once exhibited at the Bronx Zoo?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Zoological Racism</p>
        <p>Q.  Is it true that an African pygmy was once exhibited at the Bronx Zoo?</p>
        <p>A.  For two miserable, tumultuous weeks in 1906, Ota Benga, a 23-year-old pygmy from the Belgian Congo, was put on display at what was then called the New York Zoological Society in the Bronx. The public, appalled and entertained in equal measure, flocked to the primate house, where Benga could be observed playing with Dahong, the zoo's orangutan, beneath a sign that read in part, ''Height 4 feet 11 inches. Weight 103 pounds. Exhibited each afternoon during September.''</p>
        <p>Benga was already something of a professional pygmy. After he was enslaved by villagers near the Kasai River in 1904, Samuel P. Verner, an American explorer and impresario, bought Benga's release and persuaded him to help recruit other Batwa pygmies for the 1904 World's Fair in St. Louis. Benga then agreed to accompany Verner to St. Louis, where he was displayed -- along with 1,400 American Indians, Japanese Ainus, Eskimos and other ''emblematic savages'' -- in the fair's anthropology department. Verner and Benga later returned to Africa together, and went to New York in 1906.</p>
        <p>Verner, by that time penniless, left Benga in the care of the zoo, where it was agreed he would live and hunt in a forest of several hundred acres, apart from the exhibit area. Benga, who by that time spoke some English and liked to wear white duck suits, was instead displayed before as many as 40,000 spectators a day.</p>
        <p>Facing protests from newspapers and black clergymen, the zoo's director, William Temple Hornaday, allowed Benga to leave his cage and wander freely around the zoo during the day, then return to the primate house to sleep at night. But according to The New York Times, the crowds ''chased him around the grounds all day, howling, jeering and yelling.''</p>
        <p>''Some of them poked him in the ribs, others tripped him up, all laughed at him,'' The Times said.</p>
        <p>Exasperated by the growing scandal, Hornaday released Benga into the care of the Howard Colored Orphan Asylum in Brooklyn. That arrangement proved awkward, since Benga had been married twice, and in 1910 he was placed in a seminary and college in Lynchburg, Va. He later worked on a nearby tobacco farm and taught local boys how to hunt in the woods. In 1916, lonely, despondent and homesick without a home, Ota Benga took his own life.</p>
        <p>No Lap Needed, Usually</p>
        <p>Q.  What is the Transit Authority's policy for children who do not pay a fare? I always thought they were required to sit on an adult's lap, but whenever the bus or subway car is full and I ask a parent to hold a child so that I can sit down, I get dirty looks from everyone.</p>
        <p>A.  Simply put, children under 44 inches in height ride the subways and local buses free, and they are not required to sit on a parent's lap, according to Melissa Farley, a spokeswoman for New York City Transit. The rules are different for the express buses that travel between Manhattan and the other boroughs, where children under 2 are required to sit on a parent's lap, and separate seats must be bought for older children. And what if a 45-inch-tall child tries to outwit the system? ''Enforcement of the rules is a police matter,'' Ms. Farley said. ''We can only tell them to pay their fare.''</p>
        <p>When Joni Met Chelsea</p>
        <p>Q.  Did Joni Mitchell, who wrote the song ''Chelsea Morning'' actually live in Chelsea?</p>
        <p>A.  Yes. When Mitchell composed the song in 1967, she was living in a ground-floor apartment at 41 West 16th Street. One cannot help wondering if the sun actually ''poured in like butterscotch.''</p>
        <p>DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</p>
        <p>E-mail address: daschn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: daschn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
