<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Lili St. Cyr, b. 1918; When Burlesque Was Beautiful</title>
    <meta content="MB103150" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Striptease</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sante, Luc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">St Cyr, Lili (1918-99)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0D91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Lili St. Cyr, b. 1918; When Burlesque Was Beautiful</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Luc Sante</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sante, Luc</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Luc S</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lili St. Cyr, who died last January at the age of 80, was one of the last survivors of an era that now seems as remote as the Hapsburg dynasty. That era might be called the age of burlesque, which makes it sound rather grand, and let's say it lasted from 1893 until 1960, or thereabouts. Burlesque was a stratum of entertainment, not exactly underground but not quite legit -- in the theatrical sense of the word -- which might or might not involve singers, comedians, chorus lines or canned-ham raffles. Its essential feature, however, was women slowly removing most or all of their clothing. Lili St. Cyr excelled at this art and introduced several refinements, like her trademark emergence from an onstage bubble bath with the bubbles selectively clinging to her salient parts.</p>
        <p>Burlesque's putative starting date of 1893 refers to the appearance of the celebrated Little Egypt doing the hootchy-kootchy at the Chicago Columbian Exposition. While much racier things were common at the time in Paris, and leg shows on the American stage go back at least as far as the 1860's, Little Egypt's influence on popular culture was nevertheless enormous. Risque entertainment dominated vaudeville at the beginning of the 20th century, as the Indian nautch dance was augmented by assorted bumps and grinds; the first striptease was apparently performed by a woman named Odell in New York in 1907.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lili St. Cyr, who died last January at the age of 80, was one of the last survivors of an era that now seems as remote as the Hapsburg dynasty. That era might be called the age of burlesque, which makes it sound rather grand, and let's say it lasted from 1893 until 1960, or thereabouts. Burlesque was a stratum of entertainment, not exactly underground but not quite legit -- in the theatrical sense of the word -- which might or might not involve singers, comedians, chorus lines or canned-ham raffles. Its essential feature, however, was women slowly removing most or all of their clothing. Lili St. Cyr excelled at this art and introduced several refinements, like her trademark emergence from an onstage bubble bath with the bubbles selectively clinging to her salient parts.</p>
        <p>Burlesque's putative starting date of 1893 refers to the appearance of the celebrated Little Egypt doing the hootchy-kootchy at the Chicago Columbian Exposition. While much racier things were common at the time in Paris, and leg shows on the American stage go back at least as far as the 1860's, Little Egypt's influence on popular culture was nevertheless enormous. Risque entertainment dominated vaudeville at the beginning of the 20th century, as the Indian nautch dance was augmented by assorted bumps and grinds; the first striptease was apparently performed by a woman named Odell in New York in 1907.</p>
        <p>Over the next 50 years, burlesque was subject to police raids and pulpit denunciations (while deriving undeniable benefits from this publicity), went in and out of fashion, went highbrow (Gypsy Rose Lee wrote novels and cultivated the bon ton) and low. Edmund Wilson, describing a revue at the 14th Street Olympic in 1926, captured the essence of the standard grind-house show: ''The spectators . . . sit in silence and quite without smiling and with no overt sign of admiration toward the glittering and thick-lashed seductresses who stand on a level with their shoulders and who address them with so personal a heartiness. . . . They have come to the theater, you realize, in order to have their dreams made objective, and they sit there each alone with his dream.''</p>
        <p>Burly, as Variety called it, peaked in the 1950's. It thrived on the tension between a male population who as soldiers had seen Paree (or its equivalent) and the repressed society they returned to. Las Vegas, which coated the demimonde with cubic zirconia, was coming into its own and encouraging higher production values. The grind was developing a star system: Tempest Storm, Blaze Starr, Ann Corio, Bettie Page -- and Lili St. Cyr, nee Willis Marie Van Schaack of Minneapolis and rechristened after the French military academy. She had blond hair, blue eyes, the classic 36-24-36 proportions. She started stripping in the mid-40's, but it was a 1951 arrest for indecent exposure after a bubble bath at Ciro's in Hollywood that put her on the map.</p>
        <p>Soon she was a headliner at clubs, a cover model for magazines ranging from Sir to Uncensored, and appearing in motion pictures with such titles as ''Love Moods'' (1952), ''Strip-o-rama'' (1953) and ''Varietease'' (1954). She developed new gimmicks -- in one routine, an invisible fishing line whisked her G-string away over spectators' heads just before the lights dimmed. She appeared in a few mainstream pictures; for instance, the screen adaptation of Norman Mailer's ''Naked and the Dead.'' Sundry sugar daddies contributed to her upkeep.</p>
        <p>But by the end of the Eisenhower administration her career had reached its twilight. She would make one more picture in the 60's, briefly run a lingerie shop in Los Angeles and eventually become a drug addict. Burlesque was over, too. By the time Jack Ruby, the owner of the Carousel Club in Dallas, made headlines in 1963, the allure of burleycue seemed sadder and tawdrier than ever. A few years later, ''Oh! Calcutta!'' brought nudity to the legitimate stage, albeit in a pile of high-hat and Aquarian baggage that gave the razzberry to the old grind-house nudge and wink. By the mid-70's, when Plato's Retreat had made even the orgy commercially viable, the striptease had been reduced to the status of nostalgia item -- Ann Corio toured the nation with revivals of her revue, conclusively titled ''This Was Burlesque.''</p>
        <p>Now the eternal pendulum between license and prudery seems to be swinging in both directions at once. While what the old baggy-pants comedians called ''dubble entenders'' are all over the TV screen and the far frontiers of smut are easily available online, you practically have to go to Nevada to see nudity on a stage. Could it be that the spirit is willing but the flesh is weak?</p>
        <p>Luc Sante is the author of ''Low Life,'' ''Evidence'' and ''The Factory of Facts.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Luc Sante is the author of ''Low Life,'' ''Evidence'' and ''The Factory of Facts.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
