<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Faces and Facets at the Station House</title>
    <meta content="02WEIN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bochco, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milch, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinraub, Bernard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Nypd Blue (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3D91638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Faces and Facets at the Station House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinraub, Bernard</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report on new cast members and plots for seventh season of television series NYPD Blue; photos; co-creators David Milch and Steven Bochco insist they will continue to play creatice, albeit diminished, roles even as they move on to other projects (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a corner of the closed ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' set at the 20th Century Fox studios, David Milch, the co-creator of the series, with Steven Bochco, sat on a wooden chair restlessly tapping his foot. Mr. Milch, who controls the writing and often the direction of every episode, is now in the midst of his seventh -- and final -- season (at least with such day-to-day involvement) on this acclaimed television series about the lives of a group of New York cops. The season's first episode will be shown next Tuesday, Jan. 11.</p>
        <p>''The big pitfall is thinking of it as the seventh season instead of a new season,'' said Mr. Milch, a 54-year-old former literature instructor at Yale with a passion for the racetrack. ''Changes are being introduced. New characters. New facets explored of the other characters. We're like a jazz ensemble. We trust each other. No one is afraid to improvise. Like good jazz, it never gets old.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a corner of the closed ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' set at the 20th Century Fox studios, David Milch, the co-creator of the series, with Steven Bochco, sat on a wooden chair restlessly tapping his foot. Mr. Milch, who controls the writing and often the direction of every episode, is now in the midst of his seventh -- and final -- season (at least with such day-to-day involvement) on this acclaimed television series about the lives of a group of New York cops. The season's first episode will be shown next Tuesday, Jan. 11.</p>
        <p>''The big pitfall is thinking of it as the seventh season instead of a new season,'' said Mr. Milch, a 54-year-old former literature instructor at Yale with a passion for the racetrack. ''Changes are being introduced. New characters. New facets explored of the other characters. We're like a jazz ensemble. We trust each other. No one is afraid to improvise. Like good jazz, it never gets old.''</p>
        <p>In fact Mr. Milch and Mr. Bochco are fully aware that the series, which has won 19 Emmy Awards, is getting old -- and slowly,  inevitably reaching its final lap. Perhaps next year -- especially with the show in other hands -- perhaps the year after.</p>
        <p>From its season debut last year until the end of May, ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' averaged 14.5 million viewers, its lowest season average ever, and ranked No. 15. ABC initially considered moving the show from its traditional time slot (Tuesday at 10 p.m.), but when an angry Mr. Bochco went to newspapers and complained about the network's disloyalty, ABC backed down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bochco, who is consumed with a new CBS series, ''City of Angels,'' about an inner-city hospital, has signed a five-year $45 million to $50 million deal with Paramount to develop series for various networks, starting in January. Similarly, Mr. Milch, who began his television career writing for ''Hill Street Blues,'' has signed a separate and lucrative deal with Paramount.</p>
        <p>Both men insisted that they would continue to play creative, albeit diminished, roles on ''N.Y.P.D Blue.'' And the longtime cast members Dennis Franz and Kim Delaney said that Mr. Milch was so obsessed with the show -- and so personally identified with its characters, especially the tormented Franz character, Detective Andy Sipowicz -- that he would continue to be a forceful presence.</p>
        <p>(Mr. Milch endured a half-dozen angioplasties to deal with heart blockages in the first two years of the series, and the ordeal was realistically employed last year on the series when Jimmy Smits's character, Detective Bobby Simone, died of heart disease.)</p>
        <p>''Even if the baby grows up,'' said Ms. Delaney, who portrays Detective Diane Russell, ''David and Steven will take care of it.''</p>
        <p>For the moment, Mr. Milch and Mr. Bochco are immersed in not only taking care of the show but somehow proving to ABC, and perhaps themselves, that ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' will endure beyond next season, and the one after that.</p>
        <p>''The show will change; there's no question about it,'' said Mr. Bochco, seated in his spare, elegant office in a corner of the Fox lot. ''Particularly after the first years, David's hands-on, day-in-day-out writing of the show has been its heart and soul. His talent and humor and sensibility and angst have informed the show. He works tirelessly and madly. But with David essentially leaving, it's a great opportunity to feature different voices. There'll be different passions. But that's nothing to be afraid of.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps half of the new season's 22 episodes have already been made, mostly on the Fox lot, with periodic trips to New York to shoot exterior scenes. Although some of the plot lines are secret (and many are still swirling in Mr. Milch's imagination), the fact is, ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' is facing some dramatic changes in the new year.</p>
        <p>Partly to lure younger audiences, the relatively new character, Andy Sipowicz's partner, Detective Danny Sorenson (Rick Schroder), will have an affair with a policewoman. (The casting last year of Mr. Schroder, who looks like a sweet-faced choirboy, was a bit of a surprise. But Mr. Schroder, who is 29 and plays Sorenson with a thick New York accent, has given the series a certain cockiness and authenticity that eluded the more glamorous and remote Mr. Smits.)</p>
        <p>ACHARACTER who has been underused in the series, Detective Jill Kirkendall (Andrea Thompson), a single mother, will be the focus of several early episodes involving her sleazy former husband, with whom she's still in love.</p>
        <p>''Actually, what I like so much about the show is that they didn't hook me up with anybody right away and you just got to see her working as a good solid cop,'' said Ms. Thompson, who has been on the show four years. ''So often when you're on television you're somebody's wife or girlfriend and you rarely just get to see women working,  doing a job and not making a big deal of it.''</p>
        <p>A new character, Detective Baldwin Jones, who is black (his fictional mother named him after the writer James Baldwin), will become a full-time character in midseason.</p>
        <p>The detective, played by 29-year-old Henry Simmons, a 6-foot-4 former soap opera actor who once worked as one of those sleek doormen at Morgan's Hotel in New York, will inevitably pose some challenges for the Sipowicz character, who has unresolved racial problems, as will Lt. Arthur Fancy (James McDaniel), the other significant black character in the series. Mr. Simmons essentially replaces Nicholas Turturro, who is easing up on his involvement with the show to pursue a film career. (Mr. Turturro's character, Detective James Martinez, will become ill.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmons still seemed a little shaken at his good fortune. He drove cross-country from Manhattan in June with a U-Haul and landed the part in October after several auditions. Mr. Milch told Mr. Simmons he had the job but asked him to meet Mr. Bochco. ''I went in and Mr. Bochco asked me how I felt and I told him, 'Look, I just want to get our of here and scream.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmons said he was even more intimidated about meeting Mr. Franz, whom he initially thought would turn out to be like the sometimes snarling and angry Sipowicz. ''He turned out to be the nicest and most humble man,'' said Mr. Simmons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franz will, of course, remain a major focus of the show but the tragedy and emotions that have shaped his character will be muted. The Sipowicz character, an alcoholic who is on and off the wagon, has endured the deaths of his son, his wife(played by Sharon Lawrence) and his partner  (Mr. Smits).</p>
        <p>Mr. Franz himself has slimmed down under doctor's orders, losing about 40 pounds on a low carbohydrate, high protein diet. (As a result, Mr. Milch had asked the actor to climb into the shower for a nude scene. But Mr. Franz said he had not lost that much weight, and the scene was shot from the waist up. (He was not so cautious several seasons ago when his bare posterior was shown in one scene.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Franz, as well as Mr. Milch and Mr. Bochco, have sought in the new year to give Sipowicz's life a certain normalcy.</p>
        <p>''We can't continue to put him through this constant torment forever,'' said Mr. Franz. ''He has to mellow out. He's a single father now  and is realizing that role. I would like him to possibly try his hand at romance again.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bochco put it another way. ''Nobody can live in a perpetual state of despair,'' he said. ''And no one wants to watch somebody in a perpetual state of despair.''</p>
        <p>Asked why he was so fascinated with law enforcement, Mr. Bochco, who has helped create series like ''Brooklyn South'' and ''Hill Street Blues,'' said: ''For me, cops personify themes that are very interesting: ethics, justice, law. I also find cops compelling because they're flawed and ordinary people who are asked to be incredibly brave and courageous. And these are people who have tremendous on-the-job stress and often go home to complicated home lives, as we all do. The difference is they strap a gun.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch is even more intrigued with the police. A retired New York City detective, Bill Clark, now an executive producer, brings out a handful of police officers every week to Los Angeles to talk to the writers about their experiences.</p>
        <p>''A broad audience is reluctant to invest in characters who cannot bring about change in a decisive, simple way,'' said Mr. Milch. ''So that kind of leaves you with doctors and cops. I once did a show about reporters, but they don't carry guns.  And a good cop, a really good cop, understands the criminal mind because he's half a criminal.''</p>
        <p>It's characteristic of Mr. Milch's constantly evolving, sometimes blurry writing style that series stars like Mr. Franz, Mr. Schroder (who replaced Mr. Smits), Ms. Thompson, Ms. McDaniel and Ms. Delaney have little idea where the overlapping plots are heading. In fact the actors often arrive at the studio not fully aware of that day's plot line or dialogue, an unusual way for a series to operate.</p>
        <p>''Tomorrow's work will be written today, and in one day we've shot scenes for three different episodes,'' said Mr. Schroder, the Staten Island-born former child star, seated in his trailer covered with pictures of his wife and their three young children. ''I've never worked like this before. I don't think anyone has.''</p>
        <p>In a nearby trailer, Bill Brochtrup, who plays John Irvin, a gay secretary working in the squad room, said his character was devised as a type of Greek chorus whose often nonverbal reactions to events -- a gaze, a look of shock, a laugh -- are intended to mirror the reactions of the television audience. Like Mr. Schroder, Mr. Brochtrup said that the show's success was based partly on the unusual improvisational style and last-minute writing that gives the show its immediacy.</p>
        <p>''Right now it's 2 o'clock in the afternoon and I still don't quite know yet what's happening,'' said Mr. Brochtrup, breaking into a laugh. ''David is constantly changing things and reworking scenes and writing them kind of as the inspiration comes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milch said it would, of course, be difficult for for him to leave the show. ''I'm 54 years old and I have other things I want to do, but I'm not sure I will ever really leave the show,'' he said. ''It's simply that at this point there are other windows I want to look out from. Fitzgerald said, 'Life is best looked at from a single window.' Well, I've certainly looked at it from a single window. Maybe Fitzgerald was wrong. Maybe there's more than one window.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
