<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loiterers Depart, and a Bus Stop Along With Them</title>
    <meta content="02BUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: ROCKAWAY PARK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bus Shelters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E1D91538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loiterers Depart, and a Bus Stop Along With Them</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD WEIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Civic group succeeds in moving bus stop and shelter from in front of Seaside Public Library in Rockaway Park in order to get rid of the drug dealers and other undesirables who loitered there, but the sudden removal of the bus stop creates a backlash that has sparked sharp debates in community (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The grounds outside the Seaside Public Library in Rockaway Park had attracted so many drug dealers, prostitutes and vagrants in recent years, Virginia Smith said, that she stopped going there with her two young boys.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Smith said she was unwilling to accept that the loiterers, who on several occasions approached her to offer drugs, had taken over the steps of the library, at Beach 117th Street and Rockaway Beach Boulevard. They even intimidated residents who became afraid to walk to nearby stores at night, she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The grounds outside the Seaside Public Library in Rockaway Park had attracted so many drug dealers, prostitutes and vagrants in recent years, Virginia Smith said, that she stopped going there with her two young boys.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Smith said she was unwilling to accept that the loiterers, who on several occasions approached her to offer drugs, had taken over the steps of the library, at Beach 117th Street and Rockaway Beach Boulevard. They even intimidated residents who became afraid to walk to nearby stores at night, she said.</p>
        <p>As chairwoman of a civic group, Rockaway Park Residents, Ms. Smith, along with several neighbors, held meetings with community leaders for two years in a campaign to restore a sense of safety to the spot.</p>
        <p>Their early efforts failed: the library, while agreeing to improve its outdoor lighting, was unwilling to remove the planters and bike rack that had become de facto park benches and the drug dealers' preferred hangouts.</p>
        <p>Moreover, although the police had handed out 81 summonses for drinking in public and other quality-of-life offenses, and made 16 arrests in front of the library in 1998 alone, they faced a problem -- the Q-22 bus stop in front of the library. People on the plaza could simply claim they were waiting for the bus.</p>
        <p>So Ms. Smith's group pushed to get the bus shelter, and later the bus stop, in front of the library removed.</p>
        <p>The shelter was razed last spring, and the Department of Transportation eliminated the bus stop in November. Since then, Ms. Smith said, law and order has returned. ''Now I can go there freely,'' she said. ''It's beautiful.''</p>
        <p>But the sudden removal of the bus stop, without any public hearings, created a backlash that has sparked sharp debates at meetings of Community Board 14 and filled the letters page of the local weekly newspaper, The Rockaway Wave.</p>
        <p>''What annoys me the most is that no alternative bus stop was installed,'' said Lew Simon, a Democratic district leader who in his guest column in the newspaper called the bus stop's removal ''unacceptable.'' Mr. Simon said he has received numerous calls from residents, particularly the elderly, who are angered at having to walk to stops at either Beach 114th or Beach 119th Streets.</p>
        <p>Stan Brettschneider, president of Green Bus Lines, which operates the Q-22 route, said his company opposed the elimination of the stop, which made for easy transfers to the A train at Beach 116th Street and to four other bus routes.</p>
        <p>Vince Castellano, former chairman of Community Board 14's transportation committee, said the committee declined to recommend eliminating the stop because it felt the step ''was a little extreme.''</p>
        <p>But Jonathan Gaska, the district manager, said that after consulting with Rosemary Murray, the board's chairwoman, and other board leaders he contacted the Transportation Department to request that the stop be removed.</p>
        <p>''When it comes to inconvenience or safety, our board's policy is to always choose safety,'' Mr. Gaska said. Besides the issue of crime, he noted, there have been a number of accidents at the bus stop caused by cars pulling around parked buses on the narrow residential street.</p>
        <p>''There was no plain, easy answer,'' he added. But with the bus stop gone, he said, ''I think it will force everyone back to the table to look at this in the right way and find a solution.''</p>
        <p>RICHARD WEIR</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: ROCKAWAY PARK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
