<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An N.B.A. Power Broker Who Lost His Power</title>
    <meta content="02NBAA$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agents (Business)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wilhelmina Models (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fleisher, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Professions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DB1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1380" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An N.B.A. Power Broker Who Lost His Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Basketball Notebook article focuses on suitt</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just over two years ago, he secured for Kevin Garnett the richest contract in professional sports history -- a $126 million deal that helped stoke the flames of a labor war between players and owners. Eric Fleisher was becoming such a feared power broker, he even held a franchise hostage while inviting a bevy of comparisons to David Falk, the shrewdest and best known of the sports agents. Fleisher's clientele included Stephon Marbury, Joe Smith and Al Harrington.</p>
        <p>Today his company, Assist Sports Management, has been reduced to being a bit-part player in the agent game. The most prominent players he represents are the journeyman Antoine Carr, the Nets reserve guard Sherman Douglas and the Knicks reserve forward John Wallace. Fleisher filed a lawsuit two weeks in New York State court in Manhattan, naming 14 individual and 4 corporate defendants. In a 23-page complaint, Fleisher alleges that his former protege, Andrew Miller, 10 players and Wilhelmina Models of New York engaged in a scheme to defraud him out of his multimillion-dollar agency. Fleisher is seeking more than $30 million in damages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just over two years ago, he secured for Kevin Garnett the richest contract in professional sports history -- a $126 million deal that helped stoke the flames of a labor war between players and owners. Eric Fleisher was becoming such a feared power broker, he even held a franchise hostage while inviting a bevy of comparisons to David Falk, the shrewdest and best known of the sports agents. Fleisher's clientele included Stephon Marbury, Joe Smith and Al Harrington.</p>
        <p>Today his company, Assist Sports Management, has been reduced to being a bit-part player in the agent game. The most prominent players he represents are the journeyman Antoine Carr, the Nets reserve guard Sherman Douglas and the Knicks reserve forward John Wallace. Fleisher filed a lawsuit two weeks in New York State court in Manhattan, naming 14 individual and 4 corporate defendants. In a 23-page complaint, Fleisher alleges that his former protege, Andrew Miller, 10 players and Wilhelmina Models of New York engaged in a scheme to defraud him out of his multimillion-dollar agency. Fleisher is seeking more than $30 million in damages.</p>
        <p>''Things have clearly turned around,'' Fleisher said last Thursday. ''I try not to dwell on what's happened, but momentum is a funny thing. It can change quickly.''</p>
        <p>At the heart of his complaint, Fleisher alleges that Miller, whom he hired as an unpaid intern in 1992 and who rose to be the firm's president, betrayed him by secretly signing clients while still employed by Assist, then left the firm last July, taking Fleisher's impressive client base with him. Miller now works for WSports, a division of Wilhelmina Models.</p>
        <p>''The complaint has absolutely no merit,'' Miller said by telephone last week. ''My lawyers intend to have it dismissed immediately.''</p>
        <p>Miller's lawyers have yet to file a motion to dismiss the complaint, but Fleisher said they had asked for immediate depositions and discovery.</p>
        <p>Among Fleisher's more sensational claims is that the players were lured away by promises of ''romantic liaisons'' with unidentified Wilhelmina models.</p>
        <p>''Everyone wants to know about the models; that's getting all the attention,'' Fleisher said. ''But there's much more to this than that. This says a lot about loyalty in this business. Clearly, as you become more high profile, there's a competitive element there. But this was from inside. This particularly hurts because it was someone who I trusted.</p>
        <p>''Obviously there's a financial component, but also an emotional component to it. I'm very angry. This was a young kid who I brought along.''</p>
        <p>Fleisher has lost 16 clients to Miller's company, including Garnett and Smith. But they are not defendants in the suit; Fleisher said he had settled his differences with them out of court. Marbury left Fleisher for Falk in late 1998. Among the 10 players named in the suit are Chauncey Billups, Harrington and Tyronn Lue, a fact that has raised concerns at the office of the players union.</p>
        <p>''You don't want to be suing players; that's not good for business,'' said Ron Klempner, a lawyer with the National Basketball Players Association. ''Little good can come from that. The repercussions down the road could be severe for him.'' But Klempner added, ''Maybe he felt so wronged by what happened that was the only way he felt he could go.''</p>
        <p>None of the players who are being sued could be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>Fleisher said: ''When someone does something wrong, you have two choices: look the other way or take action. The reality is, they were under contract. Will it have potential future implications? Yeah, it may. But it was something that needed to be done. Those were all of the young clients that the business was geared toward the next 10 to 12 years. When I look at it objectively, that was my retirement.''</p>
        <p>Fleisher, the son of the late union chief Larry Fleisher, is no stranger to controversy. During the Garnett contract negotiations, Fleisher told the Minnesota Timberwolves' owner, Glen Taylor, and the general manager, Kevin McHale, that Garnett would not sign with the franchise after the club divulged to the news media that Fleisher and Garnett had turned down a $100 million offer. Fleisher and his client were pilloried for turning down $15 million more than the owner had paid for the franchise before finally getting Taylor to fork over an extra $26 million.</p>
        <p>Fleisher also engaged in a legal fight with a former partner -- his brother, Mark -- over the breakup of their business association.</p>
        <p>Lakers Turn Defensive</p>
        <p>It is such a familiar story line -- Lakers Grow Up, Learn How to Win -- that not even Phil Jackson is buying it until the postseason begins. But in his first year with Shaquille O'Neal and Kobe Bryant, Jackson has gotten the Lakers to buy into a defensive philosophy that may pay huge dividends in a few months.</p>
        <p>There is a reason the Lakers won their 10th straight game last week, have won 17 of their last 18 and at 25-5 possess the best record in the National Basketball Association. It is not the triangle offense as much as it is a collapsing defense that has taken ammunition from some of the league's top guns.</p>
        <p>The Lakers are not as pretty but they are much more gritty.</p>
        <p>''Phil has got us believing in helping each other out and shutting teams down,'' O'Neal said. ''We're still unstoppable sometimes on offense. But when we turn up the defensive intensity, it's lights out, baby. People think we're just pretty boys out here.</p>
        <p>''We can get down and dirty, too. It just took a few years for us realize our capabilities.''</p>
        <p>The Lakers finished December with a 14-1 record. They have not lost since Dec. 8 in Sacramento.</p>
        <p>Blaming the Coach</p>
        <p>In the wake of his firing last week, it is open for debate whether P. J. Carlesimo had lost the respect of his players at Golden State.</p>
        <p>But one wonders if his tenure in the Bay Area would have been different had the franchise made a concerted effort to draft and build around Vince Carter instead of his North Carolina teammate, Antawn Jamison, drafted one spot behind Carter.</p>
        <p>Or if the Warriors had decided to send Latrell Sprewell to Miami for a legitimate power forward, P. J. Brown, and a serviceable shooting guard, Dan Majerle, instead of to the Knicks for John Starks, Chris Mills and Terry Cummings.</p>
        <p>''P. J. wasn't the problem as much as everyone thinks he was,'' said a recently released Warrior, who requested anonymity. ''We didn't have any players. They still don't have any players.''</p>
        <p>Around the League</p>
        <p>As the Year 2000 begins, it has come to this: Isaiah Rider says he is sick and tired of teammates who don't care enough about winning. Rider, a renowned malcontent, laced into teammates after a loss to the Pacers on Wednesday, using an expletive-filled diatribe to vent his frustration over the Hawks' being outscored by 40-10 in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>''People don't care, man,'' Rider said. ''I'm tired of this laughing and giggling. We're losing. I care. I want to win.''</p>
        <p>Rider entered the weekend averaging 23.0 points, good for 10th in the league. He said those numbers mean little because of the Hawks' 11-18 record.</p>
        <p>He was so angry about the loss, he missed Atlanta's team flight to Detroit on the same night, his third missed flight of the season, and the Hawks suspended him for one game. . . . From the Future-Hall-of-Famers-Play-Hurt Dept.: John Stockton's nose was broken in the closing minute of Monday night's 92-91 victory over the Phoenix Suns, when Jason Kidd struck him with an elbow. Stockton, 37, played Wednesday against Vancouver.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
