<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>View With a Room</title>
    <meta content="02DINE$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Highlawn Pavillion (West Orange, NJ, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Catherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4DC1438F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>View With a Room</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Catherine</byline>
      <dateline>WEST ORANGE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>VA</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PERCHED atop Eagle Rock Reservation, Highlawn Pavilion makes every effort to be a destination restaurant, a place to come for a stroll along the promenade, to sip drinks in the lounge, to pause and watch the chefs at work, and to enjoy a leisurely dinner beside a stunning view of the New York City skyline before finally taking a winding drive through the woods back down to civilization.</p>
        <p>But, in reality, the tall ceilings trap a lot of noise, the bar is so crowded that it's hard to get served, and the service could be a lot more polished.  At some point, the diversions become distractions, and in turn Highlawn Pavilion has lost a bit of what a restaurant should be: a comfortable setting in which one can graciously be fed delicious fare. Ossana Mickail, clearly an accomplished chef, seems to have gotten caught up in the hubbub. But some of his dishes reveal pure talent that should take center stage and might even eclipse the view.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PERCHED atop Eagle Rock Reservation, Highlawn Pavilion makes every effort to be a destination restaurant, a place to come for a stroll along the promenade, to sip drinks in the lounge, to pause and watch the chefs at work, and to enjoy a leisurely dinner beside a stunning view of the New York City skyline before finally taking a winding drive through the woods back down to civilization.</p>
        <p>But, in reality, the tall ceilings trap a lot of noise, the bar is so crowded that it's hard to get served, and the service could be a lot more polished.  At some point, the diversions become distractions, and in turn Highlawn Pavilion has lost a bit of what a restaurant should be: a comfortable setting in which one can graciously be fed delicious fare. Ossana Mickail, clearly an accomplished chef, seems to have gotten caught up in the hubbub. But some of his dishes reveal pure talent that should take center stage and might even eclipse the view.</p>
        <p>One of these dishes is the sashimi tuna tasting appetizer, featuring tuna tartare, seared tuna, and a tuna  roll. The fresh tartare was marinated in lime rind and olive oil and set over a papaya salsa. Beside this lay a tuna loin, coated in crushed peppercorns, quickly seared and presented above a small mound of seaweed salad. The sushi roll contained juicy slices of raw tuna, paired with a brilliant green scallion slice, and doused with a spicy dab of wasabi sour cream and a splash of a soy and maple syrup reduction. Mr. Mickail's jumbo lump crabmeat ''brulee'' was  delicious. The crabmeat was set in a souffle dish, covered with warm truffle mashed potatoes and a rich vin blanc sauce. Another favorite was the sea scallops ceviche with sea urchin. The marinade for the fish, consisting of lime juice, cilantro, olive oil, red peppers and shallots  permeated both the fish and the avocado salsa underneath. And the dressing (served in a tiny glass) was palatable on its own, should you desire a nonalcoholic bloody Mary.</p>
        <p>Other appetizers needed work, however. The Yukon gold potato sandwich, enclosing smoked salmon and American sturgeon caviar, was overly gummy and starchy. The lobster lasagne, served between layers of Mornay sauce, was frightfully sodden, perhaps because it came in a copper pot whose lid kept it warm but also kept it cooking. In contrast, the pan-seared New York State foie gras terrine arrived overly chilled, so that the layers of grilled portobello, julienned carrots and sliced pineapple were more numbing than flavorful.</p>
        <p>The entrees were similarly hit or miss. The Cajun-rubbed red snapper was clearly a hit. For this dish, Mr. Mickail (who trained at Lausanne in Switzerland and then spent nine years at the Terrace Restaurant in Manhattan) slowly caramelized shallots in white wine, brown sugar and butter, and the resulting stew gently flavored both the fish and the  sliced red potatoes.</p>
        <p>The meat courses were hearty but bland. The sesame-crusted rack of lamb was the best of the lot, cut into loin and chops. The lamb was dressed in an Asian-infused barbecue sauce and a pomegranate lamb jus, whose flavors married well but were often hard to uncover amid the heavy accompaniments of feta cheese polenta, roasted acorn squash, and wilted spinach. The pepper-seared veal chop, the size of a fist, had lost most of its flavor during cooking. Similarly, the grilled chicken cutlet, set over a pine nut couscous and Moroccan vegetable tagine, was overcooked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mickail's real passion is for pastries. His experience at a Geneva pastry shop provided inspiration for  the warm Granny Smith apple tart, whose pate sable crust was as rich as a classic butter cookie. A generous portion of this simple fruit was all I craved at the end of this creative meal. The fricassee of fresh fruit and berries was also spectacular in its clean simplicity. Encased in a caramel tulip, the fruit and berries were colorful and fresh, heightened by a  trio of lime, raspberry and mango sorbets.</p>
        <p>The pecan chocolate tartlet, made with caramel, chocolate chips and pecans in a sweet pate brisee shell, was delightful on its own. But it was even better when set atop seared marshmallows and a sauce of marshmallow and creme anglaise.  The chocolate caramel tower, made of chocolate sponge cake and caramel mousse, was lightened by a dollop of chilled mint chip ice cream, offset by fried mint leaves and a swirl of white and dark chocolate sauces.</p>
        <p>Three desserts were somewhat bungled versions of beloved classics.  The banana split, a glass boat filled with caramelized bananas and toasted almonds, fresh berries, vanilla and chocolate ice cream and raspberry sauce was crowded and overpowering. The creme brulee was eggy and chunky rather than smooth and decadent. The cheese cake was dry and dense.</p>
        <p>A resident of Chatham, Mr. Mickail was a former customer of Highlawn Pavilion during his tenure at the Terrace Restaurant. In the three years since he's been cooking rather than dining there, he has transformed the bistro fare of simple steaks and fries into creative, mostly successful haute cuisine. If he can keep his eye on what he does best, which is to marry flavors in a straightforward but elegant manner, then people will continue to flock to Highlawn Pavilion not just for the  ambience or the view, but for the one reason he hopes they come already: for the food.</p>
        <p>Highlawn Pavilion  Eagle Rock Reservation, West Orange  (973) 731-3463</p>
        <p>GOOD  ATMOSPHERE -- An excellent view from a fanciful, noisy space.  SERVICE -- Courteous but slow.  SMOKING -- Permitted in the lounge only.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Sashimi tuna tasting; jump lump crabmeat brulee; sea scallop ceviche; Cajun-rubbed red snapper; sesame crusted rack of lamb; seared jumbo prawns; warm Granny smith apple tart; fricassee of fruit and berries, pecan chocolate tartlet; chocolate caramel tower.  PRICE RANGE -- appetizers: $6 to $14; salads: $6 to $7; entrees: $19 to $30; desserts: $7.25.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major accepted.  HOURS -- Lunch: weekdays: noon to 3 p.m.; Dinner: Mondays to Thursdays: 5:30 to 9:30 p.m., Fridays 5:30 to 10:30 P.M., Saturdays 5 to 10:30 p.m., Sundays 5 to 9:30 p.m.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Restaurant, bar and bathrooms on one level (elevator to private rooms upstairs).</p>
        <p>RATINGS -- Poor to Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
