<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN A BUSY START, NEW RUSSIA LEADER GOES TO CHECHNYA</title>
    <meta content="02RUSS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Movements and Secession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chechnya (Russia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohlen, Celestine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Chechnya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E3DE1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN A BUSY START, NEW RUSSIA LEADER GOES TO CHECHNYA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bohlen, Celestine</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Jan. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Acting Pres Vladimir V Putin celebrates New Year with Russian troops fighting in Chechnya; visit offers nation used to Boris N Yeltsin a new image of an active, concerned leader and reflects Putin's close association with Chechnya battle; his success in presidential elections now scheduled for March 26 could well hinge on success of campaign; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On his first full day as Russia's acting president, Vladimir V. Putin left before dawn today to visit with Russian troops fighting in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>While his predecessor, Boris N. Yeltsin, spent his first day of retirement at a government country house outside Moscow, Mr. Putin and his wife, Lyudmila -- he in a turtleneck sweater, she in pants and a sheepskin coat -- spent what was left of the momentous New Year's holiday greeting Russian soldiers and handing out hunting knives as presidential souvenirs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On his first full day as Russia's acting president, Vladimir V. Putin left before dawn today to visit with Russian troops fighting in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>While his predecessor, Boris N. Yeltsin, spent his first day of retirement at a government country house outside Moscow, Mr. Putin and his wife, Lyudmila -- he in a turtleneck sweater, she in pants and a sheepskin coat -- spent what was left of the momentous New Year's holiday greeting Russian soldiers and handing out hunting knives as presidential souvenirs.</p>
        <p>Accompanied by a popular Russian singer, Mr. Putin attended an improvised New Year's celebration, at which he hugged several mothers of soldiers injured while fighting in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>Besides offering the nation a new image of an active, concerned leader, the visit reflected Mr. Putin's close association with the Chechnya battle. Since he was named prime minister last August as a largely unknown K.G.B. officer, his visibility and popularity have soared with the conduct of the campaign in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>But now the war has apparently entered a far more difficult phase as Russian troops seek to dislodge Chechen fighters from Grozny, the capital. And Mr. Putin's success in presidential elections now scheduled for March 26 could well hinge on the success of the campaign, and the ability of the Russian commanders to hold down their casualties.</p>
        <p>In Gudermes, the second largest city in Chechnya, now in Russian hands, Mr. Putin said: ''We are not going to liberate anything quickly. We are going to do our best. The best means with the least losses among our personnel, our military men among the population.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin again said there was no deadline for concluding the war.</p>
        <p>The unexpected trip, taken less than 24 hours after Mr. Yeltsin resigned and handed his job to Mr. Putin, gave Russians a different image of their leadership from the hesitant, breath-holding fumbles and gaffes they had grown used to in the final years of the Yeltsin era.</p>
        <p>In his brief time in office, Mr. Putin -- who retains the office of prime minister -- has crammed in what previously would have been a week's worth of presidential events, including the taping of a televised New Year's message, a meeting with the Security Council, another with his cabinet and two sessions with Mr. Yeltsin, including a final meeting late Friday at the former president's residence.</p>
        <p>And at 6:30 p.m. Friday, he signed a decree, one of his first as acting president, which apparently held the key to the the sudden but smooth transfer of power. Besides granting Mr. Yeltsin and his family an array of benefits and privileges, the decree gives him immunity from criminal investigation, and protects his houses, cars, papers and belongings from search and seizure.</p>
        <p>Today, Dmitri Yakushkin, Mr. Yeltsin's press secretary, disputed any suggestion that the president and his prime minister had bargained over the terms of the extraordinary transfer of power Friday.</p>
        <p>There were no negotiations, said Mr. Yakushkin, who added that the decree was most likely prepared in advance by Mr. Yeltsin's staff.</p>
        <p>The decree, described by Mr. Yakushkin as seven pages long, describes in precise detail how much of a salary the former president will get in the initial months after his resignation (75 percent of his salary of about 10,000 rubles, or $40,000), how much money he will have available to spend on staff, his access to government air and train terminals, and other perks associated with the top Kremlin job.</p>
        <p>But the immunity clause, limited to the president himself, was the most striking, hinting at the kinds of concerns that Mr. Yeltsin had as he prepared secretly to leave office. Former aides to Mr. Yeltsin, whose administration has been scarred by reports of wide corruption, have said in the past that the president and his family would consider early resignation only if their physical safety and economic security could be guaranteed.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Yeltsin was the first democratically elected president in Russia, there were no precedents for such guarantees. Mr. Yeltsin, who moved into the Kremlin after the dissolution of the Soviet Union, gave its previous occupant, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, a generous package of benefits and privileges and a rent-free office building when the Soviet president left office on Dec. 31, 1991.  But as Mr. Gorbachev was to discover, those benefits could also be taken away, depending on the whim and mood of the man who granted them.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Putin's decree ostensibly gives the Yeltsin family the guarantees it was seeking, the benefits and privileges are still not fixed in law. Passing a law on the status of former presidents was a proposal made last summer by former Prime Minister Yevgeny M. Primakov, then a leading opposition candidate for the presidency, as he tried publicly to assuage Mr. Yeltsin's anxiety about giving up his Kremlin job.</p>
        <p>But by propelling the presidential elections forward by three months, thus giving Mr. Putin -- his preferred successor and the current political hero -- a considerable advantage, Mr. Yeltsin apparently could not wait for legislation that would have to clear Parliament.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Yakushkin, Mr. Yeltsin kept his decision to resign a closely guarded secret until the last minute. Although Mr. Putin may have known ahead of time, no official preparations for such a hand-over of power were made by the Kremlin staff, he said.</p>
        <p>As press secretary, he got a call early in the morning, and found Mr. Yeltsin in his Kremlin office at 8:30 a.m., ready to tape the broadcast that went on the Russian government channel at noon Friday. All day Friday, Mr. Yeltsin was very calm and friendly, Mr. Yakushkin said. Mr. Yeltsin gave flowers to the television crew, drank Champagne and said goodbye to many people with whom he had worked. That was the mood of the day.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
