<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Civics to You, Greek to Nassau</title>
    <meta content="02NASS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DB1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2222" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Civics to You, Greek to Nassau</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>MINEOLA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democrats will take over Nassau County's legislative branch for first time in more than 80 years; advent of two-party system in county raises many questions for all concerned; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NO, John W. Canning was explaining, the Nassau County Legislature was not like Major League Baseball. He and his fellow legislators actually have to live in the districts they represent, unlike the Yankees, who do not have to live in the Bronx or even in New York.</p>
        <p>A hand shot up. How old do legislators have to be? a fifth grader from Glenwood Landing School asked on a recent class trip here to the county legislature. Eighteen years old, Mr. Canning replied. Then a final question was broached. Do the legislators do secret Santas? The answer was no.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NO, John W. Canning was explaining, the Nassau County Legislature was not like Major League Baseball. He and his fellow legislators actually have to live in the districts they represent, unlike the Yankees, who do not have to live in the Bronx or even in New York.</p>
        <p>A hand shot up. How old do legislators have to be? a fifth grader from Glenwood Landing School asked on a recent class trip here to the county legislature. Eighteen years old, Mr. Canning replied. Then a final question was broached. Do the legislators do secret Santas? The answer was no.</p>
        <p>School civics classes are not the only ones asking questions about the inner workings of the Nassau County Legislature these days. With the Democrats taking over the county's legislative branch this week for the first time in more than 80 years -- after Mr. Canning and four of his Republican colleagues were voted out of office in November's election -- local government here is being launched into uncharted waters.</p>
        <p>The citizens of Nassau are learning about some several new concepts in local governance, like the two-party system. It is true that the nation's founding father, George Washington, once warned against such a system. But in the two centuries since his day the system has gained great currency in the vast stretches of country that lie beyond Nassau County's borders.</p>
        <p>Here in Nassau, though, it is still a somewhat exotic proposition. When the Legislature was created in this overwhelmingly Republican county in 1996 -- replacing the old Board of Supervisors, which had always been controlled by Republicans -- the Grand Old Party won a 13 to 6 majority. The county executive, Thomas S. Gulotta, is very much a Republican himself, so the county's Democrats, who saw their ranks on the Legislature dwindle to just 5 in 1998, had little say in what went on here.</p>
        <p>But come this week they will get their turn in the driver's seat, with a wafer-thin 10-to-9 majority.</p>
        <p>With the advent of this so-called two-party system will come another idea that is being described in local political science circles here as checks and balances. Some scholars credit the Greek historian Polybius with recognizing the benefits of checks and balances more than 2,100 years ago in his analysis of the Roman constitution. Others cite more recent thinkers, like Montesquieu and Locke, not to mention the Federalists.</p>
        <p>What it boils down to in Nassau County is this: if Mr. Gulotta hates the laws passed by the Legislature he can veto them. And if the Democrats hate his proposals or budgets, they can prevent them from passing.</p>
        <p>Of course, the county had a brief preview of checks and balances this year when Republican lawmakers fell out with Mr. Gulotta. They tore up his proposed budget, passed their own version and then partly undid it by repealing a real estate transfer tax that they had included at his urging. Their huge majority in the Legislature made them veto-proof. They could simply override any vetoes of Mr. Gulotta's, so their actions stood.</p>
        <p>This is where things stand to get quite interesting this year. The Democrats will not be veto-proof. They will lack the two-thirds majority needed to override Mr. Gulotta's vetoes.</p>
        <p>All of which points to a potential risk of the checks and balances system: there can be such a thing as simply too much balance. In chemistry, equilibrium is desirable. In government, it is more often called stagnation. The risk here is that if things here are checked too much -- by constant vetoes on Mr. Gulotta's part or by a refusal by the Legislature to pass any of the bills he champions -- nothing will get done.</p>
        <p>This means that local politicians of all stripes and creeds may need to brush up on what was known by the Roman lawmakers as quid pro quo and in frontier democracies as horse-trading but is better known these days simply as deal-making.</p>
        <p>The big question is who will deal with whom.</p>
        <p>* Will the Democrats hold out an olive branch to Mr. Gulotta, agreeing to pass some laws he wants so that he won't veto the laws they want?</p>
        <p>* Will Democratic and Republican legislators band together against Mr. Gulotta, a perceived common enemy, and muster the votes to override his vetoes?</p>
        <p>* Is it remotely possible that Republican legislators will make up with Mr. Gulotta, whom they reviled and blamed for their defeat, so they can present a unified Republican front against the Democrats?</p>
        <p>* Or will everyone simply be at each other's throats all the time, blocking everyone else so that nothing ever gets done?</p>
        <p>At this point few people around the county seat are taking bets. To be sure, all three local powers -- the executive, the Democrats and the Republican legislators -- are using phrases like ''working together,'' which is usually coupled with the suffix ''in a bipartisan fashion.'' But no one here is sure quite how, or even if, this will come to pass.</p>
        <p>Of course, this is not Prime Minister's Question Time from the British House of Commons. It is a county legislature. Most of its regular business is mundane, nuts-and-bolts appropriations bills and appointments to county boards and the like. Many legislators also work hard to provide small services for constituents, whether by cutting red tape or lobbying county agencies to provide local services. These items rarely generate much debate and often pass unanimously.</p>
        <p>But on occasion the Legislature actually does pass new laws. Just last month it decided to regulate the placement of tobacco products and to restrict the display of sexually explicit materials in stores.</p>
        <p>And with a budget crisis roiling the county, there is sure to be some lively political back and forth in the coming months as the Legislature begins to keep closer tabs on the county's spending, and to wrangle over budget cuts.</p>
        <p>Some worry that the county is in such bad shape that it will take outside intervention in the form of a fiscal control board or monitor to pull it out of its fiscal mess of recurring budget deficits and bond ratings near junk.</p>
        <p>But the Legislature has an important role here. During its recent war of words with Mr. Gulotta, the old Republican-led Legislature passed a number of laws giving the Legislature much more oversight of the budget process. Now the Democrats will inherit that system. And at the end of the year they will no doubt have to pass a pretty austere budget for the county.</p>
        <p>It is a tall order for a four-year-old Legislature that is a work in progress. It was created after the courts abolished its predecessor, the Board of Supervisors, a six-member panel with a system of weighted votes, on the grounds that it violated the one-person-one-vote principle.</p>
        <p>''I think it is too early to judge whether this new system is working well,'' said Herbert D. Rosenbaum, a professor emeritus of political science at Hofstra University. ''Unfortunately, they are being forced to make some very dramatic decisions which give them no choice but to grow up in a hurry. They get no political childhood or adolescence; they have to grow up right away.''</p>
        <p>Basically, the Legislature works like this: there are 19 legislators, each representing around 70,000 of Nassau County's 1.3 million residents.</p>
        <p>The majority party, now the Democrats, names the Legislature's presiding officer, a position much like the speaker of the House of Representatives in Washington. Judith A. Jacobs, a Democratic legislator from Woodbury, will be formally given the job tomorrow. She replaces Bruce A. Blakeman, who served in the role for the past four years and lost not only his Republican majority but also his legislative seat in the November elections.</p>
        <p>As presiding officer, Ms. Jacobs will more or less run the Legislature. She will call meetings to order, cede the floor to speakers she recognizes and refer proposals to committee.</p>
        <p>More importantly, Ms. Jacobs will have the power to refer proposed laws to committees for study and to bring them before the rest of the Legislature for votes. This is where things get done. And this is one area where Ms. Jacobs and her Democratic colleagues are proposing to make some changes.</p>
        <p>When the Democrats were in the minority, they complained that their bills were almost never brought out of committee to be voted on. ''They would fall into a black hole,'' Ms. Jacobs said recently, ''never to be heard from again.'' So Ms. Jacobs has pledged to streamline the bill-passing process to make sure that no bills, regardless of the party affiliation of their sponsors, languish in what she calls ''the darkness.''</p>
        <p>Peter J. Schmitt, a Republican from Massapequa, will serve as the minority leader. His job will be to keep his fellow Republicans voting together and to make sure they remain an entity to contend with. Mr. Schmitt said he did not object to Ms. Jacobs's proposals, several of which would strengthen the minority party. But he did defend the old system, noting that the practice of picking and choosing which bills come to a vote makes for more efficient governing and is modeled on the New York State Assembly's system.</p>
        <p>And he took issue with the Democrats' labeling of the proposed changes as Open and Honest Government Reforms. ''It's a bit shrill,'' he said. ''They make it look like we practiced closed and dishonest government.''</p>
        <p>The presiding officer and the minority leader each assign legislators to sit on committees that monitor everything from the Legislature's own rules to public safety, local municipalities, public works and finance. And, behind the scenes, each party has its own counsel, well versed in the intricacies of local government and lawmaking.</p>
        <p>Many of the proposals by Ms. Jacobs and the Democratic counsel, Chuck Cutolo, aim to make the Legislature more user-friendly.</p>
        <p>For one thing, the Legislature has not been known in the past for its punctuality. Last month, for example, dozens of social workers descended on the building at 1 West Street in Mineola, where the Legislature meets, to protest budget cuts, only to be kept waiting for more than two hours before the meeting started. Then they had to wait longer before the meeting was opened for comments; the rules give public speakers only three minutes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jacobs wants to make it mandatory to keep the public informed of delays as they happen, and wants to open meetings with a 30-minute public comment period so people can come to speak without wasting their whole day. She also wants to begin letting the public speak at committee meetings, which is often where bills are substantively shaped into final form, and to provide summaries that explain legislation in understandable English. That last item is not insignificant. In the past the Legislature has borne some resemblance to the old joke about the two convicts who have been in jail for so long that they know all of each other's jokes and have even numbered them, so one only has to say ''49!'' to get a big laugh out of the other. The Legislature, for its part, has been known to vote on items and resolutions and ordinances by number only, with little further explanation or debate. It has not always been easy for members of the public to follow.</p>
        <p>Neal M. Lewis, executive director  of the Long Island Neighborhood Network, who worked on the charter revision committee that created the Legislature, praised the proposed reforms as much needed. ''People would end up waiting eight hours to make a three-minute comment,'' he said. ''I would often get these comments that 'You created a disaster' or 'You created this thing and they shut out the public completely.' ''</p>
        <p>Whether any of this will help the county emerge from its financial straits is another question. The Democrats must now move from critics with little clout to rulers who must come up with solutions. The Republicans will have to adjust from a position of absolute power to their new status as outsiders.</p>
        <p>Howard A. Scarrow, a professor of political science at the State University at Stony Brook, said he believed that with the advent of two-party government and checks and balances, the Legislature could come into its own.</p>
        <p>''The Republicans have been so dominant that the Democrats weren't even able to get something on the agenda,'' he said. ''They almost might as well have not even been there. Now, with all the changes, it will really be the first time the people will see how the legislature could work. I often wonder if the voters in Nassau County even realized the importance of creating a Legislature, because it acted so much like the old system.''</p>
        <p>''It is going to be wonderful fun,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
