<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A/Lynne Lehrman Weiner; Films Honor a Writer's Father, and Freud</title>
    <meta content="02FREU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Freud, Sigmund, Museum (Vienna)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freud, Sigmund (1856-1939)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Lynne Lehrman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lehrman, Philip R (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2D81638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A/Lynne Lehrman Weiner; Films Honor a Writer's Father, and Freud</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONNA GREENE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lynne Lehrman Weiner discusses documentary films she has produced about Sigmund Freud, compiled from home movies taken by her father, Dr Philip R Lehrman, during his studies with Freud in Vienna in 1920's; interview; photo; films are part of exhibits at Freud Museum in Vienna (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of Lynne Lehrman Weiner's regrets is that at the age of 2 in 1928 when she was asked by Sigmund Freud to sing him a nursery song, she said no, preferring to play with his dogs. A White Plains resident now, she was living in Vienna at the time with her family, because her father, Dr. Philip R. Lehrman, a psychoanalyst, was studying with Freud.</p>
        <p>Along with studying, Dr. Lehrman was taking movies -- movies of his family and of Freud and his associates. For many years these black-and-white movies without sound sat in a closet. But now, as a result of Ms. Weiner's efforts as an editor and producer, they are part of two exhibitions, one at the Sigmund Freud Museum in Freud's house in Vienna and the other part of a touring exhibit, now also in Vienna, sponsored by the Library of Congress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of Lynne Lehrman Weiner's regrets is that at the age of 2 in 1928 when she was asked by Sigmund Freud to sing him a nursery song, she said no, preferring to play with his dogs. A White Plains resident now, she was living in Vienna at the time with her family, because her father, Dr. Philip R. Lehrman, a psychoanalyst, was studying with Freud.</p>
        <p>Along with studying, Dr. Lehrman was taking movies -- movies of his family and of Freud and his associates. For many years these black-and-white movies without sound sat in a closet. But now, as a result of Ms. Weiner's efforts as an editor and producer, they are part of two exhibitions, one at the Sigmund Freud Museum in Freud's house in Vienna and the other part of a touring exhibit, now also in Vienna, sponsored by the Library of Congress.</p>
        <p>Ms. Weiner is a freelance writer, former member of the White Plains Human Rights Commission and former committeewoman of the New York State Democratic party. When her father died in 1958, she continued the work they had begun together to edit the films. Here are excerpts from a recent conversation:</p>
        <p>Q. Why did your father go to Vienna to see Freud?</p>
        <p>A. He was a psychoanalyst and had been working with A. A. Brill, who was America's first psychoanalyst. No one knew much about psychoanalysis then, but Brill was the first to translate Freud's works into English. And he was quite a bit older than Dad, some 28 years or something, and Dad met him when he was a young student and Brill really became his mentor and suggested that he seek further psychoanalytic training. Dad really did want to do this, but only with Sigmund Freud. So Dad began a correspondence with him that lasted many, many years. And finally Freud accepted him in 1928, when I was 2. So my mother, father, brother and I all went to Vienna, and we spent a year there, and Dad became his student.</p>
        <p>Q. When did your father begin taking movies of Freud?</p>
        <p>A. Dad began to film everybody that he met. It actually became somewhat of a joke. Of course, in those days it was black-and-white and without sound. It was also a six-focus lens, which was a very good lens at the time, but it meant he had to get people into the light. And this was hard because it was a long, very bitter winter, apparently. Dad said it was difficult to get people to lean out of a window or to get them out in the sun. He did the best he could, and I thought his photography was quite excellent.</p>
        <p>Q. Your father was taking these films as a family memento, correct?</p>
        <p>A. Oh, yes, and also because he recognized that Freud was a historical subject, that he was doing something of greater import than just taking movies of just anybody. And Freud was very loathe to have him take movies of him. He didn't like to be photographed, and he kept putting Dad off. But finally he said: You're very compulsive about this. Let's analyze it first. And that became the family joke. So that was the way it went. After a few months of analysis, Freud relented.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you have memories of meeting Freud at the age of 2?</p>
        <p>A. I do have some memories of sitting on Freud's lap. And I do have memories of being in his apartment because he had small dogs, and I was very intent on playing with them. Once, he called me over to sing him a little song, and it seems that I had a good pitch and could sing these songs. But I didn't want to do it for him because I was so busy with the dogs. That is a very strong memory and it was reinforced over the years by Dad and Mother always telling me the tale. I regret it now.</p>
        <p>Q. What happened to the films after you left Vienna in 1929?</p>
        <p>A. We came back to the United States, and Dad went on with his practice and saw Freud, I think, twice after that time before he died. Dad had a successful practice here. All that time, the films were in his closet in his office. He was still taking family photos, and he showed me how to splice film and gave me the job of doing it with the family films. But I never saw the Freud films until I was a teenager. They obviously were very precious to him, and he didn't want to just take them out and show them to just anybody. And he never did until 1950.</p>
        <p>Then there was a major meeting of American psychoanalysts in New York City. It was one of the first major meetings after World War II, and a lot of those people that he knew in Europe had come here as refugees. He had a showing of his films. This was just the raw footage, and he asked my help in putting them in a logical order. By that time, he had forgotten a lot of the names and didn't have the time to do some of the research that he should have done. He showed the movie, and there was an audio tape made of his extemporaneous narration and there were people in the audience who shouted out names. And people would say, there's me, that's me. So later when I was working on putting the film together after my father died I found that tape absolutely by accident among his papers. When I listened to it, I burst into tears. It was like Dad had come back to life. It was the first time I had heard his voice in so many years. And then I realized that I had what I needed to make a proper documentary.</p>
        <p>I got a grant in 1985 from the general funders of the Sigmund Freud Museum in London, and I promised them that when I finished the film I would take all the restrictions off it.</p>
        <p>Q. Was there then an earlier version of your father's Freud home movies?</p>
        <p>A. Dad and I had done a 20-minute version. I later learned they were supposed to be locked until 2057. I called Dr. Kurt Eissler, the former director of the Sigmund Freud Archives, and said: You know what will happen in 2057. You're going to find nothing but dust in that vault. The films will be dust. You cannot lock them up. I want to unrestrict the films. I said I was sure my father didn't realize the implications of locking up the film. Papers, maybe yes, patient records, maybe yes. But certainly not the films.</p>
        <p>Q. Why should anyone have cared if the Freud films were made public?</p>
        <p>A. He cared because Anna Freud apparently did not like the idea that these pictures were so good that they showed Freud's wound on his cheek. He had cancer of the mouth, and he was in pain a lot from 1923 on. He was in pain almost every day of his life, and she didn't want it known. She also declined to help me identify people because she said she didn't approve of making the films public. She thought if the general public were to see him in the distress he was in that it would take away from his intellect. To have anybody say anything negative was a tremendous source of horror for her. She was really his protector before he died and after.</p>
        <p>But I decided I was going to go ahead with my project -- they were my father's films. I had copyrighted them, and I could do what I liked. I didn't want to be irresponsible about it, but I certainly felt they should be seen by the public and as soon as they were done, that's what I have done. I have been running around the world showing them to groups that invite me.</p>
        <p>Q. So now they are on exhibit in Vienna. Describe the exhibition.</p>
        <p>A. It is called, when translated from the German, ''Psychoanalysis in Motion.'' The film, which is shown on the hour, is titled ''Sigmund Freud, His Family and Colleagues, 1928-1947.'' It is not about anything. They are home movies of people walking in the street, of Dad seen screaming from behind his camera: Do something, shake hands, raise your hat. He was sort of the director. The exhibit that they did in Vienna is most amazing to me, because Lydia Marinelli is the curator and a highly intelligent, energetic young woman who had a vision. She took images off the film of the Viennese groups, and they had in their archives in Vienna a tremendous amount of information about almost all of the people who were in the movie, and they had books and articles and manuscripts of all kinds. They knew their birth dates and death dates and much about their contributions to psychoanalysis. So they proceeded to simply turn the museum into a living moving picture. They made posters of these images, and some of these posters became placards all over Vienna. Every place they could they had Dad's name, mine too, of course, but I was just thrilled to see Dad's name prominently displayed all over.</p>
        <p>They invited me to come and give an introduction to the film on the opening day of the exhibit, which I did, Oct. 20. The next day, the 21st, was the opening of the Library of Congress Exhibit in Vienna.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
