<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lives Lived Well And the Lessons That They Teach</title>
    <meta content="116750SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D8163BF931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="6611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lives Lived Well And the Lessons That They Teach</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY never made the cover of People magazine. Sometimes they did not even make headlines in their community's weekly newspaper. But they made a difference in the way they lived. And they made a difference in Westchester, where they lived.</p>
        <p>Some were young, just in their 40's. Others had 90 or more years to make their mark. Some of their accomplishments were very public. Others were very private. Many were teachers at heart, even if they never set foot in a classroom or made a formal lesson plan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY never made the cover of People magazine. Sometimes they did not even make headlines in their community's weekly newspaper. But they made a difference in the way they lived. And they made a difference in Westchester, where they lived.</p>
        <p>Some were young, just in their 40's. Others had 90 or more years to make their mark. Some of their accomplishments were very public. Others were very private. Many were teachers at heart, even if they never set foot in a classroom or made a formal lesson plan.</p>
        <p>They had this in common: though their lives ended in 1999, their legacies endure: landscapes reshaped both physically and politically, doors opening for racial minorities or the arts promoted with passionate devotion.</p>
        <p>Here is a collection of vignettes, all written by Kate Stone Lombardi, about people whose deaths did, indeed, diminish Westchester. But, more importantly, they are stories of people whose lives continue to enrich the communities where they lived and the people they lived with -- both those who knew them well and those who will be making their acquaintance here for the first time.</p>
        <p>WRITING HIMSELF INTO LEGAL HISTORY</p>
        <p>IT remains the largest mass murder trial in Westchester's history, and one of the county's most dramatic legal moments. Four days after a jury convicted a waiter of setting the fire that killed 26 people at the Stouffer's Inn in Harrison in December 1980, Judge Lawrence N. Martin set aside the verdict, freeing the man who stood trial.</p>
        <p>Judge Martin said the prosecutor had not proved his case and had persuaded the jury by ''trying to twist and turn the pieces of the puzzle to fit the picture he had painted.'' There were gasps in the packed courtroom, and the district attorney who had prosecuted the case, Carl A. Vergari, called Judge Martin's decision ''a grave perversion of justice.'' The case was appealed, but New York's highest court upheld Judge Martin's ruling.</p>
        <p>The decision was entirely in keeping with Judge Martin's character, his widow, Carmen Martin, said. ''He had no doubts whatsoever,'' she said. ''He never cowered, and he was never concerned about the political ramifications. He came home directly from court after the verdict was announced and sat down at the kitchen table, took out a yellow pad and started writing. It just flowed, and there wasn't even a second draft.''</p>
        <p>At the time, Judge Martin's decision in the high profile case took a toll on his family. For months they received hate mail and threats.</p>
        <p>Luis Marin, the man Judge Martin freed, surprised Mrs. Martin by coming to her husband's funeral. She said that Mr. Marin told her he had always been grateful to Judge Martin for giving him a second chance.</p>
        <p>''I recognized him immediately,'' Mrs. Martin said. ''He came over and shook my hand and expressed his condolences. Larry always felt good about his decision in the case. He never lost any sleep over it.''</p>
        <p>Though he is most remembered for presiding over the Stouffer's trial, Judge Martin had a varied career. A lifelong Democrat, he headed the White Plains Youth for Kennedy-Johnson, which garnered him an invitation to President Kennedy's inauguration. Lawrence Martin missed it though -- he stayed home instead to study for his bar exam. He was admitted to the bar in 1961 and worked as a trial lawyer, judge and judicial consultant for more than 35 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin worked as a lawyer for the Securities and Exchange Commission, the Manhattan District Attorney's Office, the Westchester District Attorney's Office and the Legal Aid Society of Westchester. In 1975, at the age of 37, he became the first Democrat to be elected a Westchester County judge in 41 years. As a County Court judge, he presided over more than 200 trials. He was later appointed to the state Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>After he left the bench in 1986, Judge Martin was appointed by Andrew O'Rourke, who was then county executive, to investigate a multimillion-dollar garbage hauling contract between Westchester County government and a private garbage company. Again, he did not hesitate to take a politically unpopular stance. The Martin report argued that the garbage hauling contract was in violation of the law because it had been rewritten without seeking bids from other companies. Last year, when the Westchester Board of Legislators decided to establish a solid waste commission with broad powers over the private garbage hauling industry, Judge Martin's report was among the research that influenced the decision.</p>
        <p>Judge Martin was known for never raising his voice in court. Those in the know, however, could tell if the judge was angry by monitoring the color of his ears -- the redder they got, the angrier he was.</p>
        <p>Judge Martin loved dogs and bred and trained them. He began with St. Bernards and then moved on to golden retrievers. ''He always said that dog was God spelled backward,'' Mrs. Martin said.</p>
        <p>After he closed his practice in White Plains in 1996, the Martins moved to Nantucket so that Judge Martin could be near his other love -- the water. ''If he could see the ocean, he was happy,'' Mrs. Martin said.</p>
        <p>Lawrence Martin died Nov. 29 at the age of 63.</p>
        <p>CARING FOR THE CHILDREN</p>
        <p>FOR more than 60 years, Virginia Wise Marx devoted herself to the care and education of children. An educator, psychologist and philanthropist, Mrs. Marx was most recently known for helping to establish a day-care center at Westchester Community College in Valhalla.</p>
        <p>''If it weren't for the children's center, quite a few of our students wouldn't be able to go on to college,'' Dr. Joseph N. Hankin, president of the Westchester Community College, said at the dedication of the center, which is named for Mrs. Marx. ''They wouldn't be able to get marketable skills and go on to good jobs. Those who are on welfare wouldn't be able to get off.''</p>
        <p>The center, which opened in 1996, now serves nearly 100 children. It not only helps student parents but is also used as a laboratory for students studying nursing, early childhood development and food service.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Marx also helped start the Child Development Institute at Sarah Lawrence College in Yonkers, by creating a challenge grant endowment. She worked to create a center at Teachers College at Columbia University, for training educators in child care. She and her husband, a real estate developer, endowed the Virginia and Leonard Marx Professorship in Child and Parent Development and Education at Teachers College in 1993, as well as a lecture series there. The couple had three children.</p>
        <p>With the Westchester Children's Association, Mrs. Marx worked to start remedial reading programs in five school districts. For many years she was a board member of the Scarsdale Family Counseling Service, a trustee of the Jewish Board of Family and Children's Services and a chairwoman of its Child Development Center. She was also involved with the U.J.A.-Federation of New York, the White Plains Hospital Center and the Scarsdale Edgemont Family Counseling Service.</p>
        <p>She received numerous awards, among them the Scarsdale Family Counseling Service Open Door Volunteer Award and, with her husband Leonard, the Humanitarian Award from the Mental Health Association of Westchester. The Foundation for Westchester Community College gave her the Medallion Award for Leadership in Civic Affairs and she was given the Centennial Award by Teachers College at Columbia University.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Marx graduated with a degree in psychology from Washington University, and then received a master's in social work. She also earned a master's in child psychology at Teacher's College and spent a fellowship year in clinical psychology at what was then known as the Child Guidance Institute. Before her marriage she worked for Macy's, designing children's toys. Mrs. Marx also was a contributing editor to Parents Magazine and wrote an advice column about development.</p>
        <p>An elegant woman known for her exquisite taste, Mrs. Marx pursued her interest in 19th-century American furniture by supporting the American Wing of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the friends of American Art at Yale University and the Art Museum of Sarah Lawrence College.</p>
        <p>Virginia Marx died May 23. She was 93.</p>
        <p>THE DESEGREGATOR</p>
        <p>LLOYD KING was a quiet man and an effective man. The first black ever to serve as Westchester's election commissioner, Mr. King was also integral in the efforts to desegregate Mount Vernon's schools.</p>
        <p>His civil rights activism in Westchester began in the 1960's, when Mr. King was president of the Mount Vernon chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. He filed a lawsuit in 1964 on behalf of his son Jeffrey, who was then a 5-year-old kindergartner. After years of litigation and local tension, the state ordered the schools integrated, and the district instituted an open-enrollment plan. Under the new system, students from the predominantly black South Side of Mount Vernon were allowed to attend North Side schools when space was available.</p>
        <p>''Lloyd was a trail blazer,'' said M. Paul Redd, who worked with Mr. King at the Westchester-Putnam Affirmative Action Program, which Mr. Redd heads. ''Using his own kid as a test case, he spearheaded that lawsuit.''</p>
        <p>Not only did he take on the schools in the 1960's but Mr. King, with his wife, Barbara, also organized boycotts of local white-owned stores. The Kings moved to Larchmont in 1974, in part because they were still dissatisfied with the quality of education their children, Jeffrey and Todd, were receiving in Mount Vernon, and also to distance their sons from the racial tension still present there. Mr. King then became the first black elected to the Mamaroneck Board of Education, serving from 1975 to 1978.</p>
        <p>Before he worked for the county as elections commissioner, Mr. King was an investigations supervisor in the Internal Revenue Service, an executive vice president of the Interracial Council for Business Opportunities in New York City and vice president of the Westchester-Putnam Affirmative Action Program.</p>
        <p>After serving in the Army in World War II, Mr. King graduated with a degree in political science and French literature from New York University in 1950 and from Brooklyn Law School in 1956.</p>
        <p>''He was a very quiet kind of person, very smart and very effective,'' Mr. Redd said. ''He was thorough and methodic, and he got things done.''</p>
        <p>Lloyd King died Nov. 23. He was 72.</p>
        <p>THE GREAT OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>NICHOLAS SHOUMATOFF was a nature enthusiast whose passion for the outdoors led him to the hills of Jamaica, the mountains of Central Asia and the woods of northern Westchester.</p>
        <p>As a teenager, Mr. Shoumatoff spent his summers in Jamaica, studying butterflies with his uncle, Andrei Avinoff, director of the Carnegie Museum of Natural History in Pittsburgh. Together they discovered a new subspecies, a small iridescent blue butterfly with what looked like a curved hair at the bottom of its wings. The species -- Shoumatoff hairstreak -- was named for him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shoumatoff also had a passion for mountain climbing. Toting his camera, he climbed the Alps, the Rockies, the Caucasus and the Pamirs of Central Asia, along the way taking thousands of photographs of flora and fauna. Mr. Shoumatoff published two books that included his expedition pictures.</p>
        <p>A longtime Bedford resident, he had a degree in engineering from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and worked for years in the pulp and paper industry. He was director of special projects for ITT Rayonier Inc., vice president with Parsons and Whittemore, and a manager of manufacturing services at West Virginia Pulp and Paper. He was responsible for building pulp and paper mills in Eastern Europe, Asia, and South America. Mr. Shoumatoff, who holds two patents in paper making, was one of the first United States businessmen to sign major industrial contracts with countries behind the Iron Curtain during the Cold War.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shoumatoff lectured at the Explorer's Club and the American Alpine Club, but he also frequently spoke locally. He was the president of the Bedford Audubon Society and the Westmoreland Sanctuary. He was also a trustee of the Bedford Free Library and a vestryman at St. Matthew's Episcopal Church in Bedford.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shoumatoff served as curator of the trailside museum at Ward Pound Ridge Reservation in Cross River, where he often conducted nature programs. An expert on American Indians, he gave a popular lecture on what he called the ''myths'' that had developed about Pilgrims and Thanksgiving. He argued that the occasion was not solemn but somewhat rowdy and that turkey was almost certainly not on the original menu.</p>
        <p>''Wild turkeys are not easy to gun down,'' he told visitors to the museum at one lecture. ''They are elusive and wily. Those early settlers had only soldiers' muskets, which were far from being accurate. The chances are that the fowl that graced that first table were Canada geese. They were plentiful and not nearly as difficult to bag.''</p>
        <p>Nicholas Shoumatoff died Sept. 13. He was 81.</p>
        <p>THE MASTER BUILDER</p>
        <p>MICHAEL FORSTL left his legacy on the landscape, designing dozens of buildings in Westchester and Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forstl worked for 18 years with the architect Philip Johnson. Together they designed many projects, including the New York State Pavilion at the 1963 World's Fair in Queens, the New York State Theater at Lincoln Center and the Tisch School of Commerce at New York University.</p>
        <p>After leaving Johnson Associates, Mr. Forstl started his own firm. The work he was most proud of from this period was at the Institute of Fine Arts in Manhattan, where he redesigned the conservation department, his widow, Katherina, said. His designs there led to a similar job at the Metropolitan Museum of Art.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forstl worked for a Valhalla firm, Lathrop Associates, from 1993 to 1998. There, he helped design the terminal and parking garage at the Westchester County Airport and also the Flanzer Pavilion at White Plains Hospital Center. Mr. Forstl also designed the Tyler Graphics building in Mount Kisco.</p>
        <p>The architect was in demand until the end of his life and only retired when forced to by illness, his wife said. The Forstls lived in Chappaqua for 33 years in a house that Mr. Forstl designed.</p>
        <p>''He loved everything about being an architect,'' Mrs. Forstl said. ''He was always very happy with the things he did. It was his whole life.''</p>
        <p>Michael Forstl died May 1. He was 68.</p>
        <p>REDEFINING POLITICAL BOUNDARIES</p>
        <p>RHODA QUASH, the first black woman on the New Rochelle City Council, was instrumental in creating the district she later represented. Ms. Quash, a Democrat, was a leader in organizing the vote in 1993 that abolished an at-large system of electing city council members and in its place created six districts in the city. She was then elected to the newly created District 3, which ran through the middle of the city and had a 70 percent black majority.</p>
        <p>When businesses like the Home Depot and the New Roc City came to New Rochelle, Ms. Quash personally lobbied contractors to hire blacks. She led a successful effort to rename Brook Street for Malcolm X. She also started a youth employment program that placed more than 100 local teenagers in jobs.</p>
        <p>''She was a real fighter, even far more than the black community understood,'' said M. Paul Redd, head of the Westchester-Putnam Affirmative Action Program. ''She worked behind the scenes at business meetings for opportunities for minorities and women.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Quash, who was married to Tom Quash and had one son, worked as director of government affairs at the Sound Shore Medical Center in New Rochelle. She also helped run the Sunday School at St. Catherine A.M.E. Zion Church, where she was a member. She was an executive board member of the N.A.A.C.P. She had also previously served on the city Planning Board and had headed the Westchester Black Women's Political Caucus.</p>
        <p>For many years, Ms. Quash worked as a flight attendant for TWA before becoming the airline's first black corporate manager.</p>
        <p>Rhoda Quash died May 18. She was 53.</p>
        <p>RENAISSANCE MAN</p>
        <p>CHARLES TRINKAUS, a longtime history professor at Sarah Lawrence College in Yonkers, was a leading scholar of the Renaissance. He began teaching at the college in 1936 and continued until 1970, imbuing his work with his own great devotion to the humanities and his passion for careful scholarship.</p>
        <p>''Charles's great love was the Renaissance for its poetic inspiration and for affirming the human personality to its fullest,'' said Dr. Elfie S. Raymond, a professor of Classical Philosophy at Sarah Lawrence College. ''One of his main aims in teaching was to make people into careful, sensitive scholars who would see with a double vision -- who would see details with precision, but also how they fit into the larger context of culture.''</p>
        <p>John O'Malley, president of the Renaissance Society of America, said Mr. Trinkaus was among the few American scholars who, in the 1940's and 50's, ''opened the Renaissance to Americans and launched a wonderful flowering of Renaissance historical scholarship in North America.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trinkaus's doctoral dissertation, ''Adversity's Noblemen: The Italian Humanists on Happiness,'' became his first book and was noted for its innovative view of Renaissance humanism. He also wrote a two-volume work, ''In Our Image and Likeness: Humanity and Divinity in Italian Humanist Thought'' and ''The Collected Works of Erasmus: Controversies.'' All were published by the University of Toronto Press.</p>
        <p>Born in Brooklyn, Mr. Trinkaus received his bachelor's degree from Wesleyan University and his Ph.D. in history from Columbia University. He began teaching at Sarah Lawrence even before he completed his dissertation. He was devoted to small seminars and one-on-one student-faculty conference. ''He was really the spirit of the college,'' Dr. Raymond said. ''He was a great teacher who gave enormous vitality to the humanities.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trinkaus also taught at the University of Michigan for 12 years, returning to Sarah Lawrence in 1991 to teach a course, ''Man and Cosmos, Ancient, Renaissance and Modern.''</p>
        <p>Charles Trinkaus died Sept. 15. He was 87.</p>
        <p>STAR BEHIND THE SCREEN</p>
        <p>PHILIP H. REISMAN JR.'s career as a screen writer was so eclectic that his honors ranged from five Academy Awards to the Golden Tomahawk Award presented by the Westchester Historical Society. The longtime Larchmont resident was best known for his documentary films, but his versatility allowed him to write for movie newsreels and live television, as well as producing movie screenplays and dramas for commercial and public television.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reisman was best known for ''All the Way Home,'' a 1963 film adaptation of the theatrical version of James Agee's novel, ''A Death in the Family,'' which starred Robert Preston and Jean Simmons. He also wrote documentary films like ''The Real West'' (1961), which featured Gary Cooper, and ''The End of the Trail'' (1965) with Walter Brennan.</p>
        <p>It was his script for ''The Adams Chronicles'' and ''Sandburg's Lincoln'' that captured the attention of the Historical Society. Other awards included an Edgar from the Mystery Writers of America and the Peabody Award. Mr. Reisman was active in the county.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reisman was active in the county, serving as a member of the town of Mamaroneck Auxiliary Police and as a leader in the Boy Scouts. He was a trustee of the Larchmont Historical Society and often delivered talks locally on the subject of the culture and history of the America Indian.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reisman grew up in New Rochelle. After attending Brown University, he went to work at RKO Pathe News, where he wrote one and two-reel documentary short subjects. During World War II he served in the Marines as a photographer. He returned to RKO Pathe after the war, but in 1952 he decided to write on a freelance basis.</p>
        <p>Philip Reisman died June 2. He was 82.</p>
        <p>EVERYTHING WAS 'WUNDERBAR'</p>
        <p>THE Paramount Center for the Arts in Peekskill lost its guardian angel when it lost Else Lampmann-Alberti. A devoted patron of the center, Ms. Lampmann-Alberti raised money for a new piano for the theater, for new dressing rooms and for new gallery space. Her 90th birthday was celebrated in that gallery, and -- as had been her tradition -- she asked friends to celebrate by donating to the center instead of giving her a gift.</p>
        <p>A singer and piano player, Ms. Lampmann-Alberti ran music studios in Peekskill and Manhattan. She taught voice until she was 90 and was sometimes brought to tears by her students, so beautiful did she find the music and the voices. Ms. Lampmann-Alberti herself toured Europe as a singer, performing most frequently in her native Germany.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lampmann-Alberti often set up camp in the lobby of the Paramount. She would bring her own lamp from home, and settle in to collect funds for an event, often charming visitors into signing the guest book. ''She was always thinking of new ways to find funds to keep the Paramount going,'' said Gladys Muller, board president of the Paramount. ''She had the stamina of a very young woman and never stopped. With Else, everything was 'wunderbar.' ''</p>
        <p>She was also a charter member of the Aaron Copland Heritage Association and gave yearly concerts to benefit the Hudson Valley Hospital. In 1992, Vincent Vesce, who was then mayor, declared ''Else Lampmann Day'' in Peekskill.</p>
        <p>Else Lampmann-Alberti died Jan. 31. She was 90.</p>
        <p>A LATE-BLOOMING AUTHOR</p>
        <p>AT the age of 107, she published her third book. But it was the publication of ''Having Our Say: The Delany Sisters' First 100 Years,'' in 1993 that thrust Sarah (Sadie) Delany and her sister Elizabeth (Bessie) into the national limelight. The beguiling oral history traced the sisters' lives as the daughters of a man born a slave, through their days in the Jim Crow South to their nearly four decades in Mount Vernon. The book was on the New York Times best-seller list for 28 weeks and on the paperback list for 77 weeks.</p>
        <p>Sadie Delany was born in 1889 in her aunt's home in Lynch's Station, Va. She grew up on the campus of St. Augustine's School in Raleigh, where her father was vice principal. The sisters approached life in the segregated South differently. Bessie Delany was more confrontational. Sadie Delany preferred an indirect approach to circumventing racist laws. ''Sadie is molasses without even trying,'' Bessie Delany told Amy Hill Hearth, the co-author of their book. ''She can sweet-talk the world or play dumb, or whatever it takes to get by without a fuss.''</p>
        <p>It was a strategy Sadie Delany used to become the first black woman to teach home economics in white New York City schools. After receiving a master's degree in education from Columbia University in 1925 and several years of teaching at predominantly black schools, Miss Delany applied to teach at a white high school. When she received a letter from the Board of Education asking to meet her, she skipped the appointment, later writing a polite letter apologizing for the ''mix-up.'' On the first day of class, she simply showed up for work at the school.</p>
        <p>''They just about died when they saw me,'' she wrote in her memoir. ''A colored woman!''</p>
        <p>She kept the job, and continued to teach at well-respected high schools -- among them Girls' High School in Brooklyn, Evander Childs High School in the Bronx and Washington Irving High School in Manhattan -- until she retired in 1960.</p>
        <p>The sisters lived together in Mount Vernon from 1957 to 1995, and Sadie Delany remained there after her sister Bessie died in 1995 at 104. In her book, ''On My Own at 107: Reflections on a Life Without Bessie,'' Sadie Delany wrote: ''I sure miss you, Old Gal. This being alone is hard. For the first time in my life, I don't have you by my side. I'm 107 years old now, and it's like I'm just learning how to walk.''</p>
        <p>Sarah Delany died Jan. 25. She was 109.</p>
        <p>A POLITICIAN WHO STOOD FIRM</p>
        <p>NO one ever had to wonder where Tony Veteran stood on an issue. Straightforward, decisive and outspoken, Mr. Veteran served for 18 years as supervisor of the town of Greenburgh. He led Westchester's largest town through contentious and changing times, never faltering in his vision of what he believed to be right.</p>
        <p>By far the most divisive political issue that faced Greenburgh during Mr. Veteran's tenure was the opening in town of West-HELP, a transitional housing center for the homeless. Opposition to the placement of the shelter was so passionate that at one point people who lived near the proposed site threatened to secede from the town in hopes of blocking it. Meetings on the subject were vitriolic.</p>
        <p>''I have never heard such rhetoric,'' said Susan Tolchin, who was town clerk during Mr. Veteran's administration. ''Tony would listen to the opponents yell and scream about how it would ruin the town, but he was confident it was the right site, and he made it happen. Tony stood up for what he believed was right no matter what hits he had to take.''</p>
        <p>After three years of protest and lawsuits, the shelter -- 108 units on 30 acres of county-owned land in a wooded area near Westchester Community College -- opened in 1991. Concessions to neighboring homeowners included barbed-wire fencing around the housing, round-the-clock security and a guarantee that only families with preschool children would live there, so local schools would not be burdened.</p>
        <p>''Tony was a shrewd politician,'' said his wife, Lucy. ''Politicians have a bad name and are sometimes called wheeler dealers, but Tony felt there was nothing wrong with that, as long as you were wheeling and dealing for your constituents. And he was.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Veteran also helped open up the formerly restricted St. Andrews Golf Course. Developers needed town approval to build town houses on the property, and Mr. Veteran withheld approval until they promised to open admission to the club to anyone who bought a home there. The developers were unhappy with the condition but ultimately agreed to it. The first home buyer in the development was Jewish, and he joined the club.</p>
        <p>''Tony felt that you had to lead even if people didn't like what you were doing,'' said Mrs. Veteran. ''He did what he thought was right for his constituents. He felt if they didn't agree with him, they could throw him out of office.''</p>
        <p>Clearly, Greenburgh voters wanted him to stay. Mr. Veteran was elected a trustee of Tarrytown in 1959 and later became village mayor. He was elected Greenburgh supervisor in 1973 and was re-elected to nine two-year terms. He was the first Democrat to be elected supervisor, and he transformed the formerly Republican town into a Democratic stronghold.</p>
        <p>A shrewd politician with an explosive personality, he was a man of action who was impatient with indecisiveness. Yet he could be a conciliator between opposing political parties and was respected by both his supporters and foes. ''He had a lot of guts,'' said John Lombardi, a Republican and the longtime supervisor of North Castle. ''He told you like it was and never held anything back. He was probably one of the most colorful, strongest and most powerful supervisors in the county.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Veteran also had a gentle side. He was a mentor to those who worked for him and enjoyed teaching the ins and outs of politics and government. He liked working with children and coached football and wrestling at Elmsford High School. He encouraged dozens of young men to continue their educations, and many of them stayed in touch with Mr. Veteran long after they had established their own careers.</p>
        <p>''Tony was really a giant,'' said Ms. Tolchin, who is now director of communications for County Executive Andrew J. Spano. ''He used to say: 'You are not elected to abstain or to pass the buck. You are elected to take a position. You make the right decision and you stick with it.' ''</p>
        <p>Tony Veteran died Jan. 16. He was 82.</p>
        <p>BLAZING TRAILS, MEDICAL AND OTHERWISE</p>
        <p>DR. BENJAMIN I. DYETT was a family doctor and a professional pioneer. His resume is full of firsts -- ranging from the first black doctor to join the staff of two Westchester hospitals, to the first black father to move his family into what was then all-white Prospect Park in White Plains.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dyett took great pride in his trail blazing, though it was sometimes at a price. His daughter, Dr. Deborah Desir, said her father once went to a uniform store in Westchester to buy white medical coats. When he arrived, Dr. Dyett was asked if he was there to buy a butler's uniform. While he served in the Navy and was commissioned as a lieutenant commander on the basis of his being a doctor, some white soldiers on board the ship refused to salute him.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Dyett was too busy and too easygoing to let such incidents wear him down, said Betty Dyett, his widow. ''He would say, 'Well, that's your problem, not mine.' ''</p>
        <p>He was devoted to his patients and they to him. Mrs. Dyett said she was still stopped on the streets and thanked by people her husband had treated. ''He had people who went to him from the time he opened his practice to when he closed it, and they would not consider going to anyone else,'' Dr. Desir said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dyett graduated from medical school at Howard University in Washington in 1954 and started his internship at Grasslands Hospital in Valhalla, which is now known as the Westchester Medical Center. He joined the staff of the White Plains Hospital as an assistant attending physician in 1957. He also served on the staff of St. Agnes Hospital in White Plains. Dr. Dyett was the medical director of Sing Sing Correctional Facility in Ossining during the 1980's, a time when the prison population saw a sharp rise in AIDS cases. He also ran his family practice for 39 years.</p>
        <p>While being a doctor came first to Dr. Dyett, other important things in his life were his family, his church and his college fraternity, Alpha Phi Alpha. He was a member of the Grace Episcopal Church Senior Choir for more than 30 years, where he was known both as a strong tenor and something of a joker, said Ray Levine, who stood next to him in the choir.</p>
        <p>He was also a member of the Westchester County Medical Society, the White Plains Lions Club, the Westchester County African-American Advisory Board and a Fellow, and past treasurer, vice president and president of the American Academy of Family Physicians. In 1997, Dr. Dyett received the county's Certificate of Distinguished Service.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dyett loved to travel with his family, taking cruises, visiting historic sites and, most of all, spending time at Cape Cod, where the family eventually bought a second home. But vacation time came rarely, as Dr. Dyett seldom took time away from his patients. ''He was really a very busy person, and the things he loved most -- his practice, his church, his fraternity and his family -- were his life,'' Mrs. Dyett said. ''He had not much time for anything else.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Benjamin Dyett died on March 13. He was 72.</p>
        <p>THE FIRST LADY OF CIVICS</p>
        <p>LEGISLATORS -- and a few county executives -- sometimes feared her. Younger women training to become advocates revered her. But everyone who worked with Martha Sloan Greenawalt, known as Westchester's first lady of civics, respected her.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Greenawalt's volunteer activities on a local, state and national level led her to be named a civic leader in ''Who's Who in the World.'' Among many other positions, she served for six years on the League of Women Voters' national board and for two terms as president of the New York State League of Women Voters, and she was coordinator of the Westchester Coalition for the Equal Rights Amendment.</p>
        <p>In addition, she was head of Greenburgh's Urban Renewal Commission and served for 17 years as a board member of the town's Neighborhood Health Center. She was vice chairwoman of Westchester 2000 and co-chairwoman of the Westchester Alliance on Juvenile and Criminal Justice.</p>
        <p>When Mrs. Greenawalt was chosen as the first inductee into the Westchester Women's Hall of Fame in 1985, she seemed the only one surprised. ''I'm astonished,'' she said, accepting the award. ''I've done such a crazy quilt of things; I've loved it all, but I've moved from one thing to another with no real sense of direction.''</p>
        <p>Her admirers -- and she had legions -- said Mrs. Greenawalt's activities were in fact united by one driving force: a commitment to fairness. ''Whether it was women, housing, discrimination, minorities -- her work was all related to equality,'' said Camille F. Murphy, director of the county's Office for Women.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Greenawalt, who was born in 1906, remembered her mother's being unable to vote. The 19th Amendment was ratified when Mrs. Greenawalt was a teenager. She graduated from Wilson College in Chambersburg, Pa., in 1928 and then earned a master's degree in philosophy from Columbia University in 1929. She married Kenneth Greenawalt the following year; they had four children.</p>
        <p>Her volunteerism began in 1952, when she became chairwoman of the Westchester council of Women's College Clubs, and it expanded from there. What made her remarkable, said those who worked with her, was her high level of commitment to all her activities.</p>
        <p>''Martha's involvement in so many organizations was never peripheral or casual,'' said Evelyn Stock, president of the New York State League of Women Voters. ''She served usually as the chair or co-chair. Sometimes she was the entire committee.''</p>
        <p>In all of her activities, Mrs. Greenawalt never lost sight of the human factor. As a vice president of Westchester 2000, a citizen-led group to develop a master plan for the new millennium, she listened patiently as concerns about Westchester's roads, buildings and tax system were discussed. But it was she who led the task force on human services, with particular attention to the problems of poverty, welfare dependency and teenage pregnancy.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Stock said that Mrs. Greenawalt was a mentor to many women in Westchester. She encouraged them to become involved and then shepherded their careers, having an influence on county politics that extended far beyond her own volunteerism. As a tribute, the County Office of Woman, in conjunction with the Westchester County Advisory Board, has established the Martha Sloan Greenawalt mentoring program, in which local young women will be selected for leadership training.</p>
        <p>An unfailingly courteous woman known for her beaming smile, Mrs. Greenawalt had a booming, sonorous voice. Even as she got older, she never needed a microphone.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Greenawalt lived in Hartsdale on a cul de sac, among families that were at least a generation younger than she. But it was Mrs. Greenawalt who planted and weeded the flower beds in the circle of the street. She walked everywhere she could and also enjoyed swimming.</p>
        <p>''What made her so special was that she was an icon from another time but a leader in this time,'' Mrs. Stock said.</p>
        <p>Martha Sloan Greenawalt died on March 17. She was 92.</p>
        <p>PUTTING FAIRNESS INTO DIVORCE</p>
        <p>DIANE WHITE of New Rochelle was volunteering for a self-help group in the late 1970's when she began to hear from women who had been thrust into poverty as a result of their marriages ending. In response, she founded Legal Awareness for Women, which sponsored seminars and offered counseling for women with divorce, child custody and domestic violence problems.</p>
        <p>The group soon became active in lobbying for the New York State Equitable Distribution Law, which was intended to distribute marital assets fairly at the time of divorce. Several years later, Ms. White lobbied for changes in the law, arguing that a loophole allowed the court to grant a spouse immediate divorce, leaving other issues -- including critical questions of financial maintenance, marital property, custody, visitation or child support -- for a trial at a much later date.</p>
        <p>As Ms. White grew older, she expanded the group's mission to include issues affecting the elderly, and it became known as Legal Awareness of Westchester. The group later became absorbed into Pace University's Women's Justice Center. At the age of 78 she held a series of seminars titled ''Woman to Woman -- Living Alone and Getting Older.''</p>
        <p>''I've worked all my life,'' she told an interviewer at the time. ''I never intended to retire to a rocking chair.''</p>
        <p>Diane White died March 3. She was 82.</p>
        <p>REMEMBERING THE VETERAN</p>
        <p>MICHAEL C. MONGERO enlisted in the Navy at 17 and took part in the D-Day invasion in 1944 as a landing craft pilot. It was an experience that influenced the rest of his life, making him a dedicated advocate for local veterans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mongero, who was a Cortlandt town councilman for 11 years, became the first chairman of the town's Veterans Council. For years, he lobbied New York State to build a nursing home for veterans on the grounds of the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Veterans Hospital Center in Montrose. Construction on the project began last summer and is expected to be completed next year. He also led the effort to refurbish a local memorial dedicated to those who died in service to their country.</p>
        <p>A 40-year resident of Cortlandt, Mr. Mongero liked to reminisce about his days in the service. He would often tell a story about an unlikely meeting he had while he was in the Navy. Mr. Mongero was stationed on Omaha Beach when he passed a fenced-in compound where German prisoners were being held. Suddenly he heard one of the POW's call out his name. It was an old classmate from Yorktown High School, who had returned to his family's native Germany after graduation and had then been drafted into the German army.</p>
        <p>Town Supervisor Linda Puglisi of Cortlandt said that Mr. Mongero, a Republican who sat on the town board from 1977 to 1989, was devoted to his family and devoted to his town. She said he was an enthusiastic participant in the Memorial Day and Veterans Day parades, and tried to rally others to attend as well.</p>
        <p>Mike Mongero died July 26. He was 74.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
