<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Shop Talk; Who's Got The Power?</title>
    <meta content="WLN090018" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenfield, Meg (1930-99)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Katharine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carlson, Margaret</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">schlesinger, robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3D91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Shop Talk; Who's Got The Power?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Schlesinger</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">schlesinger, robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>shop talk: w</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carlson: I never thought of Meg as someone who had a cause or thought of herself as a woman in journalism or a feminist. I saw Meg as just pure journalist, competing on the same ground. I don't like to admit it, but I got breaks. I was coming along at a time when people wanted to hire women, and I wouldn't call it affirmative action exactly, but in some ways it was. Meg never had any of that. But Meg needed to get to be where she was for me to able to think that I could get where I am.</p>
        <p>Graham: We used to discuss everything. I would ask her advice on everything, including could I send this outrageous letter, and she always said no. It was a particular kind of friendship because it was half-professional, and then it became personal. She talked to me about the first time she presided over an editorial meeting. She said everybody, including herself, was very uncomfortable with a woman running things.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Carlson: I never thought of Meg as someone who had a cause or thought of herself as a woman in journalism or a feminist. I saw Meg as just pure journalist, competing on the same ground. I don't like to admit it, but I got breaks. I was coming along at a time when people wanted to hire women, and I wouldn't call it affirmative action exactly, but in some ways it was. Meg never had any of that. But Meg needed to get to be where she was for me to able to think that I could get where I am.</p>
        <p>Graham: We used to discuss everything. I would ask her advice on everything, including could I send this outrageous letter, and she always said no. It was a particular kind of friendship because it was half-professional, and then it became personal. She talked to me about the first time she presided over an editorial meeting. She said everybody, including herself, was very uncomfortable with a woman running things.</p>
        <p>Carlson: I think men probably still don't like that. You have to be extraordinarily deft. A woman has to be a little smarter to do it well than a man has to be. And probably subtler. Meg had a terrific way with people and great humor. She was very witty.</p>
        <p>Graham: Very funny. And very offbeat.</p>
        <p>Carlson: She knew everything about the Menendez brothers' trial.</p>
        <p>Graham: Oh, she adored the Menendez brothers' story. She used to look at late-night series on television all the time. She had a really popular kind of thing.</p>
        <p>Carlson: Her humor was such a gift. And it allowed her to move more easily in the universe of men. She was not standoffish and she didn't assume any higher position than anyone else, even though she had a higher one. It was very easy to engage her. Meg could go up to the Pentagon Papers and the SALT-2 treaty and she could come down to the Menendez brothers' trial.</p>
        <p>Graham: Meg influenced by her original mind and her soul in her comments, and people paid attention to them because they were so smart. Was that power? Power -- it's sort of nuts. What power do I have except I once did run a business? Who are the women in power? Madeleine, I suppose.</p>
        <p>Carlson: A few senators. Dianne Feinstein.</p>
        <p>Graham: Donna Shalala.</p>
        <p>Carlson: Christine Todd Whitman.</p>
        <p>Graham: Women have to choose more than men. They have to decide whether they're going to have a career or whether they want a job, and either they have to, or they want to, split that with their home life.</p>
        <p>Carlson: There's such a difference between a job and a career. And women now have the opportunity for both. But there are some things you can't legislate away. A woman's peak childbearing years coincide with her peak career-building years, and there's no way to change that. You can work at the bank, but you can't be president of the bank and get home every night for dinner. That will always be true. George Will would never have been known as the first male columnist at The Washington Post, whereas I'm still introduced when I'm speaking somewhere as the first woman columnist at Time magazine, and this is 1999.</p>
        <p>Graham: That's amazing, Margaret, that is.</p>
        <p>Carlson: Many women got their jobs because inequality was brought to the attention of the world. The inequality was dramatic. Discrimination now is both less visible and less dramatic. No woman reporter at Time magazine is asked to get the coffee, but we still have the stewardess-pilot, nurse-doctor problem in that there are more women researcher/fact-checkers than there are men researcher/fact-checkers.</p>
        <p>Graham: It wasn't so long ago that women were never hired except as researchers, and there was only one woman reporter in all of Time-Life.</p>
        <p>Carlson: That's so right. And it's harder to nail them on the greater number of women in the fact-checker jobs now because they also have women in the higher jobs.</p>
        <p>Graham: Also there are more men fact-checkers.</p>
        <p>Carlson: Yes, they're being punished too. Hey! It's equal opportunity -- equal opportunity to get the coffee.</p>
        <p>Moderated by Robert Schlesinger</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
