<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suburban Parties With Some Wow</title>
    <meta content="02BUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tutera, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Connor, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7D61538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suburban Parties With Some Wow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Connor, Tom</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report on some elaborate New Year's Eve parties staged by David Tutera, consultant in Westchester County, New York; notable is Bedford party recreating Amsterdam's red-light district; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE limousines moved quietly along the dark back roads, under canopies of arching branches and leaves, before turning down a dirt drive and stopping at the courtyard of a large 1940's center-hall colonial.</p>
        <p>And these were just the cars for the staff and performers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE limousines moved quietly along the dark back roads, under canopies of arching branches and leaves, before turning down a dirt drive and stopping at the courtyard of a large 1940's center-hall colonial.</p>
        <p>And these were just the cars for the staff and performers.</p>
        <p>When the guests arrived, valets whisked away their Range Rovers and Mercedes sport utilities, and they found themselves in a reasonable facsimile of the red-light district of Amsterdam. Here in rural, stately Bedford, N.Y., the entire house and much of the 11-acre grounds were bathed in red light. Semidressed models stood in doorways and hung out of windows, like ladies of the Westchester night.</p>
        <p>A bodyguard with a list checked off the 200 guests before they proceeded to a registration tent, set up like a private club, outside the front door of the house.</p>
        <p>Suburbanites have always given parties -- birthday parties, Memorial Day parties, block parties, Tupperware parties.</p>
        <p>But lately some have been putting on affairs more reminiscent of the last days of disco than of the quiet good taste associated with holiday dinner parties or summer garden parties. Couples in their 30's and 40's, perhaps ambivalent about settling into respectable, boring middle age, have been playing host to blowouts more typical of an after-party for the MTV Awards. In the process, they have exported some of the high-spirited night life of their younger years in Manhattan to the skateboard-filled driveways and deer-tracked byways of suburbia.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of like, 'Hey, we're doing it so we can really let loose and so we can feel like we're not 40 years old and living a boring life in the suburbs,' '' said Seth Kanegis, 36, an investment manager, who with his wife, Marlene, was host to the Amsterdam theme party last fall. ''I mean, I would love to be able to go to the south of France and party like a rock star, but I can't do that -- I've got kids.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kanegis's party was produced by David Tutera, a party designer and special-events planner in Mamaroneck, N.Y., where he oversees a staff of 16 in a large concrete-block building filled with party props: classical columns, arbors, chandeliers, 50 flats of wheat grass from a House &amp; Garden shoot and a shelf of Halloween props from a party in Greenwich, Conn., for Tommy Hilfiger's oldest son.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tutera, 33, works all over the country, producing mega-events like a post-Grammy Awards celebration for 3,500 in New York, or the Kennedy Center's spring gala for 1,500 in Washington.</p>
        <p>But in Westchester and in Fairfield County, Conn., he does private parties for clients who can afford his fee, which begins at $15,000, plus expenses that can climb into six figures. Mr. Kanegis flew him to Amsterdam for three days to collect menus and soak up atmosphere. Back home, Mr. Tutera interviewed caterers until he found one who could recreate the Indonesian fare that's popular in Amsterdam. Behind the Kanegises' house, Mr. Tutera's crew erected an enormous dance tent and set up four-poster beds around the lawn.</p>
        <p>Halfway through the night, the host introduced the main attraction: Wyclef Jean of the Fugees, who had just wrapped up a monthlong tour with a side band, the Refugee Camp. Mr. Tutera arranged to meet their tour bus at an exit off Interstate 684 and escort them to the party.</p>
        <p>''When Wyclef came on, everyone was blown away,'' Mr. Tutera said. ''They wound up playing an extra hour, then were guests for the rest of the night.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tutera, who is completing a book for Simon &amp; Schuster, ''David Tutera: A Passion for Parties,'' to be published next fall, is not the only name in suburban party extravaganzas. Bill Tansey, of Tansey Design Associates in New York, put on a party last summer for a young couple in Southampton ''who just wanted an intimate, erotic dance party,'' he recalled. He covered a section of their pool with a plexiglass dance floor and, after dinner, brought out the entertainment: a club D.J. from Manhattan, five drag queens and a transsexual dressed in Saran wrap.</p>
        <p>''A lot of these people made a zillion dollars recently,'' Mr. Tansey said. ''They want to have the most fabulous, most talked-about event, whatever the excuse. They also want to have a great time. A lot of them are between their mid-30's and mid-40's. Often, you'll hear them say, 'This is the last time we can have this kind of party, because soon the kids will be aware of what's going on.' ''</p>
        <p>Moshe Aelyon of Mosaic Event Planning in Westport, Conn., produced a Moroccan feast last summer for 120 guests in 12 tents on the estate of a couple whose property straddles Westport and Weston. The tents were outfitted with cushions, tapestries and personal waiters. Also on hand were a belly dancer, an elephant, a six-piece Middle Eastern band and two lifeguards (a river runs through the property). A separate picnic with its own entertainment was organized at the opposite end of the estate for the children.</p>
        <p>''Giving parties has become part of the imaging and packaging we're all trying to sell,'' Mr. Aelyon said, explaining the motives behind such lavish affairs.</p>
        <p>To be sure, professionally produced theme parties are not every aging suburbanite's idea of a good time. Many would give thanks simply for a relaxing evening away from the children, with good conversation among a few friends as the focus, rather than an exhausting evening of dancing and living it up, as though they were still in their 20's.</p>
        <p>Still, the desire to defy the stereotype of suburban complacency is strong enough to create a steady demand for parties like Mr. Tutera's. He produced one last summer at the Westchester County home of a Manhattan couple who also have an apartment on Park Avenue.</p>
        <p>''It was for my husband's 50th birthday,'' said the wife, who asked that their names not be used, to protect their privacy. Her husband is a scion of a prominent family, with holdings worth billions of dollars. ''He wasn't real happy about turning 50, and he wanted something different,'' his wife said. Hearing the word ''different,'' a friend of hers recommended Mr. Tutera, and the two hit it off. ''David's hot,'' she said. ''He's fresh and original and still unspoiled. The worst thing that can happen is that you're bored at your own party. We weren't bored.''</p>
        <p>Running with his client's idea, Mr. Tutera erected a clear plastic tent behind the house, rented antique tables and chairs as well as contemporary furniture from ABC Carpet &amp; Home, then arranged them among the wildflower gardens -- a kind of formal indoor dining room brought outside, with wall-to-wall carpeting of thick turf. When a summer storm broke at exactly the moment the guests were seated inside the clear tent and the Hampton String Quartet began playing, it seemed as though everyone was on an movie set, Mr. Tutera said.</p>
        <p>As for the birthday boy, ''he was blown away,'' his wife said, adding, ''The guy's been to a lot of parties, but he said this was the most beautiful party he'd ever been to.''</p>
        <p>For New Year's Eve, Mr. Tutera was booked for a party for 250 at the home of Nick and Lisi Robinson, a couple in their early 30's who live in Katonah, N.Y. The theme was ''Divas of Disco,'' and Mr. Tutera had built a two-level dance floor in a white-carpeted tent with white chiffon walls. Featuring caviar stations and sushi bars, the disco tent was planned with not one, not two, but three live performers: Alicia Bridges (''I Love the Night Life''), Musique (''In the Bush'') and Lisa Lisa of Cult Jam.</p>
        <p>Come Monday morning, Mr. Tutera expects to be back in his Mamaroneck studio, designing sets for the spring round of big suburban parties. One will be for the Kanegises in June. Marlene Kanegis's sister is Lisi Robinson, and something of a ''Can you top this?'' competition seems to have sprung up between the two couples. They attend each other's events produced by Mr. Tutera and, of course, incur an obligation as guests to return their hosts' hospitality.</p>
        <p>''This one could blow away all previous parties Seth's had,'' Mr. Tutera said. He would reveal no other details except that he and Mr. Kanegis are discussing hiring four bands. ''It will be the Battle of the Parties,'' Mr. Tutera said. ''We're not talking bar mitzvah bands here; we're talking headline bands.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
