<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: On Language; Wordplayers</title>
    <meta content="WLN090040" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oates, Wayne E (d1999)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freudenberger, Herbert (Dr) (d1999)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Espy, Willard R (d1999)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">On Language (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: On Language; Wordplayers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire On Language column pays tribute to Wayne E Oates, who coined term 'workaholic,' Dr Herbert Freudenberger, who coined 'burnout' and Willard Espy, best known for almanacs of Words at Play, all of whom died in 1999; discusses terms for person who lived in Second Millennium (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What do you call somebody who continually applies his nose to the grindstone, eschews the distractions of fun and games and otherwise occupies himself with those moneymaking endeavors that make Jack a dull boy?</p>
        <p>A workaholic, of course. But what did we call that addiction to work -- that obsessive attachment to long hours and briefcases voluntarily stuffed with homework -- before Wayne E. Oates, in a burst of linguistic innovation in 1968, titled an article in a pastoral magazine, ''On Being a 'Workaholic'''?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What do you call somebody who continually applies his nose to the grindstone, eschews the distractions of fun and games and otherwise occupies himself with those moneymaking endeavors that make Jack a dull boy?</p>
        <p>A workaholic, of course. But what did we call that addiction to work -- that obsessive attachment to long hours and briefcases voluntarily stuffed with homework -- before Wayne E. Oates, in a burst of linguistic innovation in 1968, titled an article in a pastoral magazine, ''On Being a 'Workaholic'''?</p>
        <p>We had no word for it. The language suffered from a gaping hole. The French had bourreau de travail, ''work butcher,'' but not until this Southern Baptist pastor from Louisville, Ky., came up with his coinage could English speakers succinctly express themselves. ''I have dubbed this addiction of myself and my fellow ministers as workaholism,'' Oates wrote, and later defined his term as ''the compulsion or the uncontrollable need to work incessantly.''</p>
        <p>He based it, obviously, on alcoholic. In so doing, the coiner made a new suffix out of -oholic. But the question of spelling arises: if the suffix is adopted from alcoholic, why did Oates not spell his word workoholic? That was the spelling of a parallel formulation adopted the same year to describe those bittersweet-toothed souls who cannot do without a chocolate fix: chocoholic. But choco lent itself to the -oholic; why did Oates prefer the ''a''?</p>
        <p>I cannot ask him because Wayne Oates was one of those who died in the past year, remembered in history not so much for his 57 books and hundreds of published articles, but for his undisputed coinage of a necessary word. That's the way it goes in the word dodge; if you coin a good one, it becomes the lead of your obituary no matter what else you did.</p>
        <p>Same for Herbert Freudenberger, the eminent psychologist who died last month in New York. Was he noted for his work with people who lost self-esteem, became bored, discouraged and sloppy? Or for his free clinics for drug addicts, or for his court-ordered analysis of the murderous Charles Manson? No. The headline in The New York Times read ''Herbert Freudenberger, 73, Coiner of 'Burnout,' Is Dead.''</p>
        <p>He first used the word as the title of a 1974 book, subtitled ''The High Cost of High Achievement,'' which he wrote with Geraldine Richelson, defining burnout as ''the extinction of motivation or incentive, especially where one's devotion to a cause or relationship fails to produce the desired results.'' In his native Germany, from which he fled in 1938, the term is aus gebrant, literally burned out.</p>
        <p>Burnout had been a 1940's term for ''the sudden loss of power in a jet or rocket engine.'' By the 50's, it had been largely replaced by flameout, giving Dr. Freudenberger a chance to give it a new life with his psychological sense. Though he did not coin the word itself, as Mr. Oates did with workaholic, he gave burnout the sense by which it is known today.</p>
        <p>Another man known to the word trade died in 1999. (We don't use euphemisms like ''passed away'' or ''departed this vale of tears''; when you die in this business, you die.) He never tried to pass himself off as a serious linguist or lexicographer, but his wordplay delighted his readers, stimulated interest in the world of words and sometimes instructed us with a light-verse touch.</p>
        <p>The advertising and promotion man Willard Espy is best known for his almanacs of ''Words at Play,'' compiled and reissued by Merriam-Webster six months ago. Having fun with words can involve creative rhymes (''I do not roister with an oyster'') and nonce coinages (''my family was a scribacious lot''). As players of Scrabble and workers of crossword puzzles know, games are a good way to discover the glories of lexicography.</p>
        <p>My favorite Espy production is ''To My Greek Mistress,'' an odd ode. ''All you need to read off this verse as if it were English,'' he noted, ''is a vague recollection of the Greek alphabet.'' (Begin by remembering that Y is pronounced ''psi,'' and P is pronounced ''pie.'')</p>
        <p>With many a Y I ate a P</p>
        <p>That you had baked, my dear;</p>
        <p>This torpor N I you --</p>
        <p>I'm feeling very queer.</p>
        <p>O F O F upon your P! -</p>
        <p>You D cruel blow!</p>
        <p>Your dreadful P has made me C;</p>
        <p>My tears fall in a R.</p>
        <p>I would have Lnother lass</p>
        <p>Who baked that P, I vow;</p>
        <p>But still I M and M for you,</p>
        <p>As sick as any cow.</p>
        <p>Translation for those stimulated to brush up their Greek:</p>
        <p>With many a (sigh) I ate a (pie)</p>
        <p>That you had baked, my dear;</p>
        <p>This torpor (new) (I owe to) you -</p>
        <p>I'm feeling very queer.</p>
        <p>O (fie) O (fie) upon your (pie)! -</p>
        <p>You (dealt a) cruel blow!</p>
        <p>Your dreadful (pie) has made me (cry);</p>
        <p>My tears fall in a (row).</p>
        <p>I would have (lammed a)nother lass</p>
        <p>Who baked that (pie), I vow;</p>
        <p>But still I (moo) and (moo) for you,</p>
        <p>As sick as any cow.</p>
        <p>Against Millenarian</p>
        <p>On the subject of Greek coinage and the Espy playfulness: what shall we call</p>
        <p>a person who has lived in the Second Millennium?</p>
        <p>''Duomillenarian has wrong connotations,'' replies Frederic G. Cassidy, chief editor of the Dictionary of American Regional English, and ''Greek is better in any case as more classical.'' So with DARE's classicist, George Goebel, the great lexicographer turned from Latin to Greek: deutero means ''second'' and chiliast refers to the biblical ''kingdom of a thousand years.''</p>
        <p>Thus, deuterochiliast, ''a person of, or anything characteristic of, the second millennium.'' Drop this coinage in a conversation; see if it clanks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
