<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sumptuous Spots In the West 40's</title>
    <meta content="02REST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOOD EATING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Good Eating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6DB1538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sumptuous Spots In the West 40's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Capsule reviews of six restaurants in Manhattan's West 40's (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHURRASCARIA PLATAFORMA  [Rating: two stars]  (212) 245-0505; 316 West 49th Street; $$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>This all-you-can-eat Brazilian restaurant is distinguished from the others by the high quality of food and the charming attitude of the waiters. The salad bar is extraordinary, a long, two-sided affair anchored at the corners by four hot casseroles. The rodizio starts when a waiter appears with plates of fried potatoes, fried yucca and little squares of fried polenta, a bit of rice, some farofa and a dish of vinaigrette. Next, you will be enticed with at least 10 cuts of meat, many of them beef: sirloin, baby beef, top round, skirt steak, brisket, short ribs and roast beef. Salmon also is served, along with a caper sauce. Just when you've finally cried uncle, the dessert tray arrives with such items as chocolate mousse and queijo, a bright yellow dessert rich with egg yolks and coconut. (Review: 4/4/97)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHURRASCARIA PLATAFORMA  [Rating: two stars]  (212) 245-0505; 316 West 49th Street; $$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>This all-you-can-eat Brazilian restaurant is distinguished from the others by the high quality of food and the charming attitude of the waiters. The salad bar is extraordinary, a long, two-sided affair anchored at the corners by four hot casseroles. The rodizio starts when a waiter appears with plates of fried potatoes, fried yucca and little squares of fried polenta, a bit of rice, some farofa and a dish of vinaigrette. Next, you will be enticed with at least 10 cuts of meat, many of them beef: sirloin, baby beef, top round, skirt steak, brisket, short ribs and roast beef. Salmon also is served, along with a caper sauce. Just when you've finally cried uncle, the dessert tray arrives with such items as chocolate mousse and queijo, a bright yellow dessert rich with egg yolks and coconut. (Review: 4/4/97)</p>
        <p>FIREBIRD  [Rating: two stars]  (212) 586-0244; 365 West 46th Street; $$$; smoking area at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Two brownstones have been combined to recreate a pre-revolutionary Russian mansion. This restaurant deserves an award for set decoration. Current first courses include Maine peekytoe crab and jasmine rice croquettes, with purslane and mustard sauce; crisp seared sweetbreads in Madeira sauce and potato blini with marinated herring. Main courses include Arctic char and Maine sea scallops, with herb-infused tomato with basil walnut pesto; grilled sturgeon, served with sorrel-potato puree, braised carrot and chanterelle mushrooms and horseradish sauce; and mushroom-crusted halibut, with candied onion, tomato and sauce of fresh peas. The caviar are all served with sour cream and blini or toast. (Review: 2/7/97)</p>
        <p>IPANEMA +  (212) 730-5848; 13 West 46th Street, between Fifth Avenue and the Avenue of the Americas; $$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>This relaxed, gracious Brazilian restaurant offers big portions of solid fare. Current appetizers include codfish patties; crepes filled with seafood; shrimps in garlic sauce, and fried Portuguese sausage. Entrees include a rich black bean stew with an assortment of smoked meats; grilled marinated shell steak with garlic sauce; chunks of loin of pork and clams in a special herb sauce; grilled boneless chicken topped with cheese; and a medley of lobster, shrimps, clams and mussels in a Bahia sauce or green sauce. ($25 and Under: 10/29/93; New York Today:  April 1998)</p>
        <p>LATTANZI RISTORANTE +++  (212) 315-0980; 361 West 46th Street, between Eighth and Ninth Avenues; $$; no smoking; American Express only.</p>
        <p>Lattanzi is small and dim with an old-fashioned look. At night the Jewish-Italian menu is unusual and appealing. Starters include ceci beans cooked in meat broth, with rosemary and extra virgin olive oil; and homemade mozzarella and fresh tomato. Main dishes include risotto with either porcini mushrooms, barolo sauce, seafood or vegetables; fried baby squid and shrimp; chicken with peppers, onion, oregano and a marinara sauce; veal scaloppine with marsala wine and mushrooms; and homemade noodles filled with veal, chicken and tomato sauce. (New York Today: April 1998)</p>
        <p>MARITIME  [Rating: one star]  (212) 354-1717; 1251 Avenue of the Americas, at West 49th Street; $$$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>This American seafood brasserie has international leanings. The dark mahogany floors have a muted luster, like the deck of a Vanderbilt yacht. Appetizers include curry fried oysters with cucumber-mint raita; Maritime lobster and corn chowder; and creamy lump crab meat and potato latkes with mango and baby greens. Entrees include salmon satay with shrimp fried rice and peanut sauce; grilled swordfish with papaya summer roll and fermented black bean-scallion sauce; pan-seared scallops with homemade pumpkin ravioli, wilted chard and porcini-truffle sauce; and pomegranate-glazed chicken with grilled pineapple and sweet potato-coconut mash. (Review: 12/1/99)</p>
        <p>PALLADIN  [Rating: two stars]  (212) 320-2929; 224 West 49th Street, at Broadway; $$$; smoking at the bar; all major credit cards.</p>
        <p>Palladin is a techno-bistro with a lot of sass and style, housed in the Time Hotel in the theater district. Jean-Louis Palladin, the chef who ran the swank Jean Louis in Washington, is a feisty chef with plenty of ideas. Salads and appetizers include the ahi and hamachi carpaccio with a salad of microgreens; Florida conch, served with marinated green mango and red ginger coulis; and endive salad and diver scallops with young carrots and cumin. Main dishes include the herb-wrapped roasted monkfish; roasted black sea bass, with celery, potatoes, pancetta, garlic and young carrots; roasted pastrami squab with sweet and sour cabbage and a pastrami spice sauce; foie gras and duck pot au feu; and polenta-crusted skate wing, served with sweetbread ravigote. (Review:  6/23/99)</p>
        <p>What the stars mean:</p>
        <p>(None) Poor to Satisfactory  * Good  ** Very Good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambiance and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Past restaurant reviews from the New York Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics, are available on New York Today: www.nytoday.com</p>
        <p>GOOD EATING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
