<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coward's 'Wings' Never Gets Off the Ground</title>
    <meta content="02CANB$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trump, Donald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher-Corcoran, Lois</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE6D91638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coward's 'Wings' Never Gets Off the Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Vincent Canby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lois Fisher-Corcoran letter praises Herbert Muschamp's Dec 19 (1999) article about Donald Trump, but fears the Donald will need interpreter to understand it (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DESCRIBING Dublin, where his new comedy, ''Waiting in the Wings,'' was trying out before making its way to London, Noel Coward wrote in his journal of Aug. 21, 1960: ''There is an atmosphere of amiable retrogressiveness about everything and everyone which, for a little while, is curiously attractive.''</p>
        <p>Amiable retrogressiveness?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DESCRIBING Dublin, where his new comedy, ''Waiting in the Wings,'' was trying out before making its way to London, Noel Coward wrote in his journal of Aug. 21, 1960: ''There is an atmosphere of amiable retrogressiveness about everything and everyone which, for a little while, is curiously attractive.''</p>
        <p>Amiable retrogressiveness?</p>
        <p>What a deliberately lethal, if polite, way to characterize a place that is picturesque in the extreme, and which you don't mind visiting -- v. briefly -- as long as your notices are flattering and the box office is good. It is also a practically perfect way to describe the first Broadway production of ''Waiting in the Wings.'' As things turned out, the London critics treated the play rather sternly, which is one reason it is only now having its New York premiere.</p>
        <p>The production, directed by Michael Langham, is at the Walter Kerr Theater, with a big, spangly cast headed by Lauren Bacall and Rosemary Harris. Yet the occasion is of somewhat less interest theatrically than historically. It is the only Broadway production to suggest that Dec. 16, 1999 (the night this production opened), is a date to celebrate, it being the centenary of Coward's birth.</p>
        <p>You might think that Broadway could have come up with something a bit more impressive to honor the Coward career. He and heaven know that he deserves our attention: playwright, actor, director, singer, composer, lyricist, entertainer, a man who knew how to live well, how to collect and keep friends, whose work has somehow helped to illuminate and make bearable much of this century.</p>
        <p>In one way and another, he infiltrated the minds of generations of sophisticates, genuine and would-be. Is there anyone of a certain age who doesn't have buried deep in his subconscious a lyric from ''Mad Dogs and Englishmen,'' or maybe a cryptic exchange from ''Private Lives,'' possibly the one about China?</p>
        <p>You might think Broadway would have been able to mark Coward's contributions to our melting civilization with something a bit more stylish than ''Waiting in the Wings.'' A good deal happier and more in the spirit with which we think of Coward was the entertaining concert version of his musical ''Sail Away,'' starring Elaine Stritch, which played 10 performances at Weill Recital Hall in November.</p>
        <p>Scheduled to open at the Lucille Lortel later in the season is ''Suite in Two Keys,'' a program of two short Coward plays, ''Shadows of the Evening'' and ''A Song at Twilight.'' This is the slightly pared down version of ''Suite in Three Keys,'' three short plays in which Coward made his last London stage appearance in 1966.</p>
        <p>Of particular interest is ''A Song at Twilight,'' whose central character (according to Coward) was inspired both by Max Beerbohm and W. Somerset Maugham. This fellow is a bitchy, aging, successful novelist who is suddenly forced to acknowledge his homosexuality, also to consider how his closeted existence has stunted his work and warped his relations with those he loved.</p>
        <p>As it appears to have been when it made its debut in London nearly 40 years ago, ''Waiting in the Wings'' is an unredeemably foolish play. The script for this production has been ''revisited'' by Jeremy Sams, the translator and director, though it still seems as out of touch with the world of the 1960's (the time in which it is placed) as it is with  the world of today. It is neither clumsy nor mechanically inept, but it is so clueless that it seems like a setting in which Miss Marple will soon show up to solve a genteel murder that has yet to be discovered. We are in the England of the picturesque and the fatuous, positively sloshed on amiable retrogressiveness.</p>
        <p>In fact, the setting is the Wings, a country home for retired actresses in need. They are, supposedly, aging actresses, but those we see don't seem to be so old that they would be ready to turn their backs on real life, which is what the residents of the Wings have done. The only way the play makes sense is as a sort of service comedy about actresses who might have been on the stage before World War I, before the dominance of movies and television, when theater was far less elite than it became after the Second World War.</p>
        <p>As in a service comedy, each supporting character tends to be a type, which is a kind way of saying that each is a cliche. What plot there is revolves around the longstanding feud between May Davenport (Ms. Harris) and Lotta Bainbridge (Ms. Bacall), each of whom, you assume, was once a star of some fame, if only because the roles are being played by stars. The feud began when Lotta lured May's husband away from hearth and home. Toward the end of the play, the situation is resolved with a minimum of fuss and a certain amount of actressy sighing, separated by pauses.</p>
        <p>Neither Ms. Bacall nor Ms. Harris is going to win any awards for her work here, mostly because there is nothing much to act. Ms. Bacall, as we know, is good at sarcasm, and Ms. Harris can elocute with the best of them. This they do as required. The supporting roles, being shorter, are more vividly written and are decently handled by Helena Carroll, Helen Stenborg, Elizabeth Wilson, Dana Ivey and Barnard Hughes, among others.</p>
        <p>The cast is huge, numbering 18 people, and when Coward brings on a lot of characters, he writes thin. Most of ''Waiting in the Wings'' is simply anecdotal, having to do with the appearance of a pushy newspaper reporter, a small fire, attempts to get the management to build a solarium, and the celebration of New Year's Eve.</p>
        <p>There are also jokes about the vanity of actresses, which members of the public always appreciate since it makes them feel privy to inside information. There is even a geography joke that sounds like the last gasp of the man who wrote ''Private Lives'': ''Do you know Toronto?''  ''No.'' ''It's terribly Canadian.''</p>
        <p>Compared to New York, London has been awash in Coward revivals during the last 12 months, including ''Private Lives,''  ''Hay Fever'' and something that sounds especially promising, a production of ''A Song at Twilight'' with Corin and Vanessa Redgrave and Kika Markham.</p>
        <p>Coward was very proud of his propaganda work during World War II, especially of his film, ''In Which We Serve,'' a patriotic tale of the Royal Navy based on the experiences of his good friend, Lord Louis Mountbatten. After the war, he expected that his various endeavors would earn him a place on the King's honors list. However, influential members of the postwar governments, including Winston Churchill, continued to take a dim view of the homosexuality that Coward, while remaining discreet, didn't try to hide.</p>
        <p>He didn't receive his knighthood until 1970, just three years before his death. Since then, however, the royals haven't been stingy with their time in promoting Coward and, of course, the commercial commodity he is for Britain. The Queen Mother, whom Coward introduced to the joys of bullshots, unveiled Angela Conner's life-size bronze statue of Coward when it was installed at the Drury Lane Theater in London in late 1997. Prince Edward did the duty when a cast of the same statue was placed in the Gershwin Theater in New York last March, and the Duke of Gloucester was on hand to officiate when, this fall, the work was placed on a hillside at Firefly, Coward's Jamaican retreat.</p>
        <p>Maybe the Queen could step in and suggest that someone send this former colony a first-rate production of one of the classic Coward plays.</p>
        <p>'Fully Committed'</p>
        <p>Trendiness is to Manhattan what Lyme disease is to the suburbs.</p>
        <p>About the only way to avoid it is to stay home with the shades drawn, the television and radio unplugged, the phones dismembered, all magazines and newspapers forbidden, reading the collected works of Cotton Mather by candlelight. This is more or less the hilarious -- and I mean seriously funny -- point of ''Fully Committed,'' the brilliant Off Broadway comedy that has moved to the Cherry Lane Theater after a limited run last year at the Vineyard Theater.</p>
        <p>The play, written by Becky Mode, stars Mark Setlock as a commonsensical young man named Sam, who sits in a grubby basement office answering three telephones and an intercom, juggling phone reservations and other crises at this month's ''in'' Manhattan restaurant. Here is a universe in which God is just another celebrity. Mr. Setlock, being the only person in the cast, also plays 39 other hysterical characters created by him and Ms. Mode.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Martin, who directed Mary Louise Wilson and Mark Hampton's ''Full Gallop,'' the one-woman show in which Ms. Wilson played Diana Vreeland, is also the director of ''Fully Committed.'' In view of his excellent work as the director of Christopher Durang's ''Betty's Summer Vacation'' at Playwrights Horizons and George Bernard Shaw's ''You Never Can Tell'' at the Roundabout, it is obvious his talents aren't limited to single-person plays.</p>
        <p>The joy of ''Fully Committed'' comes not only from the rich quirkiness of the material, but also from the surprising ease of the performance. One wizardly man creates a world more crowded with character and life than you might find in a conventional theatrical presentation on the order of, say, ''Waiting in the Wings.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Setlock slips from one character to the next with the speed of light for priceless results. Here is a gallery of upwardly mobile rogues, con artists, nouveau riche business types, bewildered tourists, celebrity groupies, emotionally unpredictable chefs, pushy socialites, prima donna maitre d's and others. The script drops real-life names among the fictitious ones with such abandon that, as you try to keep up, you feel as besieged as the person dealing with the calls.</p>
        <p>Yet the show is more than an extended revue sketch. This is real theater, a charming comedy with a beginning, middle and end.</p>
        <p>'Dinner With Friends'</p>
        <p>Donald Margulies's ''Dinner With Friends,'' at the Variety Arts, is something you rarely find these days: a comedy about heterosexual relationships that is neither embarrassed by nor smug about its liberal, upper-middle-class values.</p>
        <p>It is sober, wise and sometimes extremely funny as Gabe (Matthew Arkin) and Karen (Lisa Emery), now in their 40's, saddled with children, mortgages and all the other trappings of suburban marriage, attempt to cope with the panic they experience when their best friends, Tom (Kevin Kilner) and Beth (Julie White), announce they are splitting up.</p>
        <p>Gabe and Karen feel responsible. After all, they introduced Tom and Beth. They are also at that point in their lives when they suddenly realize that the unexamined marriage just might be the marriage that no longer works.</p>
        <p>Mr. Margulies writes with elegance and wit about intimacy, trust, privacy, and the toll of time and monogamy on sexual passion, matters that aren't easily expressed in dramatic dialogue without suggesting an animated self-help book. These are minutely observed, recognizable folk, not sitcom types.</p>
        <p>''Dinner With Friends,'' directed by Daniel Sullivan, is nicely acted by the four cast members and aptly situated in Neil Patel's sets that, like Mr. Margulies's text, suggest an innate connection to a particular place and time without blaming the landscape.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
