<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Works That Accent the Positive and Nurture the Spirit</title>
    <meta content="02ART.$21" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165393"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, D Dominick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD91738F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Works That Accent the Positive and Nurture the Spirit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. DOMINICK LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, D Dominick</byline>
      <dateline>VALHALLA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D Dominick Lombardi reviews photography exhibit at Macy Pavilion of Westchester Medical Center; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ART can have a positive effect on one's soul. This can easily be overlooked or disfavored, especially at a time when the most offensive or provoking works are getting most of the attention. One institution in particular, the Gallery at the Macy Pavilion at Westchester Medical Center here, believes in ''nurturing the spirit'' through beauty and selects works for exhibition accordingly.</p>
        <p>This is done primarily because most of those who see the gallery's  exhibitions are some of the region's most severely ill or injured, and they and their families are in need of a positive distraction. This approach of focusing on the positive usually breeds exhibitions that fall short of the mark because they underwhelm, or even bore. The 10-member selection committee here, however, manages to amass enough good examples to support the contrary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ART can have a positive effect on one's soul. This can easily be overlooked or disfavored, especially at a time when the most offensive or provoking works are getting most of the attention. One institution in particular, the Gallery at the Macy Pavilion at Westchester Medical Center here, believes in ''nurturing the spirit'' through beauty and selects works for exhibition accordingly.</p>
        <p>This is done primarily because most of those who see the gallery's  exhibitions are some of the region's most severely ill or injured, and they and their families are in need of a positive distraction. This approach of focusing on the positive usually breeds exhibitions that fall short of the mark because they underwhelm, or even bore. The 10-member selection committee here, however, manages to amass enough good examples to support the contrary.</p>
        <p>Their current exhibition, titled ''Alternate Views,'' features the photographic work of 30 artists from as far away as the state of Washington, though most are from Westchester County. Suko Presseau of White Plains offers two of this exhibit's most poignant works. In ''Juno Beach'' (1999), Ms. Presseau takes a cue from Vermeer by taking full advantage of the effect that bright sunlight has on a roomscape. Her subject, a subdued adolescent, sits bedside, next to a large window, and appears to be either examining or repairing a garment. This scene, which could not be more benign, becomes timeless in the hands of an artist who understands the soothing effect of a limited color scheme when it is enhanced by circular light. In ''Coney Island'' (1999), she records the energy of youth by photographing a young man whose physical appearance is only outdone by his confidence. In both images, Ms. Presseau takes a formalist view without seeming stuffy or outmoded.</p>
        <p>Humor is one of the most important aspects of a show that aspires to elevate the spirit. The photographs of Barbara Reed of Bedford and Sarah Newgaard of Mamaroneck fulfill that need. Ms. Reed's ''Frogs'' shows a pair of lime green amphibians that seem to pose for the camera. As they lie sprawled across a log, they assume the positioning of a loving couple, arm in arm. Their bulging eyes and smiling expressions, when combined with their comical positioning, should bring a smile to most passers-by. Ms. Newgaard's ''Sleeping Pigs'' (1998) depicts a pair of pink piglets cuddling atop hay-covered floor boards. Their situation is at first humorous, seeing them sleeping side by side in a human-like position, but some might notice the ear tags and wonder, even worry, about their fate.</p>
        <p>Lois Palestine of Rye injects into her work a smattering of morbidity.  ''Window Playland'' (1996) is one of the exhibition's few black-and-white images and shows a young man through a large archway as he peers outside through a barred window. The floor, which has a cluster of melting snow and ice on it, reflects the image of the subject, which is counter balanced by his long shadow. A triple portrait in a sense: an image that is both alluring and, in a way, sad.</p>
        <p>A number of the artists in the show photograph the great outdoors. The Peekskill resident Gene Panczenko's ''Forest Light'' (1993) captures the heavenly rays of the sun as it passes through a stand of trees. Kiyoko Ohata Brown of Harrison and Paul W. Finch of Croton-on-Hudson offer works that focus on the visual effects of thick fog. Atmospheric perspective addresses the fact that objects appear duller in color and less defined with respect to detail as they move into the distance. This factor is more profound when nature adds a bit of misty moisture, as Ms. Ohata Brown's and Mr. Finch's art would attest.</p>
        <p>Mark Abrahamson of Stanwood, Wash., also photographs the landscape, though his vantage is from far overhead. His main concern is how some industrious people sacrifice land and water quality for profit. His aerial views of out-of-the-way industries reveal images that are as enigmatic as they are strangely beautiful, vistas that can more easily be explained as otherworldly.</p>
        <p>A Hartsdale resident, Howard Jacobs, adds a bit of Surrealism by way of the computer. His digitally produced collages take a satirical look at early modern masterpieces by combining appropriated images of some well-known Impressionists like Renoir and Monet. To these reproductions Mr. Jacob adds computer-enhanced or computer-generated images, which in some way spoof the Impressionist's work. For instance, in ''On the Terrace With Monet'' (1999), he modifies Monet's original terrace painting, ''Terrace a Sainte-Adresse'' (1867), by adding oversize flowers and a large butterfly, as if the original painting wasn't pleasing enough to begin with.</p>
        <p>Clair Palermo Flower of Garrison offers a series of color vignettes,  photographs of five Umbrian townscapes. Her approach is to find the quietest, most off-the-beaten-track places in search of the day-to-day life of the Umbrian people. She looks for areas where this age-old culture has endured, where the many layers of change, which are marked by many repairs, change only the texture of the walls and buildings but not its inhabitants. In one piece, titled ''Umbrian Doorway'' (1998), Ms. Palermo Flower discreetly left a plastic water bottle on the floor of the stone entrance area, which in this instance adds an intrusive indication of the here and now to an otherwise pleasant view.</p>
        <p>''Alternate Views'' runs through Jan. 10. The Gallery at the Macy Pavilion is on the campus of Westchester Medical Center. The number to call for information is 493-8397.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
