<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/Connecticut; Helping the Disabled to Be at Home in Their Houses</title>
    <meta content="02ZONE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charles, Eleanor</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D71738F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/Connecticut; Helping the Disabled to Be at Home in Their Houses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Charles, Eleanor</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Growing number of home builders in Connecticut are building single-family homes or retrofitting existing existing homes to accommodate people with disabilities; developers of multifamily housing are required by federal Fair Housing Act of 1988 to provide ramps, elevators, wider hallways and doorways for disabled people; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Fehmi and Mary Zeko decided to move for a third time they had the money and the incentive to finally build the house of their dreams for themselves and their four boys.</p>
        <p>Last September it was completed -- an 8,100-square-foot shingle-style house on 3.5 acres in Darien designed by Mary Zeko and their builder, Victor D'Acunto, owner of D'Acunto Construction in Darien. He had renovated their two previous homes and knew why they were determined to build rather than buy an existing house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Fehmi and Mary Zeko decided to move for a third time they had the money and the incentive to finally build the house of their dreams for themselves and their four boys.</p>
        <p>Last September it was completed -- an 8,100-square-foot shingle-style house on 3.5 acres in Darien designed by Mary Zeko and their builder, Victor D'Acunto, owner of D'Acunto Construction in Darien. He had renovated their two previous homes and knew why they were determined to build rather than buy an existing house.</p>
        <p>Their new house is laid out in an open plan, with inviting landscaping, a pool, tennis court and everything that their 10-year-old son, Ryan, needs -- ramps into the house and the three-car garage; three-foot-wide doors; four-foot-wide hallways; a specially constructed open shower; grab bars at toilets; an elevator with emergency phone, alarm, and stop button and many other features that permit Ryan to zip in, out, and around the house in his motorized wheelchair, living as independently as possible with a rare form of cerebral palsy.</p>
        <p>''Ryan is amazingly bright and outgoing even though he can't walk or talk,'' said Mrs. Zeko. He uses sign language, rides horseback at the Ox Ridge Hunt Club's Pegasus Therapeutic Riding classes, and attends the public Ox Ridge Elementary School as a mainstream student.</p>
        <p>While concerns -- and laws addressing those concerns -- for disabled people, from children like Ryan to the frail elderly, have produced ramps and other accommodations for them in public places, constructing houses with devices to improve their lives substantially is not getting the attention that its advocates believe it deserves.</p>
        <p>Ryan's new home, where he roughhouses like any other boy with his 6-, 7-  and 12-year old brothers, cost $3.5 million -- more than his parents ever imagined they would be able to spend on a house.</p>
        <p>''We didn't always have money,'' said Mr. Zeko, an investment banker. ''You should have seen our first house. But now -- why not make the most of it, especially for Ryan?''</p>
        <p>Why not, indeed. It's what most parents would do in the Zekos's circumstances, and Ryan's self-confidence is benefiting from the results. But wealth will not protect him when, as an adult, he visits family and friends whose homes are not equipped to meet his needs.</p>
        <p>Now he is still young enough to be carried and attended when necessary. But some day the lack of what advocates for the disabled call ''visit-ability'' will force him into an isolation that is unique to disabled people, or else into humiliating situations where he must be carried up other peoples' steps, assisted in their bathrooms and unable to get his wheelchair through doorways.</p>
        <p>If his relatives and friends all lived in apartment houses that were built or renovated to legal standards in the last decade, he would have no problem. Developers of multifamily housing are required by the federal Fair Housing Act of 1988 to provide ramps, elevators, wider hallways and doorways for disabled people. And in Connecticut, a law effective last May requires in addition five-foot turnaround spaces for wheelchairs in bathrooms and kitchens, but only in multi-family units. Single-family homes are exempt from both the federal and state laws.</p>
        <p>Basic barriers to making single-family homes universally accessible to the disabled are the public's perception of high costs, and certain helpful features that remind them of hospitals. But ramps can be attractively designed, and removed or re-installed as needed, and grab bars are now made of various materials color-coded to the bathroom, rather than the traditional cold steel.</p>
        <p>So subtle are the many features in the Zeko home that visitors are unaware of them, and the perception of high cost is shattered when viewed in perspective -- $75,000 worth of luxury features ($30,000 of it for the elevator) in a $3.5 million house.</p>
        <p>''England is light years ahead of us,'' said Eleanor Smith, founder of Concrete Change, a 13-year-old advocacy group for the disabled in Decatur, Ga. ''In 1998 a mandate by Parliament went into effect requiring every new house built in England or Wales to have no-step entrances, a downstairs bathroom and doors at least 32 inches wide. Here in Atlanta an ordinance was passed in 1992 requiring ramp entries and wide doors, but only for single-family housing that gets public assistance.''</p>
        <p>SINCE then, she said, 500 ''visitable'' houses were built, priced from around $120,000, and situated in neighborhoods where the city wanted redevelopment to take place.</p>
        <p>The city waived certain fees for developers to assist them in building homes for middle-income buyers. Lower-income buyers were able to receive various kinds of federal, state or city assistance to help in buying the homes.</p>
        <p>In Austin, Tex., a similar law became effective in November 1998. It requires one no-step entry, wide doors downstairs, higher outlets, lower switches and wider hallways also for single-family, government assisted housing.</p>
        <p>Stuart Hersh, director of Austin's Neighborhood Housing and Conservation Department, a municipal agency, said his city planned to expand the program ''to make visitability a common form of construction.''</p>
        <p>If the plan is adopted, all new housing would be required to have basic ramps, wider halls, doors and other features to accommodate disabled people. The extra expense incurred by developers, he said, would be compensated by waiving fees for construction project reviews required by the city.</p>
        <p>Bruce Lawler, a New Haven builder, completely gutted and rebuilt a farmhouse in Middletown for rent to a disabled person and a caretaker. The owner, William Wasch, who paid $300,000 for the experimental renovation, rents the fully and somewhat luxuriously equipped ground floor to a frail elderly woman for $1,200 a month, and the upstairs to a graduate student who pays $400 a month and acts as caretaker.</p>
        <p>''It's cheaper than a nursing home or assisted living complex,'' said Mr. Wasch.</p>
        <p>Retrofitting existing homes for the disabled accounts for up to 20 percent of Marty Legault's business. He is president and chief executive officer of the Corporation for Independent Living in Hartford, a nonprofit real estate development corporation.</p>
        <p>''We do an assessment, layout, and the construction,'' he said. Costs, paid by the homeowner, can run from $3,000 to $70,000 depending on the disability and the house. ''Sometimes insurance will cover part of it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Legault has dealt with disability in his own family, sensitizing him to the issues. But builders in general have strong reservations about universally mandated visitability.</p>
        <p>Carl Kuehner, president of Building and Land Technologies in Wilton, a housing developer, said he believed that buyers are put off by features for the disabled, fearing the house would have less of a resale value.</p>
        <p>Moreover the numbers don't justify universal accessibility. ''More than 90 percent of people are not handicapped,'' he said. Out of 300 units he builds in a year, only three or four are customized for handicapped buyers with diverse needs that might include a pushbutton at the bedside to ring elsewhere in the house, wider doors, a ramp outside, lower light switches, higher outlets, rooms identified by Braille and five-foot wheelchair turnarounds in bathrooms and kitchens. Single-story ranch houses, ideal for disabled people, he said, ''take up more floor area and more land, so you can't build as many units and all costs go up.''</p>
        <p>However, he said, ''we will do anything a disabled customer wants, on a case by case basis. No sill in the shower is no problem if it's a tiled bathroom. It doesn't cost more if we can talk prior to our doing the mechanicals. It's not uncommon for us to put in a chairlift,'' he noted, ''but the stairs may have to be widened.''</p>
        <p>Recently he has installed bathtub grab bars and lever door handles, which are easier to grip than doorknobs, in some of his developments as a matter of course, and ground floor master bedrooms are now commonplace.</p>
        <p>The National Association of Home Builders and local affiliates across the country are frequently targets of complaints by a disabled community that perceives them as too conservative to deal with change.</p>
        <p>''Builders are between a rock and a hard place,'' said Leslie Marks, executive director of the trade organization's Council on Senior Housing, which reviews universal accessibility for the disabled. ''Most builders are production builders, not custom builders,'' she said, ''and most buyers don't want to face the reality that they will grow old or have a handicap. They are put off by ramps and grab bars.''</p>
        <p>''It is fair to say that builders resist the concept of visitability,'' she continued, ''but they have a lot on the line -- payrolls to meet, big debts. They need to sell houses.''</p>
        <p>This, she added, is ''something that's just emerging.''</p>
        <p>''We realize that it's an important issue,'' she said, ''and we are beginning to address it with publications showing builders how to build accessible housing. I think as the baby boomers turn 55 they will look more closely at this kind of design and won't be repulsed by it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
