<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Was He Wiser Than the Wise Guys?</title>
    <meta content="02FUGI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">US Financial Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khan, Mohammed Ali</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kohli, Asim S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Maurice A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gambino, Thomas F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gambino, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gambino Crime Family</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7DB1238F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3410" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Was He Wiser Than the Wise Guys?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA B. HENRIQUES</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>In-depth article on Mohammed Ali Khan, Pakistani who was lauded by Middle East publication for his highly successful career in developing first Muslin-owned investment bank on Wall Street; Khan set up profitable US Financial Group, with assistance of Asim S Kohli, his brother-in-law, and Maurice A Gross Jr, who worked for two NY brokerages; Khan is presently fugitive from justice after he was charged by Securities and Exchange Commission with overstating his business operations to raise money from investors and attract support of business leaders; Federal prosecutors also charge Khan with committing securities violations; what makes case so interesting is that some of money stolen by Khan's brokerage came from Thomas F and Joseph Gambino, brothers and members of Gambino organized crime family; Gambino brothers have filed suit against Khan and Gross; Khan is now missing and Gross and Kahli are left to face consequences of firm's collapse; photos; graphs (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON Nov. 14, The Gulf Times in the Middle Eastern emirate of Qatar published a glowing profile of a young Karachi-born financial entrepreneur named Mohammad Ali Khan, who had returned to invest in his native land after ''a highly successful career'' in New York.</p>
        <p>''I have come back to Pakistan hoping to provide solutions, on the basis of my firsthand experience, in the areas where the country is lacking,'' the article quoted Mr. Khan as saying. It went on to describe him as a man who  had made millions as ''the proud owner of the first fully Muslim-owned investment bank on Wall Street.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON Nov. 14, The Gulf Times in the Middle Eastern emirate of Qatar published a glowing profile of a young Karachi-born financial entrepreneur named Mohammad Ali Khan, who had returned to invest in his native land after ''a highly successful career'' in New York.</p>
        <p>''I have come back to Pakistan hoping to provide solutions, on the basis of my firsthand experience, in the areas where the country is lacking,'' the article quoted Mr. Khan as saying. It went on to describe him as a man who  had made millions as ''the proud owner of the first fully Muslim-owned investment bank on Wall Street.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Khan, 35, was also credited with founding a profitable holding company, U.S. Financial Group, whose board of directors ''included 11 top business leaders of America.''</p>
        <p>''As the youngest chairman and founder of an investment bank in America,'' the dazzled reporter added, ''his accomplishments are a little more than extraordinary.''</p>
        <p>Well, in a way, perhaps they are.</p>
        <p>For whatever else he is, Mr. Khan is a fugitive from justice in New York, where state prosecutors accused him last spring of stealing millions of dollars from several of his brokerage firm's customers -- including some who also happened to be members of the Gambino organized crime family. The Gambino customers, one of whom is in federal prison, have expressed their annoyance by filing a lawsuit against the absent financier and one of his top brokers.</p>
        <p>And U.S. Financial Group? Supposedly a diversified corporate empire, it apparently existed only in an inch-thick stack of paper that Mr. Khan filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission. The S.E.C. subsequently sued him, accusing him of ''vastly overstating'' his business operations in those documents and others he used to raise money from investors and attract support from business leaders, including the former chief executive of Kmart and a top executive at Forbes magazine.</p>
        <p>Finally, federal prosecutors in Manhattan have filed a criminal complaint against Mr. Khan, accusing him of committing securities fraud by using lies and exaggerations to entice at least 55 people to invest nearly $3 million in his brokerage firm.</p>
        <p>Of course, it is the plight of the Gambinos that makes Mr. Khan's story so intriguing. It is not unusual these days for organized crime figures to stand accused of manipulating sales of speculative penny stocks. But how could Joseph and Thomas F. Gambino -- themselves such experienced criminals -- have found themselves, as they contend in their lawsuit, the marks in just such a swindle? Their court complaint offers an explanation that surely resonates with penny-stock victims everywhere: They had ''a relationship of trust'' with their broker.</p>
        <p>And that trust, the Gambinos contend, was betrayed.</p>
        <p>The Beginning  An Elusive Broker At a Small Company</p>
        <p>Mr. Khan's difficulties with the Gambino family arose from their dealings with Klein Maus and Shire, the tiny brokerage firm he opened in early 1995 in an impressive suite of offices on the 24th floor of 110 Wall Street in lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>People who worked there knew him as Ali Khan and described him as an attractive young man, slim and small, with gracious manners, silk shirts and European-cut suits. Born in Pakistan, he told people that he had lived in the United States since he was 19.</p>
        <p>He was an intuitive listener. ''He was so sharp at picking up exactly the right button to push with each person,'' said one executive who knew him. But his attention to business was erratic, veterans of the firm said, and he would sometimes disappear for months, staying in touch through calls to his wife's brother, Asim S. Kohli, the firm's young and inexperienced operations manager.</p>
        <p>Among the brokers Mr. Khan recruited to his little firm was Maurice A. Gross Jr., known as Mike. Mr. Gross, now 68, is a big, dark-haired man who worked for more than a dozen years at Gruntal &amp; Company in New York before joining Klein Maus in April 1997.</p>
        <p>At Gruntal, Mr. Gross built up a fat list of clients that included members of the Gambino family. Thomas F. Gambino, who is serving a five-year prison term arising from a federal racketeering conviction in 1993, and his wife, Frances, were clients. So were a brother and a sister-in-law,  Joseph and Arlene Gambino, and Thomas C. Gambino, a son of Thomas F. Gambino.</p>
        <p>Joseph and Thomas F. Gambino pleaded guilty to state antitrust violations and paid $12 million in fines and restitution in 1992 to settle charges that they illegally controlled intra-city trucking service in New York City's garment industry. They are the sons of the late Carlo Gambino, who founded the extended crime family that was later run by the now-imprisoned John Gotti.</p>
        <p>During his years at Gruntal, Mr. Gross lost a number of arbitration cases brought by customers who accused him of making unauthorized trades in their accounts, according to public records maintained by the North American Securities Administrators Association, although that does not seem to have worried members of the Gambino clan. Indeed, their decision to follow Mr. Gross to Klein Maus and Shire in 1997 was ''a reflection of the trust that had developed'' between them and their broker over the years, according to their subsequent lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Gross nor his lawyer responded to numerous requests for comment on the case, nor have they filed any response to the Gambinos' lawsuit.</p>
        <p>According to Gabriel Bernaschina, a former executive at Klein Maus and Shire, Mr. Khan was encouraged to hire Mr. Gross by ''a lovely old Italian gentleman, a retired vaudeville performer who lived in Hoboken and was a dear friend of Ali's.'' He knew the elderly friend only as ''Vic,'' Mr. Bernaschina said. Thus it was that the investment affairs of a fairly demanding branch of the Gambino family fell into the hands of a flimsy little brokerage firm whose standards and ethical practices were policed by the ambitious but haphazard Mr. Khan.</p>
        <p>The History  Second Looks At a Resume</p>
        <p>Klein Maus and Shire may seem an odd name for a Muslim-owned investment bank. But the name had a certain logic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khan explained to an early recruit that the firm's first name was chosen by his wife -- in homage to her favorite fashion designer, Calvin Klein. ''Maus,'' Mr. Khan said, honored a Dutch lawyer who had given him his first job in the securities business; ''Shire'' was part of the name of a London brokerage firm where Mr. Khan had gotten his start, the new recruit was told.</p>
        <p>Some of that story might be true, of course. But the employment history that Mr. Khan was required to file with American regulators when he obtained his broker's license does not list any employment in London. Nor did he mention his London roots in discussing his life story elsewhere.</p>
        <p>For example, Tariq Al-Rifai, a research consultant in Islamic finance in Chicago, remembers being charmed by Mr. Khan when they first met in the early summer of 1997: ''I was very impressed by his story -- how he had come here to go to college, starting with nothing and driving a taxi as a student, and then made his money by building up a chain of video stores, which he sold off to finance his move into the investment side.''</p>
        <p>The resume that Mr. Khan submitted to regulators, however, states only that he had worked for two years at a video rental store while he was a student at Rutgers University between 1985 and 1989.</p>
        <p>No video store fortune was mentioned in the documents Mr. Khan circulated as he tried to raise money for Klein Maus and, later, for U.S. Financial Group. But he did claim that he had earned a degree in finance and economics from Rutgers and boast that he had received ''the Financial Times of Karachi award'' in 1994. Mr. Khan acknowledged later, in interviews with regulators, that he never earned a Rutgers degree. And while Karachi's newsstands carry The Financial Post and The Times of Karachi, there is no trace of a ''Financial Times of Karachi.''</p>
        <p>While still in school, where he met his future wife, Mr. Khan worked for a few months as a trainee at Magyar Savings Bank in North Brunswick, N.J., according to one regulatory filing he made; after graduation, he worked for more than a year selling insurance products at a Prudential Insurance Company office in Woodbridge, N.J., other records show.</p>
        <p>His Wall Street career began in February 1990, when he went to work as a broker at South Richmond Securities, a now-defunct brokerage firm with a beefy file of customer complaints. By September 1991, after three months at another small firm, he had landed at yet a third troubled firm, Barrett Day Securities. There, he helped sell the cheap but high-risk microcap stocks that were the firm's bread-and-butter business, until Barrett Day's regulatory problems led to the firm's collapse in March 1995.</p>
        <p>In various resumes he later showed to potential investors, Mr. Khan summarized these penny-stock experiences as employment ''at two New York-based international investment banking firms.''</p>
        <p>The Expansion  A Brokerage Firm Appears to Thrive</p>
        <p>Late in 1995, Mr. Khan began recruiting the management team for a brokerage firm of his own, hiring a compliance officer and chief trader from Barrett Day. He also approached Mr. Bernaschina, then at another small retail brokerage firm, offering him the job of chief financial officer over lunch at the St. Regis Hotel in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''He was very persuasive,'' Mr. Bernaschina said. ''He said he was going to open up a branch office in Dubai -- that he had a prime location, and prime prospects.''</p>
        <p>Soon, Klein Maus and Shire was gaining customers and something akin to credibility, at least among the lawyers, brokers and accountants who operate on the fringes of the penny-stock world and cater to small companies trying to sell stock to the public for the first time.</p>
        <p>Three small Canadian companies signed on to sell stock through Mr. Khan's firm on the strength of their accountant's recommendation, executives at those firms said. The accountant, Gerald Goldberg of the Toronto office of Schwartz Levitsky Feldman, said he had been introduced to Mr. Khan and his brokerage firm by Greg Sichensia, a New York lawyer ''with whom we do a lot of business.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sichensia, in response to a query about his dealings with Mr. Khan, said his firm ''had an office policy of never talking to any reporters about anything.''</p>
        <p>In any case, Mr. Goldberg and executives at the companies who dealt with Mr. Khan all remember him as being impressive, if difficult to reach by telephone. ''He told us he handled the finances for some major Middle Eastern people,'' Mr. Goldberg said.</p>
        <p>The firm certainly seemed prosperous. On a Saturday early in December 1996, Mr. Khan arranged for a fleet of limousines to carry his entire staff and their dates -- more than 50 people -- to a sumptuous black-tie Christmas party at Caesars Atlantic City. There was an open bar, a band for dancing, envelopes of cash for gambling at the casino's tables -- all at company expense.</p>
        <p>By early 1997, according to one former adviser, Mr. Khan was wearing $3,000 suits and offering to fly guests to the Super Bowl in New Orleans -- ''with box seats, a private jet, the works.''</p>
        <p>That May, he was invited to participate in a Harvard conference on Islamic banking and financial matters -- he sent a senior executive instead -- and he attended a banking conference in Bahrain, winning a small mention in some newspaper accounts of the event.</p>
        <p>As he traveled more often to the Middle East, trying to raise money from foreign investors, Mr. Khan talked more about opening a branch office in Dubai. One young executive at the firm actually sold his home, put his furniture in storage and moved his family in with relatives in anticipation of a promised transfer to the Middle East, according to Mr. Bernaschina. But a Dubai office was never opened.</p>
        <p>Somewhere along the way, Mr. Khan was introduced to Joseph E. Antonini, the former chief executive of Kmart. Mr. Antonini had joined Mario Andretti, the race-car driver, in the formation of the Andretti Wine Group, a small vintner that makes wines under Mr. Andretti's label.</p>
        <p>According to documents filed with the S.E.C., the company, whose shares trade on the OTC Bulletin Board, had engaged Klein Maus as its investment banker.</p>
        <p>Mr. Antonini declined to discuss his dealings with Mr. Khan, and others associated with the winemaker did not return numerous calls. A spokeswoman for the company said that the deals that gave rise to the investment banking relationship were never consummated.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, in May 1998, when Mr. Khan filed the S.E.C. documents for U.S. Financial Group, Mr. Antonini was listed as a director, along with Leonard Yablon, executive vice president and chief financial officer of Forbes Inc., which publishes Forbes and other magazines. The Andretti Wine spokeswoman said Mr. Antonini, like others on the list, had ''indicated he had potential interest in serving on the board of the new company.''</p>
        <p>''However, this interest was dependent upon the outcome of due diligence, as well as S.E.C. approval,'' she said. ''To Mr. Antonini's knowledge, the S.E.C. never approved this filing. The board has never met or played any type of role in this company.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yablon did not respond to messages left at his New York office. It was in February 1997 that a Gambino family accountant named Joseph Gluckman first noticed some disturbing activity in his clients' accounts at Klein Maus and Shire.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Thomas F. Gambino  and his family contend in a lawsuit filed in New York state courts that Mr. Gluckman immediately faxed a letter to Mr. Gross, their broker at Klein Maus, challenging the transactions.</p>
        <p>''What the hell is going on?'' Mr. Gluckman demanded. ''I opened the last reports and found a dozen off-the-wall trades. You know Tom only gets investments in quality bonds.  Please reverse or sell all these trades immediately. Call me.''</p>
        <p>Specifically, the lawsuit asserts, Mr. Gross had used money generated by the Gambinos' income-producing bonds to buy stock in a tiny young company called American Champion, which owns, among other things, a pair of San Francisco karate studios.</p>
        <p>According to the lawsuit, Mr. Gross repeatedly promised Mr. Gluckman that the trades were ''mistakes'' and would be corrected.  Instead, he ''accelerated the pace of the unauthorized trading'' in the Gambinos' accounts, the lawsuit says, filling their portfolios with shares of American Champion and other microcap stocks whose prices had been manipulated by Klein Maus. In effect, the lawsuit accuses Klein Maus of manipulating the prices through sham trades among numerous controlled accounts, after which the inflated stocks were sold into the accounts of unsuspecting customers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gluckman continued to protest these investments and demand that they be corrected, the lawsuit says.  ''We don't gamble,'' the suit says he told Mr. Gross at one point. ''Get the h--- out now.'' In July 1998, the lawsuit says, he even threatened to report Mr. Gross to the S.E.C. But after Mr. Gross promised yet again to reverse the disputed trades, the accountant did not carry out his threat, according to the lawsuit.</p>
        <p>The Denouement  The Collapse Of a Little Empire</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. nonetheless found its way to Klein Maus and Shire's offices on Wall Street. By early that September, according to court records, S.E.C. lawyers were interviewing Mr. Khan under oath about the activities of Klein Maus and his efforts to raise money for U.S. Financial Group. Yet he continued his efforts to get an initial public offering for U.S. Financial Group off the ground, repeatedly amending his corporate filings with the commission.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Gross, by January 1999 he no longer even returned Mr. Gluckman's telephone calls, according to the Gambinos' lawsuit. And within a month, the little empire on the 24th floor at 110 Wall Street was starting to unravel. Without Klein Maus's support, the prices of the stocks that the firm had been hawking to its customers were collapsing, and regulators were circling.</p>
        <p>It was at this point, according to Eliot L. Spitzer, the New York attorney general, that Mr. Khan tried to move nearly $2 million in funds from various customer accounts -- including those of Thomas F. and Frances Gambino -- to an account in Dubai.</p>
        <p>Alerted by customer complaints, Mr. Spitzer and the firm's clearing broker were able to reverse the transfer, and the money was returned to the customer accounts.</p>
        <p>On March 9, federal investigators obtained a search warrant for the premises occupied by Klein Maus and Shire; by March 17, the firm, penniless, had closed its doors.</p>
        <p>By April 23, in an action filed under seal, Mr. Spitzer's office had obtained an indictment from a Manhattan grand jury charging Mr. Khan with five counts of second-degree grand larceny arising from the attempted Dubai transfers, along with a warrant for his arrest. Less than a week later, Mary Jo White, the United States attorney in Manhattan, also obtained an indictment of the financier, accusing him of committing securities fraud in connection with the sale of $2.7 million of his brokerage firm's own preferred shares between April 1996 and June 1997.</p>
        <p>And on May 3, the S.E.C. filed its civil complaint against Mr. Khan, Klein Maus and Shire, U.S. Financial Group and Mr. Kohli, accusing them of securities fraud in connection with  efforts to raise money for U.S. Financial Group between July 1997 and January 1998.</p>
        <p>But by the time all the various legal agencies were ready to arrest him, Mr. Khan had disappeared with his wife and two young sons, leaving Mr. Gross and Mr. Kohli, his wife's brother, to face the consequences of the firm's collapse.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for the Gambinos is seeking a court order to allow the family to seize any profits that Mr. Gross realizes on the sale of his 2,500-square-foot home about six miles from the Clintons' new home in Chappaqua, N.Y. Neither the lawyer, Peter Raymond, nor the Gambinos would comment on the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kohli is ''vigorously defending'' himself against the S.E.C. charges and ''denies the allegations,'' said his lawyer, Richard Blumberg of New York.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Khan, he is facing trial if he is apprehended, and up to 15 years in prison if convicted.</p>
        <p>To judge from the Gulf Times interview, however, those bleak prospects have not appreciably diminished the optimism and enthusiasm that were the foundation of his brief Wall Street career in America.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
