<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Emotional Misfit in a Postmodern World</title>
    <meta content="02CARM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carman, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Varone, Doug</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6DA1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1370" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Emotional Misfit in a Postmodern World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH CARMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carman, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph Carman comment on work of choreographer Doug Varone, whose company will present five new pieces at Joyce Theater; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is normal for artists to put themselves at the center of their creations. But for choreographers who dance in their own pieces, the process can be complicated. Martha Graham, for example, whose technique and stylization were based on her own physique and temperament, gave up choreographing for a number of years when her body could no longer uphold her self-imposed physical demands.</p>
        <p>The sheer burden of stepping in and out of the creative act can also be problematic. Keeping a balance between the performing ego and the demands of choreographing is an art in itself, and one that has been carefully studied by Doug Varone, whose company will be at the Joyce Theater from Tuesday through Sunday. Mr. Varone will present five premieres during the week, a number made possible because he doesn't insist on dancing in the bulk of his work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is normal for artists to put themselves at the center of their creations. But for choreographers who dance in their own pieces, the process can be complicated. Martha Graham, for example, whose technique and stylization were based on her own physique and temperament, gave up choreographing for a number of years when her body could no longer uphold her self-imposed physical demands.</p>
        <p>The sheer burden of stepping in and out of the creative act can also be problematic. Keeping a balance between the performing ego and the demands of choreographing is an art in itself, and one that has been carefully studied by Doug Varone, whose company will be at the Joyce Theater from Tuesday through Sunday. Mr. Varone will present five premieres during the week, a number made possible because he doesn't insist on dancing in the bulk of his work.</p>
        <p>''In the past I've always found a way to put myself into a work somehow,'' says Mr. Varone, who at 43 can still move with mercurial speed and consume stage space voraciously. ''I'd wheedle myself into the process, leave a hole or choreograph my part on someone else. I'm not doing that any longer. I am at a place now where I clearly make better work when I'm not in a piece.'' (He will nonetheless dance in some of the works at the Joyce.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Varone danced in Jose Limon's company in the early stages of his career, and Carla Maxwell, the artistic director of the Limon company, notes certain similarities between the two choreographers. In addition to a common attention to form, gesture, lush movement and musicality, she says, ''It was Jose's sense of space and use of people in space that really affected Doug as a young dancer and made his mind churn as a choreographer.'' And by building on the influence of Limon and Lar Lubovitch, for whom Mr. Varone danced until 1986, she says, ''Doug has developed a very wonderful and specific style for himself.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps Mr. Varone's greatest gift, however, is his understanding of human nature and of how people work together as a group. ''The Plain Sense of Things,'' which Ms. Maxwell invited Mr. Varone to choreograph for the Limon company's fall season, uses the paintings of Edward Hopper as an inspiration. Comprising four vignettes, the work reveals intimate stories about the struggle of people to connect. When it was presented by the Limon company on a triple bill with Antony Tudor's ''Dark Elegies'' and Limon's ''There Is a Time,'' a palpable dramatic thread was present.</p>
        <p>''We had pieces from 1999, 1937 and 1956 by three very different choreographers, and they each presented a community and a situation,'' says Ms. Maxwell. ''They complemented each other so well.''</p>
        <p>It is that concentration on the emotional resonance of movement that has made Mr. Varone a standout, even a misfit, in the world of postmodernists. (''What is postmodern anyway?'' he asks with a spontaneous laugh.) If any label fits him, it is probably ''humanist.'' Part of his humanistic attitude allows Mr. Varone to encourage his dancers to be part of the creative process. He has kept his stable of nine dancers, some of whom have been with him for 10 or more years, very much intact.</p>
        <p>''I have been really fortunate to have long-term relationships with people in the company,'' Mr. Varone says. ''There was a period when nobody was leaving. There was a great sense that we were there together understanding the work, whatever that meant. When that happens and you walk into a studio and something breaks loose, it's because there is a great deal of trust in the room.''</p>
        <p>Trust is very much in evidence in one of Mr. Varone's latest creations, ''Polonaise No. 44,'' which is taken directly from a videotaped improvisation to a Chopin piano score created in a gymnasium by Mr. Varone and Gwen Welliver, a member of the company since 1991.</p>
        <p>''We have built an artistic relationship over time,'' says Ms. Welliver. In that particular duet, she says, ''I found that we could make movement decisions and structural-composition decisions very quickly together.'' Mr. Varone adds that improvisation at this level rests on the ability ''to know how a piece of music builds and how the physical score is going to match that, and then just going along for the ride.''</p>
        <p>Other premieres at the Joyce include ''Agora,'' which Mr. Varone choreographed before hearing the commissioned score by Julia Wolfe; ''Eclipse,'' a trio that Mr. Varone jokingly calls ''an episode from 'Melrose Place' ''; and ''Tomorrow,'' an intimate and lyrical group work to French love songs by Reynaldo Heyn, in which solos and duets waft on- and offstage like ephemeral yet poignant memories.</p>
        <p>But the biggest risk-taking project for Mr. Varone has been ''Sleeping With Giants,'' a work of brutal intensity with Larry Hahn in the central role of a man whose usefulness and worth in society are questioned, causing him to be made a scapegoat.</p>
        <p>Throughout the work, danced to a clawing score by Michael Nyman, Mr. Hahn is exhaustively dragged into a deadly human whirlpool, circled, taunted, temporarily comforted and ultimately assaulted and disposed of by the aggressive corps.</p>
        <p>''It's about a community of people,'' says Mr. Hahn, who will turn 50 in May. ''Through time, I struggle to keep up, and situations occur that I don't understand and I get lost. There seems to be something understood and going on without me. It takes you to a place that is pretty raw.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Varone admits that the new work has an autobiographical tone in examining society's view of aging. ''I do want to call it the aging process,'' he says. ''At 43, although I can still move around, I'm slowing down, and that is something I'll never be able to reverse. It is definitely about watching yourself in some way not being able to keep up any longer.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hahn adds: ''I think it is partly a reflection of Doug, but possibly what he sees in me, too. The process of getting older and not being able to keep up, because of my age.''</p>
        <p>Confronting the inevitable haunts dancers in the latter part of their careers and is the central issue in a projected new movie called ''Without a Word,'' which will star Patrick Swayze and his wife, Lisa Nieme. The film, to be directed by Ms. Nieme, is being choreographed in its preproduction stage by Mr. Varone and five other choreographers from the contemporary dance world. The story focuses on three dancers in midlife who return after five years of absence to dance in a gala performance with their former modern-dance company after the founding choreographer dies. Through the eyes of the performers, a dance career becomes a metaphor for life, reflecting a similar dramatic arc.</p>
        <p>''In a way, they face their own personal demons to come back for one last chance to rediscover a dream that they had left behind,'' Ms. Nieme says. ''They discover that the value in life is not something outside. It doesn't lie with dance or whatever kind of work you do. Any value comes from inside yourself. It's a spiritual victory rather than a 'Rocky' victory.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Swayze, who is also the producer of the film, emphasizes the advantage of experienced dancers over what he calls the young ''techno-monsters.'' ''On a large scale,'' he says, ''the piece really goes into just how much more informed your work as a dancer can be when you're older.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Swayze says Mr. Varone is the perfect artist to express the film's intent because of ''his humanity.''</p>
        <p>''You see a real human being on stage,'' he says. ''When he tells a story, it's really through a very human body language. It's not about the technical; it's about something coming from inside of you. Doug can tell an emotional story with incredible subtlety. That is what makes him a master.''</p>
        <p>DANCE Joseph Carman's previous article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the choreographer Paul Taylor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joseph Carman's previous article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the choreographer Paul Taylor.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
