<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawyers Are Necessary To Real Estate Contracts</title>
    <meta content="LTR115858" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">krieger, abraham b</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0DB1538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="342" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawyers Are Necessary To Real Estate Contracts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letter from Abraham B Krieger, lawyer, on need for lawyers during real estate transactions (Dec 12 article) (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Re: ''Agents and Lawyers Battle Over Real Estate Contracts'' [Dec. 12]:</p>
        <p>The role of the broker has traditionally been to identify the property for sale, a willing buyer and a willing seller, and to bring the parties together. Thereafter, due diligence and contract matters are traditionally the lawyer's responsibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Re: ''Agents and Lawyers Battle Over Real Estate Contracts'' [Dec. 12]:</p>
        <p>The role of the broker has traditionally been to identify the property for sale, a willing buyer and a willing seller, and to bring the parties together. Thereafter, due diligence and contract matters are traditionally the lawyer's responsibility.</p>
        <p>Under the best of circumstances, the broker's agenda is to ''close the deal,'' subject to the push and pull of the highest price sought by the seller and lowest price sought by the buyer. An undercurrent is, of course, payment of the commission itself.</p>
        <p>The Bar has previously opined on the inherent conflict of one lawyer representing both parties except in intra-family transfers or instances of fully informed disclosure and consent. Even under those circumstances, separate counsel is preferred. One broker traversing all of these issues is a disservice to the consumer.</p>
        <p>Matters involving pre-contract disclosure and investigation, the buyer's ability to carry the real costs of the home, recommending the engineering inspection to reasonably assure that ''what you see is what you get,'' negotiation of the terms of the contract, the mortgage loan commitment, title report and, particularly, issues of marketable and insurable title and post-closing rights and obligations fall within the lawyer's responsibility. The lawyer brings to the table the experience to effectively consider and negotiate these issues.</p>
        <p>Do the brokers really believe they can provide the same quality of service by attending a one-session seminar?</p>
        <p>The cost of independent, experienced and effective counsel is traditionally significantly less than 1 percent of the price of the house. The value of such counsel and security of being fully informed and represented is a more important consumer benefit than reducing, by a relatively inconsequential sum, the overall costs by removing the lawyer from the process.</p>
        <p>ABRAHAM B. KRIEGER  Krieger &amp; Schneider, L.L.P.  Great Neck</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
