<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Cleveland, Industrial Chic And Inventive Chefs</title>
    <meta content="02TAB.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CHOICE TABLES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cleveland (Ohio)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Bryan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Choice Tables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio/Cleveland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DA1E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Cleveland, Industrial Chic And Inventive Chefs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRYAN MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Bryan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bryan Miller Choice Tables review of inventive restaurants in Cleveland; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO many outsiders, Cleveland is identified with two ignominious events: the heavily polluted Cuyahoga River's catching fire in 1969, and, nine and a half years later, the city's defaulting on its loans -- the first municipality to go bankrupt since the Great Depression.</p>
        <p>Twenty-one years later, with a flush checkbook and an incombustible river, Cleveland has a burgeoning restaurant scene. From the Flats area on the city's winding riverfront to the renascent Warehouse District near downtown and the West Side's gentrifying Tremont neighborhood, the scent of char-grilled duck and truffles is in the air.</p>
        <p>Johnny's Bar</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO many outsiders, Cleveland is identified with two ignominious events: the heavily polluted Cuyahoga River's catching fire in 1969, and, nine and a half years later, the city's defaulting on its loans -- the first municipality to go bankrupt since the Great Depression.</p>
        <p>Twenty-one years later, with a flush checkbook and an incombustible river, Cleveland has a burgeoning restaurant scene. From the Flats area on the city's winding riverfront to the renascent Warehouse District near downtown and the West Side's gentrifying Tremont neighborhood, the scent of char-grilled duck and truffles is in the air.</p>
        <p>Johnny's Bar</p>
        <p>If you go to Cleveland to see I. M. Pei's striking Rock and Roll Hall of Fame or other local attractions and would like to try a classic Cleveland dining spot, head over to Johnny's, on Fulton Road.</p>
        <p>''You want some history?'' exclaimed Ricky Paletta, our winsome waiter. ''This is history, right here -- three generations!'' Mr. Paletta is one of those wonderful waiters that you come upon, if you are lucky, a handful of times in your dining life. With slicked-back hair, a crescendo laugh and irrepressible personality, he exudes enthusiasm for his profession. Mr. Paletta can recite dozens of daily specials (or so it seems), set tables with a graceful swoop and replenish wine, all the while closely monitoring other tables in the room.</p>
        <p>Johnny's, which could be called Italian-Continental, is a long, bilevel space that looks as if an architect started an Art Deco makeover but found a better job and left. The mahogany paneled main dining room, with its leopard-spotted carpet and Roman murals, is neighborly and convivial.</p>
        <p>One of the house specials is confit of muscovy duck with a pear glaze and flageolets; although it was not cooked long enough in its fat to be a succulent confit, it was enjoyable nonetheless. Duck on the appetizer list -- peppered, nearly blackened and served with a walnut and sun-dried cherry  sauce -- was terrific.</p>
        <p>A main course veal chop, full-flavored, tender and nicely seared, came with a heady veal-stock sauce along with sun-dried tomatoes, shiitake mushrooms and basil. The kitchen really cranks it up with tournedos of veal stuffed with black truffles, accompanied by caramelized apples and a Calvados reduction -- the most expensive dish on the menu, at $32.95.</p>
        <p>The one seafood dish sampled, pan-seared sauteed black sea bass, had too many actors onstage: a mussel flan, braised Swiss chard, confit of artichokes, gratin potatoes -- not bad, just confusing.</p>
        <p>Johnny's has a top-end international wine list, with California, France and Italy well represented; most selections are in the high $30's and up.</p>
        <p>For dessert, there are majestic pumpkin Napoleon with crunchy pralines, Grand Marnier chocolate mousse bombe, bananas Foster. Considering the main-course portions, these gastronomic barbells may be academic.</p>
        <p>A second Johnny's opened downtown about six years ago; and in November, a third sibling, Johnny's Bistro, made its debut in the Warehouse District.</p>
        <p>Lola Bistro And Wine Bar</p>
        <p>Like a number of top Cleveland chefs, Michael Symon, 30, did his gastronomic boot camp in the East and then returned home. At Lola Bistro and Wine Bar, his rockin' three-year-old establishment in the Tremont district, he turns out some of the city's most inventive and compelling fare. The industrial chic setting, with echoing pop music and eerie overhead lights resembling dripping candles, is both energetic and comforting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Symon has been showing up in national food magazines recently, lauded for dishes like ''slash and burn'' grouper and coriander-crusted tuna. Both are worth trying. Despite its name, the former is a low-voltage blackened fillet with a nice counterpoint relish of sweetish red peppers and onions, alongside crispy crab ''tater tots.'' The aromatic tuna, expertly  cooked, came with a refreshing sidekick of sweet-and-sour eggplant and ginger-laced tomato jam.</p>
        <p>Among starters I liked the crisp, firm-textured sweetbreads enhanced with smoked bacon, and the delectable steak tartare, with an unconventional but harmonious potato crust.  One creation sounded so off-the-wall that I had to try it: smoked trout with a spicy watermelon salad. Let's just say that these combatants should return to their respective corners.</p>
        <p>From start to finish we had terrific and discreet service. For example, when there was a temporary glitch with my credit card, our server  passed me a note under the table.  Lola has a well-chosen and modestly priced wine selection. A 1996 Dry Creek Reserve Fume Blanc ($26) had just the right degree of tartness to stand up to the variegated food.</p>
        <p>For dessert there was a mellow apple bread pudding crowned with a Jack Daniel's cream sauce, a moist and luxurious cheesecake made with pumpkin and goat cheese, and a nicely sharp lemon tart.</p>
        <p>Blue Point Grille</p>
        <p>This two-year-old restaurant in a towering brick-walled warehouse a short walk from downtown is a bright, casual spot with a restrained nautical decor. Aside from chicken and a few steaks, it's all seafood here, and reasonably good at that.</p>
        <p>At lunch our foursome started with a sparkling oyster assortment and a well-made gnocchi nestled under julienne of duck confit. Unfortunately, deep-fried oysters sank under the weight of their batter; better bets are the ripe-tasting tomato bisque with  blue cheese, or the creamy seafood chowder.</p>
        <p>The kitchen has a fondness for wrapping things in other things, and in the case of a fillet of tilapia, the coconut coating was mild enough to let the fish's flavor come through. Also well prepared are the rare-seared tuna with a punchy wasabi risotto, and the almond-crusted Lake Erie walleye, which came with a sweet and salty apple-pancetta hash.</p>
        <p>Our waitress couldn't have been more congenial and helpful. As for wine, Blue Point's list needs more inexpensive selections; we chose a lovely 1997 Sanford Rose ($30). For the finale, the best dessert was a fine cinnamon-pumpkin cheesecake.</p>
        <p>Flying Fig</p>
        <p>Naming restaurants after fruits and vegetables that perform implausible feats was popular in the 1970's, and I thought this silliness had ended. Enter the Flying Fig, a four-month-old spot in the Ohio City neighborhood. Ecletic American fare with Asian accents is the game in this minimalist industrial space with subtle Japanese touches.</p>
        <p>We arrived at 9 p.m. on a slow Sunday night, which may have prompted groans in the kitchen, but quality did not suffer. An appetizer of lightly bound crab fritters stoked with plenty of black pepper was a good starter, as was the fig and prosciutto salad. Only the spring roll of clashing elements (smoked chicken, wild mushrooms and brie) was a turnoff.</p>
        <p>Among main courses, first prize went to the seared and juicy hanger steak with caramelized shallots and garlic mashed potatoes. Next was grilled pork tenderloin -- even though we had to send it back for a little more cooking -- with a pistachio marmalade and sweet-potato-andandouille hash. (It tastes better than it sounds.) A cinder-block-sized slab of sesame-crusted tuna was well cooked and pleasantly crunchy, but a side of stir-fried vegetables fell flat from lack of seasoning.</p>
        <p>Flying Fig's eclectic wine list is well priced and thoughtfully matched with the food, with good selections from $25 to $30. We broke through the barrier with a supple claret from Niebaum-Coppola vineyards (the Diamond Series) for $33.</p>
        <p>Desserts are where the fig reaches  its highest altitude, especially with the bittersweet chocolate-and-dried-cherry bread pudding, and the caramel pecan tart with a cappuccino custard sauce. If you haven't had enough of flourless fallen chocolate cake, the version here is oozingly executed.</p>
        <p>Mojo</p>
        <p>Another Tremont neighborhood hot spot, across from Lola, is five-month-old Mojo, a hip, bibulous place that serves a tapaslike menu along with a half-dozen ''big plates.'' High-tech lighting, a black ceiling, black tablecloths, black T-shirts on servers -- you get the picture. The open kitchen and plangent rock music amplify the festive mood.</p>
        <p>On a busy Saturday night we angled into the bar and sampled what the chef, Michael Herschman, describes as contemporary American fare with Latin, Asian and Mediterranean accents. The offerings include a pleasantly piquant charred chicken salad with a red chili miso sauce for $4.50 and a lively roasted salmon with spicy pralines and quinoa, a ''big plate,'' for $19. Most are in the $6 range.</p>
        <p>A Thai-style beef salad with a red curry vinaigrette had a slight kick, while plantain fritters with lemon creme fraiche were tasty but sodden. Pizza with shaved onions, tomatoes, basil and goat cheese was a felicitous combination, agreeably tart and sweet -- what you would expect for a chef who worked for Wolfgang Puck?  Tempura of quail, not quite crispy enough, came with a zippy carrot salad and a mixture of spiced green apples and pomegranates. Succulent baby back ribs were delicious with a mango barbecue sauce.</p>
        <p>Since we stopped here only briefly before another dinner, we did not sample dessert or get a full impression of the service. The mostly American wine list has some uncommon selections that would be interesting to try; however, for a young, casual place there are too few selections under $30.</p>
        <p>Bill of fare</p>
        <p>All the restaurants accept American Express, Visa and MasterCard; all except Mojo accept Diners Club.</p>
        <p>Johnny's Bar, 3164 Fulton Road; (216) 281-0055. Lunch Tuesday through Friday, dinner Monday through Saturday. Dinner for two with wine, around $120. Smoking allowed at the bar and in designated sections in the dining room. Cigars and pipes allowed only after food service is completed.</p>
        <p>Lola Bistro and Wine Bar, 900 Literary Road; (216) 771-5652. Dinner Tuesday through Sunday. Dinner for two with wine, around $85. Smoking allowed in the bar and in part of the dining room; no cigars or pipes.</p>
        <p>Blue Point Grille, 700 West St. Clair Street; (216) 875-7827. Lunch Monday through Friday, dinner daily. Dinner for two with a bottle of wine, $100. Cigarettes allowed in the bar and adjacent smoking room; no pipes. Cigars allowed only in the Board Room, where private parties are held.</p>
        <p>Flying Fig, 2523 Market Avenue; (216) 241-4243. Dinner only, Tuesday through Sunday. Dinner for two with  wine, around $90. Smoking at the bar only.</p>
        <p>Mojo Cafe, Bar, Portico and Bakery, 2221 Professor Street; (216) 592-6656. Dinner Monday through Saturday. Take-out lunch through the bakery Monday through Friday. At dinner, tapas-style ''small plates'' average $6 each; main course ''big plates'' range up to $27. Smoking in the bar and a designated section of the dining room.</p>
        <p>CHOICE TABLES BRYAN MILLER, a former restaurant critic for The Times, is co-author with the late Pierre Franey of ''Cooking With the 60-Minute Gourmet'' (Times Books).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">BRYAN MILLER, a former restaurant critic for The Times, is co-author with the late Pierre Franey of ''Cooking With the 60-Minute Gourmet'' (Times Books).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
