<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 'Fantasia' for the MTV Generation</title>
    <meta content="02HORO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horowitz, Joseph</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fantasia/2000 (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fantasia (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D91638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 'Fantasia' for the MTV Generation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH HOROWITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horowitz, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph Horowitz article on Disney's classic animated film Fantasia, and new Fantasia/2000, second animated classical musical medley; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1939 the composer Paul Hindemith visited Hollywood, full of enthusiasm for Walt Disney's first full-length cartoon feature, ''Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs.'' Hindemith headed for the studio in which Disney and Leopold Stokowski were working on the second full-length cartoon feature, ''Fantasia.'' But its cartoon renderings of Bach and Beethoven repulsed Hindemith; he thought the new medium was being abused by philistines.</p>
        <p>Hindemith's highbrow condemnation was shortsighted. It was the Disney-Stokowski melange of longhair and Mickey Mouse that was prescient. ''Fantasia,'' completed in 1940, proved at least as enduring as anything Hindemith composed on settling in the United States in the same year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1939 the composer Paul Hindemith visited Hollywood, full of enthusiasm for Walt Disney's first full-length cartoon feature, ''Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs.'' Hindemith headed for the studio in which Disney and Leopold Stokowski were working on the second full-length cartoon feature, ''Fantasia.'' But its cartoon renderings of Bach and Beethoven repulsed Hindemith; he thought the new medium was being abused by philistines.</p>
        <p>Hindemith's highbrow condemnation was shortsighted. It was the Disney-Stokowski melange of longhair and Mickey Mouse that was prescient. ''Fantasia,'' completed in 1940, proved at least as enduring as anything Hindemith composed on settling in the United States in the same year.</p>
        <p>Disney lavished $2.3 million on ''Fantasia.'' For its New York premiere, the Broadway Theater was equipped with 90 speakers to convey Stokowski's Philadelphia Orchestra in ''Fantasound'' -- an early form of stereo. Special engagements were booked coast to coast. Time magazine ran a cover story. But ''Fantasia'' was a financial disaster, and (to Stokowski's dismay) Disney scuttled plans for a sequel.</p>
        <p>Yet ''Fantasia'' lived on. Reissued in 1956, it turned a profit. The home video release, in 1991, was a best-seller. And now Disney's nephew, Roy Disney, has created ''Fantasia/2000,'' a second animated classical music medley. Previewed at Carnegie Hall last month, it has just opened at Imax theaters; a general theatrical release is being considered for June.</p>
        <p>No one today would demand the high-culture pedigree Hindemith looked for 60 years ago. But what to look for instead? What relationship should ''Fantasia/2000'' adopt toward its precursor? Toward the new millennium? These questions afflict the film itself. However unwittingly, it exposes the hiatus between two cultural moments.</p>
        <p>Parts of ''Fantasia/2000'' read like a homage. Mickey, as the Sorcerer's Apprentice, magnificently restored both visually and sonically, makes a repeat appearance. Of the seven other episodes, all new, a rendering of the story of Noah's ark, put to music by Elgar, furnishes a comparable star vehicle for Donald Duck. The opening segment, to Beethoven's Fifth Symphony, is all shapes and colors: abstract, like the opening Bach Toccata and Fugue in D minor of 1940.</p>
        <p>If other echoes of ''Fantasia'' -- volcanoes and earthquakes, a demonic apparition, an animal ballet -- seem redundant, ''Fantasia/2000'' elsewhere strives to be innovative. The landscapes of Respighi's ''Pines of Rome'' produce seascapes: an epiphany of swimming and flying humpback whales whose lifelike three-dimensionality -- they do not look like ''cartoons'' -- is computer-generated.</p>
        <p>At the opposite extreme, Gershwin's ''Rhapsody in Blue'' is an exercise in ''flat'' animation inspired by the pen and ink drawings of Al Hirschfeld. This wealth of variety risks an absence of unity.</p>
        <p>In place of the irreplaceable Stokowski, ''Fantasia/2000'' features James Levine conducting the Chicago Symphony. No less than Disney, Stokowski defined ''Fantasia.'' He was (needless to say) more iconic than any present-day popularizer of classical music. His distinctive sonic signature -- opulent, smooth-skinned -- helped unify the musical content. (The ''Nutcracker'' and ''Pastoral'' Symphony performances are unlike anyone else's.) The film's very repertory, ranging from Bach-Stokowski to the bold inclusion of Stravinsky's ''Rite of Spring,'' was Stokowski repertory.</p>
        <p>This time around, the repertory is thinner; there is nothing remotely as challenging as the ''Rite.'' And except for the 12-minute Gershwin and the 2-minute finale of Saint-Saens's ''Carnival of the Animals,'' all the music is highly truncated. We get 3 minutes of the first movement of the Beethoven and 10 minutes of the Respighi. The rest of the program consists of a swift conflation of Elgar's ''Pomp and Circumstance'' Marches (with interpolated chorus and earsplitting obbligato by Kathleen Battle -- a gaffe), and parts of Shostakovich's Second Piano Concerto and Stravinsky's ''Firebird'' Suite. The closing credits are much longer than the Beethoven and Saint-Saens excerpts put together.</p>
        <p>The film totals 70 minutes, and its brevity is a statement of its own. In ''Fantasia'' (which also abbreviated most of its music), both the ''Rite of Spring'' and Beethoven's ''Pastoral'' were formidably extensive. The total length was two hours. As the movie was first shown, there was also an intermission.</p>
        <p>Roy Disney, in a recent conversation, confirmed what the evidence suggests: ''There's no getting away from the fact that MTV has affected us all and that audiences are a little bit more impatient than they used to be. We wanted to err on the side of brevity rather than wear out our welcome.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Disney, whose favorite Walt Disney film is ''Fantasia,''  ''Fantasia/2000'' was a labor of love. The patron saint of Disney animation, he supervised the entire nine-year project. One thing he worried about was whether to incorporate episodes from ''Fantasia'' beyond ''The Sorcerer's Apprentice.'' He had intended also to include the ''Nutcracker'' Suite. ''But when we spliced it in, we discovered that everything suddenly slowed down when the 'Nutcracker' showed up on the screen,'' he said. ''It became very clear that with the exception of 'The Sorcerer's Apprentice,' the old and new material couldn't really coexist.''</p>
        <p>Revisiting the ''Nutcracker'' Suite on home video makes the problem understandable. Its 14 minutes -- longer than anything in ''Fantasia/ 2000'' -- are non-narrative: a patient and poetic exploration of how forms -- hovering fairies, darting fishes, floating flowers, dancing mushrooms, leaping radishes -- follow music, whose arabesques and piquancies are subtly corporealized.</p>
        <p>The episodes of ''Fantasia/2000,'' by contrast, tell stories. Even the abstract animation for Beethoven's Fifth has a scenario: a contest of light and dark flying triangular shapes (say, butterflies versus bats). Like Noah's ark to Elgar, the Steadfast Tin Soldier to Shostakovich is a linear narrative. ''Rhapsody in Blue'' is (of course) a 1920's New York tableau of subways and skyscrapers, but it's at the same time an interpolated day in the life of three men and a little girl. The ''Firebird'' is a saga of nature (symbolized by a sprite and an elk) despoiled and reborn. Only Respighi's whales and Saint-Saens's flamingos are as unencumbered as the ''Nutcracker'' fairies and flowers. In such action-packed company, it is no wonder that the ''Nutcracker'' was found to slow down the show.</p>
        <p>Also, a series of celebrities, including Steve Martin, Bette Midler and Itzhak Perlman, take part on camera as hosts. (''Fantasia'' had a single, laconic host: the American composer and critic Deems Taylor, who never appeared on screen.) So there is variety galore to go with the brevity and speed. So much explanatory mediation -- the stories, the celebrity introductions -- circumscribes creative engagement with the music. The difference between ''Fantasia'' and ''Fantasia/2000'' is the difference between a dialogue with Jack Paar and a brisk ''interview'' with David Letterman, between reading a book and answering questions posed by a CD-ROM.</p>
        <p>On one level, the ''Fantasia'' concept is a grand exercise in choreography. In fact, Ponchielli's ''Dance of the Hours,'' in the 1940 ''Fantasia,'' is a sublime sendup of choreographic art, crowned by a dashing pas de deux for alligator and hippopotamus. It is Petipa at the zoo. Equally inspired is the close of the ''Pastoral'' Symphony, marrying the soaring apotheosis of Beethoven's coda with Helios's chariot of the sun. Earlier in the same work, the grace and majesty of the music (wonderfully conveyed by Stokowski) are mirrored by the winged Pegasus on high. With their invocations of classical ballet and mythology, these sequences are polyvalent; they invite a gamut of responses from a variety of audiences.</p>
        <p>Alongside such sophisticated alligators, hippos and ostriches, the dancing flamingos of ''Fantasia/ 2000'' are a vaudeville team. Juxtaposed with Zeus and Pan, unicorns and centaurs, the sprite and elk of the ''Firebird'' are impoverished representations of Nature. This diminished cultural vocabulary diminishes the music thus accompanied. In every way -- as heard, as ''visualized'' -- it registers less impressively.</p>
        <p>One sympathizes with Mr. Disney's predicament: revisiting a 1940 entertainment, he is swimming upstream. In his charmed partnership with Stokowski, Uncle Walt was buoyed by faith in the public and its capacity for discrimination and uplift. Disney and Stokowski were visionaries emboldened by self-made success to pursue technologies -- films and the phonograph -- that would reach, as Stokowski once put it, ''the greatest number of men, women and children all over the world.'' This was the day of the popularizers -- of the Book-of-the-Month Club and music appreciation, of radio's ''American School of the Air'' and ''University of Chicago Round Table,'' all brimming with confidence that quality would find an audience.</p>
        <p>None of this would be worth belaboring if ''Fantasia/2000'' were a sell-out to 21st-century marketing exigencies. But it is sincere, not meretricious. As family entertainments go, it is more creative than formulaic. It eschews violence and sexuality. It actually conveys a modicum of innocence. At least one episode -- the Tin Soldier -- achieves a seamless integration of image, narrative and music. If this segment is less endearing than ''The Sorcerer's Apprentice,'' it is because the music is less endearing, and because the stoic Tin Soldier is no Mickey Mouse. In the truncated ''Firebird,'' where the abbreviations hurt more but the music is stronger, newcomers stand a chance of becoming hooked on the intensity and grandeur of Stravinsky's score.</p>
        <p>IN sum, ''Fantasia/2000'' is a transitional achievement, mirroring a cultural moment itself transitional. Will audiences today buy it? One hopes so, if only because, according to Mr. Disney, the people who created ''Fantasia/ 2000'' are eager to begin the next one. This would be the best possible outcome for ''Fantasia/2000.'' Mr. Disney should start with the restored ''Nutcracker'' he this time discarded -- all 14 minutes of it -- and let ''Fantasia'' 1940 set the pace for a series of longer and more patient animated episodes.</p>
        <p>He should also include some real 21st-century music, and not just of the popular variety. If Stanley Kubrick could use space-age Ligeti (in ''2001''), why not Mr. Disney? How about giving the Disney animators a crack at something genuinely brain-bending and ear-curdling, like the computer-synthesized music of the contemporary French composer Tristan Murail? Stokowski insisted that young people were more open-minded than their elders; were he around today, he would certainly have come up with a few untamed selections of his own.</p>
        <p>By accentuating brevity, the Disney team has attempted to make a virtue of a necessity. But the brevity of ''Fantasia/2000'' is not a virtue; the film feels short. Whether the brevity is a necessity is an important 21st-century question. Let us hope Mr. Disney will have the opportunity to prove himself wrong.</p>
        <p>Joseph Horowitz has chronicled the popularization of classical music between the wars in his book ''Understanding Toscanini.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joseph Horowitz has chronicled the popularization of classical music between the wars in his book ''Understanding Toscanini.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
