<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Missed Kick Sets Off Michigan's Celebration</title>
    <meta content="02ORAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bowl Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Orange Bowl (Football Game)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Michigan</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Alabama</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowl Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3D91138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Missed Kick Sets Off Michigan's Celebration</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Sunday, Jan. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>a missed kick sets off m</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lloyd Carr, the Michigan coach, figured his team had to do more than pass the ball today to have a chance to defeat Alabama in the FedEx Orange Bowl. But it was Michigan's passing game -- and both teams' erratic kicking games -- that gave the Wolverines a 35-34 victory in overtime.</p>
        <p>The Wolverines could not crack Alabama's defense against the run, ranked second nationally, but used quarterback Tom Brady's 369 yards and 4 touchdowns passing before 70,461 at Pro Player Stadium. Ultimately, it came down to the kickers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lloyd Carr, the Michigan coach, figured his team had to do more than pass the ball today to have a chance to defeat Alabama in the FedEx Orange Bowl. But it was Michigan's passing game -- and both teams' erratic kicking games -- that gave the Wolverines a 35-34 victory in overtime.</p>
        <p>The Wolverines could not crack Alabama's defense against the run, ranked second nationally, but used quarterback Tom Brady's 369 yards and 4 touchdowns passing before 70,461 at Pro Player Stadium. Ultimately, it came down to the kickers.</p>
        <p>Alabama won the coin flip for overtime, but chose to defend first. Brady needed just one play to find tight end Shawn Thompson for a 25-yard touchdown, and Hayden Epstein -- who had missed a 36-yard field-goal attempt on the final play of regulation -- added the extra point.</p>
        <p>Alabama countered with a 21-yard touchdown pass from quarterback Andrew Zow to Antonio Carter. But then Ryan Pflugner's extra-point attempt was wide right.</p>
        <p>Michigan's weary defenders began jumping and hugging each other. ''If you are a lesser caliber man, you've got a lot of chances to quit,'' Carr said. ''They never quit.</p>
        <p>Michigan (10-2) lost a great opportunity to take its first lead of the game early in the fourth quarter. With a first down at the Alabama 1-yard line, Anthony Thomas went airborne toward the goal. The ball was dislodged by linebacker Miguel Merritt and recovered by Alabama's Darius Gilbert in the end zone.</p>
        <p>The Wolverines did figure how to slow down Alabama's main offensive threat, running back Shaun Alexander, after his third touchdown of the game, a 50-yard run four minutes into the third quarter, put the Crimson Tide (10-3) ahead, 21-14. Thereafter, Alexander was held to 29 yards in 8 rushes. He finished with 161 yards rushing.</p>
        <p>This game began as if two of the greatest defenses in college history were playing. Neither team could muster a first down, or a play more than 5 yards, until its third series.</p>
        <p>Michigan's initial first down came on a trick play. On fourth down from its 37-yard line, Michigan went into punt formation, only to have the ball snapped to the blocking back Ian Gold, who is normally a linebacker. As Epstein, who is also the punter, leaped pretending to be trying for an errant snap, Gold ran for 5 yards.</p>
        <p>The drive stalled later, however, giving Alabama a chance to show some offensive life.</p>
        <p>The Tide began to take charge of the game early in the second quarter, alternating Zow and Tyler Watts at quarterback. Watts's series began audaciously, with Alexander running for 32 yards and then 14 before Watts dazzled with his own elusiveness.</p>
        <p>On consecutive plays, he scrambled for 11 yards and 16 yards to put Alabama at the Michigan 7. Two plays later, Alexander capped the drive with a 5-yard run 9 minutes 48 seconds before halftime.</p>
        <p>In less than three minutes, Alabama had another touchdown. Freddie Milons returned a punt 23 yards, and 15 yards were tacked on for a late hit. That set up the Tide at the Michigan 31. Zow found flanker Tim Bowens for a 22-yard pass. Two Alexander runs, the last of 6 yards, and Alabama was ahead, 14-0.</p>
        <p>Michigan inserted its backup quarterback, Drew Henson, but his third-down scramble of 8 yards left the Wolverines a yard short of a first down and in a punting situation.</p>
        <p>Brady returned on the next series and promptly got Michigan back in the game. He completed four straight passes, including a 27-yard touchdown throw to split end David Terrell 58 seconds before halftime.  The score was 14-7.</p>
        <p>The Wolverines added to that bit of momentum early in the second half. Its third play on offense in the half was a pass from Brady to Terrell that went for 57 yards. Terrell eased by cornerback Milo Lewis 2:57 into the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Alabama responded, however, scoring two touchdowns in a 2:31 span to take a 28-14 lead -- on a 50-yard run by Alexander and a 62-yard punt return by Milons.</p>
        <p>But it took the Wolverines only another 4:41 to forge another tie.</p>
        <p>Terrell took a 20-yard pass from Brady for a touchdown. Then Thomas bolted 3 yards on third-and-goal to tie the game at 28-28.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
