<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Memo; Recipe for Political Success: Just Add Resolve and Stir</title>
    <meta content="02ISSU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gulotta, Thomas S (County Exec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3DA1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Memo; Recipe for Political Success: Just Add Resolve and Stir</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Political Memo in form of open letter to Nassau County Exec Thomas S Gulotta and Nassau County Legislature, suggesting to-do list in year 2000 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO: COUNTY EXECUTIVE THOMAS S. GULOTTA AND THE NASSAU COUNTY LEGISLATURE</p>
        <p>RE: TO-DO LIST FOR 2000</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO: COUNTY EXECUTIVE THOMAS S. GULOTTA AND THE NASSAU COUNTY LEGISLATURE</p>
        <p>RE: TO-DO LIST FOR 2000</p>
        <p>AS Oliver Hardy used to complain to Stan Laurel, it's a fine mess you've got us in now.</p>
        <p>But Nassau's fiscal crisis is no laughing matter. In these booming times, governments across the nation pile up surpluses and reduce taxes. Yet  in Nassau -- one of the wealthiest counties -- you run up record deficits, raise taxes and cut services.</p>
        <p>Wall Street reacted by downgrading Nassau's credit rating to nearly junk-bond status. In the November election, Main Street downgraded numerous incumbents to retirement status, handing the Republicans their worst losses in history.</p>
        <p>It is time now for solemn New Year's resolutions to put Nassau's finances in order, the experts say, and get the next decade, century and millennium off to the right start for the 1.3 million people who live here.</p>
        <p>Collectively, you who are elected officials are entrusted with Nassau's shaky future. To work together, you have to get over hard personal feelings and political rivalries. Yesterday the Democrats took over the Legislature for the first time since 1917. But they cling to a micro margin, 10 seats to 9. Both sides are already jockeying for advantage in next year's legislative and county executive elections. Complicating the dynamic, Mr. Gulotta, is your estrangement from your fellow Republicans. They campaigned against your failed fiscal policies and blamed you for their defeats.</p>
        <p>Your mission now? ''They really need to do the right thing,'' said the director of the Nassau Citizens Budget Committee, Phoebe Goodman. What constitutes the right thing, of course, is subject to debate. But several major themes emerged in interviews with a range of officials and experts.</p>
        <p>What follows is not a fun Top 10 list. The tasks at hand are too tough and too numerous for that.</p>
        <p>TAKE PROMPT, FORCEFUL ACTION. ''Act decisively,'' said the Nassau Democratic Party chairman, Thomas P. DiNapoli. A former Suffolk County Executive, John V. N. Klein, a Republican, said: ''Unless something is done quickly and dramatically by the county, there is going to have to be intervention by state legislation. It's pretty darn serious and getting worse by the hour.'' Ms. Goodman said: ''Right away they've got to do certain things, because the ship is sinking. They can bail out all they want, but there's a hole in the bottom of the boat.''</p>
        <p>FORGE AN OVERALL PLAN.  ''First of all, they need to have a comprehensive plan, not a piecemeal approach of a few layoffs today and some other cuts tomorrow and so on,'' said the state comptroller, H. Carl McCall, a Democrat. His Republican counterpart in Nassau, Comptroller Frederick E. Parola, agreed: ''What should be done and has not been done is a full package that addresses the whole problem, not bits and pieces.'' Helen Cregger, vice president of Moody's Investors Service, said: ''They need an overarching vision.'' Such a plan can help restore confidence and get all the players to cooperate.</p>
        <p>PICK A SMORGASBORD OF SOLUTIONS.  Your fiscal problems are too great to be solved solely by a tax increase, or by service cuts, layoffs, union givebacks, efficiencies or gimmicks. It will take a bit of everything. ''They have to tax a little, cut a little and spend nothing new,'' said Arthur J. Kremer, a Democrat and former chairman of the state Assembly Ways and Means Committee. Spreading the pain around helps reassure interest groups that they are not being unfairly singled out.</p>
        <p>CLOSE THE NEW BUDGET GAP NOW.  Your most pressing task is to get the 2000 budget under control. Comptroller Parola projected that gaps in the adopted budget, compounded by the repeal of the real estate transfer tax, threaten a $110 million deficit. Mr. Gulotta has already taken steps that he says will save $41 million by cutting payments to private human service agencies, bus subsidies, overtime and capital projects. Delay only forces more drastic remedies. Eliminating a job on Jan. 1 saves a year's pay and benefits, but saving the same amount on July 1 requires cutting two jobs.</p>
        <p>PREPARE FOR PAIN.  ''They're just going to have to scale back,'' Mr. Klein said. ''I can't see how that can be accomplished without significant personnel reductions and cuts in services and programs.'' It will not be easy. The legislature's new Republican minority leader, Peter J. Schmitt, said, ''Nobody wants to be cut. You get the moaning: 'Oh, no, not us. We're special.' ''</p>
        <p>CALL IN OUTSIDE MONITORS.  You need all the help you can get, whether a tough financial control board as Democrats advocate, or something less intrusive like requiring that the state and county comptrollers certify budget estimates as sound. ''They have to have a long-term plan for recovery and an independent oversight board,'' said Mr. DiNapoli, ''and without those two pieces I don't think the bond rating will be restored.'' Outside overseers can push the hard decisions, Mr. Klein said, and ''politically, they can take the heat off the elected officials.'' Democratic county legislators now have the votes to ask the state for such a board. If the Republicans block it in the State Senate, Nassau Democrats can stage a local referendum.</p>
        <p>DEAL WITH THE UNIONS.  By far the biggest expense is personnel. ''With mandates and basic services that the public won't let you take away, there is little room for cuts,'' Mr. Kremer said. ''So the unions, like everybody else, have to be prepared to give back.'' He called for reopening the contracts and freezing wages. The Democratic legislators' chief of staff, Darren Bloch, said: ''We need to talk with the unions and all the organizations and tell them, 'We need your help,' not to bully them.'' Spiraling police costs are a special concern. County negotiating practices and state arbitration rules have escalated police pay sharply higher than inflation rates, civil service raises and police wages in New York City. ''The leapfrogging just can't continue,'' said Mr. Schmitt. ''The people will just say no.''</p>
        <p>USE NEW BUDGET MONITORING POWERS.  Under last fall's Budget Reform Act, legislators will make quarterly budget reviews of county agencies. More budget analysts are being hired, and the new Democratic majority leader, Judith A. Jacobs, vows to ''vitalize the committee structure'' for stricter oversight. She did not say ''revitalize.'' Ultimately it is the Legislature's duty to rein in the county executive. ''It's long, painful and tedious,'' Mr. Klein said, ''but they need to do a line by line, zero-based budgeting analysis of every job title in the county.''</p>
        <p>ROOT OUT WASTE.  In last fall's campaign, the Republicans admitted unnecessary patronage and said their final budget eliminated what they found. The Democrats say there is more. Other kinds of waste range from poor supervision to excessive overtime to top-heavy administration to overlapping functions that could be merged. ''It's mismanagement, and it's got to be fixed,'' Mr. Schmitt said.</p>
        <p>CUT JUDICIOUSLY.  It would be foolish to lose key managers, fire revenue-generating workers who collect fines or eliminate state and federally reimbursed jobs. Neglected maintenance in the last budget crisis in the early 1990's cost tens of millions of dollars in repairs later on, Mr. Schmitt recalled. And Ms. Goodman cautioned that social service cuts could produce far more costly human problems.</p>
        <p>END THE RECURRING DEFICIT.  In budgetspeak, the problem is a structural imbalance. In plain words, Mr. Schmitt said, ''We're spending more than we're taking in.'' Nassau racked up a record $193 million deficit in 1998. The year just ended would have produced the second biggest deficit ever had the county not grabbed a windfall $145 million by borrowing against anticipated revenues from the national tobacco lawsuit, giving fresh meaning to criticisms of ''smoke and mirrors'' budgeting. Now 2000 starts with a budget already pronounced out of whack before it was printed. ''They've got to dismantle whatever budget is in place,'' said Mr. Klein, ''and construct a new one.''</p>
        <p>STOP THE GIMMICKS.  ''No more reliance on one-shots and the foolishness'' like overestimating revenues and underestimating costs, said Comptroller Parola. In truth, the recovery plan may have to include some one-time devices, like the recently announced payroll lag. But once the basic budget is back in balance, the county must guard against relapsing.</p>
        <p>RAISE TAXES ONLY AS A LAST RESORT.  ''Taxes are very, very much a last resort,'' said Mr. Bloch, the Democratic aide. But an increase cannot be ruled out. Mr. Gulotta's past tax paranoia is partly to blame for the crisis, Ms. Goodman said. ''It's a problem of political will, and if he won't do it, he's got to be pushed.''</p>
        <p>CAP THE BORROWING.  ''Cut up the credit cards,'' said Ms. Cregger of Moody's. Nassau's total long-term debt is now $2.5 billion, and debt service costs $180 million a year. Mitchell Pally, vice president of the Long Island Association, the business and civic organization, said: ''The debt is totally absurd, forcing tax dollars to be spent on that instead of services.''</p>
        <p>REFORM PROPERTY ASSESSMENTS.  Using 1938 construction costs and 1964 land values, Nassau has the nation's oddest, most archaic assessment system. It causes gaping inequities, thousands of grievances clogging the courts and huge tax refunds that drive up debt. ''They've got to reassess,'' Ms. Goodman said. ''It's going to take three years, so they should stop fighting the lawsuits and get started now.''</p>
        <p>REFORM THE BUDGETING SYSTEM.  When the current budget was adopted, officials said they did not know the total and the document took about six weeks to get printed. Even then, critics say its baffling format reveals little about county operations. They want a budget that describes programs and services and shows what they cost. ''Unless you have a budget where people can tell how much money is coming in and where it is being spent,'' said Mr. Pally, ''you're making decisions in the dark.'' Mr. Gulotta needs to focus top talent on the fiscal crisis, including filling the vacant post of budget director.</p>
        <p>As you tackle the budget, here is one small suggestion. Avoid repeating the mind-boggling legal notice you published in October for the annual budget hearings. After a couple of introductory paragraphs, the notice degenerated into a stream of typographic gibberish that began:</p>
        <p>''CPF,PK,10,AA;CPF,PK,10,AA (1);CPF,PK,10,AA(2); CPF,PK,10, AA(3);CPF,PK,10,AA(4);CPF,PK, 10,AB;CPF,PK,10,AB(1);CPF,PK, 10,AB(2);CPF,PK,10,AB(3);CPF, PK,10,AB(4);CPF,PK,10,BB;CPF, PK,10,BB(1);CFP,PK,10,BB(2); CFP,PK,10,BB(3);CFP,PK,10,BB(4) . . .''</p>
        <p>The notice went on like that for nearly three full tabloid pages. ''It was ridiculous,'' Mr. Klein said. ''I have never seen anything like it. It gave no notice to anybody about anything.''</p>
        <p>Surely there is a better way, perhaps by publishing a summary, with complete copies of the proposed budget filed at libraries and county offices and on its Web site. Tens of thousands of dollars in wasted advertising costs could be saved, and more people could actually see the real budget.</p>
        <p>That would still leave many millions of dollars more of savings to be found, to be sure, but at least it would be a start.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
