<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Gina Berriault, b. 1926 - Andre Dubus, b. 1937; What Writer's Writers Write</title>
    <meta content="TLTLDUBUT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ozick, Cynthia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berriault, Gina (1926-99)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dubus, Andre (1937-99)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3D91E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Gina Berriault, b. 1926 - Andre Dubus, b. 1937; What Writer's Writers Write</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Cynthia Ozick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ozick, Cynthia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>what writer's writers write*</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The saddest words of tongue or pen? ''Writer's writer,'' a synonym for obscurity. Every writer understands exactly what that fearful possessive hints at: a modicum of professional admiration accompanied -- or subverted -- by dim public recognition and even dimmer sales. Yet the writer's writer is said to write not in hope of fame but out of quiet passion, and is thereby accorded a purity not granted to the household name. Both Andre Dubus and Gina Berriault labored long under this doubtful encomium. Both escaped it; both came to be celebrated as writers, released at last from the piously diminishing apostrophe.</p>
        <p>Their literary trails occasionally crossed. Dubus dedicated his ''Adultery,'' a novella less about sex than about truth and faith, to Berriault. And in 1997, when Berriault won the $30,000 Rea Award for the Short Story -- a prize Dubus had captured the year before -- Dubus was on the jury. Inspired heirs of Chekhov, they were connected also by a brave and enduring belief in the short story -- in its clarity, concentration and winged cutting force -- at a time when there were few outlets for short fiction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The saddest words of tongue or pen? ''Writer's writer,'' a synonym for obscurity. Every writer understands exactly what that fearful possessive hints at: a modicum of professional admiration accompanied -- or subverted -- by dim public recognition and even dimmer sales. Yet the writer's writer is said to write not in hope of fame but out of quiet passion, and is thereby accorded a purity not granted to the household name. Both Andre Dubus and Gina Berriault labored long under this doubtful encomium. Both escaped it; both came to be celebrated as writers, released at last from the piously diminishing apostrophe.</p>
        <p>Their literary trails occasionally crossed. Dubus dedicated his ''Adultery,'' a novella less about sex than about truth and faith, to Berriault. And in 1997, when Berriault won the $30,000 Rea Award for the Short Story -- a prize Dubus had captured the year before -- Dubus was on the jury. Inspired heirs of Chekhov, they were connected also by a brave and enduring belief in the short story -- in its clarity, concentration and winged cutting force -- at a time when there were few outlets for short fiction.</p>
        <p>Dubus, a robust, big-shouldered Southerner from Louisiana, the father of six, an ex-Marine captain, a good shot with a pistol, was bound to a wheelchair for the last 13 years of his life. What catapulted him there was a selfless act for which he paid with his legs. Stopping at night on a dark highway to aid the driver of a disabled vehicle, he was struck by a passing car. Out of life-altering injury and consuming despair came a reborn metaphysics. Dubus disposed of his guns -- false answers, he said, for one who sits ''in the frighteningly invisible palm of God.'' When he was able to resume writing, a new consciousness infiltrated his style: tough and clear as ever, it turned many-threaded, almost visionary. Though his method was realism, his characters, too, sat in the palm of God.</p>
        <p>The child of Eastern European Jewish immigrants, Berriault, who began life as Arline Shandling, grew up in Los Angeles, where her father wrote for trade magazines. Her marriage to John Berriault, with whom she had a daughter, took her to San Francisco. In her scrupulous and pellucid prose, she appears to distance herself from the optimistic Californian light; her characters have the matter-of-factness of knowing precisely where they are not, and their ricocheting trajectories call to mind the unembittered determinism and gothic melancholy of de Maupassant -- but an absurdist de Maupassant intimate with American expectations. Under Berriault's hand -- the frighteningly invisible palm of Fate -- realism is as transparent, and as imprisoning, as ice, and redemption is unanticipated. Comfortless though they may be, rife with the invincible givens of human character, Berriault's fictions never disappoint: they read like fact and leave the impress of wisdom.</p>
        <p>Berriault's annus mirabilis was 1997: ''Women in Their Beds,'' her short story collection, won (in addition to the Rea Award) the PEN/Faulkner Award for Fiction and the National Book Critics Circle Award. For Dubus, 1988 initiated a signal period: he received a MacArthur Fellowship and the following year published his acclaimed ''Selected Stories.'' In the end, fame seized both Berriault and Dubus -- bringing the greater prize of a full phalanx of readers. But if purity and passion are the stigmata of the obscure, fame failed to erase them.</p>
        <p>Cynthia Ozick's book of essays ''Quarrel &amp; Quandary'' will be published later this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Cynthia Ozick's book of essays ''Quarrel &amp; Quandary'' will be published later this year.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
