<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frances Sternhagen: A Diva Who Relishes Eccentric Roles</title>
    <meta content="02STER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sternhagen, Frances</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">wetzler, cynthia magriel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Exact Center of the Universe, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E0DA1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frances Sternhagen: A Diva Who Relishes Eccentric Roles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA MAGRIEL WETZLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">wetzler, cynthia magriel</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frances Sternhagen discusses her long acting career and current role in Off Broadway hit The Exact Center of the Universe, interview at home in New Rochelle; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN her producers offered the two-time Tony winner Frances Sternhagen an apartment in Manhattan during her current run as the star of the Off Broadway hit ''The Exact Center of the Universe'' at the Century Theater, she turned it down.</p>
        <p>She wanted to come home every night to her big, old comfortable house here where she has lived since 1960 and where she and her late  husband, the actor Tom Carlin, raised their six children. The plop-yourself-down warmth of her home seemed a perfect setting for the unaffected Ms. Sternhagen, who would never be accused of being a difficult diva.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN her producers offered the two-time Tony winner Frances Sternhagen an apartment in Manhattan during her current run as the star of the Off Broadway hit ''The Exact Center of the Universe'' at the Century Theater, she turned it down.</p>
        <p>She wanted to come home every night to her big, old comfortable house here where she has lived since 1960 and where she and her late  husband, the actor Tom Carlin, raised their six children. The plop-yourself-down warmth of her home seemed a perfect setting for the unaffected Ms. Sternhagen, who would never be accused of being a difficult diva.</p>
        <p>Dressed in a sweater, she looked more like a youthful grandmother next door than the acclaimed and accomplished actress she is, with film, television and theater credits that include starring roles in ''The Heiress,'' ''On Golden Pond,'' ''Long Day's Journey Into Night'' and ''Driving Miss Daisy.''</p>
        <p>''I need to be here,'' she said during a recent interview at her home. ''I've got stacks of mail. I like looking out my window to see the trees and my neighbors.''</p>
        <p>In ''The Exact Center of the Universe'' by Joan Vail Thorne, Ms. Sternhagen plays Vada Love Powell, a spirited Southern matron full of prejudices who manages nevertheless to be lovable and very funny, albeit exasperating. Vada adores her grown son Apple to the point of suffocation and does her best to embarrass the young woman he wants to marry from going any further with her son. With perfect gestures and tone of voice, Vada, whom her son describes as ''somewhere between an empress dowager and a Marine Corps drill sergeant,'' is nothing less than outrageous.</p>
        <p>When Mary Lou, twin sister to Mary Ann, Apple's intended, said to Vada at tea: ''Oh, I love the past! I intend to furnish my house with all antiques,'' Vada replied, ''Your family's house doesn't look like it would have antiques.'' Ms. Sternhagen said, ''The audience gasps and you can imagine them saying, 'She really said that?' ''</p>
        <p>She loves to play people who are odd or eccentric, Ms. Sternhagen said. ''You can be maddening and say things you just wouldn't say in real life,'' she said. ''Vada says things I would never say to anybody.  For instance, to her dear friend Marybell, who complained of her suffering: 'Marybell, don't start. We're not here to discuss your multitude of miseries.' ''</p>
        <p>Cliff's domineering mother on the television show ''Cheers'' was another chance to indulge in infuriating behavior not allowed in real life, Ms. Sternhagen said. ''She was just impossible and great fun to play.''</p>
        <p>When Ms. Thorne, a longtime friend of Ms. Sternhagen's, offered her the part of Vada, Ms. Sternhagen said: ''I enjoyed Vada right away.  My and Joan's generation recalls the wonderful uniqueness and eccentricities of our mothers and their friends. Now people are not so different from one another. There's a lot of sameness, so much TV.''</p>
        <p>Vada and her friends are a tribute to the pluck and ingenuity of those Southern ladies confined to the mores of their generation and milieu. They play cards in a tree house.  Apple says: ''I wouldn't put it past that crew to flirt with God. Seventyish -- every one of them -- and they climb up to that tree house every Wednesday to play canasta and consume sweets!''</p>
        <p>Ms. Thorne said in a recent interview in Manhattan, ''I do have a picture of my mother playing canasta in a tree house. It was in a pine tree, and I actually located it in Louisiana where I grew up.'' Both twin sisters are played by Ms. Thorne's daughter, Tracy Thorne. ''Tracy knew those ladies from visits to her grandmother in Hammond,'' Ms. Thorne said. ''Not upper class but almost, they were open to change when they appeared to be trapped in tradition -- and they weren't!''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sternhagen had said earlier in New Rochelle, ''I like that Vada grows in the play.'' Vada learns to back away and enter into the world of the younger generation. She says to her young anthropologist friend, ''I don't see how a nice girl like you ever gets used to living right alongside all those naked bodies, breasts swinging, privates dangling,'' yet in a conversation with her dead husband she confides to him that when Apple and his wife, Mary Ann, disappear into the bedroom it fills her with deep regret.</p>
        <p>The role of Vada's husband is played by Reed Birney, who also plays Apple. Their conversation at this point is a touching moment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell: ''It was different in our day.''</p>
        <p>Vada: ''We missed all that, didn't we?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell: ''I'm sorry.''</p>
        <p>Vada: ''I missed all that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell: ''I'm so sorry.''</p>
        <p>Vada: ''I should have asked a lot more questions.''</p>
        <p>Continuing the interview in New Rochelle, Ms. Sternhagen said, ''It's always nice to play a character like Vada who is well defined and so well written.''</p>
        <p>Later, in effect returning the compliment, Ms. Thorne said in Manhattan: ''Frannie finds the character in the words, not in some psychological interpretation that may not have been there. My play is an opportunity to show the world what a treasure of the American theater Frannie is.  From my soul to her mouth. It was amazing destiny and synchronicity to have her play Vada.''</p>
        <p>One night at the theater, Ms. Thorne's granddaughter, Isabella Thorne, 4, was perched on her grandmother's lap. When Ms. Sternhagen came on stage in a white suit and sat up in the tree house, Isabella said, ''Oh, Mimi, isn't Frannie beautiful?''</p>
        <p>Later Ms. Thorne said, ''That little person had an object lesson in beauty -- not the model on TV but a woman of many years of life.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sternhagen was elected this year to the Theater Hall of Fame, an organization founded in 1971, which annually honors professionals for Lifetime Achievement in the American Theater and will be inducted on Jan. 31 in the Gershwin Theater in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Ms. Sternhagen's reaction? She simply said, ''It feels good.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
