<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE YEAR 2000: Speeches, Star Power and a Whole Lot of Noise Ring In the New; Quiet, Gentle Passage On the Illinois Prairie</title>
    <meta content="02SYCA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4DD1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE YEAR 2000: Speeches, Star Power and a Whole Lot of Noise Ring In the New; Quiet, Gentle Passage On the Illinois Prairie</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <dateline>SYCAMORE, Ill., Jan. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As darkness shrouded the farm fields, Bill Lenschow milked the cows and finished his chores, then sat down with his wife, Kathy, to a special dinner of steak and shrimp.</p>
        <p>Lights blazing in a cheerfully boisterous old house on Washington Place, the Newquist children played bingo and card games with their parents, Tammy and Howard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As darkness shrouded the farm fields, Bill Lenschow milked the cows and finished his chores, then sat down with his wife, Kathy, to a special dinner of steak and shrimp.</p>
        <p>Lights blazing in a cheerfully boisterous old house on Washington Place, the Newquist children played bingo and card games with their parents, Tammy and Howard.</p>
        <p>In a hospital room on Edward Street, Jeri Delaney clasped the hand of her husband, Patrick, who is recovering from a stroke, kissed him and told him that she loved him.</p>
        <p>In this small town on the frozen Midwestern prairie, people marked the passing of the 1900's in gentle, personal ways. And at midnight, so many children scampered to front porches, shouting in high-pitched voices and banging pots and pans in a noisy, homespun welcome of the new year.</p>
        <p>For people in Sycamore, an old courthouse town that sacrificed many of its sons to the Civil War and harbored many slaves on the Underground Railroad, the promise of 2000 has come like a glistening gift.</p>
        <p>''It's a wonderful time,'' said John Garman, 62, who lives in a five-story housing project for the elderly, known here as ''the high-rise.'' ''There is peace on earth.''</p>
        <p>Lillie Jackson, 73, Mr. Garman's neighbor, drifted back in her memory to a New Year's Eve celebration from her childhood, when she played with a doll she had made of a corncob, with string pulled from a burlap sack for the hair.</p>
        <p>''That was a time,'' Ms. Jackson said, ''when people didn't expect so much.''</p>
        <p>Mary Kate Diedrich, 9, and her brother, Ryan, 8, blew their noisemakers for the big celebration in the living room of their farmhouse -- they did a countdown at 10 p.m. -- and tried to imagine life 100 years ago. Their great-grandmother, Ruth Logan, had explained just the other day how different things had been.</p>
        <p>Told that women could not vote, and were expected to stay home, Mary Kate said she had other plans: ''I want to be president.''</p>
        <p>There was no wild celebration on State Street, the main avenue through town. But some people, like Debbie Saalfeld, a 52-year-old teacher, danced to the music of a disc jockey at the Stratford Inn. Steve and Nony Roush went to dinner at Johnny's Char House, the new place out on ''the four-lane,'' as people still call the highway that leads to the neighboring town of DeKalb.</p>
        <p>But for Mr. and Mrs. Lenschow, whose cows needed to be milked before dawn, the old year passed without much thunder. ''When you get up at 4 a.m.,'' Mr. Lenschow said, ''you don't stay out too late.''</p>
        <p>Almost everyone remembered dreaming about the year 2000 as children, doing the math and calculating how old they would be, and wondering whether cars would be able to fly in the coming space age.</p>
        <p>''I remember thinking, 'Boy, I'm going to be old,' '' Mr. Roush, 50, said with a chuckle. ''And, well, I guess I am.''</p>
        <p>Bishop Joseph Thomas, the leader of the Israel of God Church on North Avenue, who was born in 1903, stayed on the straight and narrow. To mark this New Year's Eve, he walked around the corner to the house of a  friend, Lessie, who was having a party.</p>
        <p>Despite the night of revelry, Bishop Thomas was staying away from vices like alcohol and cigars, just as always. ''That's how I got to be 97 years old,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
