<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Ominous Message of a Box on Union Square</title>
    <meta content="02MUSC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Union Square (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Municipal Art Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6D91638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Ominous Message of a Box on Union Square</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Herbert Muschamp</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herbert Muschamp review criticizes building at One Union Square as example of use of public art to cover up for uninspired buildings; calls on Municipal Art Society to reconsider effects of unhappy consortium of art, architecture and real estate development in New York; photos of ten-story artwork, Metronome, at base of building and sculpture of giant hand protruding into space (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE UNION SQUARE SOUTH fails on three counts. The architecture is big and boring, the artwork glued to its main facade is pretentious, and the thinking that joined the two is out of date. This is the worst example yet seen of a formula that has helped to drain the life out of New York architecture in recent years: the use of public art to cover up for uninspired buildings. What we also have here is a crisis for the Municipal Art Society, the venerable civic organization that brokered this unhappy consortium of art, architecture and real estate development. If anything of value can be salvaged from this failure, it is the opportunity to examine the circumstances from which it arose.</p>
        <p>Designed by the New York firm Davis Brody Bond, the 475,000-square-foot building occupies a conspicuous site on West 14th Street between Broadway and Fourth Avenue. The building sits on axis with Union Square West and is visible from much of the length of Park Avenue South. The subway station below is a transportation hub. It is one of the most privileged spots in lower Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE UNION SQUARE SOUTH fails on three counts. The architecture is big and boring, the artwork glued to its main facade is pretentious, and the thinking that joined the two is out of date. This is the worst example yet seen of a formula that has helped to drain the life out of New York architecture in recent years: the use of public art to cover up for uninspired buildings. What we also have here is a crisis for the Municipal Art Society, the venerable civic organization that brokered this unhappy consortium of art, architecture and real estate development. If anything of value can be salvaged from this failure, it is the opportunity to examine the circumstances from which it arose.</p>
        <p>Designed by the New York firm Davis Brody Bond, the 475,000-square-foot building occupies a conspicuous site on West 14th Street between Broadway and Fourth Avenue. The building sits on axis with Union Square West and is visible from much of the length of Park Avenue South. The subway station below is a transportation hub. It is one of the most privileged spots in lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The design adheres to zoning restrictions for mixed-use development. A 21-story residential tower rises above a wider five-story commercial base. The dull box of a base is, as they say, packed with program, meaning, in this case, that it houses a Virgin Megastore, a Circuit City, a Starbucks and a multiplex movie theater. Different materials -- metal and glass for the base, brick for the tower -- heighten the contrast between the two parts. To diminish the impression of bulk, the tower is fragmented into vertical segments of varying heights. Recessed areas between the segments are faced with glass.</p>
        <p>''Metronome,'' a public artwork by the team of Kirsten Jones and Andrew Ginzel, covers a 10-story-high area at the base of the building's northern facade. This mixed-media work, primarily fashioned from brick, metal and glass, also incorporates special effects made with lighting, steam and sound. The theme is time and place. Its most dramatic element is a composition of concentric circles, rendered in gold-flecked brick, that ripple outward from a round opening in the wall.</p>
        <p>Clouds of steam gush from the gaping hole, while musical tones issue twice a day from a long horn that extends diagonally from the steam toward the street below. The cosmic dimension is further amplified by a sphere, half black and half gold, that revolves in sync with lunar phases. On the left side, an immense, illuminated digital panel incoherently tracks some chronological measurement not worth thinking about. A simulated boulder, a souvenir of modern Manhattan's Precambrian bedrock, lodges like an asteroid fragment in the relief's rippling rings.</p>
        <p>Above the smoke, a hand protrudes into space. The hand is modeled from the equestrian statue of George Washington that dominates the southern end of Union Square Park and is intended to represent the square's social history. The place was named for the reunification of the United States achieved by the Civil War. Later it became the epicenter for the country's radical politics, the scene of rallies, protests and soapbox oration. A debate about art and architecture may lack the bloodcurdling urgency of the tempest over Sacco and Vanzetti. But for those who care about the state of the city's architecture, One Union Square South provides provocation enough.</p>
        <p>The folks who designed this art and architecture package are not bad guys. Davis Brody produced some of the finest residential projects of the 1970's. Waterside, on the East River front of midtown, and River Park Towers, in the Bronx, remain that decade's finest high-rise contributions to the New York skyline. With their notched corners and flaring upper stories, these clustered towers are triumphs of scale.</p>
        <p>Jones and Ginzel, too, have demonstrated a good grasp of scale in the past. In 1994, the team created a delicious work for the new Stuyvesant High School at Battery Park City. Souvenirs of each graduating class were encased inside bricks incorporated into the tiled walls of the school's lobby. This past year, they completed work on a series of tile-size mosaic eyes for the Chambers Street subway station. Both projects draw on the comic tension between extra-small elements and the extra-large spaces in which they are dispersed.</p>
        <p>Scale, however, has defeated both teams at One Union Square South. Despite the efforts to break down its bulk, this building bears no appreciable spatial relationship to Union Square or to the Civil War and City Beautiful-era structures that surround it. ''Metronome'' is also defeated by a poor sense of scale. The artists' basic miscalculation was to assume that a large surface called for comparably big forms. Billboard designers can make this approach work, and perhaps a commercial sign would have worked better here. Wouldn't you prefer a sultry cloud of CK One to ''Metronome's'' blast of nothingness, especially if the billboard photo of malcontent waifs were routinely changed?</p>
        <p>THE art and the architecture overlap but scarcely interact. Think, by contrast, of the Doges' Palace, where the pink-and-white brick diaper pattern of the facade (on a scale with Jones and Ginzel's previous work) is interrupted by large windows, of irregular size and placement, that correspond to the functions of the rooms within. Program should have also driven the design of One Union Square South. Theaters, shops, other public spaces and the circulation between them could have offered a perpetually changing spectacle to the surrounding cityscape. Instead, program is packed inside the box with little care for its visual potential.</p>
        <p>Zoning and commercial space design are largely at fault here. But the architects and artists cannot be accused of pushing the envelope they were given in an imaginative direction. And this is a cause for alarm, because, from its inception, the project had the support of the Municipal Art Society and the Public Art Fund, two civic groups that enjoy estimable reputations as stewards of aesthetic quality. Their role in the Union Square fiasco deserves a close look.</p>
        <p>In 1995, the Municipal Art Society was approached by the Related Company, the developer of One Union Square South, for guidance with the project. Related was trying to do the right thing. The company saw that a building at this prime location deserved to rise above the usual commercial container.</p>
        <p>The society responded by polling a group of architects with the question: What firm, besides their own, would they recommend for the job?  Those who received the most votes were then invited to participate in a limited design competition. Human nature being what it is, this approach tilted the odds toward a lowest common denominator design. A safe but scarcely inspired choice, Davis Brody Bond was unlikely to outshine any of the architects who were polled. No one would place their work on architecture's cutting edge.</p>
        <p>Moreover, it has been some years since New York itself has supported architectural innovation. Here's a recent illustration. Oculus, a newsletter put out by the New York chapter of the American Institute of Architects, is not known for beating up on its members. Last month's issue contained reports on four new buildings with varying degrees of creative ambition. The least venturesome, designed by a local firm, received a favorable review. Two, by out-of-towners, were roughly panned. The fourth, designed by an architect with offices in Paris and New York, got a mixed notice.</p>
        <p>Translation: artistic quality and ambition count for less than local standing. A mix of xenophobia and philistinism, the newsletter displayed the kind of artistic protectionism that has prevailed here for some time. It allows less talented commercial New York firms to think that they are as good as the field's most fertile minds. Or perhaps even better than them. Aren't the stars of architecture merely fashionable? goes the unstated argument. Aren't our plodding local talents more down-to-earth, more socially responsible, less captivated by passing fancy? No. But this mentality explains why New Yorkers with an interest in architecture have to spend so much time on planes.</p>
        <p>The Municipal Art Society has done little to break this all-in-the-family stranglehold. In recent decades, the society has been chiefly identified with the cause of architectural preservation. Thanks to its efforts, landmarks like Grand Central Terminal have been spared. But if the group wants to be thought of as an arbiter of architectural taste -- if it wants the authority to recommend architects to developers, for example -- then it will also have to accept some responsibility for the deterioration of this art form in New York in recent years. One Union Square South arouses scant confidence that the society can bump up the level of performance.</p>
        <p>Founded in 1893, the Municipal Art Society is a fruit of the City Beautiful movement which also produced Chicago's Columbian Exposition that same year. The integration of art and architecture was fundamental to the group's original mission. In 1977, the Public Art Fund was founded to reinvent this ideal for the modern city. It was conceived to create visual counterpoints to the severe forms of modern design. The fund reflected the same enlightened initiative, and was created by some of the same people behind the enactment of Percent-for-Art legislation ..</p>
        <p>But public art is supposed to supplement architecture. It is not meant to replace it. Which is to say, the Municipal Art Society has been letting down its side of the City Beautiful equation. If this group's responsibility is to uphold standards of architectural quality, the New York cityscape is visible proof of its shortcomings. I leave aside for now the ethical issues raised by the organization's practice of recommending architects (including its own board members) to commercial developers. But the stunning provincialism of New York architecture since the late 1960's is a cultural scandal that public art programs cannot cover up, any more than a cloud of smoke can mask the banal design of One Union Square South.</p>
        <p>The society's neglect of architecture reflects attitudes in the city at large. In the 50's and 60's, architecture had the support of a cultural consensus once rooted in liberal arts education. That consensus is what enabled projects like Lever House, the Seagram Building, the Guggenheim Museum, the Ford Foundation Building and the CBS Building to be realized. It is also what enabled such projects to be criticized. The liberal consensus culture had room both for artistically ambitious work and for robust attacks on it. Part of the consensus was the expectation of dissent, and not simply over the work of out-of-towners. What it didn't have room for was the habit of playing it safe.</p>
        <p>Playing it safe is what urbanism is all about these days. What's left of the liberal consensus now rallies behind preservation and public art, two sacred cows that need no rallies at this point. Who can argue with preservation? Wouldn't that be tantamount to joining the vandals who pulled down Penn Station? And who but a Jesse Helms would oppose public art?</p>
        <p>Yet between them, these two worthy causes have helped to generate a hostile climate for architecture, the most public of all arts. At Battery Park City, for example, an innovative public art program served as a fig leaf over the reactionary thinking that produced the development's retrograde, ersatz pre-war buildings. Reactionary? How dare you call us reactionary! Why, we've just spent millions on projects by Mary Miss, Siah Armajani and Ned Smyth!</p>
        <p>But when public art reaches the architectural scale favored by Miss, or by Jones and Ginzel, then the question naturally arises: Yes, but where's the architecture? On Union Square South, you can't miss the answer. Thanks to Jones and Ginzel, there's even a big target pasted on it. The answer is: There's no architecture here. This building has no idea what it is doing here. It has nothing fresh to say, not even an eloquent silence. It's just some space in a box with a leaky hole in it.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
