<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yeltsin Goes, Uncertainty Remains</title>
    <meta content="02PIPE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pipes, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5DA1338F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yeltsin Goes, Uncertainty Remains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Pipes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pipes, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Pipes Op-Ed article says Pres Yeltsin's unexpected resignation in Russia was brilliant political ploy that has worrisome implications for West; explains that move enhances Vladimir Putin's presidential prospects, improves chance that Yeltsin will be remembered as patriot and allows Putin to give Yeltsin immunity against corruption charges (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boris Yeltsin's unexpected resignation was a brilliant political ploy, and one with worrisome implications for the West.</p>
        <p>The move was clever because it enhanced the presidential prospects of Mr. Yeltsin's chosen successor, Vladimir Putin; it will improve the chances of Mr. Yeltsin's being remembered as a patriot rather than a leader who put ambition ahead of the nation's interests; and it allowed Mr. Putin to give Mr. Yeltsin immunity against corruption charges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Boris Yeltsin's unexpected resignation was a brilliant political ploy, and one with worrisome implications for the West.</p>
        <p>The move was clever because it enhanced the presidential prospects of Mr. Yeltsin's chosen successor, Vladimir Putin; it will improve the chances of Mr. Yeltsin's being remembered as a patriot rather than a leader who put ambition ahead of the nation's interests; and it allowed Mr. Putin to give Mr. Yeltsin immunity against corruption charges.</p>
        <p>It also went over well internationally. Once they got over the shock, President Clinton and other Western leaders welcomed the decision as insurance of a smooth transition of power and the continuation of reforms.</p>
        <p>In some respects, optimism is warranted. In last month's parliamentary elections the two parties sponsored by Mr. Putin gained a greater share of the vote than did the Communists, promising the kind of cooperation between the executive and the Duma that heretofore has eluded the Kremlin. And Mr. Putin quickly pledged close cooperation with the West.</p>
        <p>Yet closer scrutiny of how he came to power and of what he tells his domestic political audience reveals  cause for anxiety.</p>
        <p>The main pro-Putin faction, the Unity Party, gained nearly one-quarter of the vote in the parliamentary elections, yet it presented no platform. Its appeal consisted entirely of support for the Chechen war, which Mr. Putin says is necessary to save Russia's ''honor.'' He dismissed out of hand foreign protests of the war, calling it an internal Russian matter. In other words, the party's program consisted mostly of appeals to chauvinism and anti-Westernism.</p>
        <p>Moreover, in a statement on a government Internet site in December, Mr. Putin declared that Western-style democracy was not suited to Russia. Russian society, he explained, ''wants a restoration of a guiding and regulatory role of the state.'' Russians are ''not ready to abandon traditional dependence on the state and become self-reliant individuals,'' he noted, and thus the country needs ''a comprehensive system of state regulation of the economy.'' These sentiments hardly point to further political and economic liberalization.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in a speech two months ago, Mr. Putin said that to improve the economy Russia needed to beef up its defense industries -- a bizarre statement given that the Soviet economy  was ruined by runaway military expenditures. He pledged to increase military spending by 57 percent, ''to respond to new geopolitical realities, both external and internal threats.''</p>
        <p>Even more worrisome was the paean to Russia's secret services he delivered on the anniversary of Lenin's creation of the Cheka, the first Soviet secret police. ''Several years ago,'' he said on this occasion, ''we fell prey to an illusion that we have no enemies. We paid dearly for this. . . . The organs of state security have always guarded Russia's national interests.'' This praise was lavished on the Cheka, the O.G.P.U., the N.K.V.D. and the K.G.B., indispensable instruments of Communist terror that deprived millions of Soviet citizens of their lives and liberties, and kept the rest in constant fear.</p>
        <p>Yes, Mr. Putin is certainly an anti-Communist, but Soviet-style Communism no longer poses a real threat to Russia -- only a fraction of those who vote for the Communist Party want a return to the past. The danger is authoritarianism fused with nationalism and imperialism: a government that respects some basic economic and civil freedoms, because they enjoy popular support, but represses political expression and exploits anti-Western sentiments to isolate Russia from the world.</p>
        <p>It is possible, of course, that should Mr. Putin win the presidency he will prove a pragmatic politician and steer a reasonable course. But his political rhetoric makes clear that we can't take anything for granted.</p>
        <p>Richard Pipes, a research professor at Harvard, is the author of ''Property and Freedom.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard Pipes, a research professor at Harvard, is the author of ''Property and Freedom.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
