<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adventures In the Real Marketplace</title>
    <meta content="02HOME$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2D81738F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adventures In the Real Marketplace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jay Romano's Your Home column on Romano's experience of selling a house and buying another; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the last year or so, my family and I have stumbled through a variety of experiences that mirror issues covered in this column. We sold one house, bought another and went through the grind of getting the necessary mortgage in between.</p>
        <p>Here are some of the lessons we learned -- the hard way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the last year or so, my family and I have stumbled through a variety of experiences that mirror issues covered in this column. We sold one house, bought another and went through the grind of getting the necessary mortgage in between.</p>
        <p>Here are some of the lessons we learned -- the hard way.</p>
        <p>No house is ever in perfect shape for a sale.</p>
        <p>It would not be an exaggeration to say that my wife and I were contemplating selling our house for nearly two years before we actually put it on the market. There was always one more thing that needed to be fixed, painted, cleaned or replaced before the house could be officially declared for sale.</p>
        <p>Attending to those details, however, took time and money and only resulted in the gradual discovery of even more things that needed fixing, painting, cleaning or replacing. And while some of the repairs we made were worth the time and effort -- a new front door and refinished hardwood floors almost tempted us to keep the place -- I think that in retrospect, we probably would have been better off selling the house, with all its problems, two years earlier.</p>
        <p>In fact, it was only after my sister-in-law came to town and persuaded us to get started that we took the most important step in getting the house ready for market: holding a two-day garage sale and ridding ourselves of years of clutter.</p>
        <p>That garage sale -- which did more to make the house marketable than two years of tinkering -- finally allowed us to put our ''For Sale by Owner'' sign on the front lawn. But as it turned out, that resulted in Lesson No. 2:</p>
        <p>A homeowner who acts as his own real estate broker probably has a fool for a client.</p>
        <p>Most people know that the primary reason a homeowner tries to sell a house without a broker is to avoid paying the traditional 6 percent sales commission. What most people do not know, however, is how difficult the experience can be.</p>
        <p>One of the first things such a seller learns is that for every serious potential buyer who wanders through the house, there are dozens who are either just looking, just curious or, worse, just nosy. The problem is, buyers don't wear tags indicating which group they belong to.</p>
        <p>And since even the most casual buyer believes he is doing a self-seller a favor by stopping by to take a look, some feel entitled to do so just about anytime they please. We had one prospective buyer stop by -- without warning -- well after 9 p.m.; when he was told that our children were in bed, he promised to be quiet. We demurred.</p>
        <p>Another buyer -- a man who wanted the house so badly he brought ice cream cones and baseball caps for our children -- offered us full price, had his lawyer draw up a contract, hand-delivered the contract and the deposit, and then backed out of the deal the next day. (We returned the deposit but kept the hats.)</p>
        <p>Were we to try to sell a house on our own in the future -- which is unlikely -- we would make sure that any for-sale signs or advertisements made it clear that the house would be shown by appointment only.</p>
        <p>When selling through a broker, let the broker do the work.</p>
        <p>Experienced brokers rarely need a seller's help when showing a house to a prospective buyer. In fact, most brokers would prefer that the homeowner -- particularly a homeowner with small children -- be out of the way (and preferably out of the house) when a buyer comes to look.</p>
        <p>If a seller must be home while an agent is showing a house to a prospective buyer, it is wise to keep in mind the advice that the police provide suspects in crimes: ''Anything you say can and will be used against you.'' Looking back, it seems that there were at least a few occasions when I felt compelled to point out details that might have been best left unmentioned: Did a buyer really need to know, for example, that the sink and toilet in the upstairs bathroom were replaced by me (legally, of course) rather than by a plumber?</p>
        <p>It is also wise to let your listing broker negotiate the terms of any potential deals presented by another agent. In my eagerness to get a buyer's signature on a contract, I conducted my own negotiations with the buyer's sales agent. I'm wondering to this day whether the broker who eventually listed my house -- and through whom we finally sold it -- might have done a better job.</p>
        <p>While underground fuel storage tanks may be out of sight, they should not be out of mind.</p>
        <p>This is critical. Though I had written at least one column recommending that homeowners with underground fuel storage tanks have their tanks tested and then obtain tank insurance to protect against future leaks, I inexplicably failed to heed the advice I so eagerly disseminated.</p>
        <p>And while the person who was buying the house was not all that concerned about the 1,000-gallon monster buried in the yard -- he was planning to convert to gas after the purchase -- his insurance company nevertheless insisted on having the tank tested.</p>
        <p>As a result, my wife and I spent an anxious 48 hours waiting for the buyer's tank-testing company to tell us whether the tank was leaking and, if so, just how much of the surrounding neighborhood we had contaminated.</p>
        <p>Since we had never obtained insurance to protect against such an event, we would have been left with no option but to remove or otherwise decommission the tank on the buyer's terms and under the time pressure of a sale. Fortunately, the tank wasn't leaking.</p>
        <p>Mortgages have never been so easy to get -- as long as you can prove you don't need the money.</p>
        <p>This, of course, is a bit of an exaggeration. But despite the fact that mortgage lenders like to give the impression that you can get mortgage approval overnight, it usually takes a bit longer than that.</p>
        <p>In most cases, a lender will demand exacting details about the finances and creditworthiness of a prospective borrower. And while it might seem a bit much to have to explain why a gas credit card payment was late in July 1996 (I lost the bill -- really) you can be sure that the person processing the loan is not just being an economic voyeur.</p>
        <p>Generally speaking, loan officers ask only for documents and explanations they need to get the loan you want. And losing one's temper with the loan processor's secretary, it seems, has no impact whatsoever on Fannie Mae's underwriting requirements. Or so I found.</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
