<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Charter Schools Enroll Few of Learning Disabled</title>
    <meta content="02CHAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Learning Disabilities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suhay, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4D71738F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Charter Schools Enroll Few of Learning Disabled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA SUHAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Suhay, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Focus on recent report by New Jersey Department of Education's Joint Committee on Public Schools, which said charter schools lag behind public schools in number of student with learning disabilities; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When state education officials released a report last week showing that charter schools lagged behind public schools in the number of students with learning disabilities, advocacy groups representing parents were ready to say ''I told you so.''</p>
        <p>About 6.3 percent of charter school students have learning disabilities, while in public schools the number is 12.5 percent, according to the report released by the Department of Education's Joint Committee on the Public Schools. The contents of the study ranged from recommendations for adding funding for districts where students move directly from nonpublic schools to charter schools to details of charter schools' weaknesses in dealing with special needs students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When state education officials released a report last week showing that charter schools lagged behind public schools in the number of students with learning disabilities, advocacy groups representing parents were ready to say ''I told you so.''</p>
        <p>About 6.3 percent of charter school students have learning disabilities, while in public schools the number is 12.5 percent, according to the report released by the Department of Education's Joint Committee on the Public Schools. The contents of the study ranged from recommendations for adding funding for districts where students move directly from nonpublic schools to charter schools to details of charter schools' weaknesses in dealing with special needs students.</p>
        <p>Since 1996 the group Statewide Parent Advocacy Network (SPAN), which is based in Newark, has lobbied the state to pay closer attentions to how charter schools  handle children with learning disabilities.</p>
        <p>''Most charter schools in the state are ill equipped to deal with special-needs children and are turning them away,'' said Diana  Autin, executive co-director of SPAN. ''Worse, their early intervention programs are almost nonexistent and so the children who should be picked up are being missed.''</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Autin, SPAN has been getting calls from frustrated parents across the state who say charter schools turned their children away.</p>
        <p>Jeff Osowski, assistant commissioner for the state's division of Information and Management, said there could be many reasons for the difference in enrollments.</p>
        <p>''One is that a smaller percentage of parents are entering the pool because they don't want to pull their kids out of special schools and programs that they worked hard to develop,'' Mr. Osowski said. ''Second is, is there an outreach problem here in that they're not getting to these parents?  Also, maybe there is a problem out there with program availability.''</p>
        <p>In response, Ms. Autin said: ''We told them over and over again that this was  going to be a problem and they told us not to worry, that it wouldn't happen. In this case we really hate to be right.''</p>
        <p>In addressing another point of contention, the charge that the charter schools are ''creaming'' or collecting only the best and brightest students from public schools, the report flatly stated: ''No so-called 'creaming' is occurring.''</p>
        <p>The study included a profile showing that black students make up 63 percent of the population at charter schools and 51 percent at public schools.</p>
        <p>According to the report there are 47 charter schools serving approximately 9,000 students in the state for the 1999-2000 school year. That number is out of a total public school population of 1.2 million.</p>
        <p>The report concludes that there are approximately 2,888 students on waiting lists to get into charter schools in the state.</p>
        <p>The report also concluded that the schools' populations are ''clearly representative of the districts in which they are located in terms of academic achievement, economic status and minority status.''</p>
        <p>Asked if he was aware of students being refused entrance to charter schools because  they had special needs, Mr. Osowski said, ''I won't dispute that SPAN may be getting these calls, but we haven't gotten any such  complaints here in our office.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Osowski said the legislation that created charter schools in New Jersey required them to provide for the needs of children with disabilities just as public schools do.</p>
        <p>However, SPAN contends that charters were given an out, a loophole, when language was included that allows the schools to seek waivers from all regulations except those pertaining to assessment, testing, civil rights and student health and safety.</p>
        <p>When asked to comment on the waivers, Mr. Osowski said he was ''unfamiliar with  that procedure.''</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
