<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends: State of Democracy; What a Great Primary Campaign We Just Had!</title>
    <meta content="02NAGO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165534"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Voter Behavior</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7DB1338F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends: State of Democracy; What a Great Primary Campaign We Just Had!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ever-earlier presidential primaries, and decision-making, discussed; photo; many Americans perceive 2000 campaign as starting now, but truth is that both Democratic and Republican contests will likely be settled in just nine weeks, effectively disenfranchising voters who have barely started to pay attention (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR much of the American public, the 2000 election for the White House starts today. The holidays have passed and in a presidential election year that means that the country is ready to attend to what the candidates are doing and saying.</p>
        <p>Or rather, have done and said. The truth is that most people are tuning in rather late. In all likelihood, the Democratic and Republican contests will be settled in just nine weeks, if not by the first week of February.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR much of the American public, the 2000 election for the White House starts today. The holidays have passed and in a presidential election year that means that the country is ready to attend to what the candidates are doing and saying.</p>
        <p>Or rather, have done and said. The truth is that most people are tuning in rather late. In all likelihood, the Democratic and Republican contests will be settled in just nine weeks, if not by the first week of February.</p>
        <p>Since 1976, more and more states have inched their primaries back to the starting line, competing to assure their influence over the nominee. It has been a haphazard process, following no grand plan of either party, if countenanced by some Republican and Democratic leaders who believe that avoiding an intramural primary struggle is the recipe for a strong general election nominee. The result, though, is that nearly 75 percent of the delegates will be chosen by the middle of March, even as the primaries continue through June 6.</p>
        <p>But is that progress? As the primary season begins in earnest, there seems to be a consensus among political leaders and academics that it is not: that this constant tinkering with the political calendar has produced the opposite of what had been intended.</p>
        <p>Instead of a nominating process that engages voters, the ever-shortening calendar is more apt to disenfranchise them, with its early finish and narrow window within which to consider the candidates. Instead of assuring big states a big voice in choosing the nominees, the calendar dilutes their influence, since so many of them have crowded their primaries onto the same two early Tuesdays. And, instead of producing formidable general election standard-bearers, the process turns out nominees who might, come the tumult of the fall campaign, wish they had devoted more time to what is the political equivalent of spring training.</p>
        <p>''People are being rushed to judgment,'' said William F. Galvin, the Massachusetts secretary of state and the chairman of the Committee on Presidential Primaries of the National Association of Secretaries of State. ''It's become a candidate death watch, instead of an effort at finding out who these people are.''</p>
        <p>Consider this: well before this month, a series of presumably credible candidates for president -- among them, Lamar Alexander, the former governor of Tennessee and Elizabeth Dole, the former secretary of transportation -- had already quit the race, largely because they could not figure out how to surmount the political calendar. The exhausting schedule of cross-country primaries that awaits the field on March 7 and March 14 has put a premium on the candidate-as-fundraiser, in order to raise the money to finance travel and multistate advertising.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, that suffocates the long-shot candidate, like Paul Tsongas in 1992 or Bruce Babbitt in 1988, who had once put excitement into American politics.</p>
        <p>Candidates are, of course, supposed to drop out if they do badly in New Hampshire and Iowa. But not to even make it to the startling line? ''This the first year that I can remember where a whole lot of candidates dropped out before a single vote was cast,'' said William G. Mayer, a professor of political science at Northeast University, and co-author of ''The Modern Politics of Presidential Selection.''</p>
        <p>Iowans and New Hampshirites, long used to being the first judges of candidates' credentials and ideas, may be excused for feeling a little rushed. As big states have shouldered to the front of the primary line,  New Hampshire and Iowa have edged back to protect their historic first-in-the-nation status. The New Hampshire primary is now  Feb. 1, or 20 days earlier than it was in 1996, a long time in retail politics.</p>
        <p>POLITICAL campaigns remain engaging and meaningful to many Americans in part because voters are so unpredictable -- especially in New Hampshire and Iowa. That said,  most analysts believe the nominees will be known by the close of polls on March 7, by which time 43 percent of the elected Republican delegates and 37 percent of the Democratic delegates will have been selected. And if not then, certainly by the following week.</p>
        <p>''It's like 75 percent of the delegates have been selected by the middle of March, which is faster than last time,'' said Barbara Norrander, professor of political science at the University of Arizona. ''And last time it was faster than the time before.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is conceivable that the race could be over on Feb. 1, especially on the Republican side. If Senator John S. McCain of Arizona fails to defeat Gov. George W. Bush of Texas in New Hampshire, after waging a spirited campaign there, his own supporters have trouble seeing how he could survive.</p>
        <p>Similarly, a number of Democrats question how long Bill Bradley, the former senator from New Jersey, can continue if he does not make a strong showing against Vice President Al Gore there (presumably a victory, though a near-victory has done the trick for candidates in the past).</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain and Mr. Bradley are both examples of the type of candidates who have historically flourished in New Hampshire: slightly insurgent and underfunded. But even if both should win there, the calendar works against them pushing on to the nomination.</p>
        <p>There are no Democratic primaries until March 7, but there are 16 contests on that day, from New York to California. It is worse for Mr. McCain. Before March 7, he faces contests in South Carolina, Arizona and Michigan. That schedule could not be more problematic for an underfunded candidate running outside of the establishment. Nor could it be more accommodating for Mr. Bush, who spent much of last year raising money to prepare himself precisely for this moment.</p>
        <p>''McCain and Bradley have had enormous breaks in this race -- and it's still uphill for them,'' said Charles E. Cook Jr., the editor of a Washington-based political report. ''They still have to thread a needle.''</p>
        <p>Not only does the present primary system reduce the chance of an outsider winning a nomination, it will likely force them out of the race sooner, thus reducing the chance that they will help shape the positions of their party or their nominee. This, in turn, may leave their supporters feeling shut out of and uninterested in participating in the political process.</p>
        <p>The traditional view among party professionals is that the system produces a good result for the party: an early nominee. ''It's a bad thing to keep going: you'd rather get it out of the way,'' said James Carville, the consultant to President Clinton. ''Find one fighter that likes to get hit.''</p>
        <p>As the primary season grows shorter each cycle, that once-dominant view holds less and less sway.  ''It's bad for the candidate because you don't get the same feel for the country,'' said Paul Begala, who worked with Mr. Carville in running Mr. Clinton's 1992 campaign. ''I traveled with Bill Clinton to 48 states, by my count. You learn a lot. You see a lot.''</p>
        <p>Less time campaigning also means less examination of a candidate's record, experience and past.  And there are tactical complications posed by becoming the candidate too early.</p>
        <p>How do candidates fill the long months between winning the nomination and the summer convention? How do they compete with the Reform Party's likely candidates, notably Donald J. Trump, who may have the stage largely to himself in the spring? How do the campaigns hold on to the voters' attention, or do they at all? Witness what happened with Bob Dole in 1996, as he struggled to distance himself from Congressional Republicans pushing policies that played against his own campaign interests.</p>
        <p>Indeed, with few exceptions, no one is happy with the way the system has  evolved, and both the national Republican and Democratic committees have set up commissions to examine how or whether to change it.  ''If the front-loading does result in people believing they do not play the role they would otherwise, we have to do something about it,'' said Joe Andrew, the national Democratic chairman.</p>
        <p>Richard N. Bond, the former national Republican chairman, offered a more fundamental concern about the process. ''I'm a gray-hair now, and the gray-hairs of the Republican Party think it's better to have a primary than not,'' Mr. Bond said.  ''Because your guy gets tested. A feverish contest that would resolve early enough is the prescription for success.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
