<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Lady in the Van' Offers a Moral Behind the Laughter</title>
    <meta content="02NIGH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barbican Center (London)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nightingale, Benedict</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennett, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Maggie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stafford, Nick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beale, Simon Russell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wanamaker, Zoe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boyd, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lady in the Van, The (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Battle Royal (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Midsummer Night's Dream, A (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/William Shakespeare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Maggie Smith</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDE1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Lady in the Van' Offers a Moral Behind the Laughter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENEDICT NIGHTINGALE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nightingale, Benedict</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benedict Nightingale reviews London stage productions of Alan Bennett's The Lady in the Van starring Maggie Smith, Nick Stafford's Battle Royal starring Simon Russell Beale and Zoe Wanamaker, and Michael Boyd's production of Midsummer Night's Dream at Barbican; scene photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALAN BENNETT has been much on the minds of British theatergoers of late. Two different actors, each complete with specs, floppy hair and mournful Yorkshire accent, perform the playwright himself in ''The Lady in the Van,'' the dramatic memoir he recently opened at the Queen's. The National Theater is staging ''Battle Royal,'' which is by the lesser-known Nick Stafford but has been widely seen as a sequel to Mr. Bennett's ''Madness of George III.'' We would not have been too astonished if the dramatist, who has occasionally appeared on the London stage in the past, had rematerialized as a melancholy sprite in the magnificently original ''Midsummer Night's Dream'' that the Royal Shakespeare Company is presenting at the Barbican.</p>
        <p>'The Lady in the Van'</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALAN BENNETT has been much on the minds of British theatergoers of late. Two different actors, each complete with specs, floppy hair and mournful Yorkshire accent, perform the playwright himself in ''The Lady in the Van,'' the dramatic memoir he recently opened at the Queen's. The National Theater is staging ''Battle Royal,'' which is by the lesser-known Nick Stafford but has been widely seen as a sequel to Mr. Bennett's ''Madness of George III.'' We would not have been too astonished if the dramatist, who has occasionally appeared on the London stage in the past, had rematerialized as a melancholy sprite in the magnificently original ''Midsummer Night's Dream'' that the Royal Shakespeare Company is presenting at the Barbican.</p>
        <p>'The Lady in the Van'</p>
        <p>''The Lady in the Van'' originally consisted of notes published in book form in 1990, all of them involving Miss Shepherd, a genteel vagrant who parked her battered old van near Mr. Bennett's North London house in 1971 and eventually browbeat him into pushing it into the mini-driveway leading to his front door. And there the lady remained until her death in 1989, occasionally emerging from the vehicle to make a complaint, share a loony apercu, or simply fill Mr. Bennett's tiny garden with a stench that he compared to ''the inside of someone's ear'' and she variously blamed on an infestation of cheese-carrying mice and the ''things on sticks'' cooked in a nearby Greek restaurant.</p>
        <p>Transposed to the stage, the character seems purpose-built for Maggie Smith, who can outdo any performer when it comes to exuding crackpot hauteur. Her face is grimier than we've ever seen it, but her nose also seems beakier, her cheeks more withered, her eyes more bulbous. And on her head is either a Rambo baseball cap or a Rommel-style khaki helmet whose side flaps reach down to a foul brown overcoat. ''My wardrobe's driving me mad,'' says Dame Maggie in her Mayfair-hostess voice, grandly oblivious to the fact that her madness is driving her wardrobe.</p>
        <p>Since the English enjoy their eccentrics, ''The Lady in the Van'' could just be a smugly patronizing celebration of national oddity in one of its more extreme manifestations. But this is far from the case. First, the piece is as much about Mr. Bennett as his freeloading tenant. That is why he appears in duplicate in the replica living-room which shares the stage with the rusting van. Kevin McNally and Nicholas Farrell are each identically dressed in a tweedy brown jacket and rumpled corduroy pants, but Mr. McNally's task is mainly to narrate and ruminate, Mr. Farrell's to converse with Miss Shepherd and assorted intruders and passers-by. The two Bennetts also talk anxiously to each other, giving us a play that largely concerns the split liberal conscience.</p>
        <p>What are Mr. Bennett's motives in becoming this cranky old layabout's unpaid landlord? Is he a saint and martyr, as his neighbors suggest, or a weakling who cannot say no, as he himself suspects? Was there always part of him that wanted to exploit Miss Shepherd for literary profit? Is he guiltily compensating for failing to visit his own mother, in Elizabeth Bradley's performance an aged crone as reproachful and eventually as nutty as Miss Shepherd, and then putting her in a home? Such questions could come across as the standard anguishings of a self-absorbed, self-indulgent man, but in Nicholas Hytner's production they amount to more than that. They invite us to ask what responsibility we ourselves have for the bums and crazies who wander the streets and sometimes land up on our doorsteps.</p>
        <p>BUT there can also be no doubt that ''The Lady in the Van'' is an entertainment and, with Dame Maggie gawkily stalking the stage, a consistently enjoyable one. Here is a woman who can suddenly announce that she has seen Nikita Khrushchev being kidnapped in a nearby street, or wonder if the toad that has wandered into the van has fallen in love with one of the slugs inside, or decide that she will form her own political party, move her van to Downing Street and hold Cabinet meetings inside it.</p>
        <p>Again and again I found myself comparing her with Joe Orton's dramatic characters or with his relatives as he evokes them in his diary. Isn't Orton's mother's remark about her private parts, ''They've come up the size of a football, but I've no complaints, I've been given top-class penicillin,'' somewhat akin to Miss Shepherd's boast to a social worker, ''I can bathe myself, I've won awards for that''?</p>
        <p>There is the unconsciously hilarious voice of pretend-posh English suburbia -- yet, as Mr. Bennett eventually discovered, there was more to Miss Shepherd than that. She had been a novice nun who suffered a nervous breakdown, in his view because her superior frustrated her creative gift, which was playing the piano. And there are moments in the play, just a few of them, when Dame Maggie talks quietly, sanely and touchingly to herself, obliquely revealing her longings and frustration.</p>
        <p>She and her author leave you wondering, not just about our moral duty to life's losers, but about the stories behind the wild-eyed men lurching down the street, the women muttering to themselves as they push overstuffed shopping carts down Eighth Avenue or London's Waterloo Road.</p>
        <p>'Battle Royal'</p>
        <p>Poor demented George III is never seen in Nick Stafford's ''Battle Royal,'' but he is a formidable offstage presence in 1795, when the play opens, and has just died in 1820, when it ends. The subject is his son, and, specifically, his son's marriage. Think of Britain's present Prince of Wales and the late Princess Diana, a relationship that is surely at the back of Mr. Stafford's own mind. Recall Henry VIII and the wives he divorced or executed. Remember King Leontes's persecution of Queen Hermione in Shakespeare's ''Winter's Tale'' -- and, no, you still haven't caught the sheer awfulness of the future George IV's marriage to Caroline of Brunswick.</p>
        <p>But at least this royal war provides a nice role for Simon Russell Beale and a still meatier one for Zoe Wanamaker. From the first meeting that opens the play you can see how mismatched they are. Miss Wanamaker's hyperactive Caroline flutters, whirls and prances round the stage in her petticoat before goofily falling to the floor, from where she is politely rescued by footmen and crammed into a dress by maids. Enter Mr. Russell Beale's George, his wincingly fastidious manner and preposterous perm putting one in mind of an overbred Pekinese with a starring role in some celestial dog show. One sniff at his wife to be, who is given to swallowing the toilet water supposed to disguise her rank body odor -- and he exits with a strangulated mumble of ''I am not well.''</p>
        <p>The prince created by Alan Bennett in ''The Madness of George III'' was spoiled and selfish enough; but at least he boozed and plotted on the play's periphery. Here, he is seen cruelly snubbing his well-meaning if gauche bride, blaming her for the stories of his neglect that appear in the papers, banishing her to the edge of London, depriving her of the daughter he somehow managed to father and, after she has returned from self-imposed exile in Italy, unsuccessfully putting her on trial for adultery and banning her from his coronation in Westminster Abbey. Since George was a known lecher as well as a suspected bigamist -- and had in fact previously made a clandestine marriage to a widow: Mrs. Fitzherbert -- his hypocrisy did not endear him to all his future subjects.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Bennett in ''The Madness of George III,'' Mr. Stafford spends a lot of time chronicling the political fallout from regal disaster. With the Tories unwillingly backing George, the opposition Whigs supporting Caroline, and revolutionary events in France in everybody's minds, the situation seems perilously volatile. ''Queen's men'' start attacking ''King's men'' in the London streets, and, when Caroline is refused entrance to the Abbey, civil war seems conceivable.</p>
        <p>But history presents Mr. Stafford with dramatic problems he never quite solves. First, the narrative gets diffuse, scattered, only sporadically tense. Then, George is so relentlessly obnoxious that you end up feeling that only in the literal, bodily sense is he a rounded character.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russell Beale does what he can about this, suggesting a certain insecurity behind the posturing and even finding a touch of pathos in George's devotion to Suzanne Burden's chillingly exquisite Mrs. Fitzherbert. But what mainly justifies Howard Davies's production is its portrait of Caroline. That fine actress, Zoe Wanamaker, is coarse, brassy, a bit infantile when it comes to throwing a goofy tantrum. Yet there is vulnerability, warmth and a certain shrewdness behind the noise. Her Caroline is a high-born hausfrau floundering in the mannered English court, a peasant aristocrat who would have made a good wife for Farmer George, as the downright George III was nicknamed, but was always too earthy for his son.</p>
        <p>'A Midsummer Night's Dream'</p>
        <p>A troubled royal marriage is, of course, also at the center of ''A Midsummer Night's Dream.'' The king of the fairies punishes his queen by ensuring that she falls for an Athenian weaver who has been partly transformed into an ass. Not all productions nowadays give the impression that a lady in taffeta is conducting a platonic amour with a somewhat fibrous guest in a bosky dell, where tiny, winged servants trill tunes by Mendelssohn. Yet even Peter Brook's famous rethink of the play in 1970, with its circus tightropes and trapezes, undeniably lacked sex: which was surprising because Jan Kott, the critic whose ''Shakespeare Our Contemporary'' shaped Mr. Brook's production of ''King Lear,'' is particularly persuasive when he writes that nowhere else is ''eroticism expressed so brutally.''</p>
        <p>As New Yorkers will discover when his production comes to the Brooklyn Academy of Music in May, Michael Boyd has substituted eroticism and brutality for the blandness that still marks revivals of ''Midsummer.'' Indeed, when this version was first staged at Stratford last spring, some schoolteachers reportedly marched their younger charges out at the intermission. The sight of Josette Simon's Titania twisting and writhing and winding her bare legs round Daniel Evans's hee-hawing Bottom, and the two of them energetically copulating as their bed rose to the flies, was clearly for adults only.</p>
        <p>SINCE Ms. Simon begins the play as an aloof Hippolyta, and Nicholas Jones plays a dignified Theseus before he, too, is transformed into a royal sprite, there is a point to all this. She and he are about be married and ascend the throne of Athens, and Athens is a place where order and reason prevail. But beneath the respectable veneer there are repressed forces that burst out in what may be seen as a cathartic fantasy or healing dream. The forest outside Athens is where the id replaces the superego, rampaging about in the form of Ms. Simon's gorgeously sensual Titania, Mr. Jones's knowing Oberon, and human lovers who end up looking like tag-team wrestlers in a mud-filled ring.</p>
        <p>Even Theseus's major-domo, at first a bowler-hatted, black-suited blend of mortician and Kafka clerk, is transformed into a bare-chested Puck who announces himself by ripping the clothes off the wildest of Titania's attendant punks.</p>
        <p>No, this isn't fairyland as Disney would present it. But it is a refreshingly bold, imaginative piece of dramatic restoration, and one that ends with purpose and punch. All Athens clatters about in a dance whose energy suggests that ids have been reconciled with superegos -- and the human wholeness everyone craves has at least temporarily been achieved.</p>
        <p>THEATER Benedict Nightingale is the chief theater critic of The Times of London.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Benedict Nightingale is the chief theater critic of The Times of London.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
