<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From/Dobbs Ferry; Down Memory Lane at Family-Run Spot for Dining and Bowling</title>
    <meta content="02VIEW$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bowling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dobbs Ferry (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scappy's Harmony Inn (Dobbs Ferry, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reisler, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2DA1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From/Dobbs Ferry; Down Memory Lane at Family-Run Spot for Dining and Bowling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM REISLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reisler, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>DOBBS FERRY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Scappy's Harmony Inn in Dobbs Ferry, New York; 60-year-old restaurant with bowling alleys in back is 1950's time warp beloved by local customers; photo of four Scaperrotta brothers, who are selling business with stipulation that it not be radically remodeled (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN some longtime customers discovered that Scappy's Harmony Inn here was for sale two years ago, they grabbed some of the framed photographs lining the paneled hallway of this quirky Ashford Avenue landmark.</p>
        <p>The pictures showed the customers at wedding receptions, showers, graduation parties and anniversaries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN some longtime customers discovered that Scappy's Harmony Inn here was for sale two years ago, they grabbed some of the framed photographs lining the paneled hallway of this quirky Ashford Avenue landmark.</p>
        <p>The pictures showed the customers at wedding receptions, showers, graduation parties and anniversaries.</p>
        <p>The Scaperrotta family, which owned the combination restaurant and bowling alley through its 60-year history, actually had to nail a few of the remaining vintage photographs to the wall. It stopped the thievery but did not cloud memories.</p>
        <p>It appears that customers will not have to worry after all. While Scappy's is indeed for sale, the family says it is close to working out a sale with a stipulation that the restaurant not be radically remodeled. And should the sale go as planned and the tentative owners stick to the agreement, all those photographs, the three dining rooms and, yes, the 1950's bowling alleys in the back, which have been the site of generations of children's parties and have helped give the place its time-honored, down home feel, will endure.</p>
        <p>''It's like that old saying, 'If it ain't broke, don't fix it,'' said Robert Scaperrotta, one of four brothers who run the restaurant founded by their father, Christoph. ''A lot of our longtime customers said they hoped the place would stay the same. We listened.''</p>
        <p>They have been listening for quite some time. ''It has been like a family meeting place, a community center where people come in to have dinner and go downstairs and bowl,'' Robert Scaperrotta, 63, the youngest of the brothers, said of the restaurant, which opened in 1939 at the end of the Depression.</p>
        <p>With luck, the solid support of customers and some gentle lobbying on the side, the Scaperrottas are working to preserve the restaurant's well-known, slightly tatty ambience, which one patron likens to ''Cheers before the TV show.'' There have been rumors, family members and customers say, that Scappy's is about to become a sports bar or a catering hall. But the rumors appear to be false.</p>
        <p>''If I were buying the place, I would want to keep it the way it is,'' said Edward Scaperrotta, 68, another brother, who is  known as Uncle Eddie. ''They should try it out first, see how it goes, and if they have to renovate, do it a little bit at a time. They shouldn't close on our old customers. From an emotional and practical point of view, I see no reason to change.''</p>
        <p>So what is it that gives Scappy's its distinctive air?</p>
        <p>There is the Italian food and the children's birthday parties, which became popular after automated bowling lanes were built at the place in 1956. Twenty years ago, the Scaperrottas put in bumper bowling, endearing the place to a whole new generation of youngsters.</p>
        <p>Walking into Scappy's is like entering a time warp; one can almost expect to see a beehive hairdo and hear Vic Damone crooning from the sound system. Add the element of customer service, which Edward Scaperrotta said he learned from his late father. ''We watched the way our dad did it,'' he said, ''and followed his lead.''</p>
        <p>A longtime customer, Steve Hamborsky, said he sometimes drives by Scappy's and if he recognizes the cars of friends, he stops in. ''There's almost always somebody there I know,'' said Mr. Hamborsky, a lifelong Dobbs Ferry resident. ''It's a comfortable place, where you can sit down and see your friends. It's so relaxed.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, dinner at Scappy's can often take an entire evening. ''You can stay as long as you want here,'' Edward Scaperrotta said. ''That means coming in to eat, bowl and relax and not having to worry about getting kicked out because somebody needs the table.''</p>
        <p>Then there are those rows and rows of photographs from parties of all shapes and sizes over the years. A scan of the walls  reveals an informal insight into the social history of Dobbs Ferry and the nearby villages of Hastings-on-Hudson, Irvington and Tarrytown. One photograph shows the Irvington Kiwanis Club of Nov. 16, 1953; elsewhere are framed pictures of a bridal show for Rose Bucci on Jan. 19, 1956, the Beacon Hill bowling dinner of May 16, 1956, and Mr. C. Haslett's office party on Nov. 22, 1953.</p>
        <p>Look closely enough and you will see a few pictures of Donald Marra, a longtime resident and the Dobbs Ferry mayor from 1989 to 1997. His uncle, Peter DiChiara, formerly of Hastings, had his wedding reception at Scappy's in the late 50's, a photograph of which remains on a wall at the restaurant.</p>
        <p>On any given night, Mr. Marra said he can wander over to the photograph, which has no caption, and identify the people in it, and with it, a little piece of county history.</p>
        <p>''Scappy's has been an important part of the community for years,'' said Mr. Marra, assistant superintendent and head of facilities in the Irvington Union Free School District. ''There are all kinds of reasons, from the parties to the food to the hospitality. I like to think that it epitomizes this area, a family-oriented, friendly place.''</p>
        <p>That was the kind of place Christoph Scaperrotta envisioned when he arrived on his honeymoon in 1921 from Ariano Irpiro, Italy, near Naples, to visit his parents, Dominick and Agata, who had come to Dobbs Ferry in 1918. A machinist and auto mechanic by trade and a ''people person'' by nature, he was ''tired of seeing his hands blackened,'' his son, Edward Scaperrotta, said.</p>
        <p>So, he decided to enter the restaurant business. He opened his first establishment, Main Street Grill, at 28 Main Street here, where his wife, Anna, did the cooking. Then came another restaurant, Grandy's, also on Main Street, before Christoph Scaperrotta moved his establishment west of the main shopping district to Ashford Avenue, an area then known as New Village.</p>
        <p>The name of Scappy's predecessor is lost to history. The restaurant had a potbellied stove, a bar, a dining room and two bowling alleys. Christoph Scaperrotta chose to call the place the Harmony Inn, because ''everybody who came in blended together, sang and had a good time,'' Edward Scaperrotta said.</p>
        <p>Along came nine sons, five of whom survived to run the business. Each one -- Edward, Robert, Dominick, Christopher and John -- graduated from Dobbs Ferry High School and worked in the restaurant from an early age. They did everything from setting pins in the bowling alley to cooking, washing dishes and, when they grew old enough, tending bar. Dominick Scaperrotta  died six years ago; today, the rest live either in Dobbs Ferry or Ardsley.</p>
        <p>Just beyond the bar hang portraits of Christoph and Anna Scaperrotta, which were 1953 Christmas presents from their family. Edward Scaperrotta expects to take them home sometime after the sale of the restaurant goes through.</p>
        <p>But he and his family hope to see the rest of the place preserved. ''It's important to us and to the community,'' said Joanne Saporta of Mount Kisco, Christopher Scaperrotta's daughter and a weekend waitress at Scappy's. ''There's a lot of loyalty to this place.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
