<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE YEAR 2000: Speeches, Star Power and a Whole Lot of Noise Ring In the New; Small-Town Warmth On a Cold Maine Day</title>
    <meta content="02MAIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4DD1138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE YEAR 2000: Speeches, Star Power and a Whole Lot of Noise Ring In the New; Small-Town Warmth On a Cold Maine Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREY GOLDBERG</byline>
      <dateline>LUBEC, Me, Jan. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It feels a bit silly to report that, yes indeed, the sun came up here today.</p>
        <p>But this was no ordinary dawn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It feels a bit silly to report that, yes indeed, the sun came up here today.</p>
        <p>But this was no ordinary dawn.</p>
        <p>Set on the easternmost point in the continental United States, the candy-cane-striped lighthouse here at West Quoddy Head attracted nearly 500 people so eager to greet the new year this morning that they wanted to be sure to catch the first rays of its first American day.</p>
        <p>And catch them they did, though a little later than planned.</p>
        <p>Lubec's claim to the millennium's first light had been based on expectations that the sun would rise here at just after 7:04 a.m., theoretically beating out by milliseconds competitors on Cadillac Mountain in Bar Harbor, Me., and on Nantucket Island in Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>But the sun's upper tip could not be seen flaring above Grand Manan Island on the Bay of Fundy until about 7:09; and plans to compare sunrise moments in real-time with people in Nantucket and Bar Harbor failed because of spotty cell-phone reception. (The U.S. Naval Observatory declared a tie between Lubec and Bar Harbor, while Nantucket claimed the sunrise prize at 7:04:19 a.m.)</p>
        <p>No matter. Nobody seemed to have felt cheated as the rising sun gilded the blue sky, sending a glimmering column of blinding orange reflection straight across the water.</p>
        <p>Paula Tinker of Lubec, who plays the bagpipes, had prepared the crowd for sunrise with a piped rendition of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony until her fingers became too stiff from the cold; and Hovey Hall, a local trumpeter, led the crowd in the National Anthem -- whose line about the ''dawn's early light'' seemed unusually apropos.</p>
        <p>A Navy color guard raised the American flag, which was too frozen to flap in the light breeze, and a Lubec school choir in L. L. Bean-sponsored hats and gloves sang ''Children of Peace.''</p>
        <p>There were even enough fireworks left from earlier this morning to set off a last 100-shot salute in celebration of the sun's appearance.</p>
        <p>On such a morning, in midwinter Maine, ''Who would believe there wouldn't be a bit of wind,'' said Wendell Denbow, a carpenter who was watching his daughter, Brittany, sing in the chorus. ''It's a good sign, a good omen.''</p>
        <p>Marilyn Ness, a member of the town's millennium committee, was similarly thankful that the weather was not foggy, or else the foghorn at the lighthouse would have been bellowing. Some on the committee, she said, had joked about knitting a great stocking to muffle it, just in case.</p>
        <p>She and other residents remained slightly amazed at all the attention accorded to Lubec, a fishing hamlet of about 1,800 that residents candidly describe as usually quite dull.</p>
        <p>''This was a small, hometown celebration geared toward peace and children,'' Ms. Ness said, ''and somehow the media got hold of it, and it just got ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Still, unabashed, Lubec offered New Year's visitors the best of tiny-town charm, from a bonfire at the Frog Pond on Friday night to this morning's free breakfast at the American Legion hall. (Those who ventured as far as the nearest city, Eastport, on Friday night also got to see the Maine version of the Times Square dropping of the ball: A lighted lobster pot was dropped from a crane into the ocean.)</p>
        <p>Cooking on campstoves outside the American Legion hall, volunteers this morning served up blueberry pancakes, blueberry muffins, red flannel hash, eggs, bacon, ham, donuts and more to all comers -- of which there were many, a line of three dozen stretching into the parking lot by 8 a.m.</p>
        <p>Though the breakfast was a New Year's celebration, it also seemed a celebration of small-town warmth.</p>
        <p>''This takes it back to the way it should be -- you don't find communities like this any more,'' said Bill Halligan as he dished out a casserole concoction that he had decided to tell diners was ''cheese sausage toast souffle.''</p>
        <p>''The heck with the football games,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The breakfast was the idea of two Lubec friends, Alan Mead and Herb Phillips. ''We decided we'd do a breakfast,'' Mr. Mead said, ''and I said, 'Let's make it free so everyone will come.' And look at the line we've got!''</p>
        <p>Inserted Mr. Halligan, ''He's always doing something nice.''</p>
        <p>The kettle-drum-sized pan of hash that Mr. Mead was stirring seemed to keep changing back and forth between home fries and hash, depending on what ingredients came his way. What would happen, he was asked, if the food, some donated and some paid for by contributors, ran out?</p>
        <p>''Both grocery stores in town are open today,'' he said, ''so we'll have something.''</p>
        <p>That small-town flavor cheered visitors like Andy Solomon and Shirley Fan, who came from Astoria, Queens, for the celebration. As the sun rose, Mr. Solomon said, ''I was just thinking how incredibly nice everybody is here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
