<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's Doing In; Istanbul</title>
    <meta content="WDISTA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Istanbul (Turkey)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinzer, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">What's Doing In...(times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey/Istanbul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE0DC1E39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's Doing In; Istanbul</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kinzer, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Kinzer article on travel attractions of Istanbul; photos; map (What's Doing in...article) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Istanbul won a little-noticed but possibly historic triumph last month.  When the European Union extended an offer of future membership to Turkey, it was also embracing the Turkish cosmopolitanism for which this city has stood since ancient times.</p>
        <p>Turkey has both European and Asian aspects, but nowhere is it more European than in Istanbul, and Europe's gesture of friendship has sparked a sense of relief and optimism here. Istanbul is happy to bid 1999 goodbye. It began with violent protests over the capture of a Kurdish rebel leader and ended with shattering earthquakes less than 100 miles from the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Istanbul won a little-noticed but possibly historic triumph last month.  When the European Union extended an offer of future membership to Turkey, it was also embracing the Turkish cosmopolitanism for which this city has stood since ancient times.</p>
        <p>Turkey has both European and Asian aspects, but nowhere is it more European than in Istanbul, and Europe's gesture of friendship has sparked a sense of relief and optimism here. Istanbul is happy to bid 1999 goodbye. It began with violent protests over the capture of a Kurdish rebel leader and ended with shattering earthquakes less than 100 miles from the city.</p>
        <p>This year should be better. Bookings are up, and the millennium year will probably bring a surge of visitors who will use Istanbul as a jumping-off point for trips to sites across Turkey that are related to early Christianity. In winter they can expect gray, chilly days mixed with days when a brilliant sun glistens over the Bosporus. They'll also enjoy bargains from innkeepers and others  competing for fewer customers.</p>
        <p>Dozens of guidebooks catalog the splendid palaces, mosques, museums and countless other wonders that evoke the glories of the Roman, Byzantine and Ottoman Empires. But there is another side to Istanbul, one that many visitors miss. Although this is a huge city with more than 12 million residents, it is also a city of neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Until as recently as a half century ago, the city that is now Istanbul was a series of self-enclosed quarters and villages, each with its own identity. As the city gobbled up these places, many of them lost their character. But more than a few retain some distinctive flair; they make wonderful places to explore.</p>
        <p>The core of Istanbul may roughly be divided into four sections, each with its own personality and undiscovered neighborhoods. The oldest is Eminonu, the former Muslim quarter centered around major monuments like the Hagia Sophia, Blue Mosque and Topkapi Palace. Across the Galata Bridge from Eminonu is the city's most vibrant borough, the formerly Christian quarter now known as Beyoglu, much of which is in the midst of an exciting revival.</p>
        <p>North of these areas lie the Bosporus villages to which wealthy Istanbul residents used to decamp in summer. Many of these villages still boast handsome wooden mansions called yalis that overlook the magnificent waterway. The fourth and perhaps least-visited section of Istanbul is the Asian side of the Bosporus, bursting with urban life and dotted with mosques, Ottoman pavilions and other jewels.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>The hottest art show this winter  consists of a single painting, Gentile Bellini's 1480 portrait of Sultan Mehmet the Conqueror, along with a large explanatory display. The picture, fraught with historical and psychological implications for Turks, is on loan from the National Gallery in London. It has become a rallying point for Turks who share Mehmet's passion for things European. It may be seen from 10 a.m. to 7 p.m. daily through Saturday at the Yapi Kredi Art Gallery, 285 Istiklal Caddesi; (90-212) 249-5711.</p>
        <p>Just down the street, the works of 32 contemporary Turkish painters and sculptors are on display 10:30 a.m. to 7 p.m. Tuesday to Saturday through Jan. 22, at the Borusan Art Gallery, 421 Istiklal Caddesi; (90-212) 292-0655.</p>
        <p>The winter musical calendar is full. Among the most unusual events is a concert by Muzaffer Ozdemir, an inventor of instruments, composer, percussionist and master of the stringed instrument known as the baglama. Jan. 20 at the Cemal Resit Rey Concert Hall, Darulbedayi Sokak in Harbiye. Tickets are $2 and $3, at 522,000 liras to the dollar. Information: (90-212) 231-5497, extension 29.</p>
        <p>A generation of remarkably talented classical musicians is coming of age in Turkey. One of the best, the pianist Gulsin Onay, joins the Akbank Chamber Orchestra for works by Britten, Stravinsky and Mozart at the Sabanci Cultural Center in the Levent neighborhood at 7:30 p.m.  Feb. 25; $3.80 to $7.70. (90-212) 252-3500.</p>
        <p>Historical books, prints and calligraphy will be auctioned at 2:30 p.m. on Feb. 6 at the Pera Palas Hotel, 98 Mesrutiyet Caddesi. Among the items offered will be a 1579 color map of Anatolia valued at $1,000, and a three-volume history of the Ottoman Empire written in Latin and containing more than 300 woodcuts, said to be a fine example of early printing, valued at $1,500 or more.  For information call (90-212) 252-8010, fax (90-212) 249-1624. Even if you don't buy, look around the hotel; it's a turn-of-the-century gem.</p>
        <p>Two new nightclubs show how sophisticated Istanbul's music scene has become. One, the AFM Kerem Gorsev Jazz Bar, is at 61 Abdi Ipekci Caddesi, wedged into a neighborhood of trendy cafes and boutiques in Nisantasi, not far from Taksim Square.  It is run by Mr. Gorsev, a gifted jazz pianist whose trio plays from Friday to Jan. 18. A Turkish saxophonist who has made a name in New York, Ilhan Ersahin, heads a quartet Jan. 19 to 28. Cover charge is $11.50 weekdays, $15.30 weekends. Music starts at 11 p.m., reservations advisable; (90-212) 231-3950.</p>
        <p>In Asmalimescit, the artistic quarter, a club called Babylon, at 3 Seyhbender Sokak, (90-212) 292-7367, features top-quality world music from Turkey and abroad. Music from Senegal will be performed Jan. 21 and 22, Berber music from North Africa Feb. 11 to 12, and Cuban music Feb. 25 to 26. Leading Turkish acts include the clarinet-based fusion group Velvele on Jan. 12 and the harpist Sirin Pancaroglu on Jan. 18. Shows start around 9:30 p.m. on weekdays, 11 p.m. on weekends; $7 to $14.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>One of my favorite neighborhoods in Istanbul happens to be Asmalimescit (pronounced ahs-mal-eh-MEZ-jit), a postage-stamp piece of the sprawling Beyoglu borough. It is within walking distance of the district's best-known landmark, the stately Galata Tower, built in 1348 and still an ideal place from which to gaze out over the city. Asmalimescit fell into disrepair when Greeks and Jews who lived there left at midcentury, but is being turned into a vibrant community by some of Turkey's leading artists. It has dozens of galleries and studios, along with cafes, restaurants and funky shops selling antiques, used books, maps and prints, photographs and even artifacts from Ottoman courts. To find it, start on Istiklal Caddesi, a bustling pedestrian drag, turn onto Asmali Mescit Sokak and then onto Sofyali Sokak, the quarter's main street.</p>
        <p>For a taste of what villages along the Bosporus used to look and feel like, try Arnavutkoy, a few miles north of Asmalimescit. On the block facing the water and on the twisting streets up the hill, an array of wooden houses display the eclectic imagination of Ottoman architects.</p>
        <p>On the Asian side of the Bosporus, Uskudar is famous for its mosques, and Kadikoy is a colorful mix of shops, markets and faces. The Asian side is best reached by ferries that leave from docks called Eminonu Iskele and Besiktas Iskele.</p>
        <p>Many visitors overlook the splendid 14th-century frescoes and mosaics at the Church of St. Savior in Chora, now the Kariye Museum, on Kariye Camii Sokak in the Edirnekapi section. This ensemble of Byzantine works, depicting scenes from the Bible and the life of Jesus, is among the world's finest. Open 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. except Wednesday; $2.</p>
        <p>Few tourists miss the Topkapi, but not all realize that Istanbul's Archaeological Museum, which is predictably full of delights, is on the same site. Among its treasures is the magnificent late fourth-century Alexander Sarcophagus, depicting the victory of Alexander the Great over the Persians. It is open daily except Monday, 9:30 a.m. to 4 p.m.; (90-212) 520-7740. Admission $3.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The Merit Antique, 226 Ordu Caddesi, (90-212) 513-9300, fax (90-212) 512-6390, is in the Laleli district of Eminonu, across from the imposing Laleli Mosque. It has 274 modern rooms, a pool and a health club, and may be the only hotel in the world with Chinese, Turkish and kosher  restaurants. Rates: $125.</p>
        <p>Adjacent to the Asmalimescit quarter is the Richmond Hotel, 445 Istiklal Caddesi; (90-212) 252-5460, fax (90-212) 252-9707, with 106 modern rooms and a new restaurant with Bosporus views. Doubles $190.</p>
        <p>Budget: Kybele, 35 Yerebetan Caddesi, (90-212) 511-7766, fax (90-212) 513-4393, close to major sights, is a lovely 16-room inn with rich carpets, framed calligraphy and hanging lamps. Doubles $75.</p>
        <p>Luxury: Of the dozen first-class hotels in Istanbul, the two best-loved are probably the 315-room Ciragan Palace Kempinski, along the Bosporus far from the center, and the Four Seasons, with 65 rooms in the old city by the Hagia Sophia. The Ciragan Palace, 84 Ciragan Caddesi, (90-212) 258-3377, fax (90-212) 259-6686, has rooms with Bosporus views from $360. The Four Seasons, 1 Tevkifhane Sokak, (90-212) 638-8200, fax (90-121) 638-8210, has reduced rates through March, with doubles from $200.</p>
        <p>For a more unusual view of the city from an equally luxurious vantage point, there is the 14-room Bosphorus Pasha on the Asian side at 64 Yaliboyu Caddesi, (90-216) 422-0003, fax (90-216) 422-0012. Rebuilt a few years ago according to plans of the burned-out pasha's residence that had stood there for a century, it is right on the water. On weekdays, doubles cost $175 to $230. On weekends, rates for two nights are $330 to $370, with breakfast or brunch.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>In Asmalimescit, the Refik restaurant, 10 Sofyali Sokak, (90-212) 243-2834, is an institution. The portly white-haired gentleman who sits outside in the summer and just inside the door in winter is Refik himself, the quarter's unofficial mayor. You can feast on small plates of cold vegetables (eggplant and stuffed cabbage are especially popular), then move on to grilled lamb or fish, accompanied by raki, Turkey's potent anise-flavored national drink. Dinner for two with raki, about $42.</p>
        <p>For first-class kebabs and fresh salads, try Tike, at 1 Haci Adil Caddesi in Levent, 4 Aralik in Second Levent, a residential area above the European side of the Bosporus, (90-212) 284-8479. It is a fine grill house built around a garden in a renovated villa. Dinner for two with wine is about $54. Traditional Turkish breakfast, centered on baked flatbreads  with honey, olives and assorted jams, cheeses, salads and cold cuts, is served on Sunday 9 a.m. to 1 p.m.;  $9.50 a person.</p>
        <p>Istanbul is a fish-lover's paradise, and several of its neighborhoods, like Yesilkoy, are known for their concentrations of fine seafood restaurants. The best place in Yesilkoy for both fresh fish and lively atmosphere is Hasan Balikcilar, 8 Rihtim Sokak.  Reservations necessary; call (90-212) 573-8300. Point to the fish you want, or ask your waiter simply to send over what's best that day. Dinner for two with wine or raki is $65.</p>
        <p>Turkish cuisine at bargain prices is the attraction at Tarihi Sultanahmet Koftecisi, at 12A Divanyolu Caddesi, (90-212) 513-1438. It is a small and bustling spot equally favored by blue-collar workers and lawyers working at the nearby courthouse. A family of four can feast on thick soup, koftes (minced and grilled lamb), salad and helva, a sweet dessert made from semolina, for $25.</p>
        <p>For adventurous eaters, Sayan, at Yildiz Posta Caddesi, 46-47 Ayyildiz Sitesi in Esentepe, (90-212) 211-3089,  is open 24 hours a day. Kebabs are on the menu, but why bother with pedestrian fare when you can have cow's stomach soup, sheep's intestines or -- my favorite -- sheep's head soup, complete with head? A meal for two (no alcohol served) is $17.</p>
        <p>STEPHEN KINZER is chief of the Istanbul bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">STEPHEN KINZER is chief of the Istanbul bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
