<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan to Add Diesel Buses Is Criticized; M.T.A. Is Urged to Look At Less-Polluting Option</title>
    <meta content="02BUS.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diesel Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Transportation Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7D61038F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan to Add Diesel Buses Is Criticized; M.T.A. Is Urged to Look At Less-Polluting Option</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmentalists and legislators say Metropolitan Transportation Authority's $17.5 billion plan to put hundreds of diesel-powered buses on New York City streets in next five years would increase smog and health problems; note that Los Angeles and other major cities have barred purchases of diesel buses; MTA would put greater emphasis on speed and capacity by adding faster and larger buses using diesel fuel; is focusing its antipollution efforts on experimental hybrid engine that runs on diesel and electricity; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A plan by the Metropolitan Transportation Authority to put hundreds of new diesel-powered buses on New York City streets in the next five years is drawing determined resistance from environmentalists and legislators, who say it will increase smog and health problems.</p>
        <p>Those critics note that Los Angeles, Cleveland and other major cities have barred purchases of diesel buses and have switched to models that use cleaner-burning compressed natural gas. But the M.T.A.'s $17.5 billion capital plan, announced in September, would put greater emphasis on speed and capacity by adding faster and larger buses using diesel fuel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A plan by the Metropolitan Transportation Authority to put hundreds of new diesel-powered buses on New York City streets in the next five years is drawing determined resistance from environmentalists and legislators, who say it will increase smog and health problems.</p>
        <p>Those critics note that Los Angeles, Cleveland and other major cities have barred purchases of diesel buses and have switched to models that use cleaner-burning compressed natural gas. But the M.T.A.'s $17.5 billion capital plan, announced in September, would put greater emphasis on speed and capacity by adding faster and larger buses using diesel fuel.</p>
        <p>And while the authority does plan to continue buying some natural gas buses, it is focusing its antipollution efforts on an experimental hybrid engine that runs on both diesel and electricity.</p>
        <p>''We haven't put our heads in the sand on this issue,'' said Lawrence G. Reuter, the president of New York City Transit, the M.T.A. subsidiary responsible for subways and buses.</p>
        <p>In an interview on Wednesday, Mr. Reuter said the authority was taking a bold step forward in the technology of mass transportation. Within eight years, he said, it hopes to begin converting the hybrid buses to use fuel cells, a technology that powers buses entirely with rechargeable electric batteries.</p>
        <p>Until now, most of the criticism of the capital spending proposal had focused on whether the authority was thinking big enough about new construction projects like the Second Avenue subway. But with the spending plan entering serious negotiations in Albany, where it must be approved by the Legislature and Gov. George E. Pataki, attention has shifted to the proposal to buy 1,056 new buses. The authority says more than 70 percent of them will be powered at least in part by diesel fuel.</p>
        <p>The critics say the M.T.A. should move more rapidly to reduce diesel emissions, which have been linked to asthma and other respiratory illnesses. In New York City,  studies have shown the asthma rate to be three times the national average. Natural gas provides the only proven low-pollution alternative to diesel, the critics say.</p>
        <p>''We know that converting the fleet to natural gas is a big, tough task, but we are hopeful that the M.T.A. will find a way to do it,'' said Richard Kassel, a senior lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council. Mr. Kassel met with senior transit officials last week to make the case for natural gas.</p>
        <p>The transportation authority may face a more powerful opponent in Sheldon Silver, the Assembly speaker, who is one of four members of a state panel that oversees the agency. The authority needs the panel's unanimous approval to put the five-year plan in place. Other members include representatives of the Senate, Governor Pataki and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver, who represents Manhattan's Lower East Side, has reserved his strongest objections for the failure to plan on an extension of the Second Avenue subway to Lower Manhattan. But he has also sharply criticized the authority's plan to buy diesel buses.</p>
        <p>''It just doesn't make sense,'' Mr. Silver said on Wednesday, adding that he would use his veto power if the authority did not reduce its reliance on diesel. ''Buying dirty buses is counterproductive to the overall goal of improving air quality.''</p>
        <p>The M.T.A. plan would spend $800 million on the 1,056 new buses, including 300 standard-size 44-seat buses. Although the authority has said all the new standard-size buses will be fuel efficient, it said that how many would be diesel-electric hybrids and how many would use natural gas had not been decided.</p>
        <p>About a third of the new buses -- 356 in all -- would be express coaches serving commuters to Manhattan. Those models, similar in design to long-distance buses, would use standard diesel engines.</p>
        <p>And along congested, heavily used routes, the authority wants to add 400  ''articulated'' buses -- oversize vehicles that bend in the middle vaguely like an accordion. They are 50 percent larger than standard buses and use diesel engines.</p>
        <p>By 2005, with these purchases and with the retirement of older buses, the current fleet of 4,300 will have been reduced to 3,900 buses, but it will include faster and bigger ones that can carry more passengers.</p>
        <p>Christopher P. Boylan, the authority's deputy executive director, said diesel engines were the only proven technology available to power the new express coaches and articulated buses. Even so, Mr. Boylan said, the faster and bigger buses will reduce pollution, both because newer diesel engines will emit less pollution and because bigger and faster buses will increase the efficiency of the transit system.</p>
        <p>By carrying more riders greater distances, he said, more people will be encouraged to ride buses, which will in turn reduce traffic and pollution.</p>
        <p>But advocates for riders and environmental groups contend that the health risks of diesel emissions outweigh the gains in efficiency. A series of medical studies across the country by such groups as the California Scientific Review Panel and the American Journal of Public Health have established a direct link between diesel emissions and respiratory ailments.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta and others have documented a sharp rise in asthma and other respiratory diseases in New York City and other urban areas. Recent studies by New York State's Department of Environmental Conservation have shown particularly high levels of soot from diesel exhaust in Midtown Manhattan and other congested city neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Although the chief cause of such pollution is diesel truck traffic, critics of the transportation authority argue that it should lead the way in reducing air pollution.</p>
        <p>Gene Russianoff, a staff lawyer for the Straphangers Campaign, an advocacy group for riders, said passengers would be served just as effectively by more standard-size natural gas buses on the same routes where the M.T.A. plans to use the larger articulated models.</p>
        <p>And despite the authority's assertion that the express coaches must use diesel, other critics note that New Jersey Transit early this year began using 50 express models, similar to the ones sought by the authority but slightly smaller, that run on compressed natural gas. They are made in Illinois.</p>
        <p>The M.T.A. does plan to buy some natural gas models for its standard buses, but the authority appears to be betting heavily on the hybrid electric-diesel engine, which is being developed in a consortium with the Lockheed Martin Corporation. The system is powered by a small diesel engine that constantly charges an electric generator, producing levels of air pollution that Mr. Boylan said were as low as or lower than compressed natural gas.</p>
        <p>After experimenting with 10 of the hybrid electric vehicles for a year, the authority made its first major commitment to the technology in December when it ordered 125 of them, even without the financing sought in its five-year plan. Mr. Reuter of New York City Transit said the hybrid buses had been purchased without competitive bidding because only one company manufactures them.</p>
        <p>The company, the Control Systems division of Lockheed Martin, based in Johnson City, N.Y., has developed the engine over 10 years, with a combination of $10.4 million in grants and low-interest loans from the New York Power Authority and the state's Energy Research and Development Authority. The hybrid engines are installed in buses produced by two other New York companies, Orion Bus Industries of Oriskany and Nova Bus of Schenectady.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boylan said the authority was also concerned about high costs associated with compressed natural gas. The city's bus depots must be renovated to handle the gas under extremely high pressure, he said, and the natural gas buses in the fleet break down more frequently than the diesel buses.</p>
        <p>The hybrid buses would not require any expensive changes to the depots and could be deployed more quickly at a time when ridership is increasing rapidly, he said.</p>
        <p>But the M.T.A.'s critics say the authority is making a major commitment to a technology that remains experimental, while neglecting to upgrade its depots to prepare for one that is already widely available.</p>
        <p>''The M.T.A. already has a track record of delay and evasion in moving into a compressed natural gas technology that has been proven around the country,'' Mr. Russianoff said. He said the hybrid buses ''simply may not work, and we will find ourselves five years later incurring the expense of a technology they don't like.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Russianoff and other advocates of buses using compressed natural gas say the authority should move much more aggressively in renovating the depots to handle the high-pressure fueling systems required.</p>
        <p>Of the 22 depots, only one has been equipped to serve the authority's 89 natural gas buses.</p>
        <p>Those buses were sidelined for most of this month, M.T.A. officials said, after a series of small explosions forced that depot, in Sunset Park, Brooklyn, to shut down in late November. Three transit workers were injured and hospitalized, and two of them may have suffered permanent hearing loss, Mr. Reuter said. The depot reopened on Dec. 25.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
