<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived: Gorilla Monsoon, b. 1937; When Wrestling Was Noir</title>
    <meta content="MB103809" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hajdu, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gorilla Monsoon (Robert Marella) (1937-1999)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0D91F39F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived: Gorilla Monsoon, b. 1937; When Wrestling Was Noir</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Hajdu</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hajdu, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Hajdu artic</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first time I saw the face of Evil, I was 8 or 9. It was a little after midnight, and I had sneaked out of the bedroom and felt my way into the basement, where my father kept an old black-and-white TV with a cracked wooden cabinet in his workshop. I clicked it on in the dark and froze in terror at a sight I had never seen upstairs before bedtime: a human monster, repulsive in a one-piece bodysuit, twirling a man over his head, cackling demonically. He was Gorilla Monsoon, the announcer said with a suitable tremor, and for some time I thought he existed only on a broken TV in the basement at night.</p>
        <p>I wasn't far off. In Monsoon's prime during the mid-1960's, professional wrestling was a dark and filthy, crooked, seedy, low-budget venture on the fringe of mainstream entertainment. Many bouts were staged for several hundred fans (and often fewer) in V.F.W. halls and high-school gyms, and even those that were televised could be seen only once a week after prime time on low-wattage independent stations. In his two-decade career, Gorilla Monsoon fought some 8,000 bouts. He was, like the dime-store novelist Jim Thompson or the crime photographer Weegee, a master practitioner in a disreputable American pulp milieu; he occupied the same world of lowlifes, transients and grifters; and his performances provided a similar kind of raw and harrowing thrill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first time I saw the face of Evil, I was 8 or 9. It was a little after midnight, and I had sneaked out of the bedroom and felt my way into the basement, where my father kept an old black-and-white TV with a cracked wooden cabinet in his workshop. I clicked it on in the dark and froze in terror at a sight I had never seen upstairs before bedtime: a human monster, repulsive in a one-piece bodysuit, twirling a man over his head, cackling demonically. He was Gorilla Monsoon, the announcer said with a suitable tremor, and for some time I thought he existed only on a broken TV in the basement at night.</p>
        <p>I wasn't far off. In Monsoon's prime during the mid-1960's, professional wrestling was a dark and filthy, crooked, seedy, low-budget venture on the fringe of mainstream entertainment. Many bouts were staged for several hundred fans (and often fewer) in V.F.W. halls and high-school gyms, and even those that were televised could be seen only once a week after prime time on low-wattage independent stations. In his two-decade career, Gorilla Monsoon fought some 8,000 bouts. He was, like the dime-store novelist Jim Thompson or the crime photographer Weegee, a master practitioner in a disreputable American pulp milieu; he occupied the same world of lowlifes, transients and grifters; and his performances provided a similar kind of raw and harrowing thrill.</p>
        <p>At a time when professional-wrestling events were measured by the bulk of their participants (''10 exhibitions involving weights totaling 4,871 pounds''), Gorilla Monsoon, weighing in at 401, was duly revered as ''heaviest of all.'' He virtually created and best embodied the role of ''the heel,'' the bad guy in the ritual morality drama that wrestling became during his era. It was just a role, of course; college-educated and a onetime high-school teacher, the private Robert Marella remained an articulate and demurely mannered gentleman. When he spoke about his profession, he did so with reverence and none of the gutter bravura of its more recent practitioners. ''For those who believe in our sport, no explanation is necessary,'' Monsoon said. ''For those who disbelieve, no explanation is satisfactory.'' Not quite St. Augustine, but the same line of reasoning.</p>
        <p>The only time I met him, at an event in a Midtown Manhattan steakhouse about 10 years ago, I asked him what he thought of the transformation pro wrestling had undergone since he left the ring in the early 80's. Reinvented for a generation of kids with cable TV and video games in their bedrooms, the World Wrestling Federation and its imitators ballooned, steroid-style, into a glitzy jillion-dollar industry. ''It's comic books,'' he said matter-of-factly.</p>
        <p>But what was wrestling in his day, I asked -- literature? ''I don't know,'' he responded softly. ''But we were more serious. People really thought I was the Devil incarnate. Now it's all a joke.''</p>
        <p>Without getting too sentimental about Evil, I think he had a point.</p>
        <p>David Hajdu is writing a book about American folk music in the 1960's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Hajdu is writing a book about American folk music in the 1960's.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
