<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Annals of Y2K: Ants and Grasshoppers</title>
    <meta content="LTR145441" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stockpiling</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gomez, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stockpiling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2D81538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Annals of Y2K: Ants and Grasshoppers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lynne Gomez letter, commenting on December 19 article on arrival of new millennium, says stockpiling to avoid possible problems from Y2k computer bug is idea with some merit (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Well, it was bound to happen.</p>
        <p>I just broke into my Y2K survival stash (''Tiptoeing Into the Millennium,'' Dec. 19). The kids had friends over for lunch and the remaining can of tuna on the shelf was not going to stretch far enough.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Well, it was bound to happen.</p>
        <p>I just broke into my Y2K survival stash (''Tiptoeing Into the Millennium,'' Dec. 19). The kids had friends over for lunch and the remaining can of tuna on the shelf was not going to stretch far enough.</p>
        <p>I was a simple thing, breaking into my millennium rations cabinet in the basement. So far I'd only managed to tuck away four cans of Bumble Bee tuna, two cans of mushroom soup and a bag of egg noodles in a shoe box. Enough to keep us in tuna casserole until Jan. 3, I suppose.</p>
        <p>Actually, I don't know anyone who admits to stockpiling for the millennium, although it's an idea with some merit. When I look outside at the frazzled ground, I know I'd be hard-pressed to live off the land if I had to. Of course I'm hoping that the millennium sneaks by without much of a blip on anyone's screen. I'm hoping our terminally swollen supermarkets will be open for business as usual and that sweet money flows from the A.T.M.'s as freely as ever come Jan. 1. Even so, I wish I had a little stash of turnips in the cellar. So why not stockpile? There are still some unclaimed corners in our basement. It would be easy. I've often thought of going to one of those big wholesale chains and casually buying up a couple of shopping carts full of canned chili. Or maybe some of those industrial strength Chef Boy-Ar-Dee products.</p>
        <p>But I'm afraid that kind of buying would lead me to a personal panic of what if's. What if it's not enough? What if I'm the only one in the neighborhood stockpiling? What if I have to make Sophie-like choices? What if nothing happens? What if no one wants to eat $75 worth of canned chili?</p>
        <p>I think of the ant and grasshopper tales from my youth. You remember, the industrious ants and the fly-by-night grasshoppers. If I were an ant, I'd be categorizing, labeling and cross referencing my basement stockpiles right now.</p>
        <p>But since I probably won't even get around to replacing my missing can of tuna, I guess I'm no ant. More like a lazy grasshopper.</p>
        <p>I see myself spending the next few days of the old millennium leaning back in the fading sun, legs crossed at the knee, chewing on some grass and wearing a big old at-peace-with-the-world grin.</p>
        <p>And certainly not thinking about tuna casserole.</p>
        <p>LYNNE GOMEZ  Sherman</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
