<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Immigrant's View, the Art of Trash, a Phantom's Lair: All Between Covers in 1999</title>
    <meta content="02BOOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165432"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK BOOKSHELF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccourt, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strasser, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forsyth, Frederick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Katharine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcbain, Ed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robins, Madeleine E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tis (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Waste and Want (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Phantom of Manhattan, the (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Music Lesson, the (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Big Bad City, the (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Stone War, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E3DB1538F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1218" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Immigrant's View, the Art of Trash, a Phantom's Lair: All Between Covers in 1999</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from six books published in 1999 in which New York City figures large; they are Frank McCourt's 'Tis, Susan Strasser's Waste and Want, Frederick Forsyth's The Phantom of Manhattan, Katharine Weber's The Music Lesson, Ed McBain's The Big Bad City and Madeleine E Robins's The Stone War; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'TIS  By Frank McCourt  Scribner  (Hardcover, $26)</p>
        <p>The first officer told me Albany was a city far up the Hudson River, capital of New York State. He said Albany had all the charm of Limerick, ha ha ha, a great place to die but not a place where you'd want to get married or rear children. He was from Dublin and knew I was from Limerick and when he sneered at Limerick I didn't know what to do. I'd like to destroy him with a smart remark but then I'd look at myself in the mirror, pimply face, sore eyes, and bad teeth and know I could never stand up to anyone, especially a first officer with a uniform and a promising future as master of his own ship. Then I'd say to myself, Why should I care what anyone says about Limerick anyway? All I had there was misery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'TIS  By Frank McCourt  Scribner  (Hardcover, $26)</p>
        <p>The first officer told me Albany was a city far up the Hudson River, capital of New York State. He said Albany had all the charm of Limerick, ha ha ha, a great place to die but not a place where you'd want to get married or rear children. He was from Dublin and knew I was from Limerick and when he sneered at Limerick I didn't know what to do. I'd like to destroy him with a smart remark but then I'd look at myself in the mirror, pimply face, sore eyes, and bad teeth and know I could never stand up to anyone, especially a first officer with a uniform and a promising future as master of his own ship. Then I'd say to myself, Why should I care what anyone says about Limerick anyway? All I had there was misery.</p>
        <p>Then the peculiar thing would happen. I'd sit on a deck chair in the lovely October sun with the gorgeous blue Atlantic all around me and try to imagine what New York would be like. I'd try to see Fifth Avenue or Central Park or Greenwich Village where everyone looked like movie stars, powerful tans, gleaming white teeth. But Limerick would push me into the past. Instead of me sauntering up Fifth Avenue with the tan, the teeth, I'd be back in the lanes of Limerick, women standing at doors chatting away and pulling their shawls around their shoulders, children with faces dirty from bread and jam, playing and laughing and crying to their mothers.</p>
        <p>WASTE AND WANT: A SOCIAL HISTORY OF TRASH  By Susan Strasser  Metropolitan Books  (Hardcover, $27.50)</p>
        <p>Artists employed found materials to make statements specifically about the environment and about the connections between trash and consumerism. Jac Leirner, a Brazilian artist, used airplane boarding passes and plastic shopping bags from museum shops around the world. ''Can Man,'' a New York Performance artist named Gene Pool, rode up to public places on his unicycle, wearing a suit made of five hundred aluminum cans. Mierle Laderman Ukeles, the unsalaried artist-in-residence of New York's Department of Sanitation, constructed ''Ceremonial Arch Honoring Service Workers in the New Service Economy'' from the castoffs of the city's public sevice agencies, including gauges from the Fresh Kills landfill, mailbags, police walkie-talkies, street cleaning brushes, and hundreds of used gloves. Trash was Ukeles's topic as well as her medium; her other pieces included ''Touch Sanitation'' (1979-80), an eleven-month performance in which she shook hands with all eighty-five hundred of the city's sanitation workers, and ''The Social Mirror'' (1983), a sanitation truck resurfaced in mirrors.</p>
        <p>THE PHANTOM OF MANTHATTAN  By Frederick Forsyth  St. Martin's Press  (Hardcover, $30)</p>
        <p>Every day, summer or winter, rain or shine, I rise early. I dress and come up from my quarters to this small square rooftop terrace atop the pinnacle of the highest skyscraper in all New York. From here, depending upon which side of the square I stand, I can look west across the Hudson River toward the open green lands of New Jersey. Or north towards the midtown and uptown sections of this amazing island so full of wealth and filth, extravagance and poverty, vice and crime. Or south towards the open sea, which leads back to Europe and the bitter road I have traveled. Or east across the river to Brooklyn and, lost in the sea mist, the lunatic enclave called Coney Island, the original source of my wealth.</p>
        <p>And, I, who spent seven years terrorized by a brutish father, nine an animal chained in a cage, eleven an outcast in the cellars below the Paris Opera and ten fighting my way up from the fish-gutting sheds of Gravesend Bay to this eminence, know that I now have wealth and power beyond the dreams of Croesus. So I look down on this sprawling city and I think: how I hate and despise you, Human Race.</p>
        <p>THE MUSIC LESSON  By Katharine Weber  Crown Publishers  (Hardcover, $21; paperback, $12)</p>
        <p>Mickey had told me that he had grown up in the village of Rosscarbery, in County Cork, before leaving to attend Trinity College in Dublin -- the first family member to do so, he said with pride -- and he seemed pleased that my automatic response was to identify Rosscarbery as the birthplace of O'Donovan Rossa and Michael Collins.</p>
        <p>''You've been home, of course?''</p>
        <p>''Never.''</p>
        <p>''A sin you'll soon have to rectify,'' Mickey said merrily as he held the door to E.A.T. open for me. Two girls of about twelve in Nightingale-Bamford uniforms ducked under his arm as if they owned the world, and Mickey caught my eye and we grinned at each other over their heads before we went inside.</p>
        <p>That sort of moment is rarely easy for me. Katie would be eight now.  Would she be reading the ''Little House'' books? Rollerblading? Agitating for pierced ears? She had just started piano lessons.</p>
        <p>THE BIG BAD CITY: A NOVEL OF THE 87TH PRECINCT  By Ed McBain  Pocket Books  (Hardcover, $25; Paperback, $6.99)</p>
        <p>Monoghan said nothing. He followed his partner off, two black suits disappearing into the blackness of the night. The ME sighed, snapped his bag shut, and stood up. ''I'm done here,'' he said. ''She's yours.''</p>
        <p>''Okay to remove the wedding band?'' Carella asked.</p>
        <p>''She's no child bride,'' the ME said, as if Monroe's earlier remark had just registered. ''Maybe twenty-two, twenty-three.''</p>
        <p>''Okay?'' Carella asked again.</p>
        <p>''Sure, go right ahead.''</p>
        <p>''Tell the paramedics I'll need a few minutes.''</p>
        <p>''Take your time,'' the ME said, and walked toward where a man and a woman in hospital gear were leaning against the ambulance. There was the incessant chatter of invisible insects on the soft night air. Carella knelt beside the dead girl.</p>
        <p>Rings were often difficult to remove in the summertime, but this one came off with very little effort.  He held it up to the light. There were three initials engraved inside the band: IHS.</p>
        <p>''She's a nun,'' he almost whispered.</p>
        <p>THE STONE WAR  By Madeleine E. Robins  Tor/Tom Doherty Associates  (Hardcover, $23.95)</p>
        <p>Westbound service had been temporarily suspended.</p>
        <p>''What's the fastest way into the city?'' he demanded.</p>
        <p>''To New York?'' The old man was plainly appalled. ''Mister, you don't want to go there. You heard what they're saying on the radio?''</p>
        <p>Tietjen wanted to pick the man up and break him in two. He clenched his hands at his sides and said as levelly as he could. ''Of course I have.  That's why I have to get back. My family is there.''</p>
        <p>The old man shook his head. ''If they're lucky they're getting out, mister. Jeez, I'd say out of it if I was you.''</p>
        <p>''You're not. How do I get back?'' Tietjen's voice was icy.</p>
        <p>The old man looked at Tietjen warily, as if he'd suddenly realized the man he was talking to was dangerous. He leaned back against the wall of the station, considering.  ''You'd have to drive all the way down, I guess, if you got a car, and the highway permits and such. But I head the Guard ain't letting people past White Plains anymore, not till they get word from the city that it's okay. And they got their own hands full with people coming out, now. Better stay here a few days, maybe.  There's a lotta motels out near the college.''</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOOKSHELF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
