<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Twilight Zone</title>
    <meta content="02DIEKMAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dieckmann, Katherine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dark, Alice Elliott</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">In the Gloaming (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EFDB1539F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Twilight Zone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Katherine Dieckmann</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dieckmann, Katherine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Katherine Dieckmann reviews book In the Gloaming. Stories by Alice Elliott Dark; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the Gloaming</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Alice Elliott Dark.</p>
        <p>288 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the Gloaming</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Alice Elliott Dark.</p>
        <p>288 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
        <p>Rarely does a work of fiction arrive in book form well after the movie version has already imprinted a specific interpretation on prospective readers. Such is the strange case with the title story of Alice Elliott Dark's collection ''In the Gloaming.'' After being published in The New Yorker in 1993, this story -- about a preppy son who bonds with his reserved mother after coming home to die from AIDS -- was adapted to film not once but twice, most notably in an HBO production starring Glenn Close that was shown in 1997.</p>
        <p>Now ''In the Gloaming'' anchors a new collection of short stories, Dark's follow-up to ''Naked to the Waist'' (1991), and it's difficult not to hear in the book a tone that's already been firmly established in celluloid: muted, mannerly, controlled. In fact, the HBO movie, directed by Christopher Reeve and set in a world of affluent propriety, of neat lawns and even tidier feelings, perfectly captured the contours of Dark's dominant landscape. By stretching the work to feature length, the film also pointed out the small-scale strengths of her enterprise; little was gained by giving secondary characters more to do and amplifying nuances that worked best by remaining modest.</p>
        <p>Dark is a stubborn miniaturist, an adept of the chamber piece. The story ''In the Gloaming'' -- with its focus on a single relationship and use of twilight as a resonant metaphor for the process of dying -- reveals how Dark's prose delivers particular forms of meaning. How could a movie adequately capture the particular language of this moment, when a mother notices that her son is ''making knitting motions over his chest, the way people did as they were dying''? Dark writes, ''She knew that if she went to get the nurse, Laird would be gone by the time she returned, so she went and stood behind him, leaning over to press her face against his, sliding her hands down his busy arms, helping him along with his fretful stitches until he finished this last piece of work.''</p>
        <p>Such intensities of loss know no boundaries, certainly not of class and decorum, which is part of Dark's point. It takes a gay son dying too soon to puncture the dominant air of restraint; once it is ruptured, grace and honesty acquire new definitions. And yet making a strong connection to the kind of stories Dark tells throughout ''In the Gloaming'' -- stories of entanglements gone wrong, of accidents and miscommunications and dread and loss -- depends on a willingness to enter her microcosm of lily-white privilege, one that's tended and guarded with an implied disdain for the larger, messy world.</p>
        <p>Many of Dark's stories are set in a leafy town called Wynnemoor, a place whose implicit rules and regulations are spoofed gently in a story called ''Watch the Animals,'' which closes Dark's collection as effectively as ''In the Gloaming'' opens it. An eccentric, animal-obsessed woman is dying of cancer, and the anonymous member of the community who narrates the story with an imperious ''we'' notes how their sick friend deviated from the norm: ''We assumed she'd follow the path we all walked: marriage to someone like-minded, a house of her own but similar to her parents', children raised with the traditions that she remembered fondly, all the little habits that connect one generation to the next.'' Clearly Dark wants to point out the limitations of such prescriptions, but she also tacitly approves of them on more than one occasion.</p>
        <p>When her characters step away from Wynnemoor into a less regimented world -- usually New York City or overseas -- they invariably seem lost; they're creatures who lack a workable code to navigate daily life. The withdrawn Manhattan bachelor who narrates ''The Tower'' falls in love with a much younger woman, if only because she breaks the mold of the women his own age to whom he should be joined. But his transgression comes to a grim end when, on a trip to Italy, he discovers he once slept with the girl's mother. In ''The Jungle Lodge,'' two sisters, one in high school and the other in college, take a trip to Peru with their stepfather, and nasty secrets are uncovered, as though coaxed out of hiding by the climate. When a father-to-be visits his childhood home in ''Close,'' it shakes him from his fantasies of divorcing his wife and running off with his mistress. His decidedly unmythic return to his roots only forces him to realize how dismantling a family is a real and often terrible act.</p>
        <p>Dark is trying to probe the intersection of traditional habits and unpredictable contemporary life, but her attempts to shake things up often lead her to overload her stories with florid twists. A woman's lover can't be hit by a car and die unless her father perished in a car crash, too. An episode of rape can be followed only by the implication of incest. A middle-aged man won't run off with a woman who could be his daughter unless it's revealed that he's slept with her mother, too. These calculated shocks begin to strain credulity and rob Dark's tales of their sharper, less melodramatic insights into human nature.</p>
        <p>More jarring still are Dark's attempts to be of-the-moment, which often bump up awkwardly against her characters' fusty dialogue. A knowing reference to Dean &amp; DeLuca, the upscale food market, occurs in the same conversation where a date is referred to as a ''fellow.'' Characters trade formal lines that lack the leavening humor of manners lampooned; you're reminded of the stilted formality of the director Whit Stillman's smugly elitist youths in films like ''Metropolitan,'' minus the droll undertone. Sometimes Dark's ''in'' jokes fall disastrously flat, as in the story ''Close,'' where two men discuss the deadening limitations of marriage and one of them says: ''You'll walk into the house at night and you'll feel like a stranger. Remember that Talking Heads song where he says, 'This is not my beautiful house, this is not my beautiful wife'? Pretty soon that will start making sense!''</p>
        <p>Dark works best when she homes in on a narrow target and hits it dead center, without any attempt at expansiveness. Writing for male characters often brings out the self-conscious strain in Dark's voice, whereas her writing about women moves far more organically. So perhaps it's no surprise that the stories in ''In the Gloaming'' that pierce and linger all have female friction at their core. A daughter's intense dislike for her mother's flamboyant, self-centered best friend drives ''Dreadful Language,'' and in ''Triage,'' a matriarch's narcissistic ramblings on theology mask her refusal to acknowledge her grown daughter's new role as a mother. The daughter sets down the telephone to tend to her infant daughter as her mother continues talking (''Ella's precise words were indistinguishable, nothing more than a murmur, a swarm of bees pestering a growth of peonies''). Then the daughter unleashes an exclamatory four-letter word, which amounts to a rebel yell in Dark's muffled universe.</p>
        <p>Just as memorable is ''Maniacs,'' the tale of two adult sisters who, while in an airport, bump into a man they've both loved and find ancient rivalries reignited. The story begins with a passage of extraordinarily beautiful prose, and never lets up the pressure as it traces old passions and contemporary pains: ''Silent sound, vivid absence, pressure from beyond the quilts and walls, the taste of pennies on the tongue; several miles apart two sisters awoke within moments of each other and instinctively knew it had snowed.'' Who could guess that this tale would end up with a grown woman's daughters flying off to visit the father their mom has divorced, and that same woman burning her diaries in the fireplace? Just as the word ''Maniacs'' provides no real clues to Dark's larger meaning -- too often her titles are thuddingly descriptive -- it's refreshingly difficult here to see just where she's going.</p>
        <p>Dark's tour de force in ''In the Gloaming,'' however, is her most constricted and deliberately unlyrical story, a twisted piece of work called ''The Secret Spot.'' Two mothers meet in Central Park when their young sons begin playing together. Helen recognizes Julia as someone she suspected of having, or trying to have, an affair with her husband some years back, and she begins to play mind games in what becomes an increasingly fruitless game of revenge. Dark creates in Helen a fierce battle of conflicting projections, wrought through a series of subtle revelations and turns -- a letter misinterpreted, a neurosis plumbed, a marriage perilously defended. Here Dark dares to toss away the politeness that dominates, and occasionally chokes, her stories. With ''The Secret Spot'' and the less pristine narratives in ''In the Gloaming,'' Dark does what she does best: lay bare the most personal of troubles in controlled but devastating prose.</p>
        <p>Katherine Dieckmann is writing a book about the making of her first feature film, ''A Good Baby.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Katherine Dieckmann is writing a book about the making of her first feature film, ''A Good Baby.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
