<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Elias Has the Hot Hand for the Devils</title>
    <meta content="02DEVI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Bruins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Boston Bruins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E5D91138F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Elias Has the Hot Hand for the Devils</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Jan. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils and Boston Bruins play to 2-2 tie; photo (M)4</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he ended his streak without a goal in 12 games just over two weeks ago, Patrik Elias of the Devils said that the goals would start to come more frequently. They have indeed come at a rate that even Elias failed to predict.</p>
        <p>The Boston Bruins have been Elias's biggest victim. After scoring the game-winner in overtime against the Bruins in New Jersey on Wednesday night, Elias scored again tonight in a 2-2 tie with the Bruins at the Fleet Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he ended his streak without a goal in 12 games just over two weeks ago, Patrik Elias of the Devils said that the goals would start to come more frequently. They have indeed come at a rate that even Elias failed to predict.</p>
        <p>The Boston Bruins have been Elias's biggest victim. After scoring the game-winner in overtime against the Bruins in New Jersey on Wednesday night, Elias scored again tonight in a 2-2 tie with the Bruins at the Fleet Center.</p>
        <p>Elias's goal put the Devils in the lead, but Jason Allison's second goal of the night tied the game for the Bruins, who have only two victories in their last 16 games (2-9-5). This was a National Hockey League-high 13th overtime game for the Bruins, who are 13-16-10-2 over all.</p>
        <p>Elias's goal was his eighth in the last 10 games after scoring just twice in his first 18 games. After missing all of training camp and the first nine games of the season as an unsigned restricted free agent, Elias has combined with Jason Arnott and Petr Sykora to bring the line back to where it was last season as the Devils' most productive combination.</p>
        <p>''I was getting a lot of chances and it was a matter of time before they started going into the net,'' Elias said. ''Our line is working really well right now.''</p>
        <p>Elias's play has helped the Devils (21-12-5-2) to their seventh victory in the last 10 games (7-2-1).</p>
        <p>His goal came on a marvelous individual effort 10 minutes 3 seconds into the second period, and it gave the Devils a 2-1 lead. He muscled his way through the left side behind Kyle McLaren of the Bruins and found goalie Byron Dafoe's far corner with a backhand.</p>
        <p>''That wasn't just nice, it was unbelievable,'' Bobby Holik said of the goal by Elias. ''It was another highlight goal.''</p>
        <p>The way things have been going for the Bruins lately was demonstrated just 22 seconds into the game. The Devils scored at that point, the first time they entered Boston's zone, when Scott Niedermayer stepped in front of Dafoe and deflected Holik's shot from the left side for his fourth goal of the season.</p>
        <p>Niedermayer's goal discouraged the Bruins to such a degree that they did not take their first shot at Martin Brodeur until the 8:06 mark of the first period. Once they took that first shot, however, the Bruins took control for the rest of the period.</p>
        <p>Boston's domination was translated into Allison's eighth goal of the season with 4:15 left in the first period. It was the first game for Allison after missing three with a wrist injury. He got his goal when he deflected McLaren's shot to the left of the screened Brodeur, who faced 25 shots, including one in the overtime.</p>
        <p>''Our guys did a good job,'' Devils Coach Robbie Ftorek said. ''I like the way the guys worked.''</p>
        <p>Ftorek rarely praises individuals, but he had kind words for Elias.</p>
        <p>''He's gifted,'' Ftorek said. ''He can dangle and he has speed.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
