<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'We Accepted That We Were Working for the Good of the Country'</title>
    <meta content="01LALA$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: LOS ANGELES, U.S.A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fleetwood, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nguyen, Thuy Ti</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sterngold, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E6DF1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'We Accepted That We Were Working for the Good of the Country'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Sterngold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sterngold, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Fleetwood recalls moving from Kansas City to Southern California in 1939 to work in aircraft manufacturing; Thuy Ti Nguyen, who left Vietnam when she was two and moved first to New Orleans and then to Oakland and Los Angeles, where she is studying law, describes her hopes for the future; photos; chronology of California's history since 1913 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not so long ago, when people referred to immigrants in Southern California, they usually meant someone like John Fleetwood. Mr. Fleetwood, 80, came from Kansas City in 1939 to work in aircraft manufacturing. He climbed his way up to running the operation that produced the Apollo command modules. His daughter has become the mayor of the town in which he lived for many years, Downey. He left when it started to become heavily populated by the next wave of immigrants, Hispanics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not so long ago, when people referred to immigrants in Southern California, they usually meant someone like John Fleetwood. Mr. Fleetwood, 80, came from Kansas City in 1939 to work in aircraft manufacturing. He climbed his way up to running the operation that produced the Apollo command modules. His daughter has become the mayor of the town in which he lived for many years, Downey. He left when it started to become heavily populated by the next wave of immigrants, Hispanics.</p>
        <p>For Thuy Ti Nguyen, the American Dream is that she is being given the opportunity to solve the problems she encounters in her new home. Ms. Nguyen (pronounced Win) was born in 1975 on the day Saigon fell. Her family fled Vietnam two years later, settling first in New Orleans, then Oakland. She is now studying law at the University of California at Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>JAMES STERNGOLD</p>
        <p>JOHN FLEETWOOD</p>
        <p>I had heard that there were jobs in the aircraft plants and that you needed a skill, so I went to a trade school to learn the sheet metal work. I finished up and took a train to Santa Monica. I went the next day to the plant. It was Douglas Aircraft and the line went halfway around the block. They only needed 13 people, and since I had been to trade school they hired me.</p>
        <p>You could see the mountains. It was beautiful. You could see the snow. The countryside was beautiful. I had a good job. That was California to me. I built my first house with my own hands. It was in 1948. It took me 9 or 10 months.</p>
        <p>We were never hurt by a recession while I was there. We felt that we were doing something important.</p>
        <p>We moved a few years ago to Vista. Well, I guess you could say the neighborhoods changed in Downey. It wasn't what I wanted. It was a different atmosphere. It wasn't for us.</p>
        <p>THUY TI NGUYEN</p>
        <p>When I think back, sometimes I wonder whether I considered New Orleans Vietnam. The village we lived in, and we called it a village, was a community of Vietnamese folks, mainly Catholic.</p>
        <p>The more you got out and saw people who were different from you, that's when my sense of identity solidified as an immigrant. I was a minority in Oakland. There were stares because I was different. There were comments, like ''chink,'' which is a derogatory expression for Chinese. I thought of saying, ''If you're going to get it right, call me a gook, not a chink.''</p>
        <p>Prop 187 [Proposition 187, which barred illegal immigrants from receiving government services] was definitely a wake-up call for me. I mean, ''immigrant'' became a kind of bad word. The irony is, I'm Republican. At the same time, I realized there was this xenophobic consciousness in California.</p>
        <p>This stuff is just a glimpse of what we're going to get. It's going to be a big part of the 21st century.</p>
        <p>I'd like my children to grow up in a diverse community like you have in California, no question. But I want them to have a sense of identity culturally. Who I might marry is a huge deal for me. I know I'm being very discriminatory in that sense. But, if anyone will have me, I want to marry a Vietnamese person, and one who is Catholic. Actually, I think I'm a little bit harsher than my parents about this.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: LOS ANGELES, U.S.A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
