<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The United States of Africa -- It May Yet Come.'</title>
    <meta content="01GHAN$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: GHANA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ghana</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ackah, Ambrose</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yankey, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onishi, Norimitsu</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ghana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The United States of Africa -- It May Yet Come.'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Norimitsu Onishi</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onishi, Norimitsu</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ambrose Ackah, 64-year-old retired Ghanaian teacher, believes that Africa can achieve peace and even unity, while Paul Yankey, a 19-year-old who struggled to complete secondary school, is not hopeful about the future and says he wants to emigrate; photos; chronology of Ghana's history since 1902 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1957, the Gold Coast became the first country to gain independence in sub-Saharan Africa, led by Kwame Nkrumah. Nkrumah's vision of African solidarity inspired independence movements across the continent, but his rule ended in a morass of corruption and an army coup in 1966. Nkrumah's hometown lies in western Ghana, a small town called Nkroful, where Ambrose Ackah was born some 64 years ago. Mr. Ackah, the son of farmers and one of seven children, was the first one in his family to attend school. He became an elementary school teacher and retired three years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1957, the Gold Coast became the first country to gain independence in sub-Saharan Africa, led by Kwame Nkrumah. Nkrumah's vision of African solidarity inspired independence movements across the continent, but his rule ended in a morass of corruption and an army coup in 1966. Nkrumah's hometown lies in western Ghana, a small town called Nkroful, where Ambrose Ackah was born some 64 years ago. Mr. Ackah, the son of farmers and one of seven children, was the first one in his family to attend school. He became an elementary school teacher and retired three years ago.</p>
        <p>Also born in Nkroful, Paul Yankey, 19, has known only one president, Jerry J. Rawlings, who has brought the country stability and a small measure of prosperity since seizing power in a coup in 1979. Mr. Yankey comes from a family of subsistence farmers, and he has two sisters and a brother. Mr. Yankey struggled financially to graduate from secondary school, and he is not hopeful about the future. He would like to go to a polytechnic college, but his family lacks the money. He also knows that Africa is filled with university graduates who don't have jobs.</p>
        <p>NORIMITSU ONISHI</p>
        <p>AMBROSE ACKAH</p>
        <p>It was very, very, very good. Many people -- everybody was happy that this time Ghana is independent. People were enjoying themselves. People from different places, they all came to celebrate.</p>
        <p>Everybody, we all liked Nkrumah. So whatever he told them, they did it.</p>
        <p>We were all happy that Ghana was going to be an independent country. It was thought there would be development after independence. You see, before independence, the secondary schools were very few in the country. But after independence, the secondary schools were distributed evenly in the country. Even in Nkroful here, there is a secondary school now. The educational system became very good.</p>
        <p>I got a job teaching. There were other farmers who joined the workers' brigades. We had workers' brigades, tailors, artisans and all these things. For everybody to get work.</p>
        <p>My grandfather promised to send me to a secondary school. But very unfortunately, before I left middle school, he died. There was nobody to help me. I was admitted to secondary school -- I passed the examination. If I had gone, I would be a very big man now. I was disappointed.</p>
        <p>Africans have to stop the fighting and live peacefully. If people are peaceful, they can develop. But they are power drunk.</p>
        <p>That is why there is a lot of fighting all over the continent.</p>
        <p>Today's leaders? Tough -- they are trying, it's not so great. Africa is not united. If it's united, it would be the United States of Africa. You don't know. It may yet come.</p>
        <p>PAUL YANKEY</p>
        <p>There is no unity in Africa. There is always -- I'll say discrimination in the country. ''Because you are not from my father's line or my mother's line, so I do not regard you as a brother or sister.'' Nkrumah was pleading with Africans to unite for aiding ourselves. It's not possible.</p>
        <p>He was not able to fulfill it because he was overthrown. I don't think it can happen. Even though the presidents in Africa are trying their best, we don't have the one who has tested himself to unite all Africans.</p>
        <p>If we unite, we become one body. Lack of employment in Ghana? We can go to another place. United, we can fix prices for our resources. If it's not possible, it means our difficulty in life will continue. And our life will be poor, for ever and ever.</p>
        <p>All of us want to leave this country, the young people. We all want to depart this country for America. Britain, America, any foreign country. Japan, German, Italy. But I would come back to help Ghana. If we get something, we must come back home to help our friends.</p>
        <p>Everything concerning education, we must provide it ourselves. After I finished secondary, I wanted to go to polytechnic. But because of lack of money, I have to wait. If there is availability of money, I would have continued.</p>
        <p>I want to be someone. I know that all will depend on my going to school. It is only with school that I can be somebody in the future. I believe that, because I have been able to see that that is my talent. My main choice is to be an agriculturist.</p>
        <p>My parents own a piece of land. O.K., it is for them. But they can't use the land because money for them to engage in farming is too small. Therefore they cannot expand. They can only cultivate for themselves.</p>
        <p>My parents could not afford my secondary school fees. So I cut bamboos in the bush. Someone will come to you and inform you that he needs 10 bamboo sticks. But the money is very, very small. You spent the whole day for 2000 cedis [about 80 cents]. You deduct your chop money that you eat. What's left is very few.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: GHANA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
