<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Children Saw What We Had Not Seen, That We Must Fight.'</title>
    <meta content="01SAFR$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: SOUTH AFRICA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mlungisi (South Africa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mvunelwa, Flamma</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jompolo, Mvuselemo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5DB1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Children Saw What We Had Not Seen, That We Must Fight.'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rachel L. Swarns</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Flamma Mvunelwa, 77-year-old retired teacher in Mlungisi, South Africa, considers widespread protests and disruptions that swept up nation's young people in 1980's to be the most profound experience of her life; Mvuselemo Jompolo, 13, hopes to make life better in Mlungisi by building houses; photos; chronology of South African history since 1910 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Flamma Mvunelwa, 77, and Mvuselelo Jompolo, 13, both live in Mlungisi, a township in the eastern Cape province of South Africa.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mvunelwa, a retired teacher, said she considered the widespread protests and disruptions that involved so many of South Africa's young people in the 1980's to be the most profound experience of her life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Flamma Mvunelwa, 77, and Mvuselelo Jompolo, 13, both live in Mlungisi, a township in the eastern Cape province of South Africa.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mvunelwa, a retired teacher, said she considered the widespread protests and disruptions that involved so many of South Africa's young people in the 1980's to be the most profound experience of her life.</p>
        <p>In Mlungisi, young people organized a successful boycott of white stores; they demanded change from the police and the city leaders. And they won: Stutterheim, the white town that now includes Mlungisi, began installing electricity and building some houses.</p>
        <p>Mvuselelo was more interested in talking about the future. He shares a two-room house made of mud and cement with his parents, his sister and the family rooster. They have no running water. There is an outhouse out back, and they share outdoor communal water taps with other families on the street. Mvuselelo, who grew up speaking Khosa (English is his second language), hopes the next century will bring his family and his community better conditions.</p>
        <p>RACHEL L. SWARNS</p>
        <p>FLAMMA MVUNELWA</p>
        <p>We really feared the white people, though we saw they were doing nothing for us.</p>
        <p>But we thought we couldn't do anything. The children saw what we had not seen, that we must fight. They were sick and tired of being bullied by white people. Those children were very strong! To see them challenging the unchallenged -- that made us see that we could fight, too!</p>
        <p>And when they said they were going to town, I was the first in town with them. I was part of it. All the streets were full of soldiers. But it was wonderful. We were not scared. We were asking for freedom. All we thought was: ''One day, it will come. One day, we will be free.''</p>
        <p>When I finally got to vote, I had the hope that things would change. I don't think I voted for nothing. There is a change. But change comes slowly. We still need houses and water and better schools.</p>
        <p>In the next century, I hope the young people will understand that they have to work hard and put right their lives now.</p>
        <p>If only they could understand it's not a war of guns and knives now to get material things. They are demanding too much in too short a time. We can only go step by step to correct the problems of the past.</p>
        <p>I wish, too, that I could see a Mlungisi that has changed. Things will change. If not in my lifetime, they will change for my grandchildren and my great-grandchildren.</p>
        <p>And these young people must know they must be part of this change.</p>
        <p>MVUSELELO JOMPOLO</p>
        <p>The millennium, it's the year of love and peace. It's not the 90's anymore.</p>
        <p>In the millennium, I want to build a new life in Mlungisi.</p>
        <p>I'd like to see new houses here, houses with four rooms and bathrooms and water taps in the houses.</p>
        <p>I'd like to see Mlungisi important. Because Mlungisi is not important; it's not beautiful. The houses are made of mud. An important place is like East London, because it's beautiful and it's built with bricks.</p>
        <p>I see the life overseas. I see on television. I see it's special. It's not like in South Africa. The houses overseas are nice.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to get nice houses. But they will come.</p>
        <p>It's a new government now. It's not the old government. It's better for me. You see the houses they're building? [He points to a new house going up across the street.] I want to be a bank manager, because I want to make money. This job makes the biggest money. I will build nice houses if I have money.</p>
        <p>My mother, she tells me I am a great man and I think special things. She says I'm going to get these things.</p>
        <p>If I make money, I will build houses and I will make Mlungisi important.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: SOUTH AFRICA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
