<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets to Face A Truer Test On the Road</title>
    <meta content="01NETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DB1338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets to Face A Truer Test On the Road</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Nets will play nine of their next 14 games on road; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As tremendous as the Nets' recent resurrection has been, their 10-3 record over the final four weeks of 1999 comes with an asterisk.</p>
        <p>Nothing can be taken away from their impressive victories over Sacramento, Milwaukee, Philadelphia, the Knicks and Orlando, but it must be understood that those victories, as well as four of their five other victories in December, took place in the comfortable surroundings of the Continental Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As tremendous as the Nets' recent resurrection has been, their 10-3 record over the final four weeks of 1999 comes with an asterisk.</p>
        <p>Nothing can be taken away from their impressive victories over Sacramento, Milwaukee, Philadelphia, the Knicks and Orlando, but it must be understood that those victories, as well as four of their five other victories in December, took place in the comfortable surroundings of the Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>Receiving a gift from the National Basketball Association schedule makers, the Nets played 11 of their 15 games last month at home, where N.B.A. teams win 62 percent of the time. They will receive no such luxury in January, however, as nine of their 14 games will be on the road, the first seven of those road games coming against teams with winning records.</p>
        <p>While the Nets, who recently tied a franchise record with nine consecutive home victories, realize what type of change they are in for, they do not expect it to alter their fortunes. They attribute their turnaround more to improved play than to a kind schedule.</p>
        <p>''I just think it's been time,'' said Jamie Feick, the league's fifth-leading rebounder at 12.2 a game. ''As time went along this season, we've just gotten better. Our team chemistry has gotten better. And it just happens to be that we've had this home stretch where we might be at the top of our game right now. So I don't know if it has much to do with being on the road or at home.''</p>
        <p>This will be the Nets' telltale month. After botching November (2-13), they surged to improve their record to 12-18 and get themselves in position to make a charge at the Eastern Conference playoffs. Though they still rank only 12th in the conference standing, they are just three and a half games out of the eighth and final playoff spot. With 52 games remaining, they are legitimately back in the hunt.</p>
        <p>''We've defended our home turf and made the moves to get close to a .500 record in December,'' Coach Don Casey said. ''We are now closing in on the .500 mark, which has been our goal. If we get to the .500 mark, then we hope we can use that as a launching pad.''</p>
        <p>To keep themselves in the playoff picture, the Nets will most likely have to pull within a couple of games of .500 by the end of January. If they founder on the road, they could wind up playing strictly for pride over the season's final three months.</p>
        <p>While the Nets have definitely become a better team, there is reason for concern as they head into what could be their toughest stretch on the schedule. They have just a 2-10 record away from home, and while most of those losses occurred before their revival, they had three inexplicably poor road performances in December.</p>
        <p>After defeating tough Sacramento and Milwaukee, they were beaten by the horrible Chicago Bulls (2-25) at the United Center. They won their next two games at home and then squandered a 9-point fourth-quarter lead in losing at Washington (10-20). They rebounded for a rout in Cleveland and a home victory over Atlanta, but experienced a meltdown on Dec. 21 at Toronto, which scored 75 points in taking a 30-point halftime lead. The Nets have not been away from the Meadowlands since.</p>
        <p>Jump-shooting teams, of which the Nets are undoubtedly one, have historically struggled on the road, so the Nets will have to find a way to overcome that. And quickly.</p>
        <p>They open the new year on Tuesday at Indiana, the hottest team in the Eastern Conference at 20-9 and the owner of a 12-2 mark at the new Conseco Fieldhouse. After returning home to play Vancouver (6-23), the Nets will visit Miami (19-9) on the second night of back-to-back games. Two days later, they play at Orlando (15-14).</p>
        <p>They will also visit Philadelphia (17-15) and the Knicks (18-12) before ending the month with stops in Portland (22-7), Seattle (18-12), Vancouver and Los Angeles, where they will play the Clippers (9-20).</p>
        <p>One positive for the Nets is that four of their five home games in January are against teams with losing records. So if they can continue to exploit their home-court advantage and steal a few road games, they could close in on .500 by the All-Star Game break in February.</p>
        <p>Keith Van Horn, for one, does not put much stock in home and road theories.</p>
        <p>''The dimensions of the basketball court are the same on the road as they are here,'' Van Horn said after Thursday's home victory over Orlando. ''So whatever we're doing here in the confines of those four lines, we need to do out in Indiana and Miami and wherever else we head.''</p>
        <p>If it is that simple, the Nets should be fine.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
