<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brooklyn Groups Back Use Of Park by Mets Farm Team</title>
    <meta content="01STAD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minor Leagues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Claims Against Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stadiums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Prospect Park (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Golden, Howard (Boro Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Julian E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minor Leagues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DE1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brooklyn Groups Back Use Of Park by Mets Farm Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIAN E. BARNES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barnes, Julian E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brooklyn community groups drop their opposition to plan to move minor league Mets team into plannd ballpark in Flatbush, now that city has promised to renovate park where team would play; Brooklyn Boro Pres Howard Golden wants higher caliber ball club than Mets have offered, and he may be stumbling block to agreement; team would be put in Parade Grounds, adjacent to Prospect Park; deal to fix park will fall apart if Golden does not agree to drop his suit; coalition of community groups, including many critics of Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani, is pressuring Golden to drop his suit and endorse $12 million overhaul plan; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group of Brooklyn community groups that sued to stop a minor league Mets team from moving into a planned ballpark in Flatbush has dropped its opposition to the plan, now that the city has promised to  renovate a park where the team would play.</p>
        <p>But the Brooklyn borough president, Howard Golden, is the stumbling block to an  agreement to put the team in the Parade Grounds, which is adjacent to Prospect  Park. Mr. Golden, an opponent of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, wants a higher caliber ball club than the Mets have offered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group of Brooklyn community groups that sued to stop a minor league Mets team from moving into a planned ballpark in Flatbush has dropped its opposition to the plan, now that the city has promised to  renovate a park where the team would play.</p>
        <p>But the Brooklyn borough president, Howard Golden, is the stumbling block to an  agreement to put the team in the Parade Grounds, which is adjacent to Prospect  Park. Mr. Golden, an opponent of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, wants a higher caliber ball club than the Mets have offered.</p>
        <p>In November, a coalition of soccer parents and community advocates filed suit along with Mr. Golden and marched to City Hall to condemn Mr. Giuliani's plan to build a temporary stadium in the Parade Grounds, which they said would take away their children's playing spaces.</p>
        <p>But the coalition, which includes many of Mr. Giuliani's critics, has switched sides. Some members gathered at the park on Thursday to pressure Mr. Golden to endorse the $12 million overhaul plan.</p>
        <p>''The Parade Grounds have been in terrible shape for 30 years,'' said Ellen Shea, a plaintiff in the lawsuit whose two daughters play soccer games in the park on weekends. ''I've picked up enough broken glass and dead rats to last a lifetime. Howard Golden has to be farsighted enough to realize this is the only way the Parade Grounds are going to get fixed up.''</p>
        <p>The deal to fix the park will fall apart if Mr. Golden does not also agree to drop his suit, said Michael G. Carey, president of the city's Economic Development Corporation. The city must settle the two suits by next week to have time to prepare the park for the minor league season in June, Mr. Carey said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Golden's suit demands that the city follow a formal land use review to win approval for the stadium. The city and the Mets have said that if they are forced to do a review, which could take at least six months, they will have to find a new site.</p>
        <p>During negotiations, the neighborhood groups and the city agreed on a deal to renovate the entire Parade Grounds, shrink the size of the stadium to 2,500 seats from 4,500 and reduce the amount of parking, in return for allowing the Mets to use the park for up to two years.</p>
        <p>Greg Brooks, Mr. Golden's chief of staff, said that Mr. Giuliani was wrong to link the repair of the Parade Grounds to the minor league team.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has said we want the Parade Grounds restored,'' Mr. Brooks said. ''Very few have said we really need the Mets.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Carey said bringing in the Mets provided a pool of money to renovate the Parade Grounds that would not otherwise be available.</p>
        <p>''The fact is the Parade Grounds have been neglected for many, many years,'' he said, ''and what we have here is a program to allow them to be restored.''</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Giuliani brokered a deal to bring a Class A Yankees affiliate to Staten Island and a Mets affiliate to Brooklyn. Mr. Golden has long argued that Brooklyn can support, and deserves, more than a short-season Class A team, the lowest rung of professional baseball. But the Mets and Yankees fear that more advanced teams would siphon fans from big league games.</p>
        <p>Mr. Golden also wants the city to begin building an amateur athletic arena, to be called Sportsplex, next to the Coney Island stadium that is to become the permanent home of the minor league Mets. Sportsplex supporters fear that once the permanent stadium is complete, the city will be unwilling to build the arena next door, on what is now intended to be the Mets' parking lot.</p>
        <p>City Councilman Stephen DiBrienza said the city should negotiate with Mr. Golden and offer to let work on the Sportsplex begin. But Councilwoman Una S. T. Clarke said Mr. Golden should not stop the renovation.</p>
        <p>''The borough president should not hold the Parade Grounds as the only bargaining chip,'' Ms. Clarke said.</p>
        <p>For now, Mr. Golden's aides insist they will not settle for anything less than a formal review. And Mr. Carey said the only offer on the table was the Parade Grounds restoration, not Sportsplex.</p>
        <p>Members of the coalition who met at the Parade Grounds on Thursday said Mr. Golden should take the city offer, declare victory and forget about luring another team to Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''It's not going to happen, we are not going to get a bigger team,'' said Roy E. Landsmark, a member of the Association of Community Organizations for Reform Now, the advocacy group leading the coalition. ''My concern is for the kids and the park. It's about what the community wants, not what Mr. Golden wants.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
