<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haven't I Seen These Shows Before?</title>
    <meta content="01TVTV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1D71630F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haven't I Seen These Shows Before?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bill Carter</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill Carter article says the hit television show will disappear in 21st century as technological advances make it possible to individualize programs for every viewer and make it impossible for producers to establish a new show among a wide variety of viewers at the same time; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TELEVISION in the next century will surely be about choice. No matter what form the television set itself takes, the number of programs it delivers will be virtually limitless with the notion of separate, distinct channels all but extinct. Instead, every home will have the ME channel -- really a series of channels, one for each member of the family, offering a completely individualized lineup of programs assembled from the all-but-infinite selections pulsing through the digital web.</p>
        <p>Thus television, the most effective mass medium ever devised, will be undermined as a vehicle of mass distribution -- and with it will go the hit show. Why? Because the same digital forces will also affect magazines, newspapers and radio, causing them to narrow their focus -- and making it almost impossible for producers to establish a new show among a wide variety of viewers at the same time. There will be no reason to broadcast a show at a given hour (except for live events like sports), so the possibilities for creating a nationally popular entertainment program will be drastically limited.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TELEVISION in the next century will surely be about choice. No matter what form the television set itself takes, the number of programs it delivers will be virtually limitless with the notion of separate, distinct channels all but extinct. Instead, every home will have the ME channel -- really a series of channels, one for each member of the family, offering a completely individualized lineup of programs assembled from the all-but-infinite selections pulsing through the digital web.</p>
        <p>Thus television, the most effective mass medium ever devised, will be undermined as a vehicle of mass distribution -- and with it will go the hit show. Why? Because the same digital forces will also affect magazines, newspapers and radio, causing them to narrow their focus -- and making it almost impossible for producers to establish a new show among a wide variety of viewers at the same time. There will be no reason to broadcast a show at a given hour (except for live events like sports), so the possibilities for creating a nationally popular entertainment program will be drastically limited.</p>
        <p>With few bona fide hits, advertising revenues will most likely shrink. That will mean a switch to an almost entirely pay-per-view system for the ME channels, just like at a movie theater.</p>
        <p>Programmers will try to counter with interactive communications, made possible by the merging of the television and the computer, to create instant word of mouth about new shows.</p>
        <p>In place of traditional commercials, there will be incessant product placements on the shows. And because programmers will know the buying trends of viewers, the products will be changed digitally from home to home.</p>
        <p>But the weekly hit series, followed avidly across the country and discussed the next day in offices, over back fences and online, will likely be a distant memory. For a show to make it into enough individual ''program mixes'' to score well in the ratings, it will need national recognition. That should bode well for big-time sports and golden oldies whose names have long since been established.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
