<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Works In Progress From All Over; Bloodless Knife for Epilepsy</title>
    <meta content="01EPIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Epilepsy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gamma Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sweden</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of California (San Francisco)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Virginia</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Pittsburgh</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Northwestern University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caruso, Denise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbaro, Nicholas M (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Epilepsy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Epilepsy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E5DE1238F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Works In Progress From All Over; Bloodless Knife for Epilepsy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENISE CARUSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caruso, Denise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arts &amp; Ideas looks ahead at works-in-progress; Dr Nicholas M Barbaro and team at University of California at San Francisco joins with epilepsy specialists at Yale, Pittsburgh, Northwestern and Virginia universities to study bloodless radiosurgery technique to help patients with temporal lobe epilepsy, which is drug-resistant but is responsive to traditional surgery; $5-million Gamma Knife developed in Sweden focuses low-dosage gamma radiation on brain target; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The centruy's turn has been a time of retrospectives: what was the most important event, who was the most influential thinker? Arts &amp; Ideas decided to take a look ahead at what some of today's researchers are working on. From the most raked-over field, like the history of the ancient world, to the latest medical technology, scholars are coming up with fresh insights. Some ideas may turn into breakthroughs, and others may turn out to be dead-ends, but the journey is rarely boring. Here is a handful of works in progress.</p>
        <p>About 1 percent of the population, nearly three million people in the United States, has epilepsy. Because drug therapy is not always effective, finding new ways to treat the disorder without the risk and cost of open brain surgery has been of keen interest to medical researchers like Nicholas M. Barbaro, a neurosurgeon and epilepsy specialist at the University of California at San Francisco.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The centruy's turn has been a time of retrospectives: what was the most important event, who was the most influential thinker? Arts &amp; Ideas decided to take a look ahead at what some of today's researchers are working on. From the most raked-over field, like the history of the ancient world, to the latest medical technology, scholars are coming up with fresh insights. Some ideas may turn into breakthroughs, and others may turn out to be dead-ends, but the journey is rarely boring. Here is a handful of works in progress.</p>
        <p>About 1 percent of the population, nearly three million people in the United States, has epilepsy. Because drug therapy is not always effective, finding new ways to treat the disorder without the risk and cost of open brain surgery has been of keen interest to medical researchers like Nicholas M. Barbaro, a neurosurgeon and epilepsy specialist at the University of California at San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Now Dr. Barbaro and his team at the U.C.S.F.-Stanford Medical Center are joining with specialists at four other leading epilepsy treatment centers -- Yale University, the University of Pittsburgh, Northwestern University and the University of Virginia -- in a study to see if there is an answer.</p>
        <p>Their study will focus on 40 patients with temporal lobe epilepsy, which is known to be resistant to drug therapy but can be located precisely in the brain and is very responsive to traditional surgery.</p>
        <p>The consortium has applied for a $2 million grant from the National Institutes of Health to make a two-year study of the safety and effectiveness of a bloodless radiosurgery technique with a $5 million piece of equipment called the Gamma Knife.</p>
        <p>The Gamma Knife, made by the Swedish medical technology firm Elekta, focuses low-dosage gamma radiation from 201 sources on a precise target in the brain. Areas adjacent to the target receive only slight doses of radiation, while the target gets the full intensity.</p>
        <p>Until recently the Gamma Knife was used only to treat tumors and vascular disorders of the brain, not epilepsy. But animal tests showed promise, and in November a team of French doctors published a preliminary report in the medical journal Epilepsia that claimed the elimination of seizures in six of seven human patients who were treated with the Gamma Knife.</p>
        <p>But the apparent success of the French study, Dr. Barbaro, the study's principal investigator, said, raises almost as many concerns as hopes, highlighting the importance of a larger and more controlled study in the United States.</p>
        <p>''We already know the French have gotten a pretty favorable outcome, with the vast majority of their subjects becoming seizure-free,'' he said. ''But there are still big questions, and we're concerned that as soon as a couple of their publications come out, everyone with a Gamma Knife will think they can try this without having enough long-term data to decide the most effective and safest protocol.''</p>
        <p>For example, Dr. Barbaro said, the French study did not compare the effectiveness of low and high doses of radiation, as the American study will. He added that there have not been enough subjects to determine the safety and effectiveness of the procedure.</p>
        <p>''We consider our study to be a pilot,'' Dr. Barbaro said. ''We believe you should treat 100 patients or more before you're able to say, 'Here's the formula, here's how you treat epilepsy with a Gamma Knife.' We won't have good, hard data about safety until then.''</p>
        <p>But if larger studies continue to show positive results, he said, the benefits of Gamma Knife surgery may be great. For example, children with drug-resistant epilepsy who have radiosurgery may be able to reduce or eliminate the antiseizure medication that has been shown to depress I.Q.</p>
        <p>Fewer patients will suffer postoperative language impairment, ''something that's unavoidable in an open surgical procedure,'' Dr. Barbaro said, because radiosurgery does not require cutting through the outer surface of the brain where language skills are located.</p>
        <p>What is more, Dr. Barbaro said, especially if lower doses are found to eliminate seizures effectively, the ''potential exists to treat people who cannot be operated on today,'' particularly those whose epilepsy is centered in parts of the brain that affect speech and movement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
