<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big City; Millennium? It's Really 1703!</title>
    <meta content="01BIG.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square and 42d Street (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/John Tierney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DE1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big City; Millennium? It's Really 1703!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney The Big City column wonders why citizens of world's most technologically advanced society celebrate future by gathering to watch ball slide down a pole; suggests more elaborate plan: to replace ball with huge illuminated swing shaped like crescent moon, which would transport leggy chorine across Times Square, accompanied by elaborate lights and holograms in the sky (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ARE you already disappointed by the alleged new millennium?</p>
        <p>Do you think you missed out on the good millennial parties? Did you suspect, during yesterday's television marathon, that you were the only person on Earth not overcome with the desire to dance in the street?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ARE you already disappointed by the alleged new millennium?</p>
        <p>Do you think you missed out on the good millennial parties? Did you suspect, during yesterday's television marathon, that you were the only person on Earth not overcome with the desire to dance in the street?</p>
        <p>Are you still unable to understand why the citizens of the world's most technologically advanced society celebrate the future by gathering to watch a ball slide down a pole? And does your brain this morning feel even slower than it did in 1999?</p>
        <p>I can offer two bits of solace. The first comes courtesy of The National Enquirer. It reported, in an article on the ''bizarre ways stars will kick off the new year,'' that Carol Connors, the author of the ''Rocky'' theme song, would be flying her baby grand piano to a mountain in South Africa to sing to the lions in the Shamwari Game Reserve.</p>
        <p>''When the millennium rolls in,'' she told The Enquirer, ''I'll be on top of a mountain performing my new song, 'We Must Stop.' It's a plea for conservation on this planet.''</p>
        <p>If you can imagine that moment, how can you not feel better about life? No matter how dreary your New Year's Eve was, you did not greet 2000 listening to ''We Must Stop.'' The lions of Shamwari surely envy you.</p>
        <p>The second bit of solace comes courtesy of Heribert Illig, a German who fully understands why you may not be feeling especially millennial this morning. According to his calculations, today is the beginning of the year 1703.</p>
        <p>Dr. Illig, who lives near Munich, is an independent scholar who has been called the ''von Daniken of the Middle Ages,'' a tribute to his robust book sales as well as to his dismal reputation among academics. The  Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung called him ''Dr. Seltsam und die Zeitbombe'' -- Dr. Strange and the Time Bomb.</p>
        <p>His zeitbombe is a marvelously simple explanation for the paucity of archaeological remains and other records from the Dark Ages: there was no such period. In his two books, ''The Middle Ages Invented'' and ''Who Adjusted the Clock?'' he argues that history from 614 to 911 -- including the reign of Charlemagne -- was fabricated after the calendar was bumped ahead nearly three centuries.</p>
        <p>Dr. Illig has a couple of hypotheses for the origin of the conspiracy. It might have been a seventh-century Byzantine ruler anxious to ''spruce up'' his empire's history. Or maybe Otto III, crowned Holy Roman Emperor in what we think of as the year 996, was actually crowned much earlier and then conspired with the pope to advance the calendar so that he could be ruling when the millennium arrived.</p>
        <p>Was it possible that Otto wanted to stimulate the empire's tourist economy by presiding over a millennial ball-lowering ceremony in Rome? Alas, Dr. Illig does not address the question, and there are no records of Otto discussing that aspect of his Y1K plans.</p>
        <p>While academic scholars dismiss Dr. Illig's theory as preposterous, it has been embraced by a growing band of amateurs. The movement has even begun to splinter. This year, when another writer in Germany published a book called ''Invented History,'' Dr. Illig dismissed the author as a  ''Trittbrettfahrer'' -- someone riding on a car's running board -- who was trying to ''make money off my name.''</p>
        <p>IT'S easy to see why the theory has a certain appeal. The zeitbombe frees history students from some of the drearier chapters in their text books, and its majestic scope makes other conspiracy theories seem paltry. What's an extra gunman in the Kennedy assassination against three centuries of world history? Oliver Stone will be on the case soon.</p>
        <p>Most important, the zeitbombe provides us with a second chance to plan a proper millennium celebration for Times Square. The basic technology of a ball sliding down a pole wasn't even novel in Emperor Otto's day. The Crossroads of the Millennium deserves something more exciting.</p>
        <p>My dream, which city officials have been carefully ignoring for two years, is to replace the ball with a huge illuminated swing shaped like a crescent moon. It would start out where the ball is and transport a leggy chorine all the way across Times Square to the rooftop above the Coca-Cola sign, accompanied by elaborate lights and holograms in the sky.</p>
        <p>The plan isn't quite finished -- I haven't figured out how to hang the swing yet -- but thanks to Dr. Illig we have 297 years to work out the details. Or to come up with something better. I'm open to anything as long it doesn't involve any songs about saving the planet that sound like the theme from ''Rocky.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
