<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All's Well Now Between Sprewell and Van Gundy</title>
    <meta content="01KNIX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sprewell, Latrell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gundy, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0D71338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All's Well Now Between Sprewell and Van Gundy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks forward Latrell Sprewell says his relationship with Coach Jeff Van Gundy is much smoother because Sprewell understands his role on team (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fourth-quarter clock was slipping toward the final two minutes Thursday night as Latrell Sprewell sat on the bench with the patience and contentment of a bird watcher.</p>
        <p>He didn't huff, puff or make a fuss. He didn't scowl, glare or stare down his coach. With all the adjustments Sprewell has made in his game since last season -- including the inclination to think of his teammates on the floor before himself -- his attitude toward Jeff Van Gundy may be the most remarkable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The fourth-quarter clock was slipping toward the final two minutes Thursday night as Latrell Sprewell sat on the bench with the patience and contentment of a bird watcher.</p>
        <p>He didn't huff, puff or make a fuss. He didn't scowl, glare or stare down his coach. With all the adjustments Sprewell has made in his game since last season -- including the inclination to think of his teammates on the floor before himself -- his attitude toward Jeff Van Gundy may be the most remarkable.</p>
        <p>Last season, Sprewell didn't know Van Gundy. He wasn't sure how much respect to give a coach who had never played in the National Basketball Association, never starred in a national commercial and never strolled the sideline in an Armani. As soon as Sprewell was acquired last January, there was tension created by the unknown.</p>
        <p>To begin with, Van Gundy decided to bring the All-Star guard off the bench and force him to play forward. Sprewell grumbled. Once, Van Gundy pulled Sprewell aside at a practice in Los Angeles to suggest that he cool down his impulsive play and think of winning as an important statistic. Sprewell insisted he wasn't going to change.</p>
        <p>Then, in Game 1 of the second round of the playoffs against Atlanta, Sprewell was spotted snarling at Van Gundy like a bull eyeing a red cape when he was left on the bench too long for his liking to start the second half. He had scored 17 points in 20 minutes during the first two quarters only to sit until there were 3 minutes 4 seconds left in the third.</p>
        <p>''I think I do remember that,'' Sprewell said Thursday after the Knicks beat the Wizards. ''I was playing well, and I wanted to stay on the floor. But there was nothing said between Jeff and I.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell didn't have to say anything last season. His facial expressions gave away his thoughts. But now, the coach and the player trade compliments like recipes. Van Gundy has called the unselfish play of Sprewell ''beautiful basketball.'' And Sprewell hasn't second-guessed his coach, not even Thursday when he was left on the bench for all but two minutes of the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>''The lineup Jeff had out there was doing the job,'' Sprewell said. ''I have nothing to complain about as far as playing time. I probably get more than anyone on this team. Sitting on the bench for one game is not the end of the world.''</p>
        <p>The world according to Sprewell is far different than it was last season. It is hard to be miserable when you're a starter. More than anything else, being a starter with a defined role has transformed his attitude toward Van Gundy.</p>
        <p>''That makes it easier,'' Sprewell said. ''Jeff and I don't have to worry about all the stuff that's being written and said about 'Spree wants to start and Jeff wants him to come off the bench.' It seems that the relationship is perceived to be a lot smoother. And I think it is, because I know my role.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell is back in his comfort zone. Although his shooting percentage has hovered around 40 percent, he is averaging 19 points, 4.4 assists and 5 rebounds a game. His performances -- which have included a few mind-boggling scoring streaks -- may be enough to get him on the All-Star team. Just maybe.</p>
        <p>''It's not my call,'' Sprewell said. He is listed as a forward, so that may work against him, considering the trouble he has had scoring on and defending against small forwards like Jamal Mashburn and Juwan Howard. He is also considered an outcast. He has said he will be disappointed if coaches voting on the reserves hold his choking of P. J. Carlesimo against him.</p>
        <p>As a result of that incident, in December 1997, Sprewell was punished with a 68-game exile from the league. In his down time, Sprewell lost some of the edge on his game. Last season, he struggled from 3-point range and had difficulty going to his left. This season, the long-range touch has begun to resurface.</p>
        <p>''I think if I've lost anything, it's my explosiveness,'' Sprewell said. ''When I got in the paint before, I was able to go over guys a lot easier than what I'm doing right now.''</p>
        <p>That's hard to believe, considering the fury of his dunks. At least for now, the court is where all his emotion is directed. His relationship with his coach is the picture of contentment -- even when he is a spectator for the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>''I understand that it's all about winning,'' Sprewell said. ''I had no complaints.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
