<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The United States of Africa -- It May Yet Come.'</title>
    <meta content="01GERM$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: GERMANY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Israel, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matzner, Bernd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E4DE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The United States of Africa -- It May Yet Come.'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edmund L. Andrews</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fritz Israel, 74, who was German soldier in World War II, recalls the war and how he learned about Holocaust, while Bernd Matzner, a 27-year-old who grew up in East Germany, reflects on country's unification and future; chronology of German history since 1919 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fritz Israel and Bernd Matzner were witnesses to two of this century's most transforming events. Mr. Israel, 74, fought as a German soldier during World War II and grew up with the horror of Hitler and the Holocaust. Mr. Matzner, 27, grew up under communism in East Germany and watched in amazement when the Berlin Wall fell without bloodshed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Israel, despite his name, is not a Jew. He was wounded on D-Day and spent two years as a prisoner of war in a British hospital. After the war, he started a printing business in Konigstein, near Frankfurt, where he prospered and recently retired.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fritz Israel and Bernd Matzner were witnesses to two of this century's most transforming events. Mr. Israel, 74, fought as a German soldier during World War II and grew up with the horror of Hitler and the Holocaust. Mr. Matzner, 27, grew up under communism in East Germany and watched in amazement when the Berlin Wall fell without bloodshed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Israel, despite his name, is not a Jew. He was wounded on D-Day and spent two years as a prisoner of war in a British hospital. After the war, he started a printing business in Konigstein, near Frankfurt, where he prospered and recently retired.</p>
        <p>Mr. Matzner grew up in a gritty industrial city called Karl Marx Stadt, which was renamed Chemnitz after the fall of the Berlin Wall. Today, he is a Web-page designer and co-founder of an advertising agency in Berlin.</p>
        <p>EDMUND L. ANDREWS</p>
        <p>FRITZ ISRAEL</p>
        <p>It was assumed that every young person would be a member of Hitler Youth. The Hitler Youth naturally had a political side, but it also had another side of bringing young people together in sport and in play. The political tendencies were there but at that time we had not suffered from those.</p>
        <p>Our first encounter with that was really on the night of the pogrom, Kristallnacht. I was 13 at the time. It all seemed incomprehensible. I remember there was a vegetable salesman, a Jew, who would come through our neighborhood. Everybody liked him. When the persecution of the Jews began, he tried to protect himself by wearing an Iron Cross from the First World War on his chest. But then he disappeared.</p>
        <p>The persecution of Jews was known. There had been some talk about concentration camps and the Holocaust. It was known, at least to some extent. But most people acknowledged it with just a shake of their heads. No one could oppose anything without endangering himself.</p>
        <p>I first learned about the magnitude of the concentration camps when I was in the hospital, watching English news films. At first we couldn't believe that it was true. But it slowly became clear that it was.</p>
        <p>I got the chance to speak a little English with the doctors and nurses, and we all asked each other the same thing: What have you done to me?</p>
        <p>But we could see that we were individuals and that the conflict wasn't between us but rather at this level far above us. The most decisive thing was that we rediscovered a sense of human rights. If you said to me, ''You Nazi pig,'' we had the possibility of at least talking. You could learn that I was just born there and that I couldn't do anything about it.</p>
        <p>No one should ever forget what happened or deny what happened. But I do hope for the day when Germany can be treated the same as other countries and not be treated as a second-class nation.</p>
        <p>BERND MATZNER</p>
        <p>I went to a high school that was mainly for youth heading on to the  university or to the leadership ranks.  As a result, it was a school that  stayed very close to the party line and demanded a strong identification with the system. It was essentially a ''red school.''</p>
        <p>Once a year, our class would be taken to see a movie and we would always have a discussion about its meaning afterward. We all viewed this as a bit of theater: we knew what questions they would ask and what answers had to be given. And we did give them.</p>
        <p>But in 1989 we saw a Russian movie called ''The Dragon'' based on a tale about a dragon that occupied a city like a dictator. The whole city was run by a ''nomenklatura,'' and it was obvious that the film reflected the impact of glasnost.</p>
        <p>This time, there was no discussion after this film -- and they never showed it again. For me, that was a signal. They were suddenly afraid that the criticism of their own system would be too obvious.</p>
        <p>The first time I went to a demonstration supporting political changes in East Germany, it was very quiet. In my hometown there was a large statue of Karl Marx in the city center and people simply lit candles, without saying anything, and put them in front of the statue. One realized suddenly that this complete stillness was much more powerful than the system.</p>
        <p>It was very emotional. You could tell that something had happened, but the uncertainty was great. Scenarios with tanks rolling forward like in Prague or Beijing came to our minds. But for some reason we didn't have the feeling that would happen. The system that had been so strong suddenly seemed defenseless.</p>
        <p>The worrying afterthought is that when people rallied for a fast reunification they strove to re-create a state of complacency that does not require participation. The pursuit of individual prosperity is well and good. But people shouldn't forget about their responsibility for the community.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: GERMANY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
