<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Vigilant Army of Officers Encounters Few Problems</title>
    <meta content="01COPS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: A PEACEFUL PARTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFDB1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Vigilant Army of Officers Encounters Few Problems</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saddling up all its horses, putting all its helicopters in the air and sending nearly all its officers out on the street in uniform, the New York Police Department yesterday mounted one of its largest security operations ever -- three years in the planning and costing $6 million -- and by early this morning it appeared to have paid off with a genial and almost uneventful New Year's Eve.</p>
        <p>Some 8,000 police officers blanketed Times Square alone -- a force larger than that of most of the country's municipal police departments -- for the most famous and symbolic gathering. But the police also had to cover 328 other officially scheduled celebrations in all five boroughs, including a gathering of tens of thousands of people at Grand Army Plaza in Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Saddling up all its horses, putting all its helicopters in the air and sending nearly all its officers out on the street in uniform, the New York Police Department yesterday mounted one of its largest security operations ever -- three years in the planning and costing $6 million -- and by early this morning it appeared to have paid off with a genial and almost uneventful New Year's Eve.</p>
        <p>Some 8,000 police officers blanketed Times Square alone -- a force larger than that of most of the country's municipal police departments -- for the most famous and symbolic gathering. But the police also had to cover 328 other officially scheduled celebrations in all five boroughs, including a gathering of tens of thousands of people at Grand Army Plaza in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>But for the most part, the officers massed around Times Square were able to lean casually against the blue sawhorse barricades and the newer interlocking metal crowd control fences and chat casually with the celebrators.</p>
        <p>While the police had been bracing for a possible terrorist attack or disaster caused by computer failures like a breakdown of the electric system, the midnight hour, complete with the dropping of the Waterford crystal ball at Times Square, passed without serious incident.</p>
        <p>By 12:30, only a half-dozen arrests had been reported in the Times Square area, mostly for drunken scuffles with the police, and most of these seemed more ludicrous than menacing.</p>
        <p>Still, the police were edgy and vigilent, rushing up whenever they spotted a suspicious-looking bundle or unattended backpack. At one point last night they seized a man with a gas mask on his belt, but released him when he turned out to be on active duty with the military.</p>
        <p>Police detectives assigned to the Times Square detail were in the Real Park garage at 259 West 53rd Street when they saw a man, later identified as George James, walking around with handcuffs.</p>
        <p>A search of his van, which appeared dirty, lived-in and littered with pornographic magazines, turned up a loaded shotgun. Although he protested he was carrying the shotgun for his own protection, Mr. James, 29, of Saginaw, Mich., was charged with several counts of illegal possession of a weapon. He appeared to be the closest approximation to a threat uncovered last night.</p>
        <p>In all, 37,000 police officers were on duty over New Year's Eve and into the morning of Jan. 1. Days off were canceled, and detectives and others who normally work in plain clothes were put back onto the street in uniforms. All six police helicopters circled over the city, and all 102 horses in the mounted unit were saddled up.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said the crowd in Times Square was close to twice the size of last year, when it was estimated that a million people had congregated there.</p>
        <p>At midafternoon, as tens of thousands of early arrivals poured into the area, the police constantly adjusted their barricades, creating a series of frozen zones from 43rd Street north along the legs of Broadway and Seventh Avenue as far as 59th Street.</p>
        <p>Some 700 undercover officers mingled with the crowd, on the lookout for troublemakers or possible terrorists. Bomb-sniffing dogs searched for explosives. As in past years, police officers confiscated any alcoholic beverages they found, a measure that officials say has cut disorderly conduct during the once-rowdy celebration to negligible levels.</p>
        <p>Much of the concern in recent days had been over the possibility of a terrorist attack. In the Times Square area, manholes were welded shut, steel trash cans removed and mailboxes locked. Cars entering garages in the area over the past few days were searched as a condition of parking. There were also spot searches of cars entering the city through the tunnels.</p>
        <p>Concerns over terrorism mounted sharply on Thursday with the arrest in Brooklyn of a 31-year-old Algerian, Abdel Ghani, who, the Federal Bureau of Investigation charged, was an accomplice of Ahmed Ressam, the Algerian charged with trying to smuggle powerful explosives and four sophisticated timing devices across the border near Seattle in mid-December.</p>
        <p>Even as a black-clad anti-terrorist task force stormed the shabby Brooklyn apartment block where it had tracked Mr. Ghani by a scrap of paper with his phone number found on Mr. Ressam, federal agents in a half-dozen other cities questioned, and in some cases detained, people they believed had some connection to Mr. Ressam. But Mayor Giuliani, Police Commissioner Howard Safir and F.B.I. officials here and in Washington said they had no specific knowledge of any terrorist plot aimed at New York City.</p>
        <p>The Police Department plan, code-named Archangel, was three years in the making. It put the department on its highest alert and included detailed methods for responding to and investigating terrorist acts, including biological and chemical assaults.</p>
        <p>In addition to the threat of terrorism, the police had been prepared for power failures or other problems that might be caused by computer failures associated with the Year 2000 problems. None were reported.</p>
        <p>Special emergency teams were stationed in each borough with trucks equipped with banks of lights, generators and special tools in case anyone was trapped in an elevator in the event of a power failure.</p>
        <p>The Police Department bought large amounts of equipment to prepare for New Year's Eve, including extra lighting trucks for working in the dark, and about $65,000 worth of interlocking metal barricades for crowd control. Each precinct was equipped with portable electric generators. An extra three-month supply of flashlights and batteries was stashed away, and individual officers were even issued chemical illumination sticks that light up when twisted.</p>
        <p>1/1/00: A PEACEFUL PARTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
