<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russian Troops Are Edgy as They Prepare to Go 'Clean' Grozny</title>
    <meta content="Y01CHE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YELTSIN RESIGNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chechnya (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Grozny (Chechnya)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Chechnya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DB1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russian Troops Are Edgy as They Prepare to Go 'Clean' Grozny</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>GROZNY, Russia, Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russia's campaign against breakaway republic of Chechnya is still popular, but Russian casualties mount as troops become mired in urban warfare in Grozny, the capital; mood among soldiers is edgy; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After Dmitri Baidanov's legs had been shattered by mortar fire, he crawled for three days through the streets of Grozny until he reached the Russian lines.</p>
        <p>Today Private Baidanov, 19, was splayed on his stomach, unconscious in a field hospital on the western outskirts of Grozny, the Chechen capital. He may be one of the lucky ones. Six bodies lay in a row in the muddy field nearby, wrapped in shiny foil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After Dmitri Baidanov's legs had been shattered by mortar fire, he crawled for three days through the streets of Grozny until he reached the Russian lines.</p>
        <p>Today Private Baidanov, 19, was splayed on his stomach, unconscious in a field hospital on the western outskirts of Grozny, the Chechen capital. He may be one of the lucky ones. Six bodies lay in a row in the muddy field nearby, wrapped in shiny foil.</p>
        <p>''We had more than 10 wounded yesterday, and there will be more wounded today,'' said a hospital orderly, Pvt. Dmitri Turkov. ''They are fighting less than two miles away.''</p>
        <p>This is a side of the war that most Russians are rarely shown, patching up the wounded and the grisly task of disposing the dead.</p>
        <p>When the Russian military began its campaign against the separatist rebels, its generals vowed to win a speedy victory and hold down Russian losses. But as Russia begins the new year, its troops are mired in urban warfare, and the still popular war is claiming a higher toll.</p>
        <p>Russian artillery hurled round after round toward Grozny. The firepower was supposed to have broken the rebels' will before Russian Interior Ministry troops moved block by block to ''clean'' the city.</p>
        <p>But the rebels are doggedly fighting back.</p>
        <p>''Now that the army is mopping up in Grozny, we have another wave of casualties,'' said Maj. Oleg E. Zayev, a military doctor from St. Petersburg and a senior member of Special Medical Team No. 600, which runs the tent hospital.</p>
        <p>Major Zayev said the vast majority of his patients were stabilized and whisked by helicopter to the rear for extended treatment. But a few minutes after he spoke, the rebels claimed another victim on a nearby hillside.</p>
        <p>Russian scouts scampered up a hill to check for snipers before inviting a small group of Russian and Western journalists to venture forward for a commanding view of the Staropromyslovsky district of Grozny, the scene of heavy street fighting.</p>
        <p>Going up the hill, the reporters passed a soldier who had just been shot through the neck and was being tended by paramedics. By the time the reporters marched down 40 minutes later, he was dead and his comrade was torn by grief.</p>
        <p>The mood among the soldiers was edgy. Dec. 31 is the fifth anniversary of the disastrous attack on Grozny, when Russian armored columns rushed into the center of the city only to be annihilated by rebels.</p>
        <p>The troops were worried that the militants might commemorate the date by mounting a counteroffensive. Some monitored a tactical radio, trying to intercept communications. As the soldiers tried to make out the chatter, trucks full of fresh troops drove toward Grozny for a chance to ''clean'' the city.</p>
        <p>Certainly there seemed to be little respite from the war at the hospital. Rumors of ghastly setbacks have circulated among the members of the medical team. Private Turkov said he had heard that the fighting in the city had been intense and that the bodies of troops had been taken out by the truckload.</p>
        <p>As he spoke, thunderous blasts of Russian artillery rippled through the hospital tents. Several batteries of Russian artillery are deployed a few hundred yards away, and they fired 122-millimeter shells over the tents toward Grozny.</p>
        <p>Pvt. Dmitri N. Kurochkin, 20, from southern Siberia, was wounded in the leg this morning near the Zavodskoi district, and he seemed too dazed to mind the artillery. His motorized infantry unit was never ordered to downtown. Its role was to secure the outskirts while Interior Ministry troops carried out the dirty business of mopping up. Even the suburbs, however, are dangerous.</p>
        <p>''I never actually go to Grozny,'' Private Kurochkin said. ''We were just outside Grozny for a week and half. I was in a trench, and there was a shot. I was the only one who was hit.''</p>
        <p>Another orderly, Sergei Shirokov, kept Private Kurochkin company while he waited to be helicoptered to the rear. Private Shirokov knows what the battle of Grozny is like. Eight days ago, he was driving a T-62 tank that was hit by a grenade in a firefight in the city. The tank filled with smoke, and the engine melted. But the crew stumbled out into the frigid street unhurt.</p>
        <p>Private Shirokov was hospitalized with bronchitis. When the short-handed hospital asked him to stay and help out, he jumped at the chance.</p>
        <p>''I was in Grozny many times,'' he said. ''We drive into a neighborhood where there are multistoried building. We shoot and leave. There are snipers, and it's really horrible. I don't want to go back.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Putin Visits the Troops</p>
        <p>MOSCOW, Saturday, Jan. 1 (Reuters) -- Acting President Vladimir V. Putin flew unexpectedly to a Russian-held town in Chechnya early today to award medals to troops and tell them their main aim was to keep the Russian Federation intact.</p>
        <p>''I want you to know that Russia highly appreciates what you are doing,'' Mr. Putin said in remarks to officers and soldiers that were televised live on television at around 6 a.m. on Saturday from Gudermes, east of Grozny.</p>
        <p>''This is not just about restoring the honor and dignity of Russia,'' he said, with his wife at his side. ''It is rather more important than that. It is about putting an end to the break-up of the Russian Federation. That is the main task. Russia is grateful to you.''</p>
        <p>''I wish you a happy New Year,'' said Mr. Putin, flanked by troops and dressed in a thick parka coat. ''I wish you happiness, all the very best. May you be healthy and your families well.''</p>
        <p>YELTSIN RESIGNS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
