<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Top, Still a Mystery: Vladimir Vladimirovich Putin</title>
    <meta content="Y01PUT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YELTSIN RESIGNS: MAN IN THE NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (Foreign)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chechnya (Russia)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Vladimir Vladimirovich Putin</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kgb (Soviet Security Police)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">putin, vladimir v (biographical sketch)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Chechnya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3DC1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Top, Still a Mystery: Vladimir Vladimirovich Putin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vladimir V Putin, prime minister and now acting president of Russia, remains a mystery; his public record is distinguished mostly by a popular but brutal war in Chechnya and a parliamentary election victory that, by most experts' reckoning, made a hash of democratic campaign norms; his private record conceals some 15 years with KGB, largely as an intelligence officer based in East Germany; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the Kremlin's newborn political party registered a thumping victory in parliamentary elections last week, reporters asked Prime Minister Vladimir V. Putin whether his strengthened hand might lead to changes in the government. Mr. Putin was characteristically forthcoming. ''We'll see,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That much Russia now sees, in spades. But in its new president's fashion, much about the man who now runs Russia, and who seems likely to win the suddenly scheduled election for the presidency in March, remains behind a veil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the Kremlin's newborn political party registered a thumping victory in parliamentary elections last week, reporters asked Prime Minister Vladimir V. Putin whether his strengthened hand might lead to changes in the government. Mr. Putin was characteristically forthcoming. ''We'll see,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That much Russia now sees, in spades. But in its new president's fashion, much about the man who now runs Russia, and who seems likely to win the suddenly scheduled election for the presidency in March, remains behind a veil.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin is extolled by admirers as the ideal man for Russia's darkest hour. He is, they say, for a strong Kremlin, but democratic to the marrow; dedicated to government economic controls, but pro-market; former President Boris N. Yeltsin's man, but apart from his infamous entourage of tycoons, schemers and supposed thieves.</p>
        <p>And that may all be true. But President Putin so far remains an empty vessel, his public record distinguished mostly by a popular but brutal war in Chechnya and an election victory this month which, by most experts' reckoning, made a hash of democratic campaign norms.</p>
        <p>His private record -- and much of it is private -- conceals some 15 years with the K.G.B., largely as an intelligence officer based in East Germany.</p>
        <p>''It's very difficult to say who he is. He's just a nicely wrapped package,'' Andre Piontkovsky, a political analyst and one of Mr. Putin's most merciless critics, said in an interview today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin, he suggested, may be the so-called ''Russian Pinochet'' -- a reference to the former dictator of Chile, Gen. Augusto Pinochet -- a kind of strongman that some liberal, democratic reformers now say they long for: a leader willing to wring the last czarist and Communist impulses out of the nation so that capitalism may come to full flower.</p>
        <p>But the man who may know Mr. Putin best, the former St. Petersburg mayor, Anatoly Sobchak, says that is simply wrongheaded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sobchak taught law to Mr. Putin at Leningrad State University nearly 30 years ago, and later recruited him to a mayoral team of democratic, pro-market activists.</p>
        <p>''Only fools and ignoramuses in Russia speak of Pinochet. They don't know who Pinochet is or what he did,'' he said in a telephone interview today. ''Putin is relying not on the army, but on political power. He's created his own political party. And he is planning to work through it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin certainly speaks the lines of a democratic reformer.</p>
        <p>''Modern Russian society does not identify a strong and effective state with a totalitarian state,'' he wrote in a newly published treatise on Russia at the cusp of the millennium. ''We have come to value the benefits of democracy, a law-based state, and personal and political freedom.''</p>
        <p>But ''at the same time,'' he added in the next sentence, ''people are alarmed by the obvious weakening of state power. The public looks forward to the restoration of the guiding and regulating role of the state to a degree which is necessary.''</p>
        <p>Deciphering Vladimir Vladimirovich Putin is not made any easier by the fact that his analysis is very likely correct on both counts.</p>
        <p>Trim, blue-eyed and balding, at 47 more resembling an actuary than a politician, Mr. Putin is by all counts an extremely competent, cautious and intelligent man. Born in Leningrad, later St. Petersburg, he graduated with honors in 1975 from Leningrad State University's law department, where he studied economic law under Mr. Sobchak.</p>
        <p>He did not become a lawyer. Instead, he joined the K.G.B.'s foreign intelligence arm, the First Chief Directorate, and by various reports, served in Moscow before being assigned to Dresden, then part of East Germany, in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>Officially -- and perhaps actually -- his task was to track the political leanings of East Germans and their contacts with the West.</p>
        <p>Unofficially, according to news reports and Mr. Sobchak, Mr. Putin was involved in economic intelligence gathering, perhaps the K.G.B.'s central task in the 1980's as the Soviet economic engine began throwing rods and lurching toward collapse.</p>
        <p>He returned to Leningrad in 1989, speaking fluent German and steeped in Western business knowledge, and left active K.G.B. service to join the university's international affairs department. Then and now, many speculated that Colonel Putin actually remained a K.G.B. operative and that his job was to monitor the city's flourishing democratic reform movement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sobchak, a leader of that movement, was by then chairman of the Soviet equivalent of the Leningrad legislature, and he hired Mr. Putin as an aide. When Mr. Sobchak became mayor in June 1991, Mr. Putin followed him into city government, steadily rising to the post of first deputy mayor.</p>
        <p>He was widely known then as ''the gray cardinal,'' a reference not just to his influence but also to his penchant for remaining out of public view. And he played a key role in bringing Western investors to the city, signing the American firm  KPMG to advise officials on economic policy and luring Germany's BNP-Dresdner Bank to set up offices there.</p>
        <p>In a television interview today, Sergei V. Stepashin, a former Russian prime minister, now a Russian Parliament deputy from St. Petersburg, said Mr. Putin had another nickname: ''Stasi,'' after the feared East German secret service.</p>
        <p>''In outside appearance, he is a calm, inconspicuous, quiet man,'' he told the television network NTV. ''But his grip, which was felt by all the financiers in St. Petersburg, was amazing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sobchak lost a re-election bid in 1996, but Mr. Putin continued to rise, apparently brought to Moscow and the Kremlin by another St. Petersburg reformer, Anatoly B. Chubais.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's first Kremlin job was as a top aide to Pavel Borodin, the Kremlin property manager who is now at the center of bribery and corruption charges surrounding the vastly expensive renovation of Mr. Yeltsin's residence and other official buildings.</p>
        <p>He rose swiftly through the ranks, first overseeing the implementation of Mr. Yeltsin's presidential decrees, then becoming head in 1998 of the K.G.B.'s successor, the Federal Security Service, with a mandate to focus on economic intelligence.</p>
        <p>By March, he was head of Mr. Yeltsin's security council, responsible for internal security and national defense. On Aug. 9, he replaced Mr. Stepashin as prime minister and Mr. Yeltsin's heir-apparent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's political potential was dismissed from the start, but wrongly. His aggressive pursuit of the war in Chechnya, which followed the bombings of five buildings in Moscow and other cities, blamed on terrorists, established his image as a tough and no-nonsense leader at a time when Russians were seeking just such a person.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Putin, a refined man by any standards, pointedly said last fall that he would wipe out Chechen rebels even if they were killed in their toilets -- a vulgar piece of Russian army slang -- he began to rocket upward in the polls. By this month, nearly half of the respondents in some polls favored him as Mr. Yeltsin's successor, an astronomical figure in a nation where a politician with a 20 percent rating is considered a comer.</p>
        <p>But whether Mr. Putin was the originator or the beneficiary of such shrewdness is less easily gauged. As a politician, his record is mixed: he was one of the leaders of Mr. Sobchak's losing mayoral campaign, and he oversaw a lackluster parliamentary campaign in the mid-1990's as a local leader of the pro-Yeltsin political party Our Home Is Russia.</p>
        <p>As prime minister, he has benefited not just from the war and the patriotic fervor enveloping it, but from an economic comeback propelled by a rise in world oil prices and a devalued ruble.</p>
        <p>The Kremlin's new Unity party is widely agreed to have performed so well in December's parliamentary elections because its candidates rode the coattails of Mr. Putin's popularity and because the Kremlin waged a war of character assassination, disinformation and manipulation against its principal rivals.</p>
        <p>None of this says much about what kind of president Mr. Putin will be when, and if, he is elected and becomes leader of a vast nation on his own right rather than by fiat of his predecessor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sobchak has no doubts. ''Together with Putin, I went through two putsches, in '91 and '93, and I know how he carried himself during these trials. This is a completely courageous person on whom one can rely, and who would never deceive you,'' he said. ''He does indeed have democratic views regarding the future of the country. But he understands very well that such a country as Russia requires strong power. Without such a power, Russia will stop existing as a unified state.''</p>
        <p>YELTSIN RESIGNS: MAN IN THE NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
