<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stanford Hopes To Follow Path Wisconsin Cut</title>
    <meta content="01ROSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rose Bowl (Football Game)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stanford University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Wisconsin</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gurnick, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E5D71338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stanford Hopes To Follow Path Wisconsin Cut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN GURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gurnick, Ken</byline>
      <dateline>PASADENA, Calif., Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on upcoming Rose Bowl between Stanford and Wisconsin; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Going into Saturday's 86th Rose Bowl, there is great uncertainty about the playing status of Troy Walters, the Stanford all-American receiver, defensive lineman Willie Howard and center Mike McLaughlin. It is unclear, too, whether Coach Barry Alvarez of Wisconsin, recovering from knee replacement, will man the sideline or coach from the press box.</p>
        <p>But this much is certain: Ron Dayne, Wisconsin's Heisman Trophy winner and the National Collegiate Athletic Association's career rushing leader, will be handed the ball early and often in his Badger farewell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Going into Saturday's 86th Rose Bowl, there is great uncertainty about the playing status of Troy Walters, the Stanford all-American receiver, defensive lineman Willie Howard and center Mike McLaughlin. It is unclear, too, whether Coach Barry Alvarez of Wisconsin, recovering from knee replacement, will man the sideline or coach from the press box.</p>
        <p>But this much is certain: Ron Dayne, Wisconsin's Heisman Trophy winner and the National Collegiate Athletic Association's career rushing leader, will be handed the ball early and often in his Badger farewell.</p>
        <p>And Stanford must find a way to stop him.</p>
        <p>''As I've said all week, no one to my knowledge has stopped Ron Dayne,'' said Coach Tyrone Willingham of Stanford, who is hoping to become the first black head coach to win a Rose Bowl.</p>
        <p>The presence of Dayne has helped make the No. 21-ranked Cardinal a heavy underdog to the No. 4-ranked Badgers, but Willingham and his players consider it an advantage and offer last year's Rose Bowl as proof.</p>
        <p>In that game, Wisconsin was supposedly going to be outmanned by U.C.L.A. The Badgers were called ''the worst team to ever play in the Rose Bowl'' by one television commentator the week before the game. Then Dayne gained 246 yards and scored 4 touchdowns as Wisconsin pulled off a 38-31 upset. Afterward, the Badgers delighted in having proved the experts wrong.</p>
        <p>''When you're the underdog and people take shots at you, it makes you stay focused and be more determined,'' Alvarez said.</p>
        <p>Now Wisconsin (9-2) can become the first Big Ten school to win consecutive Rose Bowls (the conference had a no-repeat rule from 1946 to 1960) by beating Stanford (8-3), a team that  Alvarez has compared to last year's U.C.L.A. team and to the Michigan team that beat Wisconsin this season, 21-16.</p>
        <p>Psychologically, Dayne sees why Stanford might look at last year's Rose Bowl for motivation. ''Last year we were in the position that Stanford is in this year -- a lot of people are saying they are the worst team or that they don't belong here,'' he said. ''But you have to be good to make it to the Rose Bowl, so I don't understand why people say that.''</p>
        <p>Alvarez said he reminded his team how it turned public skepticism into an advantage a year ago, but he cannot control the affect such talk has on Stanford, a two-touchdown underdog.</p>
        <p>''The point spread is ridiculous,'' Stanford quarterback Todd Husak said. ''A lack of respect is nothing new to us. We know what it's like to play as an underdog. We know how to respond to that.''</p>
        <p>The Cardinal coach most responsible for stopping Dayne is the defensive coordinator, Kent Baer, whose maligned defense is ranked 110th in the N.C.A.A. and 58th against the run.</p>
        <p>''I don't think they respect us at all from what I've heard from people who have called me and read what's been written in Wisconsin,'' Baer said of the Badgers.</p>
        <p>To overcome a 52-point crushing by Texas and an equally embarrassing loss to San Jose State, Stanford earned its Rose Bowl trip with a big-play offense that thought it lost its biggest playmaker, Walters, to a dislocated wrist in a mishap at Tuesday's practice.</p>
        <p>But Stanford has been wily -- some might say deceptive -- about discussing player injuries. After originally ruling out Walters, Willingham today threw around phrases like ''holding the window open,'' implying Walters might shed the soft cast and play after all.</p>
        <p>''We don't know,'' Willingham said. ''If he plays, we are talking about actually participating and having a vital role in the game.''</p>
        <p>Willingham conceded that his staff has been optimistic all week about Howard's availability, despite issuing pessimistic reports.</p>
        <p>As for McLaughlin, Willingham said the center had suffered a potentially serious knee injury early in the week, and that if he does not play, it would ''affect us tremendously.''</p>
        <p>Healthy or not, Stanford must do something to counter the 5-foot-10-inch, 252-pound Dayne, as well as teammates like the redshirt freshman quarterback Brooks Bollinger and cornerback Jamar Fletcher, who leads the defense.</p>
        <p>Dayne's breakout game as a freshman came Sept. 21, 1996, against Stanford. He gained 75 yards on 10 carries in a 14-0 victory, the only shutout of Stanford in the last nine years. Perhaps that will turn into just one more insult to motivate the Cardinal.  COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
