<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As the 'American Century' Extends Its Run,</title>
    <meta content="01USAA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: POWER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2D61530F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As the 'American Century' Extends Its Run,</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. Apple Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>R W Apple Jr article on the prospects for America retaining its global power into the new century; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was Henry Luce, as every red-blooded Yankee knows, who christened the 20th the American Century. He proved to be right, but that was not necessarily obvious throughout the 100 years.</p>
        <p>At the start, the United States largely absented itself from the world stage. The collapse of world capitalism, a system then as now closely identified with the United States, raised grave doubts in the 1930's, and the rise of Japan undermined American economic confidence for anxious moments in the 1980's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was Henry Luce, as every red-blooded Yankee knows, who christened the 20th the American Century. He proved to be right, but that was not necessarily obvious throughout the 100 years.</p>
        <p>At the start, the United States largely absented itself from the world stage. The collapse of world capitalism, a system then as now closely identified with the United States, raised grave doubts in the 1930's, and the rise of Japan undermined American economic confidence for anxious moments in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>In the geopolitical sphere, the outcomes of the great struggles against fascism and communism did not seem nearly as inevitable before the fact as they seem now.</p>
        <p>Those ups and downs are worth remembering as we sit on the cusp of the 21st century, having just crossed President Clinton's bridge from the old millennium to the new. Today, America bestrides the world. In strategic terms, it is the only superpower. Its economy is the most powerful. Its language, its popular culture (from jeans to burgers to films) and its preferred model of free-market democracy make new converts daily.</p>
        <p>We have come to see this as the culmination of a naturally occurring process, not unlike the Marxists who saw the rise of communism as the preordained consequence of a scientific process. We, or most of us, expect United States dominance to continue for the foreseeable future. We expect several more American Decades, if not an American Century, version 2.0.</p>
        <p>''Our technological leadership and the size of our economy give us every chance to maintain our position,'' said Lloyd Cutler, Washington wise man, superlawyer and adviser to Democratic presidents. ''We are the only country in the world that can settle its debts in its own currency. When times are tense and money seeks a safe harbor, it comes to America.''</p>
        <p>The American capacity for continual self-renewal -- as contrasted, for example, with Japan's rigidity -- bodes well for the future. It is related, many believe, to the nation's openness to immigration, and to the physical and social mobility, as contrasted with much of Europe, that encourages entrepreneurship and makes bootstrap success an everyday phenomenon.</p>
        <p>But much, as always, depends upon the quality of leadership.</p>
        <p>''The greatest threat to our world role is us,'' said David Abshire, a veteran of Republican administrations who runs the Center for Strategic and International Studies in Washington. ''Our political system has clearly gone wrong. With continued dominance by money and single-issue lobbies, will we be able to attract talented people to public office? Will we hit a period like the one after Lincoln's assassination and have a series of second-rate presidents?''</p>
        <p>Critics of the United States, like John Gray, the English scholar, already see signs of frailty, such as the fraying of family life and the resort to ''mass incarceration'' as a means of controlling crime. It remains to be seen, others suggest, whether Americans can retain a sense of social cohesion as the economy becomes ever more driven by technology, threatening to divide the haves ever more sharply from the have-nots just as major states like California and Texas head toward white-minority status.</p>
        <p>In terms of its relationship with other countries, the United States may be more secure than any nation in history, largely because of geography, the nuclear deterrent and the relative weakness of potential adversaries. China has not even begun to resolve the contradictions between its economic and political systems. Russia is a mess. A unified, coherent Europe remains a dream, and even if it comes closer to reality, it is not likely to confront the United States. Try to beat Boeing with Airbuses, certainly; build a unified defense force, perhaps. But turn sharply away from shared values? Not likely.</p>
        <p>That is not to say, however, that United States power will continue unchallenged, particularly if Washington, with its heavy hand, tries to assert or expand American hegemony -- if it gives in to the inevitable temptation of the big guy to play the bully. The refusal until recently of the United States to pay its United Nations dues; American insistence that its troops will never serve under a foreign commander; and American second thoughts about a ballistic missile defense system and the nuclear test ban treaty -- all of these developments and more have begun to produce European calls for action to rein in the United States.</p>
        <p>The French foreign minister, Hubert Vedrine, said recently, ''We cannot accept either a politically unipolar world, nor a culturally uniform world, nor the unilateralism of a single hyper-power.'' The Germans and Russians have made similar criticisms of the United States lately.</p>
        <p>''The more the United States tries to run the world, the more the United States will alienate its friends and unite its rivals,'' Samuel Huntington of Harvard University wrote in the quarterly Foreign Affairs. ''The world's only superpower is automatically a threat to other major powers.''</p>
        <p>Richard N. Haass, director of foreign policy studies at the Brookings Institution, argues that an erosion in American power is inevitable. Any attempt to dominate, he said, inevitably ''would lack domestic support and stimulate international resistance, which in turn would make the costs of hegemony all the greater and its benefits all the smaller.''</p>
        <p>BUT what, as a practical matter, could other nations do about it? Form alliances, for one thing, and that is what many scholars expect to happen in the decades to come.</p>
        <p>Ronald Steel of the University of Southern California expects to see a multipolar world, with the United States, ''probably the European Union and maybe some sort of Asian combination, like Japan and China,'' competing on the world stage. The challenge for American policy, of course, will be to see that the competition is not destructive.</p>
        <p>But there is a larger challenge. Achieving a balance of power among groups of states, like that which prevailed in the 19th century, will not be enough in the 21st. Power is more diffuse, wielded not only by nations but by terrorists like Osama bin Laden; supranational bodies like the World Trade Organization, which excited such animosity during the trade talks in Seattle; the worldwide stock and bond markets and the global mass media.</p>
        <p>A commission headed by former Senators Gary Hart and Warren B. Rudman has been studying the possibilities of trouble caused by failures of leadership, terrorist attacks or assaults against what they called ''an increasingly integrated and complex but highly vulnerable international economic system.'' In a first report issued in September, the commission concluded: ''For many years to come Americans will become increasingly less secure, and much less secure than they now believe themselves to be.''</p>
        <p>The same thing said 100 years ago, whether by Americans or the Britons who then ruled the waves, might have evoked laughter. But then who could have predicted the calamity of 1914 and the vast consequences that flowed from it?</p>
        <p>VISIONS: POWER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
