<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking Back, With an Eye to the Future</title>
    <meta content="01INDI$27" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: INDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dugger, Celia W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malhotra, Balraj</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aggarwal, Rasika</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5DE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking Back, With an Eye to the Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Celia W. Dugger</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dugger, Celia W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Balraj Malhotra, 71, recalls how he experienced throes of India's independence and partition, while Rasika Aggarwal, a 21-year-old teacher, describes her hope for the future; photos; chronology of India's history in 20th century (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For India, the last century was bisected into a before and after on Aug. 15, 1947, the day the British Indian empire gained its independence and was divided into Islamic Pakistan and overwhelmingly Hindu but secular India.</p>
        <p>Among those alive then -- people like Balraj Malhotra, 71 -- the idea of nationhood will forever be haunted by the carnage between Hindus and Sikhs on the one hand and Muslims on the other. Hundreds of thousands of people were murdered; millions became refugees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For India, the last century was bisected into a before and after on Aug. 15, 1947, the day the British Indian empire gained its independence and was divided into Islamic Pakistan and overwhelmingly Hindu but secular India.</p>
        <p>Among those alive then -- people like Balraj Malhotra, 71 -- the idea of nationhood will forever be haunted by the carnage between Hindus and Sikhs on the one hand and Muslims on the other. Hundreds of thousands of people were murdered; millions became refugees.</p>
        <p>But for many of the four-fifths of India's billion people born since that terrible moment, the violent shadow of Partition has largely lifted. For the young, independence and freedom are simply givens of life. And many urban, middle-class women like Rasika Aggarwal, 21, have a sense of possibility that was beyond that of their mothers and grandmothers.</p>
        <p>Still, the hatreds unleashed between India and Pakistan more than half a century ago continue to threaten to plunge the subcontinent into war -- a sobering prospect now that both are building nuclear arsenals.</p>
        <p>CELIA W. DUGGER</p>
        <p>BALRAJ MALHOTRA</p>
        <p>I am from a small town in Pakistan. The place is Malkwal. We were forced to leave right after 15th August, 1947, Independence Day. Most of Malkwal was Hindu. The whole town was surrounded by Muslims. We saw crowds of men carrying swords, daggers and spears. They were shouting, ''God is great! Kill the Hindus!'' They looted and burned the houses and humiliated the ladies. The young, beautiful girls were kidnapped and raped.</p>
        <p>My father was a bank manager in a small branch, and the Muslims respected him. They looted the bank but didn't harm us. My father used to give loans without security. He had been very kind.</p>
        <p>All the Hindus were moved to a camp near the police station, then to a cotton factory. It was arranged to move us by train to India. We huddled, 30 people in compartments meant for 10. We were reluctant to get on the train, afraid they might take us somewhere to kill us, but there was no choice.</p>
        <p>It was devastation from our town to Lahore, dead bodies lying all over, thousands, thousands. We saw a train moving alongside ours full of butchered bodies. The windows were open. Some people were still alive, crying. I did not know whether we would reach Amritsar or meet the same fate as these people.</p>
        <p>But we did. The roads were choked with people. All over, tents were being erected. Then we came to Delhi, the center of the country. There was no work, nothing to eat except from charity. For us, independence was overshadowed by the miseries we had been through.</p>
        <p>We said: ''Is this independence? When a man has nothing to eat, nowhere to live? If this is independence, we were better off under foreign rule.''</p>
        <p>But time is the biggest healer.</p>
        <p>We were quite young. We sold a little of the gold we'd carried on our bodies and managed to buy one or two rickshaws that we hired out to pullers on daily wages. I started working in a fountain pen shop. The owner was a Congress Party politician. He knew a minister in the local Delhi government very well. He said, ''This is my man, and I want him to be given a shop.'' Khan Market had opened in 1949 for refugees. I started a bookshop in 1953.</p>
        <p>We realized this was the place we had to live and stand on our own feet. We should forget what we were before Partition. Now we are quite happy. We are better off financially, and we have a broader outlook in Delhi. In our small native place, we knew nothing about the world.</p>
        <p>I would still say that Hindus and Muslims by and large were not against each other. All these conflicts are created by the politicians or the religious people for their own gain. A normal citizen is interested only in a decent living: shelter above his head, education for his children, food for the family.</p>
        <p>RASIKA AGGARWAL</p>
        <p>We've always been told India is a free country. It came to me as a free country. I think life is improving day by day. Tomorrow should be better than today.</p>
        <p>Everybody's coming up with something new. I never thought of working when I was in school. I always thought I'd get married and be a housewife like my grandmother and mother. But after college I started teaching and now I feel so good I don't want to sit idle. It's not the money, it's the satisfaction.</p>
        <p>You feel your independence. I want to marry someone who will let me work. I don't want to lose my independence.</p>
        <p>My grandmother used to tell me she wasn't permitted to go out. From childhood, she did not have that much of freedom. Now, if I want to go out, I don't have to ask for permission. Once or twice a week, I go with friends to dinner, a disco, a pub. That's party time. My grandmother's pretty curious about it, and happy, too.</p>
        <p>I hear my mother telling me about what she wasn't allowed to do. She loved to paint and wanted to take a career, but she wasn't permitted to do so. Today, when I tell her I want to be a teacher, she encourages me.</p>
        <p>I would love to have a daughter. And she'll have a better life than me.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: INDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
