<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Invades the Pantry</title>
    <meta content="01EGGG$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: BIOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eggs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE0DD1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Invades the Pantry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Barnaby J. Feder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rice, milk, produce, eggs and corn that have been improved through genetic engeering or more traditional tools of biotechnology will be available in early years of 21st century; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>So far, most of the inventions of agricultural biotechnology have been new weapons for farmers in their fight against insects and weeds. A few make processes like making cheese more efficient. One big seller, a cow hormone produced in genetically altered bacteria, increases milk production.</p>
        <p>But many consumers think that there may be unacceptable health and environmental risks in biotechnology. The food industry is under pressure to show  that it can produce not just more food, but also food so obviously improved that the benefits to consumers clearly outweigh any risks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>So far, most of the inventions of agricultural biotechnology have been new weapons for farmers in their fight against insects and weeds. A few make processes like making cheese more efficient. One big seller, a cow hormone produced in genetically altered bacteria, increases milk production.</p>
        <p>But many consumers think that there may be unacceptable health and environmental risks in biotechnology. The food industry is under pressure to show  that it can produce not just more food, but also food so obviously improved that the benefits to consumers clearly outweigh any risks.</p>
        <p>Researchers say an impressive array of such products will become available in just a few years. Some will be the result of the kind of biotechnology that makes consumers most nervous -- namely, moving genes between organisms that would never mate naturally. Others will be created through traditional breeding and food production.</p>
        <p>BARNABY J. FEDER</p>
        <p>Rice</p>
        <p>THE ALTERATION:  Enriched with beta carotene, which the body converts into vitamin A.</p>
        <p>HOW IT'S DONE: Three genes -- two from the daffodil and one from a bacterium -- are inserted into the rice.</p>
        <p>THE BENEFITS: Would reduce the one million deaths of children and millions of cases of blindness that are attributed to vitamin A deficiency in developing countries each year.</p>
        <p>WHEN AVAILABLE: In 2003, to farmers.</p>
        <p>THE RESEARCHERS: The Institute of Plant Sciences in Zurich and the International Rice Research Institute in Los Banos, the Philippines, which will coordinate breeding and distribution.</p>
        <p>Milk</p>
        <p>THE ALTERATION: Elimination of the most common allergen.</p>
        <p>HOW IT'S DONE: Exposure to an enzyme during processing breaks down beta lactoglobulin, the allergenic protein that occurs naturally in milk.</p>
        <p>THE BENEFITS: Would help the 1 in 20 children with this allergy avoid vomiting and diarrhea; would reduce the risk of occasional deaths from the allergy.</p>
        <p>WHEN AVAILABLE: In 2005, to consumers.</p>
        <p>THE RESEARCHERS: Basic research led by Bob B. Buchanan at the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>Produce</p>
        <p>THE ALTERATION:  Adding vaccines for diseases like hepatitis B.</p>
        <p>HOW IT'S DONE: Viral genes are inserted into the seeds.</p>
        <p>THE BENEFITS: Would replace injections with a cheaper, more convenient means of distributing vaccines.</p>
        <p>WHEN AVAILABLE: In 2005, probably first in powdered potatoes and tomatoes.</p>
        <p>THE RESEARCHERS: Initial research by Charles J. Arntzen and Hugh Mason of Cornell University's Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research Inc.</p>
        <p>Eggs</p>
        <p>THE ALTERATION: Enriched with appetite-reducing antibodies.</p>
        <p>HOW IT'S DONE: Hens are immunized to stimulate the production of antibodies that activate peptides in the human digestive system associated with feeling full.</p>
        <p>THE BENEFITS: Healthier, cheaper weight-reduction regimens.</p>
        <p>WHEN AVAILABLE: In 2005, to consumers</p>
        <p>THE RESEARCHER: Initial research by Mark E. Cook at the University of Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>Corn</p>
        <p>THE ALTERATION: Conversion to polyester.</p>
        <p>HOW IT'S DONE: Bacterial genes are inserted into yeast so that the end product in the fermentation of corn sugar is trimethylene glycol, a building block of high-performance polyesters</p>
        <p>THE BENEFITS: A biodegradable, easily recyclable polyester that is too expensive to make with current technology.</p>
        <p>WHEN AVAILABLE: In 2004, for use in upholstery, carpeting and clothing.</p>
        <p>THE RESEARCHERS: Scientists at the DuPont Company.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: BIOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
