<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; Penny Serenade</title>
    <meta content="01DOWD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DA1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; Penny Serenade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd column chronicles 20th century through life of her mother, who was born in 1908 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a penny, you could buy The New York Times on June 2, 1908, and read these stories on the front page:</p>
        <p>The Mauretania beat the record of the Lusitania for fastest ocean crossing. Wilbur Wright got an offer of $100,000 for his flying machine. Teddy Roosevelt was jousting with Panama over the canal. A young, beautiful ''gray-garbed'' ghost was haunting the governor's mansion in Georgia. And big news from Philadelphia: ''Mrs. Frank Gould has lost several expensive gowns which she brought to this city to attend the Horse Show.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a penny, you could buy The New York Times on June 2, 1908, and read these stories on the front page:</p>
        <p>The Mauretania beat the record of the Lusitania for fastest ocean crossing. Wilbur Wright got an offer of $100,000 for his flying machine. Teddy Roosevelt was jousting with Panama over the canal. A young, beautiful ''gray-garbed'' ghost was haunting the governor's mansion in Georgia. And big news from Philadelphia: ''Mrs. Frank Gould has lost several expensive gowns which she brought to this city to attend the Horse Show.''</p>
        <p>My mother, Margaret Meenehan, was born on that distant day, before cellophane, airplane fatalities, rap and the Gap. I asked her to sum up 100 years in 500 words:</p>
        <p>1900-1909: ''I learned to eat solid food.''</p>
        <p>1910-1920: ''Washington was a small Southern village with horses and carriages. My father managed my uncle's bar, Meenehan's. There was a side entrance that said 'Ladies Only.' But women never really drank until Prohibition. We got one of the earliest automobiles in Washington, a black, seven-passenger Reo touring car. You had to crank it. We were also one of the first to have a telephone. My friend Betty didn't have a phone. So I would call her friends down the street who did, and they would run up to her house.</p>
        <p>''During World War I, we would go out every Sunday for a drive around Arlington Cemetery and look at the thousands of crosses. The Germans used mustard gas. It blistered our boys' lungs. Pat McGuinn, a suitor of your Aunt Greta, was gassed.''</p>
        <p>1920-1930. ''In January 1922, the roof of the Knickerbocker movie theater collapsed under the snow. There were snowbanks taller than I was. Ninety-eight people died watching a George M. Cohan comedy. A girl in my class, the brightest one, was killed. We prayed for her the next morning at Mass.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to be a flapper. But my mother was very strict. I couldn't go to fraternity houses. And she wouldn't let me ask college boys home to dinner. Boys would go out with anybody for a home-cooked meal.</p>
        <p>''We all liked Rudolph Valentino and Mary Pickford. Before a movie started, they would put a sign up on the screen: 'Ladies, please remove your hats.' We never understood what happened with Fatty Arbuckle and that girl.''</p>
        <p>1930-1940: ''One night when your father was working, I went to the drugstore. There was a nice gentleman with a mustache there named Max Factor. He was just starting his business and wanted to demonstrate his makeup. He told me to put the lipstick on the upper lip first, then press into the bottom lip to make an impression. I didn't have enough money to buy anything. He was just killing an evening, too.</p>
        <p>''I was alone on an elevator once with J. Edgar Hoover. I never believed he wore dresses. He looked very masculine.''</p>
        <p>1940-1950: ''Bananas were very scarce during the war. There was a fella who worked in the A.&amp;P. produce department. Whenever a shipment came in, he would meet me in the liquor store across from the Sheraton Hotel and give me bananas.</p>
        <p>''It was exciting but overcrowded during the war. We moved three kids into one bedroom and took in roomers, some Pentagon meteorologists.</p>
        <p>''The kids went to bed listening to 'The Shadow' and 'The Lone Ranger' on the radio. Then, in 1948, we got a seven-inch used television set with a magnifier. Mike and I stayed up all night watching when Truman won. Later we rearranged the dinner hour so we'd be through in time for 'Dragnet' and 'Milton Berle.' Radio had better morals.''</p>
        <p>1950-1960: ''I was at a party at the Capitol. I met Jack Kennedy. He was very attractive, coppery hair. Neat, like he just came out of a bandbox.</p>
        <p>''In 1952 your father brought me home a dryer for your diapers.''</p>
        <p>1960-1970: ''It was unruly. There were riots and they shut down Glen Echo, the amusement park. I wore my first pantsuit and my first pantyhose. I never owned jeans. In my immediate circle, nothing changed with feminism. Even before that movement, I had never felt cramped. I never went outside the house to work. Your father thought women belonged in the kitchen. But I didn't mind 'cause I liked the kitchen. I just wish mine had been bigger.''</p>
        <p>1970-1980: ''I was glad when polyester came along. I would love anything you didn't have to iron.''</p>
        <p>1980-1990: ''I loved Patrick Swayze in 'Dirty Dancing.' I didn't care much for yuppies. They were pretentious.''</p>
        <p>1990-2000: ''I feel sorry for Clinton. He reminds me of myself, wanting so much to be liked. I think Monica is very pretty. And Hillary looks great.</p>
        <p>''How does the Web work?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
