<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking Back, With an Eye to the Future</title>
    <meta content="01DETR$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: DETROIT, U.S.A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unionization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Khalilah A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bardelli, Alfred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meredith, Robyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unionization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking Back, With an Eye to the Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Keith Bradsher and Robyn Meredith</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meredith, Robyn; Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alfred Bardelli, 91, sole surviving member of negotating team that concluded United Auto Workers' first contract with Ford Motor Co in 1941, says workers went through hell at Ford until contract was signed; Khalilah A Johnson, 23-year-old attending job-training classes for 12 hours a day, says she intends to rise out of poverty and become a Ford engineer; chronology of milestones in auto industry history (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The enormous growth and subsequent unionization of the auto industry created opportunities for millions of Americans to enter the middle class. Alfred Bardelli, whose family immigrated from Italy to a Pennsylvania coal town 10 months after his birth in 1909, began cutting glass for windows in 1928 at Ford Motor's Rouge complex in Dearborn, near Detroit. It was the world's largest factory then, with 103,000 workers. He joined the United Automobile Workers in 1937, a time of violent clashes between union organizers and company security personnel. He is the sole surviving member of the negotiating team that concluded the U.A.W.'s first contract with Ford in 1941.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The enormous growth and subsequent unionization of the auto industry created opportunities for millions of Americans to enter the middle class. Alfred Bardelli, whose family immigrated from Italy to a Pennsylvania coal town 10 months after his birth in 1909, began cutting glass for windows in 1928 at Ford Motor's Rouge complex in Dearborn, near Detroit. It was the world's largest factory then, with 103,000 workers. He joined the United Automobile Workers in 1937, a time of violent clashes between union organizers and company security personnel. He is the sole surviving member of the negotiating team that concluded the U.A.W.'s first contract with Ford in 1941.</p>
        <p>Khalilah A. Johnson, 23, works and attends classes for 12 hours a day at Focus: Hope, a nonprofit group in Detroit that provides job training. She also has custody of her nephew, 6, and her niece, 4, waking up at 4 a.m. every morning to drop them off at day care by 5:30 and clock in at Focus: Hope's factory by 5:45. Ms. Johnson plans to have earned a bachelor's degree in manufacturing engineering by December 2001. Then, she said, she'll begin her rise out of poverty as so many other Detroiters have in past decades: she'll work for an auto company, and she has her heart set on Ford.</p>
        <p>KEITH BRADSHER AND ROBYN MEREDITH</p>
        <p>ALFRED BARDELLI</p>
        <p>We talked Italian in my house until I was 12, and then my mother said, ''No more Italian in the house, we're going to speak English.'' When I was 17, we worked seven months in the coal mines in order to get our families out because they were shutting down. You had to dig on your knees with a pick and then take all that coal out. With my brother-in-law, we got enough money to get our family out here, to Michigan.</p>
        <p>Ford was the lousiest place to work in the country. The bosses were pushing, pushing, pushing. They'd borrow money, say ''We'll pay you back on payday,'' and come payday they'd say, ''You're lucky I keep you on the job.''</p>
        <p>We kicked the hell out of a lot of guys, the company goons. They were coming in trying to disturb our picket lines, and the more they disturbed our picket lines, the more they got beat up.</p>
        <p>You wanted a drink of water, you had to ask the foreman. What kind of life is this? After the union, we could go get a drink when we wanted.</p>
        <p>Ford brought a bunch of guys from down South, they were all black, to break our union, you know, give them our jobs and all, and break the union. A lot of people, they hate blacks, they hate every nationality, they even hated me as an Italian. A guy told me, ''Go back where you came from'' when I was 11 years old.</p>
        <p>You ought to have seen this place in 1941, it was just black with clouds. I don't think we have any pollution here now, hardly. We may have a little, yes. When the powerhouse was in operation, they had a constant plume of black smoke.</p>
        <p>They were the rottenest outfit to work for. I still hate them and I was the first negotiator.</p>
        <p>I don't trust them, I don't trust the Ford Motor Company. What we had to go through from 1928 to 1941, until we got our union, why, I went through hell there.</p>
        <p>This union, U.A.W., doesn't owe Bardelli anything. I thank the U.A.W. for everything I now have, and I hope everyone joins the union.</p>
        <p>KHALILAH A. JOHNSON</p>
        <p>By the time I have grandchildren, Detroit is going to be all new. The houses are going to look different, the people are going to have a different mind-set.</p>
        <p>Others? They have different views of Detroit than I have. They feel that Detroit is hopeless, that it is going to corrupt their children. I feel like if your children are going to be corrupted, they're going to be corrupted because of you. My big house is going to be in Detroit.</p>
        <p>You can just see the hope in everybody's eyes at Focus: Hope. Where I grew up around here, it's like the houses are just terrible, most of them are condemned, you have nothing to look forward to. The mothers are usually working jobs at McDonald's, making enough to pay the baby sitters. There's not really much to look at.</p>
        <p>But when you come here, it's like you see African-American engineers, and it says, ''I can do that.'' That could be me.</p>
        <p>More and more African-Americans are becoming engineers, but we still have white Americans in those positions also. I think it is going to be more equal. It's cool because you have to have diversity. If I just came and I just saw my particular race in power, then I would start probably looking negatively on the other race, like maybe they aren't as good.</p>
        <p>I want to be a design engineer, or a quality engineer. But I don't want to do that for too long. I want to make enough money so I can start my own business -- real estate -- and I want to start a modeling agency.</p>
        <p>It's nice to be a part of a union, but I'm not looking at me being unionized or a union member.</p>
        <p>I just want to make my name known, be a part of the company and be great at whatever I do. Whatever it is. No one in my family is a part of a union.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: DETROIT, U.S.A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
