<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the City's Bunker, Much Ado About Not Much as the Celebrations Proceed</title>
    <meta content="MB021926" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: A PEACEFUL PARTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4DA1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the City's Bunker, Much Ado About Not Much as the Celebrations Proceed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The city's $13 million crisis center suddenly fell to a hush. Dozens of beefy officials wearing uniforms or windbreakers or suits -- the mark of real power -- stood up from behind their computer consoles and stared in awed silence at what the video monitors were showing.</p>
        <p>They, themselves,were on TV, in the background of the latest briefing for the media. What was being said was much less interesting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The city's $13 million crisis center suddenly fell to a hush. Dozens of beefy officials wearing uniforms or windbreakers or suits -- the mark of real power -- stood up from behind their computer consoles and stared in awed silence at what the video monitors were showing.</p>
        <p>They, themselves,were on TV, in the background of the latest briefing for the media. What was being said was much less interesting.</p>
        <p>As midnight drew near, the city's preparations for a New Year's Eve disaster were beginning to look almost like overkill, at least as viewed from the inside of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's so-called bunker, the hardened command and communications center billed as able to withstand most bullets, some bombs and all bugs -- the year 2000 kind.</p>
        <p>Fears of widespread computer, power and electronic-system failures around the world had fizzled, leaving the mayor's aides to relay the most mundane incidents, like a cut chain-link fence at an electrical substation in Jamaica, Queens. (It was garden-variety criminal mischief, not an attempt at sabotage, officials said.)</p>
        <p>At an early evening briefing, Mr. Giuliani said there had been more bomb threats than usual yesterday -- 16, as compared with 9 on the average day -- but that all had been checked out immediately and ''proved bogus.''</p>
        <p>Jerome Hauer, director of the office of emergency management, and Deputy Mayor Joseph Lhota said at 11 p.m. that there were no more police and emergency medical service calls than usual, that banks were reporting no greater use of automated teller machines than usual, and that the higher-than-usual temperature in Times Square had left the city's medical stations underused.</p>
        <p>With so little in the way of emergencies to manage, officials in the bunker exasperated the 75 or so journalists watching through a glass wall yesterday by repeatedly lowering a screen installed to block any view. Only when television reporters went live, and when the mayor appeared, did the screen get raised.</p>
        <p>Asked what secret business was being conducted behind the screen, Mr. Lhota joked that he did not know -- he was in an adjoining room, smoking cigarettes.</p>
        <p>But when Sen. Charles Schumer appeared in the press room just after midnight, the screen was abruptly lowered again, so that Mr. Schumer could not be photographed with the important-looking backdrop.</p>
        <p>Senator Schumer, a Democrat, praised Mayor Giuliani for his handling of the millenium celebration, saying, ''I think he had the right blend of being careful, but at the same time not scaring people.''</p>
        <p>But when he was finished, television and radio reporters suddenly discovered that they had not been able to record his remarks.</p>
        <p>Someone, it turned out, had cut the audio.</p>
        <p>1/1/00: A PEACEFUL PARTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
