<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Party Like It's 1999? That's So, Like, 'Stalg</title>
    <meta content="01PART$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: IDENTITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Patton, Phil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED81030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Party Like It's 1999? That's So, Like, 'Stalg</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phil Patton</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Patton, Phil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phil Patton article gives transcript of a 2025 videotex letter written to a friend by a woman living on a space station describing a nostalgic visit down to Terra; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To: Marcy  From: Britanny  Videotex, 6/6/2025 (a transcript)</p>
        <p>WELL, I'm just back from Tiffany's big bash. It's been 25 years since we finished high school and Tiffany says, ''Let's forget the reunion and just have a party and hang.'' And her big idea was: do the whole 90's theme. So 'stalg!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To: Marcy  From: Britanny  Videotex, 6/6/2025 (a transcript)</p>
        <p>WELL, I'm just back from Tiffany's big bash. It's been 25 years since we finished high school and Tiffany says, ''Let's forget the reunion and just have a party and hang.'' And her big idea was: do the whole 90's theme. So 'stalg!</p>
        <p>It was my first trip back to Terra in 10 years, and Tiffany had all kinds of neat stuff I hadn't seen. The induction table, of course, that heats up the food on the plates. And you can look down and see different scenes. Sky. Forest. Brook. I go, Neat, but spare me the underwater Caribbean view if you serve sushi.</p>
        <p>When we sat down, there was this cute little Pikachu scooting around that I find out is the saltshaker, and Jigglypuff is the pepper. And every time I dribbled something, a little Tasmanian Devil crumbot zipped by and there was this whishy sound. And then who arrives but that Tracy, who I still hate, and the first thing she says, like she was still the snotty head cheerleader, was, ''So where have you been? I thought you'd left the planet?'' Not even knowing, you know? And I'm like, Well, du-uh, exactly.</p>
        <p>Snapped her righteously!</p>
        <p>I have to admit she had a point. We really are out of it on the Big Can. But living here is all right. I know they make fun of us, but we laugh at them, too. We call them Aussies, 'cause they're down under. Actually it's more 90's on the Can -- or Oneilia, as absolutely nobody calls it, after the nutty professor who first scoped out the Lagrange points here as the neatest spot for the big space station -- than anywhere on Terra. They had to give it that cute look to get people here. Hired the same team that did that old theme park or whatever it was, Celebration, to make it as Terran as possible.</p>
        <p>When we graduated in '99, no one thought it would happen so quickly. You wrote in my yearbook ''Onward and upward,'' but I don't think you meant actually. I suppose it was basically cheap ion engines and Club Med sending up all those honeymooners -- remember those ''moon'' ads? -- that got it going. And after the debt bust of the Noughties, when NASA hooked up with MasterCard and the others, it just made sense to sign on if you were maxed out like Tony and me.</p>
        <p>Anyway, back to the party. This is the best: Tracy has on this outfit from Sony-Hilfiger of old 90's TV shows, with great scenes from ''Dawson's Creek'' and ''Friends'' in two-inch boxes all over her, woven into the fabric. She acted so superior, like, asking me, Would I wear that on the Can, and raving about Jnco and Fubu, her gene-ious (pun!) kids. So I lean over and whisper to Mandy, ''Well, it's bright but it's still checks.'' And on her figure, which, let me testify, hasn't exactly stayed trim, checks are definitely disindicated.</p>
        <p>By the way, Tiffany had even matched the holos to the 90's thing. I hadn't seen much of them before this trip but now it seems you can't go anywhere on Terra without a holographic celeb chatting away with the latest downloaded dish. Funny how you just don't see the real celebs anymore, in ads and stuff, since Amazon started personal vidmail, telling people what the boss or whoever was buying. As Bezos (that single-name thing is so over) says, it taps the greatest marketing force in history, the green-eyed monster of jealousy.</p>
        <p>So she had a Martha, who said how the centerpiece was made, and a Version 2.0 Oprah and a Geraldo. But the really funny one was the Alan Greenspan, who had to license himself after they turned over monetary policy to the computers that run the derivatives.</p>
        <p>The food was themed, of course, though it was all customized, since our diet cards got plugged into the Nutrifab. Wraps and frappes, Tiffany announces. The only true innovations of the 90's.</p>
        <p>Well, to get back to the dress. We're eating this stuff I haven't seen in years and I'm talking to Mandy, when somebody spills piquant sauce. The crumbot goes whirring across the table, crashes, and there's this little burst of sparks. A blue arc leaps across the table toward Tracy and her dress starts cycling through all these images faster and faster until it's like a fog and then it dissolves. She sat there basically in the raw with this, like, droopy fishnet of melted fibes hanging off her.</p>
        <p>Justified the shuttle fare, to see that, but I was happy to get back home, I can tell you, and see Terra come up in the morning the normal way again.</p>
        <p>Kiss-kiss,</p>
        <p>B.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: IDENTITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
