<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Thinking Finds a Free Market</title>
    <meta content="01FREE$15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: POWER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DF1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Thinking Finds a Free Market</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Floyd Norris</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILL the forces of globalism continue to push the world toward American-style capitalism?</p>
        <p>As the 21st century begins, advocates of the free market have no doubt that they have won the economic argument. Socialism is dead. Moreover, as a means of creating wealth and material progress, American capitalism seems to be clearly superior to the Asian variety, with its greater level of government planning, or the European version, with its emphasis on social welfare and protection of workers from losing their jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILL the forces of globalism continue to push the world toward American-style capitalism?</p>
        <p>As the 21st century begins, advocates of the free market have no doubt that they have won the economic argument. Socialism is dead. Moreover, as a means of creating wealth and material progress, American capitalism seems to be clearly superior to the Asian variety, with its greater level of government planning, or the European version, with its emphasis on social welfare and protection of workers from losing their jobs.</p>
        <p>The proponents see the coming era as a period of global transformation: prosperity will rise around the world as technological change and global integration spread along with democracy. ''This new boom has the potential to pull the whole world into it, allowing literally billions of people to move into middle-class lifestyles,'' Peter Schwartz, Peter Leyden and Joel Hyatt write in their 1999 book, ''The Long Boom: A Vision for the Coming Age of Prosperity.''</p>
        <p>Certainly capitalism has extended to areas where it was previously unfamiliar. From Ghana to Mongolia, stock markets have sprung up, even as the world's largest -- the New York Stock Exchange -- scrambles to hold on to its position as technology opens up new ways to trade. Private enterprise is the dominant economic force, and it is hard to see that changing soon.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the technological revolution brought on by computers is tying the world together as never before. Peter F. Drucker, the business historian and management thinker, compares the effect of the Internet to that of the railroad. By lowering transportation costs, the railroad made national businesses possible. Now, with information available instantly, the Internet allows even small businesses to have global ambitions, and it places pressure on nations to relax regulations and cut taxes that make it more difficult for their businesses to compete.</p>
        <p>That pressure is to follow the American path. By making it relatively easy to start companies -- and to hire and fire workers -- the American way has produced innovation. Microsoft, the company that investors think is worth more than any other, did not exist a quarter-century ago. Without such flexibility, the computer revolution might not have been so dominated by American companies.</p>
        <p>But the forces of globalism and American capitalism face resistance. The Asian economic collapse in 1997 brought home the risk to countries of dealing with huge, uncontrolled capital flows. Free trade may bring overall benefits, but there are losers whose political influence may be substantial. The protests at the World Trade Organization meeting in Seattle last month united those who fear world government with those who want stricter standards on the environment and the treatment of workers.</p>
        <p>The suspicion has grown, even among Americans, that globalism is really a means of helping big business. In a poll of Americans by the Program on International Policy Attitudes at the University of Maryland, 54 percent said that Washington trade officials gave ''too much'' consideration to the views of multinational corporations; 73 percent believed ''too little'' attention was paid to the views of ''people like you.''</p>
        <p>That viewpoint has little support among major political leaders, but it could yet resonate. Jude Wanniski of Polyconomics, a conservative research organization, complains that multinational corporations want ''an international trade bureaucracy that serves their interest all the time.''</p>
        <p>''This means,'' he said, ''having more international government under their control, beyond the reach of ordinary Americans who do not understand the imperatives of this new bang-bang world of cyberspace and megadeals.''</p>
        <p>That such resentment has appeared now -- with the American economy booming and the current period of growth soon to become the longest in its history -- may indicate just how vigorous the debate could become, if and when the economy stumbles.</p>
        <p>It may be worth recalling that a century ago there was also a trend toward globalization. Improved transport and instantaneous transmission of information -- remember the telephone and telegraph? -- were hailed as being certain to bring the world together. Trade barriers fell -- until World War I. Charlene Barshefsky, the United States trade representative, says that much of what has been accomplished in trade talks over the last couple of decades has simply removed roadblocks that were erected between the two World Wars. Had people acted in an economically rational way, the gains in free trade made a century ago might not have been lost. But they did not.</p>
        <p>The economy a millennium ago was far different from ours, but it may hold a lesson as a new millennium begins. In their book, ''The Year 1000,'' Robert Lacey and Danny Danziger write that honey was the principal source of sweetness. ''People paid taxes with it, and it was a lucky day when a swarm of bees settled in your thatch,'' they write. Not only was honey valuable, but beeswax provided the best candles, and thus the most reliable lighting system.</p>
        <p>''Thus,'' observed Marc Faber, a Hong Kong-based money manager, in a review of that book he sent to clients, ''it is probable that honey and beeswax were as precious a commodity in medieval times as the Microsoft operating system is today.''</p>
        <p>WHEN sugar arrived in Europe, the value of honey collapsed. Mr. Faber thinks something similar will happen to the value of Microsoft one day.</p>
        <p>That change is not on the immediate horizon. For now, the information economy is king, and its effects include pressures on other countries to come closer to American-style capitalism. The extent to which opposition to global capitalism slows or even reverses that trend may be the most important economic story of the next few decades.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: POWER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
