<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Many in a Throng? Crunching the Numbers</title>
    <meta content="01CROW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AT THE CROSSROADS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFDB1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Many in a Throng? Crunching the Numbers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Half a million? A million? A zillion? The world will never know how many humans squeezed their way into the Designated Watching Zones around Times Square to see the ball drop, but it is not impossible to estimate how many people could have been there.</p>
        <p>Around 11:20 p.m., the mayor said the crowd was ''pushing two million.'' But a calculation shows that the theoretical capacity of the area open to spectators was considerably less.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Half a million? A million? A zillion? The world will never know how many humans squeezed their way into the Designated Watching Zones around Times Square to see the ball drop, but it is not impossible to estimate how many people could have been there.</p>
        <p>Around 11:20 p.m., the mayor said the crowd was ''pushing two million.'' But a calculation shows that the theoretical capacity of the area open to spectators was considerably less.</p>
        <p>Keep in mind, this calculation does not include Central Park, where the mayor said spectators were congregating. Nor does it include those watching from skyscraper windows or peering at video screens along side streets,  or simply partying somewhere in the vicinity of mid-Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Here's the math: According to practitioners of crowd size estimation, an average standing person will fit in a square about 17 inches on each side, or about two square feet. The city was only allowing spectators into pens that took up about half of the pavement area along each block of Broadway and Seventh Avenue, between 34th Street and 59th Street. But to take the most-crowded-case scenario, assume that every inch of pavement along Broadway and Seventh, as well as a few feet of each side street, was filled with people.</p>
        <p>A typical block of Seventh Avenue around Times Square is 265 feet long and 60 feet wide, for a total of about 15,900 square feet -- enough room for 7,950 people. A typical block of Broadway is a bit longer -- about 275 feet, enough space for 8,250 people.</p>
        <p>Adding up all the blocks of Broadway and Seventh Avenue between 34th Street and Central Park South, including the trapezoid where Broadway and Seventh intersect, and figuring 20 feet or so of cushion on each side street, the total capacity of the viewing area is -- approximately -- 430,333.4 people.</p>
        <p>There was considerable spillover onto Eighth Avenue and Avenue of the Americas north of 42nd Street. But even if those streets were also filled, there would be room only for another 265,000 or so spectators, for a total of about 700,000.</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AT THE CROSSROADS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
