<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Direct Line to God In an Impersonal Era</title>
    <meta content="01PENT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: IDENTITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentecostal Church</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodstein, Laurie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E0DF1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Direct Line to God In an Impersonal Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurie Goodstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodstein, Laurie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pentecostal movement, which was born in Los Angeles in 1906, has caught on among half a billion people and is likely to continue growing in next century because it is well suited to a world of continual change, of immigration and refugees, of people adrift and yearing for a bit of respect and a sign of hope from God; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Pentecostal movement was born in Los Angeles in 1906 on forlorn Azusa Street, inside an abandoned church previously used as a stable and still reeking of horses. Led by a half-blind black preacher from Louisiana named William J. Seymour, a band of whites, blacks and Hispanics defied the strictures of segregated worship, gathered together and prayed for a sign from the Holy Spirit.</p>
        <p>Their prayers were answered in ways that few could have imagined when they began babbling in strange tongues, falling in faints, weeping and embracing. Word spread that the Holy Spirit had visited Azusa Street, and people flocked there, some to mock, some to succumb to the preaching and dancing, saxophones and tambourines, and to exclaim that they had experienced miraculous healings of body and soul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Pentecostal movement was born in Los Angeles in 1906 on forlorn Azusa Street, inside an abandoned church previously used as a stable and still reeking of horses. Led by a half-blind black preacher from Louisiana named William J. Seymour, a band of whites, blacks and Hispanics defied the strictures of segregated worship, gathered together and prayed for a sign from the Holy Spirit.</p>
        <p>Their prayers were answered in ways that few could have imagined when they began babbling in strange tongues, falling in faints, weeping and embracing. Word spread that the Holy Spirit had visited Azusa Street, and people flocked there, some to mock, some to succumb to the preaching and dancing, saxophones and tambourines, and to exclaim that they had experienced miraculous healings of body and soul.</p>
        <p>In the 94 years since, Pentecostal worship has caught on among almost half a billion people, nearly 1 in 4 Christians worldwide. This momentum is likely to continue in the next century because it turns out that Pentecostalism is a form of religion made for the world the way it is today: a world on the move, of immigrants and refugees, of people adrift and yearning for a bit of respect and a sign of hope from God.</p>
        <p>''The main attraction,'' said Harvey Cox, a professor at Harvard Divinity School who has studied worldwide Pentecostalism, ''seems to be that it holds out the possibility of a very direct experience of the holy, the sacred and the transcendent.'' To Professor Cox, it is ''Everyman's mysticism.''</p>
        <p>Estimates are that more than 200 million people belong to Pentecostal denominations and that more than 300 million others can be classified as ''charismatics'' and ''third wavers'' -- people who stay in mainstream Protestant or Catholic churches that have adopted Pentecostal practices like healings, speaking in tongues, casting out demons and laying on of hands upon the sick. Pentecostalism is most potent in the developing world and in places where only a century ago Christianity was regarded as a foreign intruder: in Africa and in Asia, especially South Korea and China. In other parts of the world it is encroaching on the dominant Christian traditions. In Latin and Central America, Pentecostalists are winning millions of converts from Roman Catholicism, and in Russia and other former communist countries, Pentecostalists are challenging the monopoly of Orthodox Christianity.</p>
        <p>The movement has spread fastest among displaced people and immigrants. In cities like Rio de Janeiro and Nairobi, disoriented immigrants from the countryside find that Pentecostal congregations offer a social network and connections to jobs and housing. In the United States, it is growing fastest among newcomers from Central and South America. ''In many countries, rapid changes brought about by urbanization and technology have shaken people loose of their traditional religious moorings,'' Professor Cox said. ''And this is a highly available, very portable religion which is uncannily suited to urban life and appeals to people who are cut off from their previous religious expressions.''</p>
        <p>Tessie DeVore, the editor of Vida Cristiana, a Pentecostal magazine for Spanish speakers, discovered Pentecostalism after moving from Puerto Rico, where she was brought up a Roman Catholic, to attend college in Alabama. While there, she learned that her mother had cancer, and she says that the only person who really offered her comfort was the wife of one of her professors, who prayed with her and invited her to a Bible study and then to a Pentecostal church. Mrs. DeVore says she soon found herself at a service speaking in tongues.</p>
        <p>''It felt natural, like it was something I should have been doing all the time, like walking,'' she said. ''I said, 'O.K., God, if this is you, I want it all. I may not understand all of it, but I trust you.' ''</p>
        <p>Every church member is expected to be an active missionary, and this helps Pentecostalism grow. Like the professor's wife who reached out to Mrs. DeVore, members and new converts introduce friends and neighbors to the church. Pentecostalism thrives on ministry by lay people and is not dependent on clergy to spread the gospel.</p>
        <p>Back on Azusa Street 94 years ago, William Seymour envisioned a multiracial church that would eventually unite all of Christianity. Instead, the movement splintered into myriad denominations, like the white Assemblies of God and the black Church of God in Christ.</p>
        <p>But that splintering held a key to Pentecostalism's staying power: there is no single denomination or creed, no Pentecostal pope. Pentecostalism has thrived because it is decentralized and easily blends with the religious practices of its host cultures. Pentecostal churches in South Korea incorporate shamanism; in Guatemala, Indian healing rituals; and in Africa, ancestor worship -- provoking debate in the movement about how malleable a church should be.</p>
        <p>THIS is, in part, why Pentecostalists are of many denominations and why some identify with none at all. They worship in tiny storefront churches, in homes and in megachurches. The largest church in the world is Pentecostal -- the Yoido Full Gospel Church in Seoul, South Korea, which holds six Sunday services to accommodate its 730,000 members in a chapel the size of Fenway Park.</p>
        <p>But ask Pentecostalists about the pull of their faith and their churches, and they talk most about hope. The growth of the movement itself is to them proof that the world is in the midst of a religious revival, a fulfillment of God's promise.</p>
        <p>''God is really stepping up the spiritual heat all around the globe,'' Mrs. DeVore said recently during a break in a multiracial crusade led by an Argentine preacher and attended by thousands in Winter Park, Fla. ''We are right around the corner from one of the greatest revivals the world has ever seen.''</p>
        <p>Stephen E. Strang, founder of Strang Communications, a family of Pentecostal publications, said, ''At the beginning of this century you had zero Pentecostals in the world, and today you have who knows how many hundreds of millions.</p>
        <p>''I'm a Christian and I believe in the Holy Spirit,'' he said. ''And I believe this is a fulfillment of prophecy.''</p>
        <p>VISIONS: IDENTITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
