<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turnaround Buffs the Tarnish Off Alabama's Season</title>
    <meta content="01ORAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fedex Orange Bowl</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Alabama</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Michigan</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dubose, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0D71338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turnaround Buffs the Tarnish Off Alabama's Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Alabama Coach Mike DuBose in view of upcoming FedEx Orange Bowl against Michigan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In October, Alabama Coach Mike DuBose was trying to live down a major scandal and two losses, and the howls for his job were intensifying. But entering the FedEx Orange Bowl on Saturday night against Michigan, DuBose seems to have plenty of job security.</p>
        <p>His team has won six straight games, including a 34-7 rout of Florida for the Southeastern Conference title. The two years of his five-year contract that were stripped away as part of his punishment from the scandal have been restored, and Alabama officials are talking with him about an extension beyond 2002.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In October, Alabama Coach Mike DuBose was trying to live down a major scandal and two losses, and the howls for his job were intensifying. But entering the FedEx Orange Bowl on Saturday night against Michigan, DuBose seems to have plenty of job security.</p>
        <p>His team has won six straight games, including a 34-7 rout of Florida for the Southeastern Conference title. The two years of his five-year contract that were stripped away as part of his punishment from the scandal have been restored, and Alabama officials are talking with him about an extension beyond 2002.</p>
        <p>''I've experienced highs and lows in the coaching profession, but never anything like this season,'' DuBose told reporters this week.</p>
        <p>Over the summer, DuBose acknowledged an extramarital affair with his secretary, Debbie Gibson, who received a $350,000 settlement from the university after filing a sexual harassment suit against DuBose and the university. In August, Alabama said DuBose's salary would be cut by $360,000 in the next three years. DuBose's salary is estimated at $525,000 a year.</p>
        <p>Even in the close-knit environment of Alabama football, DuBose faced intense criticism. But the pressure came more from fans than from within the football program, although the athletic director, Bob Bockrath, resigned in September after university trustees formed a committee to oversee athletics. Bockrath had not consulted with the board of trustees when he decided to punish DuBose rather than dismiss him.</p>
        <p>''The players had ideas of our own,'' defensive tackle Cornelius Griffin said. ''He admitted it was wrong, and he always teaches us that you pay for your mistakes. What happened had nothing to do with football. We were drawn closer together. Players didn't feel the coach should be fired.''</p>
        <p>Alabama's turnaround coincided with the dramatic improvement of its defense. It allowed just 140 yards rushing over its final five games, a 28-yard average that catapulted its rushing defense to second nationally, at 75.3 yards a game.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the Tide's overall defense improved from 11th in the S.E.C. to ninth nationally.</p>
        <p>The defensive coordinator, Ellis Johnson, said his group had been dropping too many passes that could be intercepted. ''We made a couple of shifts in the secondary, some of our young players up front began putting more pressure on the quarterback, and we blitzed more effectively,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The result is a 10-2 record and a No. 5 ranking in the Associated Press poll entering the Orange Bowl.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Michigan, at 9-2, arrives with a four-game winning streak and a No. 8 ranking.</p>
        <p>This game will not be for the national championship, but if you want tradition, there is plenty here. Michigan has more Division I-A victories (795) than any other team, and Alabama is the leader in bowl appearances -- Saturday will mark the Tide's 50th bowl game -- in addition to being fifth in victories at 734.</p>
        <p>Both teams have running backs who appear destined for work in the National Football League. Despite missing one game with an ankle injury, Alabama's Shaun Alexander ran for 1,383 yards and set conference records for points (144) and touchdowns (24). Michigan's Anthony Thomas rushed for 1,257 yards, which is more impressive when you consider the teammate closest to him, David Terrell, had 89.</p>
        <p>They share a similarity at quarterback as well.</p>
        <p>Alabama will alternate quarterbacks for some, if not all, of the game. DuBose went to that strategy late in the season, after the sophomore Andrew Zow missed two games with an ankle injury and the freshman Tyler Watts played so well in his place. It was particularly effective in routing Florida.</p>
        <p>Michigan, meanwhile, began the season using the tag-team approach. The senior Tom Brady split time with Drew Henson, a sophomore who played third base in the Yankees' farm system in the off-season. Eventually Brady, who has thrown for 2,217 yards and 16 touchdowns and completed 61 percent of his passes, took over the job full time.</p>
        <p>Still, Wolverines Coach Lloyd Carr said Henson could be used in case of injury or simply to jump-start the offense.</p>
        <p>Whatever happens, it now appears DuBose will be the Tide's coach for years to come.</p>
        <p>''When you have tradition, there's pressure that comes along with it,'' he said. ''Pressure motivates us, but if it becomes stressful, it'll kill you. It came close to that. I made huge mistakes and I asked for forgiveness. God forgave me and I have peace. That doesn't mean I don't have problems, but I know where the answers are.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
