<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Quarterback Reverse: Lucas Stars as Foley Sits</title>
    <meta content="01JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Seahawks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lucas, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foley, Glenn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Seattle Seahawks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DA1338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Quarterback Reverse: Lucas Stars as Foley Sits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ray Lucas, former backup quarterback on New York Jets, will start against Seattle Seahawks, while Glenn Foley, former starting quarterback for Jets, will be backup for Seahawks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a final twist to the regular season, which shows just how unpredictable pro football has become, a former backup quarterback on the Jets will start Sunday against Seattle, while a former starting quarterback for the Jets will be the backup for the Seahawks.</p>
        <p>Glenn Foley, who when last season began was the Jets' quarterback of the future, now is a Seahawks bench warmer. And Ray Lucas, who was simply hoping a year ago that someone would have enough faith in him to keep him around, is the Jets' starter as the team tries to end the season with a flourish by winning its fourth game in a row.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a final twist to the regular season, which shows just how unpredictable pro football has become, a former backup quarterback on the Jets will start Sunday against Seattle, while a former starting quarterback for the Jets will be the backup for the Seahawks.</p>
        <p>Glenn Foley, who when last season began was the Jets' quarterback of the future, now is a Seahawks bench warmer. And Ray Lucas, who was simply hoping a year ago that someone would have enough faith in him to keep him around, is the Jets' starter as the team tries to end the season with a flourish by winning its fourth game in a row.</p>
        <p>The 7-8 Jets have .500 to shoot for, which would be redemption in a season that fell apart early. But the stakes are higher for the Seahawks (9-6), who can clinch their first American Football Conference West title since 1988 with a victory. But if they lose, and the Kansas City Chiefs win, the Seahawks will be out of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''I still want to be a starter,'' said Foley, who now backs up Jon Kitna.</p>
        <p>Foley did have one moment this season -- in the team's second game, in Chicago. Seattle had lost its opener, and Kitna was sidelined with an injury. Foley started against the Bears and won, throwing two touchdowns and no interceptions.</p>
        <p>Going into that game, Foley, now 29, did not have a complete-game victory in the National Football League that he could boast of. His Jets career had seemed headed upward, but when a rib injury sent him to the sideline early last season, Vinny Testaverde replaced him, and Foley was traded to the Seahawks in the off-season.</p>
        <p>Foley and Lucas remain close. Foley called Lucas last Monday before the Jets faced the Dolphins in Miami and produced their third straight victory over a playoff contender.</p>
        <p>''He's one of my best friends off the field,'' Foley said. ''We hung out, spent a lot of time together. It's great to see him doing well. He's a guy who's been patient, and making the best of it. I'm real happy for Ray.''</p>
        <p>Still, Foley reflects on how it might have been different for him as a Jet. How in his first start as the quarterback of the future last year, a 36-30 overtime defeat against the 49ers, he threw for 415 yards.</p>
        <p>''But we lost,'' he said. ''Not winning that game was my downfall. And the next week I get hurt and my season's over.''</p>
        <p>Even now, Foley claims, he never understood -- or was told -- the reasons for his departure, which came when the Jets traded him to Seattle in March for a seventh-round draft pick, which turned out to be tackle Ryan Young. Since he left, Foley has seen Jets Coach Bill Parcells at a golf tournament. They have also spoken several times. But the questions remain in his mind.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, because Vinny came in and turned the whole thing upside down, it was a blessing for the Jets organization,'' Foley said. ''So the plans for me were pretty much done.''</p>
        <p>The Jets had a problem with Foley's salary, which was due to hit $1.5 million this season. Then there was the issue of his durability -- he has been seriously injured twice in his career -- and his ability to start and finish a game.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, Foley, a New Jerseyan with New York sensibilities and attitude, found himself in a different environment.</p>
        <p>''It's unbelievable,'' he said. ''One minute I'm there and the next I'm gone. They don't know how to handle me out here. New York's the town that never sleeps and Seattle's the town that always sleeps.''</p>
        <p>So now Foley returns to the Meadowlands and will see Lucas trying to stop his team, just as the pair squared off in 1993 -- Lucas for Rutgers, Foley for Boston College.</p>
        <p>Foley said: ''What I remember about Ray Lucas that game was every play he rolled right and tried to find someone to pass to. And there was never anyone there.''</p>
        <p>''Oh, yeah?'' Lucas said today, when told about Foley's statement. ''You know what I remember about Glenn Foley? Nothing.''</p>
        <p>Lucas smiled, and added, ''He was a monster drop-back quarterback. When I got to the Jets he would help me with my reads. He could tell me what was going to happen.''</p>
        <p>But neither quarterback could have seen this far into the future.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The Jets handed out four annual team awards, including the Dennis Byrd trophy for the team's most inspirational player, which went to quarterback RAY LUCAS. Linebacker MARVIN JONES, who missed all of 1998 because of knee surgery, was given the Ed Block award for courage. The Kyle Clifton ''good guy'' award went to linebacker BRYAN COX, and DWIGHT STONE, the receiver and returner, received the Marty Lyons award for his charitable work. . . . If TOM TUPA can raise his 45.1 yards-per-punt average by three-tenths of a yard against Seattle, he will become the Jets' single-season record-holder. The club mark of 45.3 was set by CURLEY JOHNSON in 1965. . . . Lucas trails only PEYTON MANNING in the A.F.C. passer rating. The Colts' Manning, who faces a difficult Buffalo Bills defense on Sunday, is at 91.5 to Lucas's 88.6.  PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
