<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Artist Formerly Known as Spectator</title>
    <meta content="01ARTT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165199"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: IDENTITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDF1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Artist Formerly Known as Spectator</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ann Powers</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers article suggests that culture will be interactive in 21st century, with no lines between artist and appreciator or between individually rendered masterpiece and commonly created work-in-progress (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IMAGINE yourself as a member of an empty orchestra. The music, ever changing within a basic set of themes, wafts forth from instruments held by invisible hands, but the chairs are open for you to occupy and add your part.</p>
        <p>''Empty orchestra'' is the fancy term for karaoke, a fad that trendsetters would just as soon forget. Yet despite the corniness of singing along to instrumental versions of pop hits, or maybe partly because of it, it defines the paradigm we are moving toward. When we dive into popular culture, we increasingly expect to leave a mark, or at least determine the shape of our own good times. Technology will enable that impulse to such an extent that the already decayed lines between artist and appreciator, or individually rendered masterpiece and commonly created work-in-progress, will vanish in a flurry of interactivity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IMAGINE yourself as a member of an empty orchestra. The music, ever changing within a basic set of themes, wafts forth from instruments held by invisible hands, but the chairs are open for you to occupy and add your part.</p>
        <p>''Empty orchestra'' is the fancy term for karaoke, a fad that trendsetters would just as soon forget. Yet despite the corniness of singing along to instrumental versions of pop hits, or maybe partly because of it, it defines the paradigm we are moving toward. When we dive into popular culture, we increasingly expect to leave a mark, or at least determine the shape of our own good times. Technology will enable that impulse to such an extent that the already decayed lines between artist and appreciator, or individually rendered masterpiece and commonly created work-in-progress, will vanish in a flurry of interactivity.</p>
        <p>That, of course, is the hipper term for the trend toward actively shaping the entertainment experience, rather than just sitting back and enjoying it. A survey of trade publications, Web magazines and other popular-culture beacons suggests that interactivity is not only the moment's craze but also the basic structure that culture is following into the new century.</p>
        <p>Internet culture is the most technologically enriched aspect of our hunger for the ancient spirit of carnival, once manifested within the holy festival and the bawdy circus. We are not going back, though, to a time before mass culture colored consciousness. Rather, we are developing a parodoxical hybrid of the mass-produced and the local, as audience members enter directly into the fantasies presented them.</p>
        <p>We love talk radio and television, in which audience members bond with or berate the hosts and guests. MTV's most popular program is the viewer-dictated ''Total Request Live.'' The Beastie Boys let fans create their own greatest-hits packages by downloading selections from 150 posted on the rappers' Web site. Films are still sit-back experiences, but ''The Blair Witch Project'' created a participatory aura with its use of cheap video, its open-ended plot and its invitation to viewers to speculate on its mysteries using the Internet.</p>
        <p>The dominance of the crowd increased over the last century, with mass communication uniting locals into audiences of millions. In the next era, those millions will step, one by one, into their own spotlights. Global mass culture may be burying home-grown character beneath identical Disney Worlds, but the human impulse to personalize is infinitely adaptable.</p>
        <p>Technology is already allowing people to make concrete their long-held feeling about mass art, which is that it is folk art with a bigger frame. Already they are using video cameras and hip-hop samplers to create pop hits. More space within mass culture will soon be devoted to these homemade efforts. Internet radio will allow individuals to create instant remixes and sound collages and transmit them worldwide. The often tacky efforts of cable-access auteurs will be integrated into professionally produced cable network shows, completely closing the gap between fiction and reality, which is already perilously thin on television.</p>
        <p>These changes within ''low'' culture will be mirrored on high. As art becomes more like a game, the idea of great works -- and the institutions that support them -- may fade. People will go into art spaces (not ''museums,'' which will survive mainly as archives) and add strokes to computer-generated ''paintings'' and installations directed by imagination-leaders, formerly called artists. They will join in global choruses led by interdenominational monks. As for the solitary pursuit of reading and writing, it will face competition from the community journals and real-time oral histories that students and autodidacts alike will create together.</p>
        <p>This folksy vision isn't meant to overshadow the pervasive influence of megacorporations on popular culture. Mergers will continue to narrow the field at its top end, but those media empires won't be able to absorb all the rogue artist-entrepreneurs that interactive technology will enable. Instead, the companies will make deals, perhaps providing production and distribution support while allowing the artists to direct some of culture's content.</p>
        <p>We may even learn to embrace anonymity, as the old folk practice of not signing works evolves into a sport of multiple identities. The shape-shifting now taking place online, in cyberpickup joints and clubhouses, could move into the physical world, as theater is rejuvenated by becoming an improvisational game. David Cronenberg's latest science fiction film, ''Existenz,'' imagines a virtual realm so real it could make you bleed; perhaps we're headed for a physical realm so fired by imagination that we'll sometimes experience our own flesh and blood as chimeras.</p>
        <p>To some, such an age may sound like a nightmare. Those already horrified by today's spectacles will further lament the decimation of individual will within the personal sphere. But when a singer takes the microphone at karaoke, isn't she herself magnified? Amplified, so she can hear herself better? That's what we'll be aiming for as we enter our empty orchestras.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: IDENTITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
