<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Past, Present and Future in One Stroke</title>
    <meta content="01ESSA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DC1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Past, Present and Future in One Stroke</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD EDER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''But where are the snows of yesteryear?'' the poet Francois Villon asked in the 15th century, not even halfway through the millennium we are making a fuss about leaving. Nothing new under the sun, though in his case it was not an early global-warming alert but a lament for departed loveliness. Nothing new there either.</p>
        <p>Maybe the past is prologue, but here at the changing of the hundred- and thousand-year guard, prologue is chiefly the past. The flood of writing on the subject, including this additional teacupful, looks back more than forward. ''Millennium'' has a great gong sound, but is it the gong announcing the end of an era or summoning the one to come? The first is bronze, the second is tin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''But where are the snows of yesteryear?'' the poet Francois Villon asked in the 15th century, not even halfway through the millennium we are making a fuss about leaving. Nothing new under the sun, though in his case it was not an early global-warming alert but a lament for departed loveliness. Nothing new there either.</p>
        <p>Maybe the past is prologue, but here at the changing of the hundred- and thousand-year guard, prologue is chiefly the past. The flood of writing on the subject, including this additional teacupful, looks back more than forward. ''Millennium'' has a great gong sound, but is it the gong announcing the end of an era or summoning the one to come? The first is bronze, the second is tin.</p>
        <p>If the past is another country where things are done differently, as L. P. Hartley put it, at least it is a country, with features, memories good and bad and maybe lessons to be drawn. The future is no country at all. At best it is a reservation made through a fly-by-night travel agency that may send us quite otherwise than we'd planned, or go out of business overnight and no refunds.</p>
        <p>History, we are told, is the use the present makes of the past for the sake of the future. This millennial looking-ahead is the use the present makes of the future for the sake of the past -- to salute or at least to confirm it. Hey, we call out ahead to the year 3000 while stuffing a time capsule with our bric-a-brac and bright ideas: This is where we are and what we've done with the thousand years just gone. Show-and-tell time. Please grade.</p>
        <p>Of course it is a notional plea. Having asked what truth was, jesting Pilate didn't stay for an answer. We won't arrive for one.  Prophecy itself is a judgment on today, not tomorrow, a judgment seasoned with triumphalism or foreboding, depending on who we are and have been, and much less on what we foresee. Reading entrails is most likely an older form of vaticination than reading stars. Even stargazing is reading what happened millions of years ago.</p>
        <p>Insofar as it casts ahead, ''millennium'' is a large package for not very large thoughts. They rattle. Arranging this shindig, we've rented a banquet hall for a takeout lunch; a journalistic arrangement, among other things. So was the original ''Yes, Virginia, there is a Santa Claus.'' Some of the more facile examples of this prophetic bridge-building are not far from ''Yes, Virginia, there is a future.'' Who knows, maybe the millennium will fall under Andy Warhol's rule: famous for 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the way to think about the 2000's is to let the thousands go and fix upon the two. (That was my wife's suggestion; but then, as a painter of landscapes and figures, she works to conjure past and future in one stroke of the present.) What will next year and the year after be like? That is quite a lot, even a terrifying lot, considering the speeding-up of change. Terrifying to a sexagenarian entrails-reader, that is; much less or even not at all to his grandchildren.</p>
        <p>But what about the grandchildren? A note or two from a foreboder:</p>
        <p>Deterioration of place. Chat rooms that are nowhere, e-marketing that is nowhere and may end up contributing nothing, in the way of taxes, to the upkeep of the pavements we nonvirtually walk upon. (Why walk, of course, when we can Web?) Visiting, that magic pleasure and terror (through the woods to grandfather's house or maybe grandmother's or maybe the wolf that ate her), becomes a riskless keystroke. For a long time we've had 800 numbers that are nowhere and will-o'-the-wisp mortgages that flit from place to place around the continent. Nowhere is not quite it: all of it is somewhere, only the somewhere is all one same climate-controlled cubicle and gray-white keyboard.</p>
        <p>Deterioration of time, specifically the progressions of time embodied in the generations. There are still parents and grandparents, and a child can still draw on particular experience, tempers and stories. Youth culture tends to bypass these things. Children have always argued their contemporaries against the parental hierarchy, and a good thing, too. There was liberating growth in it. But so manipulated is it now -- one part spark to ten parts marketing -- that it has become a revolution that not only devours but predigests itself.</p>
        <p>Deterioration of reality, which has always been a dialectic between what we control and what we don't. The steel of necessity strikes the flint of invention. Not much spark to be had when necessity, supposedly bypassed, has been vanquished into a banana. Plato's great myth told our life as the shadows cast by a fire on the walls of a cave in contrast to the reality outside. Two thousand years of civilization's fitful exploration has been a reaching for the outside. The next thousand -- until war comes or the power fails or the virtual culture produces immune rejection -- more than slightly suggests an advance back into the cave's shadows.</p>
        <p>Villon's ballad was a pulsing lament, a sense that we fall through time instead of ascending through it. Seeming to look backward, it is prophecy nonetheless. Today, 500 years after, the pulse beats sooner or later even in the staunchest progress believers. Arrhythmia, they may call it; for some of us it is rhythm. Whichever; more sure than any predicting about the shape and consequences of an information universe is that this pulse will beat 500 years from now. Depending, of course, on what loveliness remains to be lamented.</p>
        <p>What the ''snows of yesteryear'' is really asking is: Where are the snows of next year? Ecology, pollution, warming come into it, of course, but I think of the decline of specific and unique forms in our life -- snow is not the only crystal -- unarranged, unmanipulated, ungeneralized and unmarketed. Also the possibility, from night to morning, of finding the world transformed and renewed by something we neither control nor are sold.</p>
        <p>Maybe a computer feels that way when rebooted. Mine died entirely for 24 hours while I was trying to write this. Millennium takes out a critic? Computer rebels against what it is being made to say? Computer -- oh, God -- agreeing and shutting down in sympathy?</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
