<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Blanket of Snow Brings Some Warmth</title>
    <meta content="Y01KRE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EED81338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Blanket of Snow Brings Some Warmth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The snow everyone had been waiting for all winter finally came. The narrow streets leading down to Red Square, usually clotted with traffic, were empty. For all its imperfections, Moscow on New Year's Eve seemed suddenly, subtly perfect.</p>
        <p>Muscovites who would normally elbow each other rushing to work flowed out of the subway station and toward the edges of the Kremlin. All that had changed in Moscow and all that had stayed the same in this decade of unimaginable twists was here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The snow everyone had been waiting for all winter finally came. The narrow streets leading down to Red Square, usually clotted with traffic, were empty. For all its imperfections, Moscow on New Year's Eve seemed suddenly, subtly perfect.</p>
        <p>Muscovites who would normally elbow each other rushing to work flowed out of the subway station and toward the edges of the Kremlin. All that had changed in Moscow and all that had stayed the same in this decade of unimaginable twists was here.</p>
        <p>In front of the KGB building, an open-air disco rolled its bass line down the blocked-off street. A 20-foot electronic billboard pulsed, ''Internet. Da!'' And people gathered where they had for generations to see in the New Year, which, for most Russians, is Christmas and Carnival rolled into one.</p>
        <p>''We've come here for five years, though there's more people here now,'' said Sasha Zorkin, a 30-year-old wielding a video recorder. ''I want things to work out for Russia in the New Year, which means that obviously they would work out for me. too.''</p>
        <p>There was a sense that all Russian preoccupations for the last 364 days had been cast aside. For a few minutes, this was not a city where terrorist bombs went off three months ago. President Boris N. Yeltsin's resignation was something to be laughed at.</p>
        <p>''Great present Boris Nikolayevich gave us!'' said Aleksandr Suldin, a Grandfather Frost whose cotton-ball beard kept slipping off.</p>
        <p>Bitterness over the course the country has taken was spit out. Sweet Russian champagne and chocolates were passed around. The bottle rockets each small party set off seemed grander than the official fireworks. Together, everyone's screams and kisses blocked out the Kremlin chimes.</p>
        <p>Some dared to believe in a better future after the century's seesaw madness.</p>
        <p>''It has been a horrible century for Russia -- it seemed we lived well under the czars and are knocked down now,'' Lena Razumova, a 22-year-old unemployed French teacher, shouted over the firecrackers and her friends singing next to her. ''But we've come here to celebrate the New Year with all Russians. I'm an optimist. I am!''</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
