<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Officials Question Security At Prison Where Guard Died</title>
    <meta content="Y01PRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prison Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Louisiana</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Angola (La)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Louisiana State Penitentiary</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prison Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DF1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Officials Question Security At Prison Where Guard Died</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Law enforcement officials question security at Louisiana State Penitentiary in Angola in light of a number of life-threatening lapses and attempted escapes, the most recent of which involved the killing of a guard and an inmate; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three days after a prison guard and an inmate were killed in an attempted escape from the Louisiana State Penitentiary, law-enforcement officials in the area raised questions today about the security of the infamous prison farm, known as Angola.</p>
        <p>Even before the incident on Tuesday night, there were lapses and attempted escapes from the 18,000-acre maximum-security prison, said Charles Shropshire, the district attorney whose jurisdiction includes the prison.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three days after a prison guard and an inmate were killed in an attempted escape from the Louisiana State Penitentiary, law-enforcement officials in the area raised questions today about the security of the infamous prison farm, known as Angola.</p>
        <p>Even before the incident on Tuesday night, there were lapses and attempted escapes from the 18,000-acre maximum-security prison, said Charles Shropshire, the district attorney whose jurisdiction includes the prison.</p>
        <p>''There have been a number of events that have raised questions about the practices there,'' said Mr. Shropshire, who is deciding whether to seek the death penalty for five surviving inmates involved in the hostage-taking incident.</p>
        <p>''You know, twice a year I have to take a grand jury to the prison to report on conditions there to the court,'' Mr. Shropshire continued. ''I'm going to have to review how we conduct that tour to make sure I don't expose the jurors to a hostage situation.''</p>
        <p>Last month four men sawed their way out of death row and nearly escaped before being caught. The hacksaws they used were apparently smuggled into the prison inside books. And last January four convicted murderers escaped after a jail employee helped smuggle a can containing guns into the prison. They were caught, and the employee is awaiting prosecution.</p>
        <p>Ten days before the incident, The Baton Rouge Sunday Advocate published a news article outlining how lapses and collusion by prison guards had led to several escapes and life-threatening situations.</p>
        <p>Citing internal prison documents, the newspaper reported that an inmate with a six-inch knife walked out of the main prison building and into another part of the complex, where he nearly stabbed a guard before being overpowered.</p>
        <p>''It's been going on for quite some time,'' said Sheriff W. M. Daniel of East Feliciana Parish in southeastern Louisiana, where Angola is situated. ''It's been kind of deteriorating over a period of time where the inmates are losing respect for the security personnel.''</p>
        <p>The news article quoted several people who criticized the prison warden, N. Burl Cain. Mr. Cain was not available for comment today. But Richard L. Stalder, secretary of the Louisiana Department of Public Safety and Corrections, said in an interview today that the reports of negligence were overblown.</p>
        <p>''The incidents of violence at Angola are as low as they have been since records have been kept,'' he said. ''The fact that this escape did not take place, that a captain sacrificed his life to protect public safety, that the tactical response was swift and decisive, shows me that you don't have a security system with a fatal flaw.''</p>
        <p>The uprising on Tuesday night was by far the most serious of the recent incidents at Angola. Armed with metal shards and a plastic craft mallet stolen from a leather-working area, six convicted murderers serving life sentences took three guards hostage after a botched attempt to escape. One of the guards, Capt. David Knapps, was bludgeoned and stabbed to death after he refused to give up his keys before other guards subdued the inmates with percussion grenades. One of the inmates was shot and killed in the fighting.</p>
        <p>Captain Knapps was buried today in Tunica, a village about a mile west of the prison.</p>
        <p>On Thursday a state judge signed arrest warrants for the five surviving inmates, accusing each of first-degree murder and aggravated kidnapping.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shropshire said the repeated incidents at the prison made it unclear whether this attempt was provoked by another hostage standoff earlier this month in the parish, or county, jail in St. Martinville, La. After a six-day siege, an unusual deal with Cuba allowed seven Cuban inmates involved in the uprising to be deported.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to say whether they were related, because we've had so many escapes,'' Mr. Shropshire said. ''But I do know they have a problem there that the Department of Corrections needs to look into.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
