<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A First Look at 2000 With Little Fanfare</title>
    <meta content="Y01MAI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DC1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A First Look at 2000 With Little Fanfare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREY GOLDBERG</byline>
      <dateline>LUBEC, Me., Dec. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pastel sky over the Bay of Fundy darkened from peach glow to dim lavender. Taps sounded; the flag descended; and there came the soft thunder of a muffled stampede: hearty applause from more than 300 pairs of gloved and mittened hands.</p>
        <p>That is how, at 3:57 p.m. today, this easternmost town in the continental United States bade farewell to the last day of the 1990's, with a bone-chilling ceremony at the candy-cane-striped lighthouse at West Quoddy Head, the easternmost point of this easternmost town. A children's chorus did its tentative best, politicians spoke, and everybody went home for hot chocolate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The pastel sky over the Bay of Fundy darkened from peach glow to dim lavender. Taps sounded; the flag descended; and there came the soft thunder of a muffled stampede: hearty applause from more than 300 pairs of gloved and mittened hands.</p>
        <p>That is how, at 3:57 p.m. today, this easternmost town in the continental United States bade farewell to the last day of the 1990's, with a bone-chilling ceremony at the candy-cane-striped lighthouse at West Quoddy Head, the easternmost point of this easternmost town. A children's chorus did its tentative best, politicians spoke, and everybody went home for hot chocolate.</p>
        <p>''This is Maine's version of Times Square, right here in Lubec, Maine,'' said Representative John Baldacci.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Baldacci nor anybody else seemed to think the Maine version came off the worse in that comparison.</p>
        <p>A town of about 1,800, miles from the nearest traffic light, Lubec is heartily exploiting the prime viewing of the new year that its easternmost position affords. National media coverage has brought visitors from as far as Virginia and Manhattan for Saturday's dawn ceremony, and the caps and T-shirts reading ''First Light 2000'' and suchlike have been selling fast.</p>
        <p>But the ceremonies, and the trinkets, and the town itself are unmistakably homespun, from the festive baked bean supper to the festive polar bear dip to the festive bonfire at the Frog Pond, and that was the core of their appeal to many visitors, more than any geographic distinction.</p>
        <p>''It's a small-town celebration, it's unique,'' said Brett Golladay, 20, a student at the College of William and Mary, explaining why she and her friend Dan Degnan had driven 15 hours to get here. ''I wanted to do something unique for the new year.''</p>
        <p>Part of the homespun appeal is that while they are happy to have visitors and attention, townspeople are too sensible to make much of this millennial moment.</p>
        <p>''I hate to be a party pooper but it's just another day,'' said Hazel Avery, a volunteer with the town's historical society. She was helping the society at the craft fair at the school gym, where handknit booties could be bought for $4. She planned to skip Saturday's dawn ceremony.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to stay where it's nice and warm,'' she said.</p>
        <p>At the town post office, clerks offered a special ''Last Light of the Old Millennium'' cancellation, but Edward Fletcher, a fisherman stopping in on an errand, was not getting one. Nor was he excited by the whole First Light thing.</p>
        <p>''I get up every morning and see the sun come up, it's no big deal,'' he said. ''When I get up tomorrow I'm still going to have bills, and I'm still going to be married to the same woman, so what's the big deal?''</p>
        <p>But to more excitable types, the Lubec area offered multiple millennial thrills.</p>
        <p>Peter and Sandy Kaynor, of Peru, Me., planned to celebrate midnight in New Brunswick, in the Atlantic time zone, then cross the bridge to Calais, Me., to celebrate in the Eastern time zone, then, Mr. Kaynor said, ''catch a quick nap and drive down here for dawn.''</p>
        <p>There has been a bit of dispute over exactly where the first rays of 2000 will hit in the continental United States. Some hardy souls planned to climb Cadillac Mountain near Bar Harbor, Me., saying they believed it would get the first rays because of its height. Nantucket Island also put forth a claim of first-light primacy.</p>
        <p>According to the official Lubec Millennium Web site, the Naval Observatory said that sunrise in the three spots would be nearly simultaneous, at about 7:04, but that Lubec would in fact be first. Just to be sure, people in each spot plan to stay in contact by cellular phone and announce when they first see the sunrise. The competition, the Web site emphasized, is friendly.</p>
        <p>There is a serious side to Lubec's millennial hoopla, however. The town may call itself a ''sleepy fishing village,'' but the subtext is that it depends on a troubled industry, and it is a poor town, with a per capita income of under $9,000, in one of the poorest counties in New England.</p>
        <p>Some residents say they hope the attention paid Lubec this New Year's, while it might not persuade many to visit in midwinter, might pay off next summer in tourism.</p>
        <p>''It's really put us on the map because of this,'' said Junia Lehman, owner of West Quoddy Gifts.</p>
        <p>Some brave travelers, though, were not about to wait for summer and miss this special dawn.</p>
        <p>''We just wanted to do something a little different, and it's a really comfortable, down-home place,'' said Jonathan Herzog, a Manhattan lawyer, who made the the 10-hour journey with his friend Allen Roth, a real-estate developer, and his dog, Nash.</p>
        <p>Times Square ''has too many people,'' Mr. Herzog said, adding, ''That's only for out-of-towners.''</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
