<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'We Just Waited for Our Moment to Be Killed'</title>
    <meta content="01CAMB$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: CAMBODIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genocide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cambodia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Khmer Rouge (Cambodia)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Touch Kea</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Touch Sopharath</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Cambodia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEEDE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'We Just Waited for Our Moment to Be Killed'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Seth Mydans</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Touch Kea, 75, barber to King Norodom Sihanouk of Cambodia, recalls horrors of Khmer Rouge genocide in late 1970's, while Touch Sopharath, a 19-year-old granddaugher of his and a law student, looks forward to a normal life; chronology of Cambodian history since 1953 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few countries suffered as deeply as Cambodia over the last half-century. The tiny, beautiful Southeast Asian land was a battleground among the great powers and the scene of hugely destructive American bombing during the Vietnam War. Then its own internal demons rose from within its people's brutalized psyche. Cambodia became the scene of horrific mass killings by the radical communist Khmer Rouge, who from 1975 to 1979 took the lives of as many as one-fourth of the population of eight million.</p>
        <p>Cambodia has still not recovered. It remains a place of political violence and of ugly daily conflicts among its traumatized people. For Touch Kea, 75, the barber to King Norodom Sihanouk, the country's culture is still dominated by its horrors and its loss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few countries suffered as deeply as Cambodia over the last half-century. The tiny, beautiful Southeast Asian land was a battleground among the great powers and the scene of hugely destructive American bombing during the Vietnam War. Then its own internal demons rose from within its people's brutalized psyche. Cambodia became the scene of horrific mass killings by the radical communist Khmer Rouge, who from 1975 to 1979 took the lives of as many as one-fourth of the population of eight million.</p>
        <p>Cambodia has still not recovered. It remains a place of political violence and of ugly daily conflicts among its traumatized people. For Touch Kea, 75, the barber to King Norodom Sihanouk, the country's culture is still dominated by its horrors and its loss.</p>
        <p>But sheer youth can regenerate hope. The possibilities ahead look very different to one of Touch Kea's granddaughters, Touch Sopharath, 19, a law student. Her generation is in pursuit of the mundane treasure of normalcy.</p>
        <p>SETH MYDANS</p>
        <p>TOUCH KEA</p>
        <p>I cannot know about the new century. I'm already 75 and won't live much longer. But I can tell you that the past has been very hard. First we had to put up with the French colonialists, then the French and the Japanese fighting over our territory. Finally we got independence under our king, Norodom Sihanouk. We had peace and prosperity for a few years and then there was the Lon Nol coup in 1970 and the fighting and the American bombing; we were suffering again.</p>
        <p>In 1975 came the Khmer Rouge, and for three years, eight months and 20 days we lived in fear. We just waited for our moment to be killed. We never knew when our time would come. Before the Khmer Rouge I owned a barbershop and a restaurant and a dance club. Then suddenly I had nothing. At that time we were so poor in everything -- clothes, medicine, food, everything. If we saw an animal or even an insect crossing our path, we would just kill it and eat it raw. That's how hungry we were.</p>
        <p>In those days, whenever we saw a horsecart come to the village, we knew that one or two families would be taken away to be killed and we would never see them again. They planned to kill me, too. Three times they planned to kill me, but I escaped. But they killed my three children and my three grandchildren and my son-in-law. All were executed. If we talk in terms of Buddhism, I went to hell while I was alive.</p>
        <p>It was only a few years when the king ruled Cambodia that I could say the country was a happy place. You do the math. The rest of my life has been suffering. I think the king has a similar feeling. I've been cutting his hair, whenever he is in the country, since 1991. He likes to chat while I am cutting.</p>
        <p>He says he is sorry that he is old and he cannot go out to see the people; he calls them his children. He is very concerned that his children might be missing him. He compares himself to a candle that is burning out.</p>
        <p>We are all like that. Everybody is tired. We are just tired from all the events of the past. I don't think about happiness anymore. I don't think about hope. I just work for today and eat for today. Tomorrow will be the same. I will get up and work and eat and sleep.</p>
        <p>But looking into the future, no. I've given up hoping. All I have to say is, goodbye to the past century and I hope we won't see anything like it again.</p>
        <p>TOUCH SOPHARATH</p>
        <p>That's just the way my grandfather talks. All the old people talk like that. We try to help him, to make him happy, but he doesn't want to be happy. He prefers to think he is not happy. He always says his family doesn't think about him, but whenever we try to take him out somewhere he says he is too busy with his business.</p>
        <p>I don't know too much about those times. I was born in 1979, the year the Khmer Rouge regime ended. I hear my parents and my grandfather and my teachers say there was a lot of suffering. But I was not affected by that.</p>
        <p>This year I got married, and I'm in my last year of law school.</p>
        <p>I want to be a good lawyer, so I can help protect all the people who are abused by the ones who hold power.</p>
        <p>I don't know if I will be good enough, but I will try. So many people are suffering. So many are poor. So many have no school. People are afraid even to go out of their houses at night. Right now, I don't even want to read the newspapers because I'm afraid to look at the photographs. Every day more people are being robbed and killed and kidnapped.</p>
        <p>But I think Cambodia will change. People will become more educated and they will stop killing each other and help each other to develop the country.</p>
        <p>For me, I want a good, happy family. I want to help people. And I want to make money so I will be able to support myself and not depend on my mother.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: CAMBODIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
