<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Soothing an Old Ache</title>
    <meta content="01BEAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1968)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Lena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beamon, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7D91338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Soothing an Old Ache</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LENA WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Lena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on former long jumper Bob Beamon discusses his unhappy childhood growing up in South Jamaica, Queens; notes that his record long jump of 29 feet 2 1/2 inches at 1968 Olympics in Mexico City stood for 23 years; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Through it all -- the Olympic gold medal for the long jump, the world record that stood for 23 years, the private audiences with heads of state -- Bob Beamon always felt like the untouched, unloved, unwanted child he was raised to believe he was.</p>
        <p>Neither the outpouring of affection from an adoring public nor the love he finally found after four failed marriages could make up for the neglect and physical abuse he suffered as a child growing up in South Jamaica, Queens. What Beamon remembers most about his childhood were the stories his father, James, and his paternal grandmother, Bessie, who raised him, told him about his mother, Naomi Brown Beamon. His mother died at age 25 when Beamon was 8 months old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Through it all -- the Olympic gold medal for the long jump, the world record that stood for 23 years, the private audiences with heads of state -- Bob Beamon always felt like the untouched, unloved, unwanted child he was raised to believe he was.</p>
        <p>Neither the outpouring of affection from an adoring public nor the love he finally found after four failed marriages could make up for the neglect and physical abuse he suffered as a child growing up in South Jamaica, Queens. What Beamon remembers most about his childhood were the stories his father, James, and his paternal grandmother, Bessie, who raised him, told him about his mother, Naomi Brown Beamon. His mother died at age 25 when Beamon was 8 months old.</p>
        <p>''They said my mother never held me,'' recalled Beamon, who was in New York in early December to accept an award from Sports Illustrated, which cited his record-setting long jump during the 1968 Olympics as one of the 10 greatest sports events of the century. ''When I was born, they said she left me in the hospital. Beyond that, nobody talked about my mother or her side of the family. It was one of those hush-hush things.''</p>
        <p>In his recently published autobiography, ''The Man Who Could Fly'' (Genesis Press), Beamon describes how, at age 35, he finally summoned the courage to confront his grandmother about a lifetime of things left unsaid. Only then did he discover he had been lied to.</p>
        <p>Not only had his mother held him, there was visual proof of it. A black-and-white photograph shows his mother standing on a street corner holding her son in her arms. His mother, who had tuberculosis at the time of his birth, died shortly after the picture was taken.</p>
        <p>''The picture was incredible in terms of what I'd heard, that she never held me,'' Beamon said. ''It was communication with my mother and I. So when my wife and I were writing this book, things started to come together and make sense.''</p>
        <p>Beamon found out that the secrecy surrounding his mother's life and the estrangement between the Brown and Beamon families were brought about because his mother, who had been physically abused by her husband, became pregnant with Bob when her husband was in prison. Beamon's biological father was a physician who worked at the hospital where his mother worked as a nurse's aide. His mother never told the doctor about the pregnancy.</p>
        <p>''She didn't take me home because she was too ill to care for me and because my daddy had threatened to kill me if she ever brought me to his house,'' Beamon said. He was sent to live with his grandmother in Harlem, while his half brother, Andrew, who was mentally retarded, lived with his mother in Queens.</p>
        <p>Bob Beamon had cause to become another one of the countless poverty-stricken urban youths consumed by the lures of the streets, drugs or violence. Instead, he rose above circumstance through sports.</p>
        <p>Beamon may have gone to school in what he described as his grandfather's ''prewar, two-sizes-too-big'' clothes, he may have gone to bed hungry and he may gone through his young life untouched by loving arms, but he knew how to jump.</p>
        <p>''I could jump higher than the older boys,'' writes Beamon, who at 6 feet 4 inches was also a talented basketball player. ''Even when I was in elementary school, everybody always wanted me on their team.''</p>
        <p>As a student at Jamaica High School, Beamon came under the tutelage of Larry Ellis, the renowned track coach, and was named to the all-American track and field team as well as the all-city squad.</p>
        <p>In 1965, his senior year, Beamon was ranked second in the long jump in the United States and received a track-and-field scholarship to the University of Texas at El Paso. Three years later, on a humid October afternoon in Mexico City, Beamon soared through the thin air, landing 29 feet 2 1/2 inches later into a sand pit of Olympic glory. Mike Powell broke the record in 1991, but Beamon still holds the Olympic record.</p>
        <p>The jump, once deemed by many as the single greatest individual achievement in sports, seemed so surreal to Beamon, it has taken years for him to fully appreciate its magnificence.</p>
        <p>''So much was going on with the black athletes threatening to boycott the games and all the stuff in my personal life and the problems back at UTEP,'' said Beamon, a soft-spoken man with an acquired flair for fashion.</p>
        <p>At the time, Beamon was living through an unhappy marriage to a former high school girlfriend he believed to be pregnant with his child -- she was not -- and had lost his athletic scholarship after he and eight other members of the university's track team boycotted a meet at Brigham Young University. The team was protesting references in the Book of Mormon that castigate the black race as inferior.</p>
        <p>What Beamon does remember about Mexico City, beyond the image of Tommie Smith and John Carlos standing on the awards podium with black-gloved fists raised above their bowed heads, was that his high school sweetheart was in the stands cheering him on.</p>
        <p>''Even with all the competitions I had been in since I was 17, I never had a loved one or family member in the stands rooting for me,'' he wrote. ''Just from that personal point of view, I knew that this was even more special than I had ever imagined.''</p>
        <p>These days life is sweet for Beamon, now 53. He lives in Miami and is happily married to Milana Walter Beamon, a film producer, who helped him co-write his book. He has a new job as director of athletic development at Florida Atlantic University in Boca Raton. His book tour is playing to receptive audiences. And a public service announcement he filmed for the Children's Court Centennial Communication Project, a program to commemorate the 100th anniversary of Juvenile Court that interviews 25 people whose lives have been changed by judges or other officers of the court, is being shown across the country.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, he still longs for those lost shared moments of his childhood and youth. So Beamon, who was not allowed to get close to his mother's side of the family, is making up for lost time.</p>
        <p>He and his cousin Diane Brown Brisbane, his mother's brother's daughter, talk often on the telephone.  Brisbane was the relative who located the only surviving print of Beamon and his mother and attended his book signing in Manhattan in November. He has also established ties with his great-aunt, Emmie King, who wanted to raise Beamon and tried, unsuccessfully, to locate him and his brother, who died in 1993. Beamon later found out that his aunt and uncle were literally just around the corner.</p>
        <p>''When Naomi died, I kept asking about her children and I never got an answer,'' King recalled. ''Bob shouldn't have had to go through life thinking he was unwanted because that wasn't the case.''</p>
        <p>On Dec. 2, when Beamon rose from his seat at Madison Square Garden to accept his award, his wife, Aunt Emmie, her companion, George Butler, Brisbane and her son, Al, 35, were present in the audience. This time around, Beamon had family cheering for him.</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
