<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'We Accepted That We Were Working for the Good of the Country'</title>
    <meta content="01RUSS$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: RUSSIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohlen, Celestine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kovalyova, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lebedev, Aleksandr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4DE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1231" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'We Accepted That We Were Working for the Good of the Country'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Celestine Bohlen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bohlen, Celestine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aleksandr Lebedev, 85, who rose from a peasant's son to become first Soviet deputy minister of higher education, and Maria Kovalyova, a 21-year-old student in Moscow, share a dismay at Russia's slipshod democracy and bandit capitalism over the last decade; photos; chronology of Russian history since 1917 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Revolution and change convulsed Russia twice in the last century, the first time in 1917, when the Bolsheviks seized power, and then in 1991, when the communist system they introduced, at such a fearful cost, collapsed under its own weight. Each time ordinary lives were swept up, sometimes swept away. In midcentury, millions died, killed by war, famine and a totalitarian regime.</p>
        <p>But millions more survived, and some came out on top, like Aleksandr Lebedev, 85, a peasant's son who rose to become the first deputy minister of higher education. Like many members of his generation, he feels that World War II galvanized his life more than the revolution. But by the mid-1980's, his sense of patriotic purpose had frayed, and disillusionment set in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Revolution and change convulsed Russia twice in the last century, the first time in 1917, when the Bolsheviks seized power, and then in 1991, when the communist system they introduced, at such a fearful cost, collapsed under its own weight. Each time ordinary lives were swept up, sometimes swept away. In midcentury, millions died, killed by war, famine and a totalitarian regime.</p>
        <p>But millions more survived, and some came out on top, like Aleksandr Lebedev, 85, a peasant's son who rose to become the first deputy minister of higher education. Like many members of his generation, he feels that World War II galvanized his life more than the revolution. But by the mid-1980's, his sense of patriotic purpose had frayed, and disillusionment set in.</p>
        <p>In that same period, Maria Kovalyova, 18, then a schoolgirl in Moscow, was just becoming aware of a system that was denying her more than it was able to offer her. She is now a first-year student in the International Business Study program at the Plekhanov Institute of Economics. For both Mr. Lebedev and Ms. Kovalyova, the last decade, with its slipshod democracy and bandit capitalism, has proved to be a disappointment. Russia, they say, has still not found its equilibrium.</p>
        <p>CELESTINE BOHLEN</p>
        <p>ALEKSANDR LEBEDEV</p>
        <p>I was 4 years old when the October Revolution happened, so I don't remember what life was like before. My father was a farm worker in a village outside Voronezh, in southern Russia, who after the revolution held a top position in the local food-processing industry, so that was a positive side of the revolution. But there were negative sides: as the son of a government employee, I had difficulty getting a higher education. All the places were reserved for workers or peasants. Still, I managed and got an education.</p>
        <p>After the army, I came back to Voronezh and went to work in a factory. When the Great Patriotic War [World War II] began, the factory was evacuated to the east. I was in charge of an assembly line that had fallen behind its production schedule. We were able to fulfill the plan, and that was when I got my first Red Banner of Labor, and went from being a candidate member to a full member of the Communist Party.</p>
        <p>After the war, I went on to university, and from there to the Ministry of Higher Education, and rose through the ranks from inspector to head to first deputy minister.</p>
        <p>It was the war, of course, that compelled me to give everything -- my whole self, all my efforts -- to my work, to my country. Like everyone else, we lived through the hard times -- repression, collectivization, industrialization. I knew people who were arrested in the 1930's. We knew people who were good people who were taken away, but we had no information to make a judgment. We could only assume that if they were arrested, then there must have been a reason.</p>
        <p>It was only after I retired in 1984 [just before Mikhail S. Gorbachev began perestroika] that I started to think, to analyze the role of the party -- not from a theoretical point of view, but from practice, from real life. I realized that our role was only to execute the commands of the party. There were people who couldn't blow their noses if they didn't get an order from the Central Committee.</p>
        <p>That was when I realized that the dictatorship of the party was constraining the people who were ready to take initiative, to do the things that needed to be done.</p>
        <p>At the beginning, we accepted that we were working for the good of the country. But experience showed me that not all of the party's commands were correct, that we were just screws in the party's machinery.</p>
        <p>What would have happened to me if the October Revolution hadn't happened? My father was a farm worker. Maybe I would have had an education, but probably not.</p>
        <p>MARIA KOVALYOVA</p>
        <p>Before 1991, I remember going to stores. There was nothing there -- empty shelves, people had to stand in line. After 1991, there was the hope that we were going to live better. The first time I realized that changes had come was when I went with my family to Spain in 1992. Before that, travel was practically impossible. As for the future, I thought there would be good jobs and a stable situation and a goal we would all be working toward. Russia is still developing, but now we know it will take a long time.</p>
        <p>We haven't been governed well. I remember our teacher in history class in school, who ran through the list of czars: one was crazy, another was half an imbecile, and so on. Our country has not been lucky. And now the political situation is not stable: there is corruption, people are taking our money and putting it in their own pockets. But it all depends on the people's choice. Everything depends on whom the people choose. I don't know how I will vote, or what will happen in the next elections. But if they choose Zyuganov [the leader of the Russian Communist Party], then it will get worse. Living here, you don't know what will happen next. Yes, I have thought of the idea of leaving, but then, on the other hand, if I go somewhere else, who will need me there? Besides, Moscow is my city, my native city. It is beautiful, and it is changing, changing fast.</p>
        <p>I have been abroad, and I am amazed at people's idea of Russia -- they think bears roam in the streets of Moscow, that people drink vodka night and day, that there is no electricity. Of course, this is very offensive to me; I don't think they understand what is happening here.</p>
        <p>I have wider opportunities than my parents had. Maybe their lives were more stable, but now the opportunities are greater, and there is a choice. The most important thing is internal freedom, the freedom to choose.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: RUSSIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
