<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Up Periscope! Submarine Service Is 100, and Unsilent</title>
    <meta content="01SUBM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stamps (Postal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, Robert A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DE1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Up Periscope! Submarine Service Is 100, and Unsilent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamilton, Robert A</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Navy's submarine force prepares to celebrate its centennial year, which begins Jan 1; special observations are planned throughout New York region; United States Postal Service will issue series of five stamps depicting 100 years of submarine history; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After spending most of its first 100 years as the ''silent service,'' the Navy's submarine force is preparing to make a lot of noise during its centennial year, which begins today.</p>
        <p>Throughout the New York region, special observations are planned -- on Long Island, where the first submarine base was established; in Connecticut, where the nation's most active submarine base is situated now; in New York Harbor, where the Intrepid Sea-Air-Space Museum will host a special submarine exhibit, and in New Jersey, where the first commissioned submarine was built.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After spending most of its first 100 years as the ''silent service,'' the Navy's submarine force is preparing to make a lot of noise during its centennial year, which begins today.</p>
        <p>Throughout the New York region, special observations are planned -- on Long Island, where the first submarine base was established; in Connecticut, where the nation's most active submarine base is situated now; in New York Harbor, where the Intrepid Sea-Air-Space Museum will host a special submarine exhibit, and in New Jersey, where the first commissioned submarine was built.</p>
        <p>The United States Postal Service will issue a series of five stamps in April depicting 100 years of submarine history, with the first-day issue planned for the newly expanded Submarine Force Library and Museum in Groton, Conn. The Smithsonian Institution in Washington will host a yearlong exhibit that will display parts of three decommissioned submarines.</p>
        <p>''I think it's a great way for us to reflect on the past, to talk about 100 years of innovation, excellence, and sacrifice,'' said Vice Adm. Edmund P. Giambastiani Jr., commander of the Atlantic submarine force. ''But it's also a great way to look at the next 100 years, to consider the innovation that we're trying to bring about.''</p>
        <p>Among other events planned during the year will be birthday balls in every submarine port, as well as in Washington; the dedication of memorials or commemorative parks in Kings Bay, Ga., Charleston, S. C., and Bangor, Wash.; and a special blessing of the fleet at the Navy Memorial in Washington.</p>
        <p>Submariners debate when to mark the actual birthday of the force. Some argue for April 11, 1900, when the Navy bought the U.S.S. Holland from Electric Boat Company, with its factory in Elizabeth, N.J., for $160,000 -- a far cry from today's $2.5 billion Seawolf submarines Electric Boat, now a division of General Dynamics, builds in Groton. Others say the force was born Oct. 12, 1900, when the Holland finished its sea trials and was formally placed in commission.</p>
        <p>Rear Adm. John B. Padgett III, commander of the Navy's Northeast Region, and a submariner, said the Northeast is still the center of the submarine force. The base in Groton is home to the Naval Submarine School, where all who serve in submarines start their careers.</p>
        <p>April 11 will see the dedication of New Suffolk Memorial by submarine veterans' groups on the site in Long Island where Navy crews tested the first ''torpedo boats'' of inventor John P. Holland, years before a permanent base was established at Groton.</p>
        <p>John R. Saeli, one of the organizers of a campaign that raised the $20,000 to build the memorial, said he hoped it would reinforce the importance of the Northeast to submarining.</p>
        <p>''People had no idea that Long Island was really the birthplace of the submarine service, or that the first submarine was built in Elizabeth, N.J.,'' Mr. Saeli said. ''In fact, there are a lot of submarine sailors who don't know about the history. So while most of the country is having an observance of some sort, we're going to kick it all off by dedicating the site here where it all started.''</p>
        <p>At the Submarine Force Library and Museum, retired Capt. John J. Demlein Jr. has headed a campaign that raised $4 million to double its size. The museum, which opened in 1986 when the Historic Ship Nautilus, the first nuclear submarine in the world, returned to Groton to become a museum ship. The museum is the fourth most popular tourism attraction in the state.</p>
        <p>In the past, the museum could show fewer than 5 percent of its 65,000 artifacts at any one time. Captain Demlein said the expansion will be dedicated the third week of April, to coincide with the centennial celebration, and will include a cross-section of a modern Los Angeles-class submarine and a control center from an older submarine.</p>
        <p>''This really is a celebration of our heritage here in New England,'' said Admiral Padgett. Not only were the first submarines built and based here, he said, but it was the tactics honed during war games in the waters of Long Island Sound and Narragansett Bay off Rhode Island that allowed them to be so vital in World War II after the attack on Pearl Harbor devastated the surface fleet.</p>
        <p>''When we didn't have anything else, the skills we had developed here in the Northeast were put into use in the Pacific,'' Admiral Padgett said. ''We are standing on the shoulders of heroes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
