<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The House of the Future? Still Four Walls and a Roof</title>
    <meta content="01HOME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165182"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: CITIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holusha, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3D81530F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The House of the Future? Still Four Walls and a Roof</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew C. Revkin and John Holusha</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holusha, John; Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts discuss trends in the kinds of homes Americans will want in 21st century and how they will be built; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT kind of house will the suburbanites of tomorrow inhabit?</p>
        <p>It could well be the same kind of house they are living in now. Despite some predictions that today's subdivisions will become tomorrow's slums -- or simply crumble into sheetrock dust -- many planners, builders and housing experts think that a lot of 20th-century housing will endure, and much of what is built in the 21st century will look familiar. While styles change -- lately, for instance, less emphasis has been placed on formal parlors and more on family recreation spaces -- the basics remain the same.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT kind of house will the suburbanites of tomorrow inhabit?</p>
        <p>It could well be the same kind of house they are living in now. Despite some predictions that today's subdivisions will become tomorrow's slums -- or simply crumble into sheetrock dust -- many planners, builders and housing experts think that a lot of 20th-century housing will endure, and much of what is built in the 21st century will look familiar. While styles change -- lately, for instance, less emphasis has been placed on formal parlors and more on family recreation spaces -- the basics remain the same.</p>
        <p>''People do not want to live in glass cubes or geodesic domes,'' said Michael Medick, chairman of the housing committee of the American Institute of Architects.</p>
        <p>Construction methods and materials, though, will be different, with the Japanese practice of fabricating big parts of houses in factories likely to spread. Home design will place more emphasis on the use of natural light and recyclable materials. Sensors will tell houses to warm or cool only occupied rooms.</p>
        <p>''There is going to be radical change in the intelligence of buildings,'' said Randolph Croxton, a New York architect who specializes in environmentally sensitive designs.</p>
        <p>The trend toward renovating existing homes is also expected to continue; during  the 1990's, Americans began spending more on renovations than on building new houses.</p>
        <p>''I pick up a lot of dissatisfaction among college design students with all the moving around their parents did,'' said Donald Carr, a senior researcher for the National Association of Home Builders. ''They want to be less mobile and have houses that are more organic -- ones that can grow with a family's needs and then shrink as the needs decline, all in the same location.''</p>
        <p>The great burst of home construction after World War II peaked along with the baby boom, creating what is now $10 trillion worth of housing -- ''one of the major storeholds of wealth in the American economy,'' said William C. Apgar, the commissioner of the Federal Housing Authority.</p>
        <p>''Some people imagine that inventory will change rapidly,'' he added. ''But you don't scrap something because a calendar year turns. That housing will be a dominant force for a long time to come.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Friedman, a longtime home inspector and carpenter in the Hudson Valley north of New York City, says there is an illusion that everything from the old days was built to last and only new houses are shoddily erected. ''It's easy to forget that in the 1800's they built lousy stuff, too,'' he said. ''It's just all fallen down or been torn down.''</p>
        <p>In decades to come, the same fate will befall houses built during the suburban boom. Houses, Mr. Friedman said, are like species or civilizations: only the strong -- or adaptable -- survive.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, new houses will continue to be built to satisfy new markets, like the exploding demand for retirement housing. The main changes are expected to be in how houses are constructed, rather than in their basic design, said Ross Heitzmann, director of the research center of the National Association of Home Builders.</p>
        <p>The use of factory-built modular sections is expected to gain in popularity. Houses -- or at least their main components -- will become akin to large appliances, Mr. Heitzmann said. They will be made in factories by relatively unskilled workers or robots and installed on a site by a few specialized workers. To cut the labor of hammering studs and hanging drywall, walls are likely to become lightweight insulated panels, often containing electrical or plumbing connections that can be clicked together like Lego pieces.</p>
        <p>Existing homes will steadily be rebuilt, resided, reroofed and expanded to suit new uses, evolving along with the economy -- as they always have. More new materials are being tried every year. A Swiss researcher, studying sausage casings, has developed a new moisture barrier for exterior walls that adjusts to suit the changing seasons, Mr. Heitzmann said.</p>
        <p>This idea may succeed -- as did insulating double-glazed windows -- or it may fail, like asbestos siding, lead paint and other once-common building materials that now present big problems. But the housing stock, over all, will endure and adapt.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: CITIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
