<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Generation's Anthem: 'Smells Like Teen Pressure'</title>
    <meta content="01TEEN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: IDENTITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Dirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E0DF1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Generation's Anthem: 'Smells Like Teen Pressure'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dirk Johnson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Dirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American teenagers feel pressure to succeed at dawn of new century; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOUNG, hip and smart, Casey Collier seems to glide from one peak to the next, knocking out A's, winning student council elections and starring in the school play.</p>
        <p>She is an 18-year-old with a dazzling future. So why does she fret?</p>
        <p>''I feel overwhelmed -- I feel like, 'Oh my gosh, this stress,' '' said Miss Collier, a senior at Shawnee Mission North High School in Kansas, outside Kansas City. ''The other night, I wondered, 'Is it possible to have a nervous breakdown at age 18?' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOUNG, hip and smart, Casey Collier seems to glide from one peak to the next, knocking out A's, winning student council elections and starring in the school play.</p>
        <p>She is an 18-year-old with a dazzling future. So why does she fret?</p>
        <p>''I feel overwhelmed -- I feel like, 'Oh my gosh, this stress,' '' said Miss Collier, a senior at Shawnee Mission North High School in Kansas, outside Kansas City. ''The other night, I wondered, 'Is it possible to have a nervous breakdown at age 18?' ''</p>
        <p>Coming of age at a time when technology is magic, the economy is purring like a mountain lion and the nation's cultural hegemony is unrivaled, American teenagers might be expected to look at the 21st century as the promised land: theirs for the taking.</p>
        <p>But in conversations about the future with dozens of teenagers -- in sleepy farm towns and hip-hop urban neighborhoods and leafy suburbs -- one word threaded them together: pressure. Virtually every one of these teenagers spoke about the looming demand that they succeed and the trepidation they feel about whether they can measure up.</p>
        <p>''People feel like young people today have so many opportunities, that if you don't succeed, then what's wrong with you,'' said Ali Cruso, a 16-year-old high school sophomore in Westerly, R.I. ''The bar has really been raised high.''</p>
        <p>Groomed by a golden age of national triumph, American teenagers see their charge as obvious: Do not drop the ball.</p>
        <p>It is too early to know how such a foundation will shape these young people, as they set out to shape the new century. With their anxieties about the future and economic security, the children of affluence seem to share something, oddly enough, with the children of the Depression, whose life and legacy was pervaded by the sense that the bottom could drop out at any time.</p>
        <p>Being a hardheaded realist can be useful. It curbs utopian excesses. But if young Americans take on the 21st century simply playing not to lose, will they undermine the expansion they are trying to protect? A willingness to risk, after all, lies at the core of American successes.</p>
        <p>In his book ''The Rise and Fall of the American Teenager,'' Thomas Hine argues that the notion of a teenager was an invention of the New Deal, a way to extend childhood as to keep young people out of jobs desperately needed by men and women.</p>
        <p>But America today needs workers, and teenagers seem ready to get to work.</p>
        <p>Miss Cruso said: ''We are the richest young generation in history. We have cars, cell phones, stereos, pagers.'' But privilege is only one end of the bargain.</p>
        <p>''It seems like, if you mess up here, it's going to affect your whole life,'' said Matt Scheidler, an 18-year-old high school senior in Chicago. ''Life shouldn't be terrible if you make one mistake.''</p>
        <p>Growing up in the culture of money, teenagers have been schooled to be shrewd. They invest in mutual funds. They plan for early retirement. They know about Bill Gates as their parents knew about Paul McCartney. The importance of possessions is so taken for granted by many that it goes unquestioned. One hit song of 1999 could have been a fashion advertisement. ''I like girls who wear Abercrombie &amp; Fitch,'' the band LFO crooned about cooler-than-cool jeans that can't be touched for less than $70.</p>
        <p>Adam Coleman, 15, a sophomore in Littleton, Colo., does not hesitate about his career goals. ''I want to be wealthy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The 31 million people between 12 and 19 spent $153 billion this year, which has made them a bull's-eye for the nation's marketers. An entire television network, the WB, aims at teenagers with ''Dawson's Creek'' and ''Buffy the Vampire Slayer.''</p>
        <p>If money reigns, ''cute'' and ''brute'' come next. The top Web site for boys features professional wrestling. The top Web site for girls is MTV's, where the musical acts are increasingly known more for heartthrob looks than their timbre.</p>
        <p>While earlier generations found touchstones in books like ''The Catcher in the Rye'' and ''Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance,'' no contemporary text seems to have galvanized today's teenagers. College professors bemoan that a big share of incoming freshmen cannot name the last full-length book they read.</p>
        <p>But teenagers hear in such lamentations the tone of a sneer. On a range of issues, they say they feel wounded by characterizations of teenagers as shallow at least, and menacing at worst.</p>
        <p>Jessica Brown, a 16-year-old high school sophomore in rural Leland, Ill., said teenagers were tired of being seen as trouble.</p>
        <p>''When a group of teenagers walk into a store, everybody gets real nervous,'' Miss Brown said. ''People are afraid of us, like we're going to hurt them.''</p>
        <p>In her view, the enormous publicity over recent school shootings has irrationally tarnished the image of teenagers, who often feel invisible around adults, Miss Cruso said. ''They won't make eye contact, as if we're all juvenile delinquents,'' she said.</p>
        <p>As some teenagers see it, the generation now running the world, notably the baby boomers, should scarcely throw stones.</p>
        <p>Ryan Watson, a 14-year-old who lives on the West Side of Chicago, said today's teenagers get along much better than their elders with people of different races. ''People now know that if you can't get along with someone because of their race, well, you're not going to get very far in life,'' he said.</p>
        <p>What concerns Mr. Watson, and many other teenagers, is the seemingly unstoppable power of technology. Although some 88 percent of teenagers have found their way onto the Internet, and sending e-mail is almost as popular as talking on the telephone, many say the computer is a dangerous tool. Mr. Watson, himself something of a computer programmer, said young people await human cloning and artificial intelligence as surely as an earlier generation anticipated man's walking on the moon.</p>
        <p>But virtual reality blurs the line between truth and image in unsettling ways. Amy Smith, 15, a sophomore in Bloomington, Ill., said she had stopped using chat rooms.  ''Who's real and who's not?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>For the most part, teenagers are much more worried about earning the right college admission, getting a sheepskin and making their way up the ladder. ''I just want to reach my goals as quickly as I can,'' Miss Cruso said. ''There's a lot of pressure.''</p>
        <p>VISIONS: IDENTITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
