<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Works In Progress From All Over; Spartan Women, Liberated</title>
    <meta content="01SPAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greek Civilization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sparta (Greece)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pomeroy, Sarah B (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zuckerman, Laurence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DD1238F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Works In Progress From All Over; Spartan Women, Liberated</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURENCE ZUCKERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zuckerman, Laurence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arts &amp; Ideas look ahead at works-in-progress; Prof Sarah B Pomeroy discusses her study of women in ancient Sparta, usually believed to have been as grim as their menfolk; Pomeroy says Sparta actually was one of few Greek states to educate their women, who drank wine and were famous for their beauty (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The centruy's turn has been a time of retrospectives: what was the most important event, who was the most influential thinker? Arts &amp; Ideas decided to take a look ahead at what some of today's researchers are working on. From the most raked-over field, like the history of the ancient world, to the latest medical technology, scholars are coming up with fresh insights. Some ideas may turn into breakthroughs, and others may turn out to be dead-ends, but the journey is rarely boring. Here is a handful of works in progress.</p>
        <p>With scholars poring over the same texts for centuries, ancient history would appear to be a field in which it is difficult to plow new ground. But Sarah B. Pomeroy, distinguished professor of classics at Hunter College and the Graduate Center of the City University of New York, says there is much to be learned about the women of Sparta, the ancient city-state in southern Greece that defeated Athens in the Peloponnesian War.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The centruy's turn has been a time of retrospectives: what was the most important event, who was the most influential thinker? Arts &amp; Ideas decided to take a look ahead at what some of today's researchers are working on. From the most raked-over field, like the history of the ancient world, to the latest medical technology, scholars are coming up with fresh insights. Some ideas may turn into breakthroughs, and others may turn out to be dead-ends, but the journey is rarely boring. Here is a handful of works in progress.</p>
        <p>With scholars poring over the same texts for centuries, ancient history would appear to be a field in which it is difficult to plow new ground. But Sarah B. Pomeroy, distinguished professor of classics at Hunter College and the Graduate Center of the City University of New York, says there is much to be learned about the women of Sparta, the ancient city-state in southern Greece that defeated Athens in the Peloponnesian War.</p>
        <p>''It's very difficult in my field to find a subject that nobody has taken seriously,'' Ms. Pomeroy said. ''This subject has been around for 2,500 years but has turned out to be totally fresh.''</p>
        <p>Sparta, which existed from 800 B.C. until A.D. 200, was renowned in the ancient world as a stoic, martial city-state that practiced eugenics. It was the society that inspired the modern English word ''laconic'' (after Laconia, the region surrounding Sparta), not to mention the adjective ''spartan.''</p>
        <p>Spartan men were raised to be soldiers from an early age. Indeed, to build and maintain esprit de corps in the ranks, they were not allowed to live apart from their military units until age 30, even if they were married.</p>
        <p>Spartan women are often portrayed as having been as grim as the men. But Ms. Pomeroy, whose previous books include ''Goddesses, Whores, Wives and Slaves: Women in Classical Antiquity,'' said that impression is wrong.</p>
        <p>''The conventional wisdom was that they were the most oppressed women in the ancient world because they were simply baby-making machines,'' she said. ''But there is much more to it than that.''</p>
        <p>Spartan women were in many ways among the most liberated of the ancient Greek world, she added. Sparta was one of the few Greek states where women received formal instruction in poetry, music, dancing and physical education. Spartan women drank wine and were famous for their beauty, Ms. Pomeroy said. Helen of Troy came from Sparta.</p>
        <p>No women in ancient Greece had formal political rights, but Spartan women, unlike their counterparts in other Greek city-states, were allowed to own property. A four-horse chariot team owned by a Spartan woman was victorious at the Olympics in 396 B.C. and again in 392 B.C. And the two wealthiest people in Sparta during the Hellenistic period (beginning in 323 B.C.) were women.</p>
        <p>Sparta has always been a challenge to ancient historians because information is relatively scarce. Unlike the Athenians, the Spartans built few public monuments and wrote little about themselves. The city had a fearsome reputation that did not invite visitors.</p>
        <p>It did not fall to a foreign invader until the Thebans conquered it in 370 B.C.</p>
        <p>Most of what is known about Sparta comes from modern archaeological evidence and the writings of Xenophon, an Athenian who was exiled to the city-state around 400 B.C., and Plutarch, who lived from A.D. 46 to A.D. 120. But Sparta cast a spell on many writers, including Plato, who used aspects of Spartan society as a model for his utopian Republic.</p>
        <p>''Every ancient source has its bias,'' said Ms. Pomeroy, who recently received a Guggenheim fellowship and said she expected to finish writing a book about her findings in another year or so. ''It's O.K. as long as you know what the bias is.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
