<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>100 Years Ago, A Penny Bought the World</title>
    <meta content="01NINE$31" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DD1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>100 Years Ago, A Penny Bought the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Clyde Haberman</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mockup of New York Times front page for Jan 1, 2100, priced $9; photo</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of the first things you learn from examining the world of a century ago is that people knew how to count. They understood that 99 years do not a century make, which is more than you can say for us today.</p>
        <p>Since 1900 was sensibly considered to be the last year of the old century and not the first year of the new, January 1900 was welcomed with ample appreciation but without dawn-of-an-era fanfare. It was, after all, still the 19th century. Rhetorical ruffles and flourishes would not be sounded until a year later, on Jan. 1, 1901, when a headline on the front page of The New York Times proclaimed ''Twentieth Century's Triumphant Entry.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of the first things you learn from examining the world of a century ago is that people knew how to count. They understood that 99 years do not a century make, which is more than you can say for us today.</p>
        <p>Since 1900 was sensibly considered to be the last year of the old century and not the first year of the new, January 1900 was welcomed with ample appreciation but without dawn-of-an-era fanfare. It was, after all, still the 19th century. Rhetorical ruffles and flourishes would not be sounded until a year later, on Jan. 1, 1901, when a headline on the front page of The New York Times proclaimed ''Twentieth Century's Triumphant Entry.''</p>
        <p>Simple math -- use your fingers, if you wish -- suggests that the hoopla now over the new millennium should have been delayed for another year. But the very fact that you are reading this underlines how irrelevant that logical point is to the billions of earthlings convinced that they entered the 21st century this morning.</p>
        <p>If the Americans among them were to take a moment to look not forward but rather back a century, they would see a country brimming with economic confidence. In that sense, it was not unlike the United States today.</p>
        <p>''The year 1899 was a year of wonders, a veritable annus mirabilis, in business and production,'' a New York Times editorial said on the first day of 1900. ''To paraphrase a celebrated epitaph, prosperity left scarcely any of our industries untouched, and touched nothing it did not enrich.'' Scanning the pages of The Times in January 1900, one sees nothing to indicate that that good times would do anything but continue to roll.</p>
        <p>Titans of industry and finance were seen as that: titans, as well as men of laudable works. The front page heralded gifts like the $300,000 that Andrew Carnegie gave to Cooper Union and the $100,000 that John D. Rockefeller presented to Columbia University. Their generosity was duly noted by a Times editorialist, who wrote:</p>
        <p>''When a man who is a great many times a millionaire, as Mr. Carnegie is, can demonstrate that he has done good both in the accumulation and in the scattering of his fortune, there is nothing left for the Socialist and the demagogue to say to which sensible persons will pay any attention.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Carnegie thought it simply wonderful to be poor -- or at least to start out that way. So he told a Bible class at the Fifth Avenue Baptist Church in New York, to which he rode in the same carriage with Rockefeller.</p>
        <p>''I was born to the blessed heritage of poverty,'' he said, adding: ''We hear a good deal in these days about poverty -- 'Oh, abolish poverty!' But the saddest day that civilization ever saw will be that in which poverty doesn't win its way. The poor, thank God, we will always have with us.''</p>
        <p>Too bad that John Massetter of Brooklyn did not get to hear that speech. Perhaps he would have understood the joys of being poor. Instead, he killed himself that January, leaving a letter for his wife that said he had no prospects and life was not worth living.</p>
        <p>The thickest clouds, however, were not at home but overseas.</p>
        <p>News from abroad in January 1900 was dominated by two events, the Boer War in South Africa and fighting in the Philippines between American armed forces and Philippine rebels seeking independence from the United States, newly in control of the former Spanish colony.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, in 1902, the British would prevail over the Boers, who were the descendants of German and Dutch colonists and the forerunners of today's Afrikaners. But in early 1900, the war was going badly for Britain. A dispatch from England on Jan. 29 quoted The Times of London as saying:</p>
        <p>''It can hardly be necessary to dwell upon the extreme probability that we shall learn, a little sooner or a little later, of a catastrophe almost without precedent in our military history, a catastrophe, indeed, without a parallel except in the surrender at Yorktown.''</p>
        <p>Some of the war's horrors seeped through the gauze of British censorship. One article quoted a British correspondent in South Africa as saying that soldiers were so thirsty that they offered ''fabulous prices for a cup of water.''</p>
        <p>''I saw one soldier lying flat on the line under an engine, catching a few drops in his mouth from a steam pipe,'' he had written.</p>
        <p>The situation was gloomy as well in the Philippines, with casualties mounting on both sides. This was accompanied by a sharp debate back home over what the United States should do with its possession in Southeast Asia. Grant it independence, some said. Others asserted that Filipinos were incapable of governing themselves. Their speeches were at times laced with racist observations that would be almost unimaginable today.</p>
        <p>''They are a barbarous race,'' a Senator Beveridge of Indiana said of Filipinos, ''modified by three centuries of contact with a decadent race.'' That last reference was to Spain. A Times reporter took it on himself to characterize the senator as having spoken with ''earnestness, vigor and eloquence.''</p>
        <p>But the wars were not so dominant that they crowded out stories closer to home, many of them quaint or quirky. Of course, much depended on the definition of news, quite different in those days.</p>
        <p>A typical midweek issue of The Times had 14 pages. Each was dense with information. Photographs were nonexistent. Instead, there were dozens of tiny articles to a seven-column page. The front page had has many as 45 separate items, many no longer than a paragraph.</p>
        <p>This may be as good a time as any to note that the daily Times cost only a penny then, the Sunday newspaper 3 cents.</p>
        <p>It was a time when six-room apartments on West 98th Street in Manhattan were renting for $22 to $28 a month. Macy's had a sale on petticoats for as little as 99 cents each and corsets for 49 cents each. Lord &amp; Taylor offered tablecloths for $1.45 as part of a linen sale.</p>
        <p>Front-page news could be about something as trivial as a New Jersey man driven crazy by a cricket that had crawled into his ear. It could be about a Boston man dubbed ''Jack the Slasher'' by the police because he went around cutting up expensive clothes. Or it could be about a Washington man fond of slicing up women's dresses. He was called ''Jack the Cutter.''</p>
        <p>A decision by the British vice consul in Kansas City to become a United States citizen qualified as big news. Maybe his jumping ship appealed to the prevailing nationalistic spirit.</p>
        <p>Also deemed noteworthy was a sleepwalking man who jumped from the roof of a two-story building -- an article that happened to catch modern eyes because the headline called him a ''somnambulist.'' Apparently, editors then could safely assume that readers knew certain 75-cent words.</p>
        <p>So much was brand new then.</p>
        <p>Tunnel-digging was about to begin in New York for a new rapid transit system that would run underground; the word ''subway'' was not yet in vogue. Baseball club owners talked about creating a new association to rival the established National League; the term ''American League'' was still unknown.</p>
        <p>The motorcar was new. Four months earlier, a New York man, Henry Bliss, had become the first North American killed by one of the newfangled machines. He was knocked down by -- what else? -- a taxi.</p>
        <p>Still, there was room for Page 1 shock in January 1900 when two New Yorkers were injured by a runaway carriage drawn the old-fashioned way: by horses.</p>
        <p>A new book was out on the British conquest of the Sudan, ''The River War,'' by a young writer named Winston Churchill. ''Aida'' was performed in January for the first time in New York at the Metropolitan Opera House, with The Times observing that ''the dusky heroine of Verdi's opera was an enchantment to the eye, if not to the dramatic sensibilities.''</p>
        <p>Later that month, Ibsen's ''The Master Builder'' had its first performance in this country, at the Carnegie Lyceum, a theater not far from Keith's, where Houdini was onstage every night. Movies? Sorry. They were still years away.</p>
        <p>For some religious denominations, the times were not brilliant. Baptists, Methodists and Presbyterians all reported declining membership. Perhaps it did not help that the price of Bibles was up, by 5 percent.</p>
        <p>But don't think for a second that religion was a dwindling force. Sunday laws were very much in effect, though there were many arguments over what qualified as necessities, whose sale on the Sabbath was permitted. On the Lower East Side of Manhattan, a policeman arrested a grocer for selling soap on Sunday. But the charges were tossed out by a judge who exclaimed: ''Soap! Why, the man ought to be commended for it. In my opinion, it would not harm the people of the city if they used more soap and used it more freely.''</p>
        <p>FOR a vivid sense of the social change that the last century has brought, consider the case of John Fisher and Lizzie Clark. Fisher was ''young, debonair and high-collared,'' Miss Clark ''a demure maid'' who looked older than her 15 years. They were strangers on a train near Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>Here, according to The Times, is what happened:</p>
        <p>''Miss Clark was standing on the platform. He thought she smiled. She got on the car and took the front seat. He beat a ragtime refrain. Then he ran his hand through his hair, brushed two specks from his coat, smiled a pensive smile, and took the seat beside Miss Clark and remarked in feeling tones 'that it looked like rain.'</p>
        <p>''Hardly were the words uttered when the conductor bore down, attracted by the girl's signals of distress.''</p>
        <p>Off to court in Camden, N.J., went the debonair Fisher. The charge: flirting. He got 60 days in jail -- for telling a girl that it might rain! A man screaming obscenities will barely cause heads to turn on the New York subway today.</p>
        <p>It must have been the feeling tones that did Fisher in.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
