<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'They Just Moved a Brick, Because the Brick Was Right in Their Face'</title>
    <meta content="01MISS$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: AMERICAN SOUTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moore, Marcus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blackwell, Uita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E2DE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'They Just Moved a Brick, Because the Brick Was Right in Their Face'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Firestone</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Unita Blackwell, 66, recalls her involvement with civil rights movement in South; Marcus Moore, a biracial 19-year-old and editor in chief of Emory University's black student magazine, says that civil rights movement seems distant to him and that race relations will improve once the icons of hard-core segregation, like George Wallace, are all gone; photos; chronology of events in civil rights movement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Those who risked their lives for the civil rights movement, like Unita Blackwell, did so to prevent the next generations from having to do the same, a dream largely realized. Ms. Blackwell, 66, the daughter of Mississippi sharecroppers, was regularly attacked and arrested while trying to register black voters, and helped found the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, an alternative to the all-white regular Democrats. She also created several education and housing programs in the state, and in 1976 became mayor of the Delta hamlet of Mayersville (population: 500), which she helped incorporate; it is a position she still holds.  Her generation's work seems distant to Marcus Moore, the 20-year-old son of a black Army officer and a white German mother. He grew up in Columbus, Ga., one of many children of interracial marriages at Fort Benning, and is now a senior majoring in African-American studies at Emory University in Atlanta. He is editor in chief of ''The Fire This Time,'' Emory's black student magazine, and has been active in campus demonstrations to persuade fraternities to stop displaying the Confederate flag. He helps teach science at a local elementary school and plans to get a Ph.D. in urban anthropology.</p>
        <p>DAVID FIRESTONE</p>
        <p>UNITA BLACKWELL</p>
        <p>I grew up in Coahoma County, on Mr. Hamilton's plantation in Lula, Miss. My  whole world was my kinfolks -- when I was a little girl, all I knew was my family. My father, he had to leave because he spoke up. At that time, you could not speak and look the white man in the eye, you had to hold your head down when you talked to white people. He told a man that he was the boss of his child, because white people then told you what to do, even in your own house. If the white man wanted my mother to go to the field, and take me to the field, then he just went to the house and told my mama to do it. And my daddy got upset, and told him, he's the boss of his family. So he had to get away from the plantation, and took a freight train to Memphis, worked at the icehouse. I was raised by my grandmother and my mother.</p>
        <p>I knew something was wrong, but I didn't understand what to ask. The Bible said God loves us all, but white people had Bibles, too. And they would send us preachers who said God wanted us to be good servants. I didn't understand this God, but I knew he didn't intend for me to be under the feet of white people.</p>
        <p>I got involved when the Freedom Riders came to Mississippi. It was the first time in my psyche that I understood what I had to do. There's no way in the world I thought we'd end up being part of a group of people who challenged the establishment, and our party and the whole state. But, you know, most people who helped break down the walls were just moving a brick. They never thought about the whole wall. They just moved a brick, because the brick was right in their face. For me, what was in my face was getting some books to my child, and giving him a chance to read and write. And it turned out to be one of the most fantastic things that ever happened, just because you dared to say no.</p>
        <p>It seems like the whole century has been about overcoming. Fighting and then overcoming. You had women's suffrage, and apartheid and segregation. And we blacks lived in that lock-in, and somehow survived. How, I do not know. Nothing but a God, I say. The whole era was full of hate, but we're trying to overcome it, and we're headed for something new, I just feel it. Maybe we are the group of people, the blacks in America, that brought everyone to their worst, and then to their best. Including ourselves.</p>
        <p>MARCUS MOORE</p>
        <p>It's important for me to identify myself as biracial, to acknowledge both elements of my heritage, but the way people interact with me is as a black American. I remember when I was in sixth grade, we had to fill out a form showing our race, and I said, ''I'm both, but there's no 'both' box on here, so what am I?'' So they sent me to the principal's office, and the secretary said, ''Whatever your father is, that's what you are.'' So I was black. And that's how I plan to identify myself for the census. For black people collectively to be advanced, they need to be represented in high numbers, and the intermediate classifications reduce the power of that.</p>
        <p>Younger blacks and whites are actually growing closer together, primarily because of popular culture. There's this fusion between rock and hip-hop, and a greater acceptance of hip-hop that you can even see on MTV. It's creating not a white-black culture but a youth culture. But it can also be dangerous. Last year the artist Jay-Z created a ghetto anthem called ''Hard Knock Life,'' and the whole country was singing the hook to it. But how many of those people really understood what he was saying, or could relate to the feelings that gave birth to that song? The music alone can sometimes give you a real limited perception.</p>
        <p>The civil rights movement seems so distant to me, the communal spirit that gave it its power seems so far gone. The students, the ones in the movement, seemed to have nothing to lose. So what if they were arrested? They would lose time off a job they didn't have. For our generation of students, though, if we were to create a demonstration, then we would miss five days of class, or whatever, and that would affect your grades, and students don't want that.</p>
        <p>The previous generation's dying will make a stronger contribution to more progress toward cultural and racial tolerance, unity, whatever you want to call it, in the next century. Once those icons of hard-core segregation, like George Wallace, are gone, then we can start with something new, and I think the next generation will be more tolerant and understanding.</p>
        <p>But we will still need affirmative action well into the next century. History has shown that in times of major black progress, beginning with the Reconstruction, after the Civil War, it only lasted so long until there was a tremendous white backlash. It will take more than a century to really undo all of the consequences of what amounts to a thousand years of minority oppression.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Those who risked their lives for the civil rights movement, like Unita Blackwell, did so to prevent the next generations from having to do the same, a dream largely realized. Ms. Blackwell, 66, the daughter of Mississippi sharecroppers, was regularly attacked and arrested while trying to register black voters, and helped found the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, an alternative to the all-white regular Democrats. She also created several education and housing programs in the state, and in 1976 became mayor of the Delta hamlet of Mayersville (population: 500), which she helped incorporate; it is a position she still holds.  Her generation's work seems distant to Marcus Moore, the 20-year-old son of a black Army officer and a white German mother. He grew up in Columbus, Ga., one of many children of interracial marriages at Fort Benning, and is now a senior majoring in African-American studies at Emory University in Atlanta. He is editor in chief of ''The Fire This Time,'' Emory's black student magazine, and has been active in campus demonstrations to persuade fraternities to stop displaying the Confederate flag. He helps teach science at a local elementary school and plans to get a Ph.D. in urban anthropology.</p>
        <p>DAVID FIRESTONE</p>
        <p>UNITA BLACKWELL</p>
        <p>I grew up in Coahoma County, on Mr. Hamilton's plantation in Lula, Miss. My  whole world was my kinfolks -- when I was a little girl, all I knew was my family. My father, he had to leave because he spoke up. At that time, you could not speak and look the white man in the eye, you had to hold your head down when you talked to white people. He told a man that he was the boss of his child, because white people then told you what to do, even in your own house. If the white man wanted my mother to go to the field, and take me to the field, then he just went to the house and told my mama to do it. And my daddy got upset, and told him, he's the boss of his family. So he had to get away from the plantation, and took a freight train to Memphis, worked at the icehouse. I was raised by my grandmother and my mother.</p>
        <p>I knew something was wrong, but I didn't understand what to ask. The Bible said God loves us all, but white people had Bibles, too. And they would send us preachers who said God wanted us to be good servants. I didn't understand this God, but I knew he didn't intend for me to be under the feet of white people.</p>
        <p>I got involved when the Freedom Riders came to Mississippi. It was the first time in my psyche that I understood what I had to do. There's no way in the world I thought we'd end up being part of a group of people who challenged the establishment, and our party and the whole state. But, you know, most people who helped break down the walls were just moving a brick. They never thought about the whole wall. They just moved a brick, because the brick was right in their face. For me, what was in my face was getting some books to my child, and giving him a chance to read and write. And it turned out to be one of the most fantastic things that ever happened, just because you dared to say no.</p>
        <p>It seems like the whole century has been about overcoming. Fighting and then overcoming. You had women's suffrage, and apartheid and segregation. And we blacks lived in that lock-in, and somehow survived. How, I do not know. Nothing but a God, I say. The whole era was full of hate, but we're trying to overcome it, and we're headed for something new, I just feel it. Maybe we are the group of people, the blacks in America, that brought everyone to their worst, and then to their best. Including ourselves.</p>
        <p>MARCUS MOORE</p>
        <p>It's important for me to identify myself as biracial, to acknowledge both elements of my heritage, but the way people interact with me is as a black American. I remember when I was in sixth grade, we had to fill out a form showing our race, and I said, ''I'm both, but there's no 'both' box on here, so what am I?'' So they sent me to the principal's office, and the secretary said, ''Whatever your father is, that's what you are.'' So I was black. And that's how I plan to identify myself for the census. For black people collectively to be advanced, they need to be represented in high numbers, and the intermediate classifications reduce the power of that.</p>
        <p>Younger blacks and whites are actually growing closer together, primarily because of popular culture. There's this fusion between rock and hip-hop, and a greater acceptance of hip-hop that you can even see on MTV. It's creating not a white-black culture but a youth culture. But it can also be dangerous. Last year the artist Jay-Z created a ghetto anthem called ''Hard Knock Life,'' and the whole country was singing the hook to it. But how many of those people really understood what he was saying, or could relate to the feelings that gave birth to that song? The music alone can sometimes give you a real limited perception.</p>
        <p>The civil rights movement seems so distant to me, the communal spirit that gave it its power seems so far gone. The students, the ones in the movement, seemed to have nothing to lose. So what if they were arrested? They would lose time off a job they didn't have. For our generation of students, though, if we were to create a demonstration, then we would miss five days of class, or whatever, and that would affect your grades, and students don't want that.</p>
        <p>The previous generation's dying will make a stronger contribution to more progress toward cultural and racial tolerance, unity, whatever you want to call it, in the next century. Once those icons of hard-core segregation, like George Wallace, are gone, then we can start with something new, and I think the next generation will be more tolerant and understanding.</p>
        <p>But we will still need affirmative action well into the next century. History has shown that in times of major black progress, beginning with the Reconstruction, after the Civil War, it only lasted so long until there was a tremendous white backlash. It will take more than a century to really undo all of the consequences of what amounts to a thousand years of minority oppression.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: AMERICAN SOUTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
