<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rx for Brain Makeovers</title>
    <meta content="01MIND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: IDENTITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goode, Erica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E7D81330F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rx for Brain Makeovers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Erica Goode</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goode, Erica</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Erica Goode article says increased understanding of interplay of chemicals, genes and enviropnmental influences will bring exponential leaps in the ability to manipulate the brain and to influence thinking, feeling, memory and behavior in the next century, perhaps as early as in the next three decades; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Scarecrow in ''The Wizard of Oz'' wanted only a brain -- he did not much care what kind.</p>
        <p>But human beings, most of whom already have such organs in their possession, have rarely been satisfied with simple ownership. They yearn for improvement: for smarter brains, happier brains, calmer brains, brains that are less forgetful, less stressed and less vulnerable to age and disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Scarecrow in ''The Wizard of Oz'' wanted only a brain -- he did not much care what kind.</p>
        <p>But human beings, most of whom already have such organs in their possession, have rarely been satisfied with simple ownership. They yearn for improvement: for smarter brains, happier brains, calmer brains, brains that are less forgetful, less stressed and less vulnerable to age and disease.</p>
        <p>To pursue these desires once meant taking up meditation, ingesting mind-altering substances without supervision or spending years on the analytic couch. But modern science has yielded other approaches to brain repair and improvement. Doctors now have ways to tweak the brain's machinery, including drugs and other techniques that can relieve depression, calm hallucinations, increase concentration and soothe jangled nerves.</p>
        <p>Yet these remedies, scientists say, are just a prelude to what is to come. In the next century, and maybe in the next three decades, they say, greatly increased understanding of the interplay of chemicals, genes and environmental influences will bring exponential leaps in the ability to manipulate the brain and to influence thinking, feeling, memory and behavior.</p>
        <p>Brain-altering drugs of the future will have several advantages over those now on the market. While many medications used to treat wayward thoughts, emotions or behaviors were discovered through serendipity,  scientists increasingly are able to manipulate drugs with intention, maximizing effectiveness or reducing side effects. While most drugs already in use have an effect on the brain that is far from specific -- the tread of an elephant, not a mouse -- a new generation of psychoactive drugs will home in on more precise targets. Advances in genetics will also let drugs be matched more successfully to the needs of individuals.</p>
        <p>A result will be not only better treatments for illnesses like depression, Alzheimer's disease and schizophrenia but also ways to make essentially normal brains work better, like enhancing memory, increasing sociability or expanding intelligence.</p>
        <p>''Will we come up with a Viagra for the brain, so to speak?'' asked Dr. Steven M. Paul, group vice president for the therapeutic area, discovery research and clinical investigation at Lilly Research Laboratories in Indianapolis. In the past, such a thing was science fiction. But in the context of finding treatments for Alzheimer's and other forms of dementia, he said, ''There is no question that we and other companies are working on things that can enhance cognition.''</p>
        <p>The availability of new compounds will pose increasingly difficult questions about who should use them, and under what circumstances. In some cases, the benefits may clearly outweigh any risks: Drugs that could better treat mental illnesses like schizophrenia and manic-depression would probably find few critics.</p>
        <p>But when it comes to altering and adjusting mental qualities that all people share to some extent, the situation grows murkier.</p>
        <p>''It is my own view that if these medications are developed, they will be used,'' said Dr. Paul Appelbaum, chairman of the psychiatry department at the University of Massachusetts Medical School in Worcester. ''I think it's almost inevitable that people, given the opportunity to improve their personalities, their cognitions, their interpersonal abilities, will take that opportunity.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most difficult challenge will be presented by drugs that hold out the possibility of sidestepping the most painful parts of life. As one example, Dr. Peter Kramer, the author of ''Listening to Prozac,''  said he had been considering what might happen if there were a drug that could interrupt the cascade of hormones and other neurochemicals set off by major stress. Several pharmaceutical companies, he said, have such medications in their pipelines.</p>
        <p>In theory, such stress reactions change the brain's anatomy in ways that may make someone more vulnerable to depression or other problems later on. ''But what if,'' Dr. Kramer asked, ''there is a 4-year-old child and the mother dies, or someone, at any age, loses a close companion or is raped, and you could give them a chemical that could prevent the more permanent encoding of that loss?''</p>
        <p>Some might argue, he said, that offering such a drug would be the only ethical thing to do. But equally persuasive is the argument that coming to terms with loss and emotional injury is essential for growth.</p>
        <p>It comes down to a question of value. How much is pain worth? How much does depression contribute? A new generation of drugs may force us to re-examine which aspects of our mental lives we consider essential and which we are willing to relinquish.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: IDENTITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
