<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Day at the Races, A Night of Big Parties</title>
    <meta content="Y01HON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165069"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2D91338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Day at the Races, A Night of Big Parties</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How do you mark the passage of 1,000 years of human history? Simple in Hong Kong, a city of chronic gamblers and cold-eyed oddsmakers: you head for the track.</p>
        <p>At 12:45 a.m., as the last wisps of smoke from New Year's Eve fireworks drifted away from the Happy Valley Racecourse, the crack of a starter's gun set off the Millennium Cup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How do you mark the passage of 1,000 years of human history? Simple in Hong Kong, a city of chronic gamblers and cold-eyed oddsmakers: you head for the track.</p>
        <p>At 12:45 a.m., as the last wisps of smoke from New Year's Eve fireworks drifted away from the Happy Valley Racecourse, the crack of a starter's gun set off the Millennium Cup.</p>
        <p>The Hong Kong Jockey Club billed it as the first horse race of the 2000's, though rumors swirled that it might have been edged out for first-in-the-world status by post-midnight races in New Zealand and Australia.</p>
        <p>Floral Joy won $110,000 from a total purse worth $200,000. It was a good prize, but not extraordinary for a jockey club that generates more than $10 billion a season in betting.</p>
        <p>Such details did not dampen the spirits of more than 50,000 people who cheered wildly as one of the favorites, Floral Joy, streaked across the line several lengths ahead of the next horse.</p>
        <p>If a horse race seems an offhand way to celebrate the ultimate New Year's Eve, remember that strictly speaking, the new year does not even arrive here until Feb. 5, when Hong Kong and the rest of the Chinese-speaking world will welcome the Year of the Dragon.</p>
        <p>Considering that Hong Kong was celebrating someone else's holiday, it threw quite a party. The city mounted a splashy fireworks display at Happy Valley. At the stroke of midnight, fireballs placed at 175-foot intervals around the track erupted into a fountain of flames. An enormous illuminated dragon, which the organizers described as the largest ever, held court in the infield.</p>
        <p>For some Hong Kong residents, gambling seemed the only way to celebrate the millennium. ''This is the perfect atmosphere for racing,'' said Wilson Chan, a local businessman who lost money on the first seven races of the evening but was sure he would win it all back on the main event.</p>
        <p>Albert Cheng, a popular local radio host, said horse racing symbolized stability in this former British colony, which reverted to Chinese rule two years ago. ''Deng Xiaoping promised us that the dancing would go on and the races would go on after the handover,'' Mr. Cheng said, paraphrasing a now legendary remark by the late Chinese  leader.</p>
        <p>The Millennium Cup capped an evening of festivities that featured performances by several of Hong Kong's biggest film and pop stars, including Jackie Chan, Chow Yun Fat and Michelle Yeoh. Mr. Chan served as the clown prince of the evening -- singing, dancing and mugging with all the cheerful exuberance he brings to roughing up bad guys in movies like ''Rumble in the Bronx.''</p>
        <p>Of less interest to the star-crazed audience, Hong Kong's chief executive, Tung Chee-hwa, led a countdown of the final seconds of 1999. Mr. Tung then slipped away to the Hong Kong Convention Center, where he caught a Whitney Houston concert.</p>
        <p>Ms. Houston performed at one of the evening's hot tickets, a dusk-to-dawn party hosted by Richard Li, the son of the Hong Kong billionaire Li Ka-shing. The younger Mr. Li only decided to hold the bash a month ago, and his organizers worked frantically around the clock to book marquee performers and ready a dinner for 1,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Li, 33, was not modest about his ambitions. The evening was advertised as ''Ultimate Millennium Party -- Utopia.'' In addition to the usual New Year's Eve trappings, Mr. Li produced a laser show on the grounds of his future technology office park, Cyberport, which was telecast to the guests inside the center. The fees for Ms. Houston and the other performers alone totaled more than $2.5 million.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Li to assemble one of Hong Kong's most sought-after New Year's Eve parties from a standing start in less than a month is a testament to his own drive. But it also reflects the long shadow of his father. At 76, Li Ka-shing remains the city's most powerful businessman.</p>
        <p>Across Victoria Harbor, the Regent Hotel vied for the status of gaudiest party. Famous for its lavish celebration of Hong Kong's handover in 1997, the Regent converted its entire harborfront hotel into a stage set that chronicled the 20th century, with ballrooms and restaurants decorated in period styles.</p>
        <p>At midnight, nearly 3,000 guests gazed out of the hotel's floor-to-ceiling windows toward Hong Kong island, where the already dramatic skyline had been transformed in a dizzying light show. Brilliant hundred-foot lighted dragons wrapped themselves around buildings, while the numerals 2 0 0 0 flashed on several skyscrapers.</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
