<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'They Just Moved a Brick, Because the Brick Was Right in Their Face'</title>
    <meta content="01MEXI$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="REFLECTIONS: MEXICO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Munoz Marquez, Sandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquez Martinez, Enriqueta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Preston, Julia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'They Just Moved a Brick, Because the Brick Was Right in Their Face'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Julia Preston</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Preston, Julia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Enriqueta Marquez Martinez, 73, tells of poverty in Mexico and her family's frequent resort to United States, where three of her 10 children have settled permanently but where she herself could never live for long; Sandra Munoz Marquez, her 24-year-old American-born niece, is happy to have been brought up in Mexico and to have an American passport; photos; chronology of Mexican history since 1911 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The spare farmsteads and bony milk cows of San Jose de Olivares, a desert plateau in central Mexico, are maintained by women and older people. Enriqueta Marquez Martinez, 73, was born there. She has lived much of her life in absolute poverty, never knowing whether there would be food for the next family meal. All of her 10 children went at one time or another to work in the United States, and three settled there permanently. Eventually, when she was in her 60's, Mrs. Marquez also began to travel to the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The spare farmsteads and bony milk cows of San Jose de Olivares, a desert plateau in central Mexico, are maintained by women and older people. Enriqueta Marquez Martinez, 73, was born there. She has lived much of her life in absolute poverty, never knowing whether there would be food for the next family meal. All of her 10 children went at one time or another to work in the United States, and three settled there permanently. Eventually, when she was in her 60's, Mrs. Marquez also began to travel to the United States.</p>
        <p>Sandra Munoz Marquez, 24, actually has two nationalities. Miss Munoz, who is Mrs. Marquez's niece, was born in Chicago but raised in Mexico. Two years ago, however, Miss Munoz left her stable life in Mexico and moved to el Norte, as the United States is known here. Her most recent job was in a cable warehouse in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>JULIA PRESTON</p>
        <p>ENRIQUETA MARQUEZ MARTINEZ</p>
        <p>I had 10 children, but one, my son Arturo, died when he was 43. When he was in his 20's he was thrown in jail. He was set up and went to jail for a robbery he didn't commit. Right before he was freed he was bitten by a rat in his cell.</p>
        <p>After that, he was never right. He had fits. When he was sick he would try to strangle people, kill them. He lived with me. One day I went out to the market for just a minute to get some vegetables. That was when he burned himself. He burned his mattress, his blankets, his sheets, his clothes. And himself.</p>
        <p>I got back and found him on the floor. I put my arms around him. He turned very slowly and looked at me. Then the ambulance came. Everyone said he was dead.</p>
        <p>But every night, as soon as I would lie down, my son Arturo was right there beside me. He came out of his bedroom and sat down on my bed. He would poke and hug and tease me.</p>
        <p>I prayed and prayed, but Arturo kept coming to visit me. That was when I decided to go to the United States. My daughter Margarita was living in Modesto, Calif., at the time. She was the one who said that praying wasn't going to be enough. She sent me to a clinic instead. That's right, a clinic for thoughts.</p>
        <p>They really helped me. They asked me questions, and I talked and talked. Nobody ever asked me to talk like that before. I had always listened. I went there for seven months, and after that I never again had a visit from Arturo. I understood that it was just a dream of sadness for my son.</p>
        <p>Before Margarita became an American citizen a few years ago, I didn't have any American papers at all, so I had to cross the border just taking my chances. Once, about 10 years ago, I went through Tijuana. The border patrol caught me and sent me back to Mexico five times. After the first times they caught me they joked with me and said, ''Don't take it too hard, Grandma. You can always try again tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>Mexico is suffering. It is a festival of tears. I got married when I was a young girl because I thought marriage would take me out of my suffering. But it just made it worse. My husband was irresponsible and he drank. When he died, I felt nothing.</p>
        <p>But I could never live in the United States. Even when I am with Margarita, I feel so lonely there. Most of my children and my grandchildren are still here in Mexico.  SANDRA MUNOZ MARQUEZ</p>
        <p>I was born to be an American passport.</p>
        <p>I was the baby who was going to make it possible for my parents to become legal in the United States. When my mother was five months pregnant with me, she left our home in Mexico and went to stay with relatives in Chicago. I was born in a hospital there.</p>
        <p>But as soon as I was born and had my American birth certificate, my mother just wanted to hurry home. She didn't even get me a Social Security number.</p>
        <p>I was happy in Mexico. I had a good job as a receptionist in a medical clinic and I went out dancing on the weekends. But my cousin Margarita, who was living in California at the time, was very insistent with me. She said she didn't have enough family in the United States. She thought of me as her little sister, and she needed someone to gossip and squabble with.</p>
        <p>So I went to the United States. It took me seven months to get my American passport. At one point I was interviewed by another Latin person who worked for the American immigration service; I think he was originally from El Salvador. He got angry with me and said: ''Why do you want to be an American? You're just like all those other people in line out there. They say they want to be American, but they just want the papers.''</p>
        <p>That's when it came to me. I told him: ''I don't want to be an American. I am an American. I just want you to give me the documents to prove it.''</p>
        <p>The truth is, I do like my Mexican nationality more. If you ask me where I am from, I will say I am from this ranch, right here. My parents were born in these lands. I like Mexico's little villages, its little houses. The United States is not the same. The people there do not show enough respect for their elders.</p>
        <p>My American nationality is my ticket to the rest of the world. Fifteen years from now, I could be living in Europe. It gives me peace of mind to have the door open. I have two life options, and I can choose the one I want.</p>
        <p>REFLECTIONS: MEXICO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
