<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bilingual Celebrations In a Border Boomtown</title>
    <meta content="Y01LAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5DC1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bilingual Celebrations In a Border Boomtown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <dateline>LAREDO, Tex., Dec. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last day of the 1900's arrived like any other at the foot of International Bridge No. 1: old women and cowboys, teenagers and tourists, all of them and thousands of others crossed back and forth from Mexico as if the notion of two countries were mostly an inconvenience not of their making.</p>
        <p>''It's like it was one city,'' said Terry Medinilla, a salesman at El Porvenir, a clothing store that depends on customers walking across the bridge from Mexico. ''We can't be without them, and they can't be without us.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last day of the 1900's arrived like any other at the foot of International Bridge No. 1: old women and cowboys, teenagers and tourists, all of them and thousands of others crossed back and forth from Mexico as if the notion of two countries were mostly an inconvenience not of their making.</p>
        <p>''It's like it was one city,'' said Terry Medinilla, a salesman at El Porvenir, a clothing store that depends on customers walking across the bridge from Mexico. ''We can't be without them, and they can't be without us.''</p>
        <p>So, naturally, Laredo and its Mexican sister city, Nuevo Laredo, decided to ring in the year 2000 together, with a ceremony shortly before midnight above the waters of the Rio Grande that divide them. With an intended dose of symbolism, the two mayors planned to meet in the middle of the closed bridge and embrace, a reminder of the artifice of boundaries created by a line on a map or, for that matter, by a tick of a clock.</p>
        <p>''We want to remind the two countries how important our people are, and the role they play for the economies of the country, both sides,'' Mayor Betty Flores of Laredo said earlier in the day.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the future arrived in Laredo in 1994 with the North American Free Trade Agreement. Even if prosperity now smells a lot like truck exhaust, Nafta has made Laredo the busiest cargo crossing point on the border and transformed a city once called the poorest in the nation into one whose population has doubled to 200,000 since 1990.</p>
        <p>''Some people refer to our town as the biggest truck stop in the nation,'' said Maria Eugenia Guerra, the outspoken publisher of the monthly newspaper LareDos.</p>
        <p>The result is a city on the make whose many contradictions were laid bare as it rang in the new year. Its new rich, many of them recently arrived executives from sprouting border industries, gathered at private parties, like the ones at the La Posada Hotel and the local country club ringed by expensive new homes. Yet in the old neighborhoods of shacks and shanties, families held more modest fiestas or trickled down to the free party at a city park beside the Rio Grande.</p>
        <p>Just across the river from the party, a huge red, white and green Mexican flag fluttered in the breeze. The night before, as pedestrians with the appropriate documentation passed back and forth over the bridge, two men in their underwear could be seen wading across the Rio Grande. They each held a bundle of clothes above the water as they reached the American side of the river and disappeared.</p>
        <p>No one on the bridge seemed to notice or care. A few blocks away, on the Mexican side of the river in Nuevo Laredo, a dinner crowd ate at the El Dorado Restaurant. Mexican cowboys in dusty blue jeans and white hatssat at one table, drinking beer and listening to a Mexican band, even as a John Denver song played on a tape in the background. Two American women wearing expensive jewelry sat at another table, while two young American men flirted with a table of even younger women. In a corner, a tourist fed her baby in an Italian stroller as her husband ate a plate of cabrito, or goat.</p>
        <p>Here on the border, the 21st century has arrived.</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
