<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Human Touch Will Only Inflate College Bills</title>
    <meta content="01COST$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165209"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: CITIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1DE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="428" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Human Touch Will Only Inflate College Bills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Wyatt</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cost of college education is expected to outpace inflation well into the new century and perhaps forever; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Mozart was alive, it took two to three months for a craftsman to make a watch and about 18 minutes for an ensemble to perform ''Eine Kleine Nachtmusik.'' Today, it takes two minutes for a machine to make a watch. But a performance of Mozart's familiar composition still takes musicians more than a quarter-hour.</p>
        <p>That illustration, says William Baumol, an economist at New York University, explains why the cost of college tuition will most likely outpace inflation well into the new century, and perhaps forever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Mozart was alive, it took two to three months for a craftsman to make a watch and about 18 minutes for an ensemble to perform ''Eine Kleine Nachtmusik.'' Today, it takes two minutes for a machine to make a watch. But a performance of Mozart's familiar composition still takes musicians more than a quarter-hour.</p>
        <p>That illustration, says William Baumol, an economist at New York University, explains why the cost of college tuition will most likely outpace inflation well into the new century, and perhaps forever.</p>
        <p>While gains in productivity have made many goods less expensive, products and services that rely heavily on human labor -- like education, health care and symphonic performance -- are rising in cost. People are demanding ever-higher pay, and no one has figured out a way to cut months or years from a course of college study.</p>
        <p>Even so, for all the complaints about tuition bills, the percentage of income used by affluent Americans to pay for a private, four-year college education has barely increased. That is because the top 20 percent of the nation's households, in terms of income, have gotten richer over the last quarter-century. According to the College Board, for families making an average of $149,000, the college bill amounts to about 14 percent of their annual income, up from 12 percent. However, for the 20 percent of households with the lowest incomes -- an average of $13,000 annually -- the costs of private schooling have doubled, to 162 percent of income from 84 percent 25 years ago.</p>
        <p>Of course, few students at private colleges actually pay the posted tuition price, depending instead on various forms of financial aid. David Breneman, the dean of the Curry School of Education at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville, attributes that fact to an oversupply of spaces at private colleges. The excess supply, however, may dry up over the next 20 years as the college-age population rises by 22 percent, far faster than the overall population.</p>
        <p>Technology may help keep costs in check, as lectures broadcast over the Internet force colleges to trim overhead and compete on price.</p>
        <p>But Thomas Kane, an economist at Harvard's Kennedy School of Government, says the earnings gap between high school and college graduates will keep enrollments high; prices will thus continue to rise.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: CITIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
