<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Celebrating a Milestone for Freedom; Black Americans Honor Anniversary of Proclamation to End Slavery</title>
    <meta content="01EMAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slavery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Emancipation Proclamation (1863)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Archives and Records Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Slavery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2D61338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Celebrating a Milestone for Freedom; Black Americans Honor Anniversary of Proclamation to End Slavery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Black Americans honor anniversary of Emancipation Proclamation, as they have done every year since it took effect Jan 1, 1863, declaring slaves in South free and heightening momentum for abolition of slavery two years later through 13th Amendment; five-page yellowed document is kept in air-conditioned vault in National Archives in Washington; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As people wake up this morning with the future on their minds, having left the 1900's for the 2000's, William Stallings will prepare to look back, 137 years to be exact.</p>
        <p>He will make his way to the Greater Centennial Missionary Baptist Church in Mount Vernon, N.Y., take his seat among fellow parishioners, bob his head to African drumming, pull out a piece of paper and scribble notes as speaker after speaker sermonizes on a five-page yellowed document kept in an air-conditioned vault in the National Archives in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As people wake up this morning with the future on their minds, having left the 1900's for the 2000's, William Stallings will prepare to look back, 137 years to be exact.</p>
        <p>He will make his way to the Greater Centennial Missionary Baptist Church in Mount Vernon, N.Y., take his seat among fellow parishioners, bob his head to African drumming, pull out a piece of paper and scribble notes as speaker after speaker sermonizes on a five-page yellowed document kept in an air-conditioned vault in the National Archives in Washington.</p>
        <p>It is the Emancipation Proclamation, and Mr. Stallings and thousands of other black Americans will honor it as they have done virtually every year since it took effect on Jan. 1, 1863, declaring slaves in the South free -- if only symbolically -- and heightening momentum for the abolition of slavery two years later through the 13th Amendment.</p>
        <p>It was the first time the federal government officially took action to end slavery. And for African-Americans across the country, especially those with roots in the South and memories of civil rights struggles, the anniversary of the proclamation gives New Year's Day, even this one that transcends hyperbole, a grander purpose.</p>
        <p>''As an African-American, that was the document that gave us our freedom,'' said Mr. Stallings, 55, a social services case examiner who lives in Yonkers. ''It was the greatest turning point in history in this country.''</p>
        <p>The tradition, which began several years ago at the church, has grown substantially, from a couple of hundred to several hundred, just as interest in slavery and the Civil War is surging with a proliferation of books and television programs.</p>
        <p>The commemorations, commonly called Emancipation Day or Jubilee Day, are usually organized by churches, which have long been the spiritual and social nexuses of black communities, often in conjunction with local chapters of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.</p>
        <p>Among the largest is one at the Ebenezer Baptist Church in Atlanta, where the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. preached. The N.A.A.C.P. chapter in Williamsbridge, the Bronx, will sponsor a more modest commemoration, with an expected turnout of 200 people, at the Refuge Temple, 716 East 233rd Street.</p>
        <p>''They represent the real Fourth of July or Independence Day for African-Americans,'' said Nelson B. Rivers III, the director of local chapters at the rights group's national headquarters. ''The first one, July 4, 1776, did not apply to us.''</p>
        <p>Historians cast the commemorations in the context of a constant yearning among black Americans for a special day to recognize and reflect on the past. The federal holiday honoring Dr. King, first celebrated on Jan. 20, 1986, satisfied that thirst to an extent, but emancipation celebrations, which take place on various dates of the calendar, reflect a desire for an expressly African-American holiday.</p>
        <p>Popular dates include Sept. 22, when President Lincoln issued a preliminary proclamation that served 100 days' notice of the actual signing. Others have adopted Juneteenth, a Texas state holiday celebrated on June 19 in honor of the day in 1865 when, it is said, slaves there finally received news of the proclamation.</p>
        <p>But the Jan. 1 celebrations are the most widespread, and are particularly popular in the South, said William H. Wiggins Jr., a professor at Indiana University who wrote a book on freedom celebrations, ''O Freedom! Afro-American Emancipation Celebrations'' (The University of Tennessee Press, 1987).</p>
        <p>''This is the granddaddy of them all,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As they do now, churches played a role on Jan. 1, 1863, in recognizing the importance of the event, he said. The text of the proclamation sped across telegraph wires in the evening, after Lincoln had signed it with a trembling hand, and reached a church in Boston where Frederick Douglass waited among a crowd of people gathered for ''emancipation watch'' services. He immediately read the proclamation and pandemonium ensued, according to the historian John Hope Franklin.</p>
        <p>Since then, Dr. Wiggins said, the reading of the proclamation, often in a dramatic and emotional cadence, has been a central part of the celebrations, which took hold especially in the Southeast, where slavery was most entrenched. Black Southerners who moved North after the war and in the middle of the 1900's carried the tradition with them.</p>
        <p>The historical nuances of Lincoln's act are sometimes lost, Dr. Wiggins said. The emancipation did not immediately free a single slave. It applied only to slaves in rebellious states and exempted parts of the Confederacy that had come under Northern control.</p>
        <p>Although historians say Lincoln personally opposed slavery, they often note his political and military motives in issuing the proclamation, which was made as the Union was suffering losses and was looking for a way to bolster its cause and crush Southern morale.</p>
        <p>By attacking the institution considered a bedrock of the Confederacy, the proclamation made the war seem less like a rebellion and more like a war of liberation. It opened the way for black men to serve in the Union Army and Navy, and by the end of war, nearly 200,000 had served under the Union flag.</p>
        <p>And so New Year's Day for the likes of the Rev. Freddie Brunswick of the tiny Salem Missionary Baptist Church in Springfield Gardens, Queens, means a time to pause and reflect on such events and their resonance.</p>
        <p>A choir will sing Negro spirituals. A young member of the congregation of 150 worshipers will read the proclamation. Mr. Brunswick will make a speech.</p>
        <p>''When we lose the past, we are subject to make the same mistakes again,'' his speech will pronounce.</p>
        <p>As it has for dozens of years, the Brooklyn Baptist ministers' conference will hold a commemoration at one of its member churches, the Brownsville Community Baptist Church.</p>
        <p>A few days before, the Rev. Dr. Charles H. Ancrum of Timothy Baptist Church in Bushwick, who is president of the conference, reflected on the importance of the proclamation.</p>
        <p>''Politically we have not arrived,'' Dr. Ancrum said. ''We have Congress people, but in comparison to whites, we are still underrepresented. We have not arrived in terms of equality of education and economically. In almost every area we are underrepresented.''</p>
        <p>Like others involved in the commemorations, he said he had observed a growth in attendance, fed by people's desire to reconnect with their past or to reaffirm it. But others are troubled that as with Sunday services, the commemorations still do not draw large numbers of young people.</p>
        <p>That bodes ill for the future of marking such historical occasions, said the Rev. Dr. Elliott Cuff of Mount Ararat Missionary Baptist Church in Ocean Hill-Brownsville, who plans to attend the service of the ministers' conference.</p>
        <p>''A lot of 'race days' have fallen on hard times in postmodernity,'' Dr. Cuff said. ''King's birthday, as we move into the next millennium, will probably go the way of the rest of the holidays, a day to rest and shop. That's unfortunate. I think it is vitally important because these are marks in the sand for what made America what it is today.''</p>
        <p>Such sentiments drew Rodney Olden to the Greater Centennial service in Mount Vernon a decade ago.</p>
        <p>He found it an ideal way to make his children, now in their 20's and 30's and on their own, more aware of the civil rights struggle.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to keep track of our heritage,'' Mr. Olden said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stallings, too, sees the service as a way to connect with history, especially his days as a college student in the early 1960's at the all-black Tuskegee Institute in Alabama. He takes notes at the service to later reflect on what was said and how it relates to history.</p>
        <p>''I marched with Dr. King in South Carolina and Charleston and participated in at least 50 marches during the summer of 1962 and '63,'' Mr. Stallings said. ''I remember sitting on the back of a bus and things we could not do.''</p>
        <p>Today, he said, he need only look at Mount Vernon to find reminders of the continuing struggle for equity.</p>
        <p>''We have a dichotomy going on,'' he said. ''On the northern side, people are doing well, we have the movers and shakers in the community with their corporate jobs and jobs in the government. And then we have the masses on the other side, who have menial or average jobs and have difficulty making ends meet. We have those kinds of dichotomies, and we have to find a way to deal with it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
