<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Ads, Candidates' Gloves Stay On</title>
    <meta content="Y01ADS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7D61338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Ads, Candidates' Gloves Stay On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Marks analysis finds that commercials run in presidential campaign so far are remarkably tame, the candidates apparently unwilling to be the first to 'go negative' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a new commercial running in early primary states this week, Gov. George W. Bush comes out squarely in favor of phonics. ''See,'' he explains, ''I believe every child can learn.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's two leading rivals for the Republican presidential nomination, Senator John McCain and Steve Forbes, as well as Vice President Al Gore, unveiled spots this week in which they reaffirm their vows to continue sending monthly government checks to retired people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a new commercial running in early primary states this week, Gov. George W. Bush comes out squarely in favor of phonics. ''See,'' he explains, ''I believe every child can learn.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's two leading rivals for the Republican presidential nomination, Senator John McCain and Steve Forbes, as well as Vice President Al Gore, unveiled spots this week in which they reaffirm their vows to continue sending monthly government checks to retired people.</p>
        <p>And in a new infomercial-length advertisement on cable channels in Iowa, Bill Bradley lays out a major rationale for his challenge to Mr. Gore for the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>''I want to be president of the United States,'' Mr. Bradley says, ''in order to use the power of that office to do good.''</p>
        <p>Few in the political world can recall a competitive primary season in which the candidates were so eager to spend so much to say so little.  Fearful, it seems, of being labeled the first to ''go negative'' with advertising, and thus draw the enmity of a public that is perceived to be fed up with divisive messages, the candidates are spending millions of dollars on a cautious, fiercely noncombative television campaign that is relentlessly uncontroversial and, in the eyes of many who are watching it, more than a little dull.</p>
        <p>''There is a sort of heightened civility this year, not only in the ads but also in the discourse in general,'' said Lynn Vavreck, an assistant professor of government at Dartmouth College, in Hanover, N.H., who worked on the staff of Dan Quayle's vice-presidential campaign in 1992.</p>
        <p>Professor Vavreck has noticed, too, that the positions staked out in the television advertisements in New Hampshire are largely of the don't-step-on-any-toes variety. ''They talk about things that nobody can be against,'' she said. ''Even when they do talk about issues, they say, 'I want to improve education.' Well, is that a position? Who's against teaching kids to read?''</p>
        <p>Aides to the various candidates  point out that the political season is still young. The tenor of the commercials in the early primary states, they say, could quickly grow sharper. In fact, as the campaigns gear up next week with the beginning of the new year -- one campaign estimates that television spending in Iowa and New Hampshire by candidates of both parties may total $6 million in January -- the media strategists are behaving like anxious generals, wondering whether the sniper fire begins just over the next ridge.</p>
        <p>It is a measure of just how sensitively the campaigns are trying to read the public mood with regard to drawing distinctions between candidacies, and how delicately the candidates are tiptoeing around one another, that their advertising at times seems enveloped in virtually indecipherable code.</p>
        <p>''It's all very pinkies up,'' said Lee Miringoff, director of the Marist Institute for Public Opinion, in Poughkeepsie, N.Y. ''The candidates are being offered as separate products; it's not comparison shopping now. On the Democratic side, there is more discussion of competing issues, but it's being discussed as genuine versus inauthentic, inside-the-Beltway versus out. The issues become surrogates for something else.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, for instance, has been running spots that are such heavily veiled critiques of Mr. Bradley's positions on health care and education that it takes several viewings to fully grasp their meaning. In his latest advertisement, a disembodied voice promises that the vice president will  ''fight against vouchers that draw money from public schools,'' an apparent reference to Mr. Bradley's acknowledgment that while in the Senate, he voted for some experimental school-voucher programs.</p>
        <p>Anita Dunn, the Bradley campaign's communications director, sees the Gore advertisements as falling into a rarefied category: ''implicit negative ads.'' They are, she  said, a manifestation of Mr. Gore's increasingly antagonistic approach. ''The attacks started in September and haven't stopped,'' she said.</p>
        <p>That type of attack, if that is what it is, hardly seems to have much growl to it. Still, Chris Lehane, a spokesman for the Gore campaign, offered an implicit message of his own: that things may get rougher if circumstances warrant.</p>
        <p>''Once you get into January, you have a very focused electorate who are going to be looking at differences in policy and substance,'' Mr. Lehane  said. ''We have made it absolutely clear we're going to fight for the voters in New Hampshire and Iowa.''</p>
        <p>Advertisements with a sting are certainly not unknown to the primary voters of New Hampshire. One of the most famous, in 1988 by Vice President George Bush, labeled Bob Dole ''Senator Straddle'' for refusing to pledge not to raise taxes; the spot, run in the closing days of the campaign, is widely thought to have contributed to Mr. Dole's defeat there.</p>
        <p>Since then, the public's patience with attack ads has worn thin. Mr. Forbes, who ran blistering spots against other Republicans in the 1996 New Hampshire race, is regarded as the recipient of residual voter resentment this year, even though his commercials this time have been considerably more restrained.</p>
        <p>The potential for voter backlash has made some media advisers  wary, and that may be why the campaigns are more adventurous with format than with policy issues. A result is that though issues are what the various camps purport to highlight in their spots, it is character that seems the predominant theme.</p>
        <p>The varied ways in which the commercials accentuate character range from the eye-catching documentary style of the Bush team's new ''crash ads'' -- 30-second spots taped at real campaign events, quickly edited and put on the air the same night or the next day -- to the straightforward evocations of the plain-spoken Mr. McCain, delivering parts of the speech announcing his candidacy, to the unvarnished 20-minute tape of Mr. Bradley mixing with voters at a town-hall meeting in Sioux City, Iowa.</p>
        <p>''One of the reasons we filmed Governor Bush in a free-form style was we were trying to capture some of the magic when he is out there with the people,'' said Stuart Stevens, one of Mr. Bush's media advisers. Similarly, Greg Stevens, Mr. McCain's media consultant (and no relation to Mr. Bush's adviser), says the senator's ability to ''connect to people'' gives his commercials their power.</p>
        <p>But how much magic and power get through to the viewers is unclear. Bruce Gronbeck, a communications professor at the University of Iowa, said the overall effect this year was a bit of a blur. Even when a candidate appears to be taking a strong stand, Professor Gronbeck said, when ''you look at the next guy's, they're pretty much the same.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
