<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lovers Who Burn the Air Around Them</title>
    <meta content="01AILE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ailey, Alvin, American Dance Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EEDE1238F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="382" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lovers Who Burn the Air Around Them</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews performance by Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater; photo of troupe dancing Polish Pieces (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the happiest aspects of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater winter season, which ends tomorrow, has been the performing.</p>
        <p>Burnished to a glow by Judith Jamison and Masazumi Chaya, longtime former Ailey dancers who are now, respectively, the troupe's artistic director and associate artistic director, the performers' high technical level and individuality were  seen to their best advantage in Hans van Manen's ''Polish Pieces'' on Wednesday afternoon at City Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the happiest aspects of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater winter season, which ends tomorrow, has been the performing.</p>
        <p>Burnished to a glow by Judith Jamison and Masazumi Chaya, longtime former Ailey dancers who are now, respectively, the troupe's artistic director and associate artistic director, the performers' high technical level and individuality were  seen to their best advantage in Hans van Manen's ''Polish Pieces'' on Wednesday afternoon at City Center.</p>
        <p>The piece, choreographed in 1995 and set to a driving score by Gorecki, has 12 dancers crossing and recrossing the stage in staggered lines and layered small groups. Three brief duets are embedded in the flow of the dance, which ends with odd abruptness. Kevin E. Boseman and Stephanie Powell were the playful, space-gobbling young lovers of the first duet. The two that followed were much more emotionally charged.</p>
        <p>Bahiyah Sayyed and Glenn A. Sims seemed to burn the air around them as the lovers of the second duet, she desperate, crooked-limbed and clinging to his resolutely passive body. There is a hint of resolution in the nobler third duet, danced with just the right clarity and heroism by Uri Sands and Linda Caceres.</p>
        <p>Staged by Mea Venana, ''Polish Pieces'' was greatly enhanced by Keso Dekker's jewel-colored unitards and Joop Caboort's strong but unobtrusive lighting. The elegant cast was completed by Asha Thomas, Troy O'Neil Powell, Cheryl Ann Rowley, Amos J. Machanic Jr., Briana Reed and Askia Swift.</p>
        <p>Ulysses Dove's ''Episodes'' might have looked better had it not followed Mr. Powell's bittersweet ''Ascension,'' a subtler jazz dance to similarly propulsive music. Nine faceless dancers stride, dash and slide across a variety of white-lighted diagonals on the dark stage, the women tossing their long hair and pausing to slug the men or leap into their arms.</p>
        <p>Eventually it all comes to seem like a postmodernist version of Jerome Robbins's ''Cage,'' a ballet about male-killing females. That impression was heightened by the chill evil projected by Lynn Barre, in a hard-dancing cast completed by Ms. Caceres, Ms. Thomas, Mr. Sims, Benoit-Swan Pouffer, Kristofer Storey, Jeffrey Gerodias and Mr. Swift.</p>
        <p>The program was completed by Ailey's ''Revelations.''</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
