<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Planetarium, the Fanciest Ball Is Inside the Cosmic One</title>
    <meta content="01PART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: A CITY CELEBRATES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Planetariums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Museum of Natural History (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hayden Planetarium</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zeiss (German Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rose Center for Earth and Space (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6DA1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Planetarium, the Fanciest Ball Is Inside the Cosmic One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More than 1,700 New Yorkers pay $500 to $1,500 a head to attend New Year's Eve party at Rose Center for Earth and Space of American Museum of Natural History, which encloses the rebuilt Hayden Planetarium, and have a preview of sky show presented by new $3.5 million Zeiss star projector; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was, at very long last, the night to party until it wasn't 1999. And then? It was time to party some more.</p>
        <p>And so, more than 1,700 revelers were lured to the bash that New Yorkers couldn't not go to. Overcoming false alarms warning of Scud missiles, millennial Manhattan-phobia and the urge to cocoon, they flocked to Central Park West last night to be the first to see the American Museum of Natural History's new $210 million planetarium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was, at very long last, the night to party until it wasn't 1999. And then? It was time to party some more.</p>
        <p>And so, more than 1,700 revelers were lured to the bash that New Yorkers couldn't not go to. Overcoming false alarms warning of Scud missiles, millennial Manhattan-phobia and the urge to cocoon, they flocked to Central Park West last night to be the first to see the American Museum of Natural History's new $210 million planetarium.</p>
        <p>Paying $500 to $5,000 per head, the party-hearty hedonists greeted the new millennium at the museum's black-tie fund-raiser, the city's most expensive, must-go, exclusive New Year's celebration. It sold out in July.</p>
        <p>After a banquet under the museum's 94-foot blue whale (where guests made fin-de-siecle jokes) they shouted the midnight countdown in the zeppelin-hangar-sized atrium of the new Rose Center for Earth and Space, the glass-walled building enclosing the rebuilt Hayden Planetarium. Along the way, they became the first to watch a preview of the sky show presented by the new $3.5 million Zeiss star projector.</p>
        <p>Thanks to the occasion, the new building -- a titanic cube surrounding the 87-foot-wide sphere of the planetarium -- was transformed into a cavernous four-level party space that resembled the launch pad of a globe-shaped starship.</p>
        <p>The construction of the Rose Center at the dawn of the new millennium was ''a happy accident of timing,'' said Ellen V. Futter, president of the museum.</p>
        <p>But given the general level of millennial anxiety, some guests made uneasy jokes about freezing in the post-midnight dark. Others were positively cheeky about the possibility for disaster.</p>
        <p>''Any evildoers would be vaporized if they dared come near New York's new planetarium,'' said one guest, City Councilman Stanley E. Michels of Manhattan, there with his wife, Molly. ''We're so excited to be among the first to see the Zeiss.''</p>
        <p>Henry Stern, the city's parks and recreation commissioner, said, ''Clearly, this is the party of the millennium,'' as he tucked into the rack of lamb in the Hall of Ocean Life adjacent to the planetarium.</p>
        <p>The party favors said it all: Each visitor received a disposable flash camera to record the millennial moment, and a flashlight. They were relieved that their flashlights became party props and not disaster gear.</p>
        <p>Outside the glass cube, Broadway theaters were dark, many restaurants were shuttered and a planned extravaganza at the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center had gone belly up. Nevertheless, the city was alive with parties, including a catered bunker blast for crisis managers and a 10-course blowout at Chanterelle, where 65 guests spent as much as $2,400 per person to consume oysters with caviar and Maine scallops with black truffles.</p>
        <p>The wanna-go party for many elegant 10021-ers and international visitors was the black-tie celebration for 200 at the Carlyle Hotel on East 76th Street and Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>There, Bobby Short and Eartha Kitt raised their voices in a conspiracy to launch cafe society into the 21st century.</p>
        <p>''I'm Y2K-compliant,'' said Mr. Short, who was holding forth before elegant admirers in the Cafe Carlyle for the 32nd straight New Year's Eve. ''And I'd like everyone to know that I'll be performing at the real millennium next year.''</p>
        <p>And though Christmas was last week's extravaganza, Miss Kitt won applause for belting out a torrid version of her signature song, ''Santa Baby.'' I think the millennium is looking a lot like Christmas,'' she purred.</p>
        <p>But hands down, the spaciest event of the evening was the museum celebration, where guests clutched Champagne glasses beside the 15-ton Willamette Meteorite in the atrium and then consumed Pink Nebula martinis to the strains of ''Stardust.'' They were serenaded by theramin music as they strolled along a black-lighted ''cosmic pathway'' to dinner, where their tables featured silver-orb centerpieces.</p>
        <p>Throughout the evening, groups of awed millennialists were beamed up by Lunar Lift elevators -- their actual name -- to the 436-seat Space Theater in the planetarium.</p>
        <p>There, they were introduced to the only Zeiss Mark IX projector in the world. Leaning back on upholstered headrests under the 38-foot-high dome, they oohed at the high-intensity, 9,100-star star field and aahed at Orion and other constellations.</p>
        <p>Then, crick-necked and happy, they were introduced to the planetarium's $4 million digital dome system. Driven by a bank of supercomputers, it is the world's largest reality simulator, transporting visitors on an astronomically accurate, five-billion-light-year tour of cosmic superclusters where galaxies seemed like grains of dust.</p>
        <p>''No audiences have ever seen these images before,'' said James S. Sweitzer, director of special projects for the planetarium. And the rest of the public will have to wait until mid-February, when the nearly finished Rose Center officially opens.</p>
        <p>''The millennium was certainly a construction deadline none of us could forget,'' said James A. Schmidt, executive director of the Rose Center construction project.</p>
        <p>''The Zeiss show made my hair stand on end,'' said one of the guests, Senator Charles Schumer, a Brooklyn Democrat. ''This is the future, and the future is New York.''</p>
        <p>Ann Druyan, who co-wrote the Zeiss show and is the widow of the astronomer Carl Sagan, said her late husband ''would have loved this evening's voyage, and he inspired it.''</p>
        <p>Lieut. Col. Cady Coleman of the Air Force, an astronaut who has flown two space shuttle missions, said, ''If there isn't a place like this planetarium, kids won't know where they live in the universe.''</p>
        <p>During the party's New Year's countdown, which had a hint of a Cape Kennedy rocket launch about it, the guests craned their necks yet again: this time to see wire walker Philippe Petit as he teetered on a steel wire at the fulcrum of the millennium. On the stroke of midnight, 1,500 star-and-moon balloons dropped, the guests warbled ''Auld Lang Syne'' along with the Drifters, and the crowd created its own light show by firing off more than a thousand throwaway flash cameras.</p>
        <p>The future-forward museum already boasts a welded stainless-steel time capsule designed to be opened in the year 3000. Was the scientific staff preparing for Y3K computer glitches? ''An interesting challenge,'' said Ms. Futter, the museum president. ''I thought I'd start looking at that problem on Jan. 2.''</p>
        <p>1/1/00: A CITY CELEBRATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
