<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pristine Cuisine Kills Germs, and Tastebuds</title>
    <meta content="01FOOD$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: BIOLOGY - RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sanitation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE5DF1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pristine Cuisine Kills Germs, and Tastebuds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov mock review of a restaurant of the future in which fear of germs is taken to extremes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the anteroom of Island, the latest Pristine Cuisine restaurant in fashionable Forest Hills, the crowd was avoiding any contact with one another as they switched their shoes for nylon booties and dipped their hands in that pricey California biocide coyly evocative of eau de Lysol (just ask your grandmother).</p>
        <p>Thus protected, they entered the pale, bare dining arena one by one. The food technicians -- gowned, gloved and masked -- completed the tedious choreography of sani-seating, draping the chairs and the diners. Though surgical green may not be everyone's most flattering color, at least it protects the white that everyone in New York has been wearing for far too many seasons now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the anteroom of Island, the latest Pristine Cuisine restaurant in fashionable Forest Hills, the crowd was avoiding any contact with one another as they switched their shoes for nylon booties and dipped their hands in that pricey California biocide coyly evocative of eau de Lysol (just ask your grandmother).</p>
        <p>Thus protected, they entered the pale, bare dining arena one by one. The food technicians -- gowned, gloved and masked -- completed the tedious choreography of sani-seating, draping the chairs and the diners. Though surgical green may not be everyone's most flattering color, at least it protects the white that everyone in New York has been wearing for far too many seasons now.</p>
        <p>Let me say this straight out: I am so tired of these restaurants that I am considering guerrilla action -- a surprise handshake or even, heaven protect me, spearing a morsel off someone's plate. I suppose the supergerms and the continuing rise in allergies requires common-sense precautions. But the Health Department's new no-sharing policy certainly makes my job more difficult. Oh, for the good old days before fear was a fashion statement, when a bite-for-a-bite was a fair trade and not considered assault.</p>
        <p>Yes, I know I sound like a decrepit geeze-bag. But while I'm at it, does anyone remember ''fusion'' cooking, when you could season the quenelles with lemongrass? Pretty soon no one will, if the new chefs continue down their isolationist road. I mean, would it be a sin to serve, say, a Vietnamese dipping sauce with the ''deep-water kreplach,'' or does that violate some sacred vow among nationalistic chefs? And why is it that chefs can serve the foods of different countries on one compartmentalized plate, but they're never allowed to touch? Are we afraid of some culinary miscegenation? And isn't anybody else sick of having everything wrapped in dumpling skins?</p>
        <p>I will concede that the dumpling disguise works well with the catch of the day these days; with marine laws restricting so many of the more pleasant-looking varieties until they replenish themselves, the bottom feeders that are permissible are best eaten concealed.</p>
        <p>But at Island, food camouflaging has been taken too far. Shrimp shumai, pirogis and lamb manti are all tasty enough, but each plate is a study in beige. And will somebody please explain to me the appeal of salad dumplings? Can anybody actually say they like dough-sheathed olives? It's as if somebody dumped the pig and put everything else in blankets, to recall a dish from the days when finger food was not a danger signal.</p>
        <p>And then, of course, there's dessert. At least the tarts -- of tropical fruit hydroponically grown on the premises since the import ban last year -- are colorful. But the Great Chocolate Scare of 2015 is long past. It's time to bring back mud pies and oozy chocolate cakes.</p>
        <p>The one redeeming feature at Island is the impressive list of antiseptic beverages; the bartender and sommelier have certainly risen to the opportunity to offer a well-chosen and potent selection. If only they would allow the clinking of glasses again.</p>
        <p>Island</p>
        <p>203-45 Austin St., Forest Hills, Queens; (832718) 555-5555.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE: All the intimacy of an operating room.</p>
        <p>SOUND LEVEL: Hushed.</p>
        <p>COMMUNICATIONS POLICY: Personal microwave contact permitted.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES: Pierogi, manti, shumai.</p>
        <p>SERVICE: Reptilian.</p>
        <p>WINE LIST: Excellent selection of Hungarians and Koreans.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CHIP: Individual and group scanners.</p>
        <p>ARTIFICIAL TRANSPORT: Fueling and charging at each table.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:</p>
        <p>(None) Poor to satisfactory  * Good  ** Very good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: BIOLOGY - RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
