<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Religion Journal; Fort Worth Saw a Way to Set This Holiday Apart</title>
    <meta content="01RELI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165116"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Peace</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University Christian Church (Fort Worth, Tex)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Colglazier, R Scott (Rev)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DD1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Religion Journal; Fort Worth Saw a Way to Set This Holiday Apart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rev R Scott Colglazier of University Christian Church in Fort Worth, Tex, appeals to colleagues around country to dedicate their first sermons of new year to subject of peace (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several months ago a Fort Worth  committee charged with planning the city's millennial events decided that this New Year's Eve ought to be  more than just a party, and instead  offer people a chance to reflect on something of greater meaning.</p>
        <p>''What we decided to do,'' said one committee member, the Rev. R. Scott Colglazier, ''was to have a few seconds' pause before midnight'' in the downtown celebration, ''a pause for peace.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Several months ago a Fort Worth  committee charged with planning the city's millennial events decided that this New Year's Eve ought to be  more than just a party, and instead  offer people a chance to reflect on something of greater meaning.</p>
        <p>''What we decided to do,'' said one committee member, the Rev. R. Scott Colglazier, ''was to have a few seconds' pause before midnight'' in the downtown celebration, ''a pause for peace.''</p>
        <p>Next Mr. Colglazier, senior pastor of the 5,000-member University Christian Church in Fort Worth, began trying to give the idea a far wider, religious currency, by appealing to colleagues around the country to dedicate their first sermons of the new year to the subject of peace. He wrote letters and made phone calls, and his church issued a press release. Along the way, he got a boost from another Texan, Jim Wright, former speaker of the House, who praised Mr. Colglazier's idea in a column in The Fort Worth Star-Telegram in September.</p>
        <p>Elaborating on the idea in a brief essay of his own in The Star-Telegram, Mr. Colglazier wrote:  ''Throughout the centuries, religious communities have been undergirded by a vision of peace grounded in the divine presence. To touch peace is to touch God, and to touch God is to touch peace.''</p>
        <p>''Although defined in various ways,'' he added, ''all religious communities agree that they have been given by God a responsibility toward the larger world. Surely no responsibility exceeds that of bringing peace to others.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Colglazier has heard from ministers in his denomination, the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), and from others who plan to preach on peace. But he has no idea how many have taken up the idea.</p>
        <p>''It's certainly ecumenical, and that's the reason I wanted to do it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A Musical 'Revolution'</p>
        <p>Speaking of sermons, it was two weeks ago, on Dec. 18, that Rabbi Eric Yoffie preached one calling for a ''revolution'' in the way that Reform Jews worship, asking that synagogues' ritual music be ''participatory, warm and accessible,'' features he said would be particularly inviting and inspiring to younger families.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Yoffie is president of the Union of American Hebrew Congregations, which represents 875 Reform synagogues, and his sermon was directed to the several thousand members attending the union's assembly, held in Orlando, Fla.</p>
        <p>In an interview, the rabbi said the music he meant was composed in a ''new American style,'' with roots in Jewish summer camps and youth groups, as opposed to more traditional music of worship that derives from Jewish communities in Eastern Europe. The traditional music, he said, is ''soaring and rich and moving,'' but often difficult to sing.</p>
        <p>In his sermon, Rabbi Yoffie also asked that the union's congregations adopt a greater focus on worship and prayer, and called for more emphasis on teaching Hebrew to adults, through the use of primers the union is developing. ''We value Hebrew for many reasons,'' he said, ''but it is most of all the great democratic tool of Jewish worship, the vehicle that opens the gates of prayer to the average Jew.''</p>
        <p>A Century-Long Run</p>
        <p>The sermon is but one of many ways of communicating religious ideas. More basic, at least to those who trace their tradition to the Bible, is the book.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview by e-mail, on the subject of the most significant religious figures of the 20th century, the eminent historian of Christianity Martin E. Marty said he believed that the single most influential book in American religion to have been written in the last 100 years was ''The Varieties of Religious Experience,'' by the psychologist William James.</p>
        <p>And why not? Published in 1902, when James was teaching at Harvard, it remains in print, a valued text in many university religion courses.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
