<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Good Run for Actor Who Specializes in Bad</title>
    <meta content="01YULI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Harris Yulin</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yulin, Harris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Price, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DC1238F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Good Run for Actor Who Specializes in Bad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Actor Harris Yulin discusses current role in Arthur Miller's play The Price, and reputation for playing 'bad guys' over 40-year career in film and on stage, interview; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harris Yulin doesn't have a killer's face, but if you saw him walking down the street you could be excused for taking cover.</p>
        <p>In his 40-year career, after all, Mr. Yulin has played more than a few disreputable characters, from the sleazy cop in Brian De Palma's 1983 cult movie ''Scarface'' to his recent turn as a double-dealing politician in the film ''Cradle Will Rock.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Harris Yulin doesn't have a killer's face, but if you saw him walking down the street you could be excused for taking cover.</p>
        <p>In his 40-year career, after all, Mr. Yulin has played more than a few disreputable characters, from the sleazy cop in Brian De Palma's 1983 cult movie ''Scarface'' to his recent turn as a double-dealing politician in the film ''Cradle Will Rock.''</p>
        <p>It is casting, the actor says, that  has more to do with his stern, rugged looks and almost senatorial presence than with any preference on his part.</p>
        <p>''I'm not always the bad guy,'' he said recently, with a shrug. ''It just seems to be what I'm known for.''</p>
        <p>Lately, Mr. Yulin has been turning that gruff reputation on its head with his subtle turn as Walter Franz, a damaged businessman looking for emotional solace in the current Broadway production of Arthur Miller's drama ''The Price.'' Ben Brantley, writing in The New York Times, called Mr. Yulin's performance ''excellent,'' adding that Walter seemed to be a character whom Mr. Yulin was ''born to play.''</p>
        <p>It's not the only role Mr. Yulin may have been made for. Indeed, the actor's talents are on particular display of late, with four major projects open or coming soon. In addition to ''The Price'' and ''Cradle Will Rock,'' Mr. Yulin can be seen in ''The Hurricane'' playing the lawyer who represents that film's wrongly convicted hero (a good guy!), and in a movie scheduled for Jan. 9 on the TNT Network, ''The Virginian.'' There Mr. Yulin reverts to form as a disreputable judge.</p>
        <p>At 62, Mr. Yulin has established himself as something of the character actor's character actor, a quiet force who parlays small roles into big moments.</p>
        <p>His status is evident in ''The Price,'' where he shares the stage with three other accomplished actors: Bob Dishy, Lizbeth Mackay and Jeffrey DeMunn,</p>
        <p>''He pays a lot of attention to details and specifics of characters: the hands, the voice,'' Mr. Dishy said. ''And I appreciate it, because I work in a similiar way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yulin, a smoker who talks in something like a casual growl, didn't plan it this way. A Los Angeles native, he worked his way through a series of professions -- and countries -- before landing on the stage.</p>
        <p>''I tried to be a painter for a while in Florence,'' he said. ''And I was extremely bad at it.''</p>
        <p>After flirting with architecture, he found himself in Tel Aviv in 1962, a time and a place he remembers as ''like Paris in the 1920's.'' There, at the urging of new friends, he began directing and acting in small shows.</p>
        <p>That calling took hold, and when he returned to the United States, he decided -- if that is the right word -- to continue acting. ''I said, 'Well, I guess this is what I'm going to do,''' he said.</p>
        <p>His first break came in 1963, when he was cast in a leading role in a production at the Phoenix, a now-defunct Off Broadway theater. The play was ''Next Time I'll Sing For You,'' which featured James Earl Jones and Estelle Parsons and was notable in a couple of regards, Mr. Yulin said.</p>
        <p>First, it was scheduled to open the week of Nov. 22, 1963, when President John F. Kennedy was assassinated. (The opening was postponed.) Second, said Mr. Yulin, the production, an absurdist take on a novel by the Anglo-Indian novelist Raleigh Trevelyan, was ''just a disaster.''</p>
        <p>''I sat on the apron of the stage, insulting the audience essentially, in a sort of elegant way, but insulting nevertheless,'' Mr. Yulin said. ''I could feel waves of hate coming from the audience.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yulin's fortunes improved, however, and over the course of the next decade, his standing was sealed. In 1980 he won raves in the Broadway production of ''A Lesson From Aloes,'' by Athol Fugard, in which he again played opposite Mr. Jones.</p>
        <p>His film work also began to increase, with roles in ''The Believers,'' ''Clear and Present Danger'' and ''Multiplicity.''</p>
        <p>For the last decade, he has also teamed with his friends and fellow actors Ed Asner and Rene Auberjonois to do staged readings of ''Don Juan in Hell,'' a favorite of his since high school. And last year, he directed ''This Lime Tree Bower,'' at Primary Stages.</p>
        <p>As he matured as an actor, Mr. Yulin says, he was also trying to get rid of another, less seemly reputation.</p>
        <p>''I think when I was young, I became known as what you would call a difficult person to work with,'' he said with a smidgen of pride. ''I never felt it was a question of ego, but I did realize I offended some people.''</p>
        <p>That attitude has apparently faded with the years, at least according to Mr. Yulin's current Broadway director, the actor James Naughton.</p>
        <p>''None of that was in evidence,'' Mr. Naughton said. ''Every rehearsal I've been in there's a day where everything goes south, or someone goes south. It never happened with this show.''</p>
        <p>In rehearsals for ''The Price,'' which began at the Williamstown Theater Festival in Williamstown, Mass., Mr. Naughton said Mr. Yulin had only one demand: that his dog, Max, a cocker spaniel, be allowed to watch.</p>
        <p>''Max would wander onto the playing field during rehearsal,'' Mr. Naughton said. ''Harris would just look at him, point, and Max would wander back off.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yulin, who divides his time between New York and Los Angeles as work demands, often drives across the country because Max has a fear of flying. Along the way, he says, he often stops in small towns.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, someone recognizes him. ''They're like, 'Hey, what are you doing here?' '' Mr. Yulin says. ''And then, once they realize I'm just an actor, people are almost always friendly and pleasant.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
