<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rappers Who Won't Let The Audience Be Lazy</title>
    <meta content="01ARSO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arsonists (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFDD1238F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rappers Who Won't Let The Audience Be Lazy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers reviews performance by rap group Arsonists; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q-Unique, one of the rappers in the Bushwick-based Arsonists crew, was home after a European tour, and he wasn't going to suffer a bland reception. ''You paid some good money to see a show,'' he urged the crowd Wednesday night at S.O.B.'s. ''Be part of the show!''</p>
        <p>The fans soon complied. Q-Unique's command came in the middle of the show's ''beat machine'' segment, in which the group's five rappers create the sound of a percussion section, augmented by the audience's singing. The first round hardly resonated, but the second shook the room. The only surprise was that it took taunting to get the response.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q-Unique, one of the rappers in the Bushwick-based Arsonists crew, was home after a European tour, and he wasn't going to suffer a bland reception. ''You paid some good money to see a show,'' he urged the crowd Wednesday night at S.O.B.'s. ''Be part of the show!''</p>
        <p>The fans soon complied. Q-Unique's command came in the middle of the show's ''beat machine'' segment, in which the group's five rappers create the sound of a percussion section, augmented by the audience's singing. The first round hardly resonated, but the second shook the room. The only surprise was that it took taunting to get the response.</p>
        <p>The Arsonists hungrily absorb the energy generated by audience participation, using banter and improvisation to cultivate the excitement of a house party. At S.O.B.'s, the rappers were looser than usual, often stopping in midsong to exchange barbs or rant. But these pauses were part of the fun in routines that never quite ended up where they started.</p>
        <p>Known for silly skits like ''Rhyme Time Traveler,'' in which Q-Unique dons different hats and necklaces to enact a history of rap, and ''Hip Hop Aerobics,'' a fancy term for getting everyone to jump around, the Arsonists play the most boisterous, popular kids in school. The crew's rapping style seamlessly connects to this image; the quintet usually raps its choruses in unison, with individual members trading verses with sparring grace.</p>
        <p>Their styles varied, from the smooth and mellow tone of Swel Boogie to the freneticism of D-Stroy, whose approach recalled another comical Latin artist, John Leguizamo. During ''Lunchroom Take-Out,'' a boasting match between Swel Boogie and the guest rapper Great Scott, D-Stroy occasionally burst through the banter with hilarious off-color exclamations.</p>
        <p>DJ Daddy Dogg gently worked the turntables during the Arsonists' set, showing skills but sometimes seeming overwhelmed. It isn't easy to keep up with so much verbal gunfire. Spinning for the opening act, Non-Phixion, DJ Eclipse had more room to create intriguing soundscapes.</p>
        <p>Like the Arsonists, Non-Phixion espouses an approach that values complicated rhyming over easy hooks and live charisma over studio wizardry. In between those acts, two members of the veteran Cold Crush Brothers performed a short set, reinforcing another tenet of underground hip-hop: that the culture's original passions, from break-dancing to the hearty raps of such early performers, are still the most potent. The infectious joy of the Arsonists did much to fortify that message.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
