<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playoffs or No, Dallas Provides The Motivation</title>
    <meta content="01GIAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165062"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Cowboys</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Dallas Cowboys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4DA1338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playoffs or No, Dallas Provides The Motivation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on upcoming New York Giants-Dallas Cowboys game; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Waiting in the visiting locker room at Texas Stadium late tomorrow afternoon, the Giants will know whether the Green Bay Packers, who play earlier against Arizona, have won or are comfortably ahead.</p>
        <p>Since either scenario, in all probability, would eliminate the Giants from the playoff race, there could surely be some disappointment as the Giants prepare to take the field for their 4:05 p.m. game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Waiting in the visiting locker room at Texas Stadium late tomorrow afternoon, the Giants will know whether the Green Bay Packers, who play earlier against Arizona, have won or are comfortably ahead.</p>
        <p>Since either scenario, in all probability, would eliminate the Giants from the playoff race, there could surely be some disappointment as the Giants prepare to take the field for their 4:05 p.m. game.</p>
        <p>Most Giants believe there will be an instant cure for any melancholy, and it will be on the other side of the locker room doors.</p>
        <p>''Running out there and seeing their fans, seeing the Cowboys, seeing the whole America's Team thing,'' the Giants 11-year center Brian Williams said earlier this week. ''That will get to me. I want to beat them. I mean, I can't even stand it when I walk around New York and see Dallas Cowboys hats.''</p>
        <p>The Giants never expected their season to end up like this, with them holding on to slim playoff hopes. These Giants, after all, were in first place at the midpoint of their season.</p>
        <p>But if Green Bay wins, it is the Cowboys who have the opportunity to win and go to the playoffs, unless the Giants can defeat Dallas by 56 more points than the Packers have defeated Arizona.</p>
        <p>Still, the 7-8 Giants say they intend to make the last act of their season a purposeful victory. Or, as many Giants put it this week, if they are going to ruin anybody's new year, they would want it to be the Cowboys' new year. That it would come in Dallas, where the Giants have won just twice in the 1990's, would be even better.</p>
        <p>''That would be a great millennium present,'' said Giants linebacker Jessie Armstead, a Dallas native.</p>
        <p>The alternative is watching the Cowboys celebrate their unexpected good fortune -- a playoff berth with an 8-8 record -- as the Giants trudge into the off-season with their first losing season under Coach Jim Fassel.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to see any of that down there,'' Armstead said. ''Them winning and celebrating and talking. We won't have any trouble getting up for stopping them. I know all about the Cowboys' image and reputation. I grew up like any other kid in Dallas; the Cowboys were my team. But the day I got drafted by the Giants, I was a Cowboys-hater like everybody else around here.''</p>
        <p>There is a certain enmity between the franchises that is tangible, something that surfaces in off-hand comments and off-the-record remarks, and something that has developed because these teams have seemed in each other's way at critical junctures of pivotal seasons for most of the last 10 years.</p>
        <p>At the end of the 1990 season the Giants won the Super Bowl, but the decade soon turned into a championship one for the Cowboys. By 1997, it was interesting to note how the Giants relished their season-ending victory at Dallas, a victory that made them the only National Football Conference East club ever to go undefeated in division play.</p>
        <p>Conversely, it was Dallas's Monday night wipeout of the Giants in 1998 that first signaled that real trouble was ahead that year. You could say the same thing about a 1995 Monday night blowout by Dallas of the Giants. And then there was the 1993 season finale at Giants Stadium, when the Giants lost the home-field advantage in the playoffs in a 16-13 overtime loss to the Cowboys.</p>
        <p>Dallas took the home field to the Super Bowl, where the Cowboys won another championship.</p>
        <p>It is all part of the rivalry, as is the obvious discord that exists between the Giants co-owner Wellington Mara and the Dallas owner, Jerry Jones.</p>
        <p>Mara admonished his players on Wednesday for their play in the loss to Minnesota last weekend. Falling down on the job in Dallas will hardly be viewed as the appropriate response.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that's going to happen,'' Williams said. ''Everybody on this team wants to be flying home knowing we did our best, that we did something good. Beating the Cowboys, regardless of what else happens, that's something good.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>When the Cowboys and Giants met in October, the Giants' defense had one of its best games, limiting EMMITT SMITH to 26 rushing yards in 22 attempts in a 13-10 Giants victory. ''That wasn't one of our better performances,'' Dallas quarterback TROY AIKMAN said. Cowboys Coach CHAN GAILEY said he thought Smith was looking forward to getting another chance against the Giants. ''Yeah, I think Emmitt remembers,'' Gailey said. ''He wants to go out and have a good game.'' . . . Giants Coach JIM FASSEL said he would not rest injured players, like running back JOE MONTGOMERY, who has a rib injury. Nonetheless, expect to see the role of the rookie running back SEAN BENNETT expanded. Bennett has been out for most of the season with a knee injury, but this could be the Giants' last chance to get him some seasoning and experience in game situations.  PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
