<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Missing in Russia: A History and a Purpose</title>
    <meta content="01SLAV$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: POWER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DF1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Missing in Russia: A History and a Purpose</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Wines</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Wines article on what will become of Russia in next century, given its lost sense of purpose after end of the cold war, its history of being ruled by strongmen and its suspicion of or hostility to the outside world; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANYONE trying to divine the next step on Russia's wandering course toward nationhood might start with this arresting fact: the last time Russians lived within borders as constricted as the current ones, Ivan the Terrible had been dead for only a few decades, St. Petersburg was a frozen swamp, and New York City was still the property of the Dutch.</p>
        <p>In Russia, more than in most places, geography is history. That the collapse of the Soviet Union wiped out 350 years of imperial expansion underlines a central fact of modern Russian history: for all practical purposes, there isn't any. Russians not only lost their shackles with the end of the cold war, they also lost their historical reason for being.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANYONE trying to divine the next step on Russia's wandering course toward nationhood might start with this arresting fact: the last time Russians lived within borders as constricted as the current ones, Ivan the Terrible had been dead for only a few decades, St. Petersburg was a frozen swamp, and New York City was still the property of the Dutch.</p>
        <p>In Russia, more than in most places, geography is history. That the collapse of the Soviet Union wiped out 350 years of imperial expansion underlines a central fact of modern Russian history: for all practical purposes, there isn't any. Russians not only lost their shackles with the end of the cold war, they also lost their historical reason for being.</p>
        <p>''Russia has a major problem finding its identity in the world,'' said Vyachaslav A. Nikonov, a political scientist and expert on contemporary Russia. ''In the people's mind, Russia doesn't belong to anything.''</p>
        <p>It is not too great a stretch to say that Russia has not been this bereft -- of friends, wealth, territory, purpose -- in centuries. The loss of empire cost her 100 million people and shattered military and political alliances that had been the basis of both foreign and domestic policies. The country's gross domestic product has declined by about half since 1991. Birth rates have plummeted and death rates have jumped. The population, now 145.7 million, is projected to fall to 120 million, and possibly to 80 million, by 2050.</p>
        <p>Also, Russians must somehow overcome the physical toll wrought by 70 years of irrational economic decisions. Much of the infrastructure, from factories to roads to telephone lines to basic things like doors and windows, is obsolete or worn out.</p>
        <p>''Rebuilding the country is going to be an extremely prolonged process -- a generation, a generation and a half, is going to be about the right time frame,'' said Thomas Graham, a former American diplomat in Moscow and now a scholar at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. ''And there's nothing inevitable about it.''</p>
        <p>The hope of Western nations was that Russians would embrace the kind of liberal democratic and economic philosophies that were their lamplights in the dark days of communist rule and reorient the nation outward toward cooperation and peaceful competition.</p>
        <p>But as Robert Legvold, a scholar at Columbia University, noted in an essay, ''The Three Russias,'' such hopes ignore Russian history. Russia has always been ruled by strongmen. It has often viewed the outside world not as something to be engaged but as either a threat to be shunned or an enemy to be defeated.</p>
        <p>It sees Russian civilization as exceptional -- a truth in many ways, but also a short hop away from the view that other civilizations are decadent and polluting. It obsesses over the ebb and surge of its western and southern borders, boundaries that historically have been unstable precisely because they were not really Russian, but imperial.</p>
        <p>''Contemporary Russia can no more escape this history than it can immaculately will itself into democracy or any other de nove identity,'' Mr. Legvold writes.</p>
        <p>For Russians, the difficulty in shedding the past is evident in trends of the last five years: the return of the belief that the West is a military threat; the interpretation of American oil deals in former Soviet states as hostile acts; the rising conviction, expressed in opinion polls, that Moscow should return to its days of empire.</p>
        <p>Many experts here speak with longing of the prospects for a ''Russian Pinochet,'' a Latin-style strongman who will restore order while imposing a permanent template of modern capitalism. More than a few analysts think the mix of xenophobia, nostalgia and simple exhaustion will instead lead Russia to the same end as did the abdication of Nicholas II in 1917 -- dictatorship, and a quest to regain lost territory.</p>
        <p>Mr. Legvold avoids a prediction, but offers yet another model -- not a Russian Pinochet or a noncommunist Stalin, but a Russian Slobodan Milosevic, whipping people's frustrations and rage into a dangerously nationalistic threat to peace.</p>
        <p>There is another possible outcome, too: a Russia that moves toward its own form of democratic capitalism. Aleksandr A. Kabakov, author of two fictional accounts of the future of Russia, said he hoped that the next president would tug Russia along that course. Not until World War II did Europe abandon the imperial model of nationhood, he observed, and even then, great nations like France could not free their colonies without wrenching transitions. His hope is that Russia will learn from the mistakes of the West.</p>
        <p>That said, the second of his futurist novels, ''The Sentenced One,'' depicts a world 50 years from now in which Russia is reduced to a Muscovite duchy, a Berlin-style wall runs through Paris, and both Belgium and Britain are split on ethnic and racial lines.</p>
        <p>''It's not a prediction,'' Mr. Kabakov said. ''It's a warning. Because if our people will be such fools as they are being now, it will be so. Not just Russia, but the whole world.''</p>
        <p>VISIONS: POWER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
