<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Solemnity and Flash In the Land of Jesus</title>
    <meta content="Y01JERU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DF1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Solemnity and Flash In the Land of Jesus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG and WILLIAM A. ORME Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a beautiful, almost ethereal scene, about 2,000 Christians quietly ascended the Mount of Olives as midnight approached. Following a lighted crucifix, they carried votive candles that flickered in the still darkness of a city devoid of any official celebration of the millennium.</p>
        <p>At the top, they planted the crucifix and gathered round, moved by the serenity. Then, switching in a flash from the sublime to the cheesy, it turned into a Dick Clark New Year's Eve special with a Fellini-esque cast, set in the heart of the Holy Land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a beautiful, almost ethereal scene, about 2,000 Christians quietly ascended the Mount of Olives as midnight approached. Following a lighted crucifix, they carried votive candles that flickered in the still darkness of a city devoid of any official celebration of the millennium.</p>
        <p>At the top, they planted the crucifix and gathered round, moved by the serenity. Then, switching in a flash from the sublime to the cheesy, it turned into a Dick Clark New Year's Eve special with a Fellini-esque cast, set in the heart of the Holy Land.</p>
        <p>There, a Franciscan priest stepped onto a rickety sound stage and into an emcee persona. Beckoning the crowd closer, he led a heavily accented English countdown to midnight. An amplified electronic keyboard let loose a bad disco version of ''Auld Lang Syne.'' And the people, from the Italian nuns to the Catholic church group from Texas, all ran for cover as sparks from a fireworks display rained on their moment of faith.</p>
        <p>''Very beautiful, the fireworks, but very, very close,'' said Sister Elisa, a Spanish nun, as she brushed a spark from her habit.</p>
        <p>Compared with the festivities around the world, at ground zero in the land where Jesus lived and died, the celebration was a modest, even rinky-dink, affair. Midnight marked just another day in the year 5760 on the Jewish calendar and 1420 on the Islamic one. Most of Jerusalem was shuttered; the Israeli government staged no events.</p>
        <p>Bethlehem was another story. Manger Square was packed, a Palestinian block party par excellence, culminating in a resounding fireworks show that coincided with the release of 2,000 doves for peace. Stunned, the doves crashed and bumped their way into the night, somewhat startled and tentative symbols, but the crowd was elated.</p>
        <p>Like Manger Square, the rocky hillside of the Mount of Olives, venerated by Jews for its ancient cemetery and by Christians as a place where Jesus preached and prayed, was heavily guarded by security officials.</p>
        <p>But it could not have been more peaceful. The faithful lined up on the steps of the Church of All Nations, praying in many languages and singing Latin hymns as they gazed on the spectacularly lit Old City.</p>
        <p>''It's a time of looking forward to the future with hope, and not toward disaster and doom and all that,'' said the Rev. Mitchell Pacwa of Dallas.</p>
        <p>Not long after midnight, the foreigners scattered, back into their hotels, tour buses and taxis, leaving only the few Palestinians walking home and the many Israeli soldiers packing up. Norma Sakhel, a Palestinian Catholic, descended the mount with a group of friends. ''Look at them,'' she said, smiling at the Israelis. ''They were protecting us. Protecting us from what?</p>
        <p>''Those who expected violence are those who do not believe in God,'' she said.</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
