<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suspect in Beatle Attack Held in Psychiatric Unit</title>
    <meta content="01BEAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165059"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abram, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DB1338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suspect in Beatle Attack Held in Psychiatric Unit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Abram is charged with attempted murder in the stabbing of George Harrison in London and is sent to a prison mental clinic for evaluation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The man accused of stabbing George Harrison on Thursday was charged with attempted murder today and then sent to a prison mental clinic for evaluation.</p>
        <p>''This is an exceptional course of action, but we feel you need treatment immediately,'' the magistrate presiding over the case told the man, 33-year-old Michael Abram of Liverpool. The magistrate, Tim Pocock, then adjourned the hearing until Feb. 11.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The man accused of stabbing George Harrison on Thursday was charged with attempted murder today and then sent to a prison mental clinic for evaluation.</p>
        <p>''This is an exceptional course of action, but we feel you need treatment immediately,'' the magistrate presiding over the case told the man, 33-year-old Michael Abram of Liverpool. The magistrate, Tim Pocock, then adjourned the hearing until Feb. 11.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abram, who the police said was knocked unconscious by Mr. Harrison's wife during the attack, is said by his family members to be a former heroin addict who is delusional, hears voices in his head and harbors a strange hatred of the Beatles, whom he believes to be ''witches.''</p>
        <p>His mother, Lynda, told reporters that repeated attempts to get help for her son had failed.</p>
        <p>''I have had no help from anyone,'' she said. ''I feel as though I have been totally isolated for the last six years. The system is totally useless unless you commit a serious offense.''</p>
        <p>It is still unclear how the intruder managed to gain access to Mr. Harrison's well-secured estate, set inside electronic gates and razor wire on 34 acres in Henley-on-Thames, about 25 miles west of London.</p>
        <p>The struggle, in which Mr. Harrison, his wife, Olivia, and the intruder were all injured, took place in several rooms in the huge mansion, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harrison, 56, was said to be in pain but recovering well today after treatment for a collapsed lung at Harefield Hospital outside of London.</p>
        <p>Robert Craig, general manager of the hospital, said that doctors were working to reinflate the lung, which was damaged when Mr. Harrison suffered a one-inch-deep stab wound in the attack.</p>
        <p>''It is a question of waiting for the treatment to take hold until his lung reinflates,'' Mr. Craig said. ''We hope that he will be able to go home in a couple of days, but that depends on the next 24 hours.''</p>
        <p>The Thames Valley police, who are handling the investigation, said that it was still too early to say exactly what happened during the struggle.</p>
        <p>But what was most likely, the police said, is that Mr. Abram attacked Mr. Harrison first, slashing him repeatedly and stabbing him in the chest, before inflicting superficial stab wounds on Mrs. Harrison, 51, when she intervened. Mr. Abram, the police said, was then knocked unconscious when Mrs. Harrison picked up a heavy table lamp and hit him hard over the head.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Harrison suffered cuts and bruises in the attack, but was released from the hospital. She spent last night at Mr. Harrison's bedside in the Harefield surgery ward.</p>
        <p>In his court appearance today, Mr. Abram had a heavily bruised forehead and a black left eye.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
