<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="01FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165135"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DB1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A11, 13-19</p>
        <p>Yeltsin Resigns, Naming Putin as Acting President  Boris N. Yeltsin shocked Russia and the world, announcing his resignation as president six months before the end of his term and handing over power to his favored successor, Prime Minister Vladimir V. Putin, above. By appointing Mr. Putin acting president, Mr. Yeltsin seemed determined to put a lock on Mr. Putin's succession to the presidency.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A11, 13-19</p>
        <p>Yeltsin Resigns, Naming Putin as Acting President  Boris N. Yeltsin shocked Russia and the world, announcing his resignation as president six months before the end of his term and handing over power to his favored successor, Prime Minister Vladimir V. Putin, above. By appointing Mr. Putin acting president, Mr. Yeltsin seemed determined to put a lock on Mr. Putin's succession to the presidency.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>After decades of secretive and brutal Communist rule, years of topsy-turvy economics under Mr. Yeltsin and countless political maneuvers that made little difference to their daily grind, many Muscovites seemed simply glad to see an aging, obviously unwell leader leave the scene, or just plain did not care.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Clinton administration officials said that Mr. Yeltsin's surprise resignation would not dramatically alter relations with Russia, and could improve the chances that Moscow and Washington break a stalemate over a major arms control treaty.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Chechnya War Takes Toll  As Russia begins the new year, its troops are mired in urban warfare in the breakaway republic of Chechnya, and the still popular war is claiming a higher toll. The Russian artillery hurled round after round toward Grozny, the capital of Chechnya, as the rebels doggedly fought back.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Hijacker Deal Frees Hostages  More than 150 people held hostage on a hijacked jet for eight days arrived in New Delhi from Afghanistan after India secured their freedom by agreeing to release three jailed militants. The five hijackers, whose names and nationalities are still unknown, sped away from the airport in a van with the three militants.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Pakistan's government welcomed the peaceful end of the hijacking ordeal in neighboring Afghanistan and, like a proud older brother, praised that country's Taliban leaders for ''showing great responsibility and maturity'' in managing the crisis.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Ethnic Strife in Indonesia  New clashes erupted in Indonesia's eastern islands, where at least 300 people have died in Christian-Muslim violence in recent days. The latest fighting comes at the end of a year of almost uninterrupted sectarian violence in the Moluccas.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Croatian Ahead in Polls  Ivica Racan, a 55-year-old ex-Communist, is likely to be Croatia's next prime minister if the polls hold and an opposition coalition wins parliamentary elections on Jan. 3. And if the opposition does win, defeating the governing Croatian Democratic Union, Mr. Racan says he will move to cut spending on social services by 17 percent.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Panama Canal Is Panama's  Many Panamanians said that as the United States turned over the Panama Canal, the day felt like Independence Day. The head of the American delegation signed the papers to formalize the transfer.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A20-28, 32</p>
        <p>Prison Security Questioned After the Death of a Guard  Three days after a prison guard and an inmate were killed in an escape attempt at the Louisiana State Penitentiary, law-enforcement officials in the area raised questions about the security of the prison farm known as Angola. Even before the incident on Tuesday, there were lapses and escape attempts at the prison, a district attorney said.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Debating Drug Industry Ties  Vice President Al Gore has denounced former Senator Bill Bradley for taking large amounts of campaign cash from drug companies and, Mr. Gore says, doing their bidding during his 18 years in the Senate. But the Clinton-Gore administration has also helped pharmaceutical companies on certain issues, and the Clinton-Gore ticket has raked in plenty of their money, too.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Rehnquist Notes Progress  Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist surveyed the state of the federal judiciary and, in contrast to many of his 12 previous year-end reports, pronounced himself quite pleased. The chief justice noted progress in three areas he had identified as problems in his report a year ago: vacant seats on the United States Sentencing Commission, compensation for federal judges and the caseload of the federal courts.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Intermediary in Cuban Case  The National Council of Churches said it had been working as an intermediary in an agreement to return to Cuba a 6-year-old boy at the center of an international custody dispute but that the deal had fallen apart. The group said it would send two representatives to Cuba on Sunday to meet with the boy's father and grandparents and with United States and Cuban government officials, in hopes of securing the boy's return.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Worker Charged in Killings  A hotel housekeeper was charged with first-degree murder in the killings of four fellow workers in a crowded hotel and the shooting death of a woman from whom he had tried to take a car as he sought to escape. The police said they were still unsure about a motive.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Environmentalists Admit Arson  A radical environmentalist group that has claimed responsibility for a series of arsons, including fires last year that caused $12 million in damage to a ski resort in Vail, Colo., said it was also responsible for the Dec. 25 arson that destroyed the Oregon offices of Boise Cascade.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Man Charged in Bomb Hoax  A Missouri man was arrested on Thursday after the authorities said he telephoned a fake bomb threat in an unsuccessful effort to delay a Korean Airlines jet in San Francisco long enough for his girlfriend to catch the flight. The plane was already en route to Seoul, South Korea, at the time of the call, and the authorities allowed it to proceed after finding the threat to be a hoax. The man, Flavio David Mendoza of Hazelwood was arrested in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>World Welcomes 2000, With Parties and Song  Two thousand years after Christ's birth, the world's six billion people rode their turning blue planet across time's invisible line and, by common consent, looked into the dawn of a new millennium. Across the United States, in Europe, Asia, Africa and Australia, in cities and towns all over the world, bells pealed, crowds shrieked and surged, skyrockets soared into the night, fireworks burst into supernovas, ''Auld Lang Syne'' rang out, lights pulsed, and loved ones and friends embraced.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Despite a few sputters and glitches, the world's computers appear to have survived the Year 2000 rollover without major problems -- and with humanity's faith in technology intact, at least for another day. There were a flurry of reports of minor problems, but any technology failures were more likely to be the result of crowding than attributable to computer software.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Times Square crowd showed every sign of being the biggest and noisiest ever, undeterred by fears of terrorism or Y2K havoc.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>No Bail for Bomb Plot Suspect  The Algerian man arrested in Brooklyn on charges of being part of a terrorist bomb plot was ordered held without bond in a court proceeding that otherwise offered few new details about the suspect or his activities. The defendant, Abdel Ghani, was arrested on Thursday.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Stadium Plan Gains Support  A group of Brooklyn community groups that sued to stop a minor league Mets team from moving into a planned ballpark in Flatbush has dropped its opposition to the plan, now that the city has promised to renovate a park where the team would play. But the Brooklyn borough president, Howard Golden, remains a stumbling block to an agreement.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>NEEDIEST CASES</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>F1-32</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Sugar Bowl Ends the Season  The eight remaining college football bowl games promise to be entertaining, but only one will decide the national title: Virginia Tech against Florida State in the Sugar Bowl on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Elliot L. Richardson  The former attorney general and ambassador was 79. He was best known for his refusal during Watergate to obey President Richard M. Nixon's order to fire a special prosecutor.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Dow Closes on an Upswing  The Dow Jones industrial average, by far the best-known average to have endured the entire century, rose 44.26, to a record 11,497.12 yesterday. For the decade, the Dow was up 318 percent, by far its best decade ever. For the century, it rose 26,130 percent.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Treasury prices ended the year lower in a half-day session, pushing yields to near their highest levels in more than two years.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Tax Lawyer Named in Fraud  A Tax Court judge has ruled that one of the nation's most prominent tax lawyers, Burton W. Kanter of Chicago, was ''the architect'' of a long-running kickback and tax-evasion scheme.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Detroit Trails in Hybrid Race  Experimental vehicles from General Motors, Ford and DaimlerChrysler face huge obstacles that raise questions about a costly partnership between Detroit and Washington. Honda and Toyota, operating with much smaller government subsidies, have already begun mass production of high-mileage cars that combine gas engines and electric motors.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Disputing Waste Merger Cost  Waste Management, the nation's biggest hauler of trash, contends in a lawsuit that it overpaid in a $1.15 billion acquisition of Eastern Environmental Services because Eastern's chairman overstated profits.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Malaysia Defers Share Dispute  Malaysia announced that it had extended by six months a deadline for resolving an impasse on $3.8 billion worth of Malaysian stocks frozen on a Singapore exchange.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: The shape of an age to come.  Columns: Maureen Dowd, William Safire, Frank Rich, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
