<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Audis and Cell Phones, Poverty and Fear</title>
    <meta content="01CITY$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: CITIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sao Paulo (Brazil)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil/Sao Paulo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DE1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Audis and Cell Phones, Poverty and Fear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Roger Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>SAO PAULO, Brazil</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sao Paulo, Brazil, fastest-growing metropolis of 20th century, provides the contrasts of poverty and riches, violence and fear that will characterize world's urban areas in 21st century, when more than half of humanity will live in cities; photos; map shows world's largest cities in 1965 and 2015 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LUCIANA MARIA DOS SANTOS lives on the south side of the world's third-largest city in Favela 19, or Slum 19, a collection of shacks traversed by a stream that doubles as the sewage system. Her waterfront property consists of a shanty with a corrugated-iron roof; rats are not infrequent visitors. Despite the limited space, she has managed to squeeze in 2,638 discarded cans.</p>
        <p>At night Ms. Dos Santos, 19, heads out past the glittering high-rises, the sleeping bodies under bridges, the buildings that surge and subside with a giddy symmetry in this city that is now a 3,100-square-mile ocean of concrete. Her destination is the clubs whose environs offer lucrative garbage. Over 10 days, she collects more than 2,000 beverage cans; they will earn her $30 from a scrap dealer. ''It's not pleasant work,'' she says. ''But the alternative is crime or crack.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LUCIANA MARIA DOS SANTOS lives on the south side of the world's third-largest city in Favela 19, or Slum 19, a collection of shacks traversed by a stream that doubles as the sewage system. Her waterfront property consists of a shanty with a corrugated-iron roof; rats are not infrequent visitors. Despite the limited space, she has managed to squeeze in 2,638 discarded cans.</p>
        <p>At night Ms. Dos Santos, 19, heads out past the glittering high-rises, the sleeping bodies under bridges, the buildings that surge and subside with a giddy symmetry in this city that is now a 3,100-square-mile ocean of concrete. Her destination is the clubs whose environs offer lucrative garbage. Over 10 days, she collects more than 2,000 beverage cans; they will earn her $30 from a scrap dealer. ''It's not pleasant work,'' she says. ''But the alternative is crime or crack.''</p>
        <p>That alternative is increasingly compelling in Sao Paulo, the fastest-growing metropolis of the 20th century, vortex of the urban problems of the 21st. Drugs and murder are on the rise as a new millennium dawns. The number of murders in the greater Sao Paulo area reached 8,312 in 1998, compared with 628 in New York City.</p>
        <p>The violence has some of its roots in the same despair that pushes Ms. Dos Santos to her recycling. What the rich discard the growing number of poor gather. Such adaptability is not new; it is merely more desperate. Brazil's economic capital has always been ready to recycle itself -- from the quaint coffee-trading center of 1900 with a population of 240,000 to the megalopolis of 17 million inhabitants today.</p>
        <p>This explosion was part of the migration from rural areas throughout Latin America. About 33 percent of the continent's people lived in cities in 1940, and more than 72 percent do today. United Nations studies suggest that for the first time more than half of humanity will live in urban areas by the first years of the 21st century.</p>
        <p>They will not be residing on the Champs-Elysees. By 2025, about 4.4 billion of those people, or 80 percent of the world's urban population, are expected to live in the megacities of developing countries like Brazil and India. Just how livable those billions of existences will be is the question pressingly posed by Sao Paulo today.</p>
        <p>Insecurity of a new kind is rampant. It is whispered in the anxious expressions of executives and visible in the barbed-wire fences around some of their homes. What has caused this unease? The world today has been described as post-communist, postmodern, post-just-about-everything. But if we seem to know where we came from, we are by no means so sure of where we are. Radical transition is clear enough: but to what? The sustained impact over a full decade of the new global economy in a city like Sao Paulo seems to offer some troubling clues.</p>
        <p>An immigrant city like New York, Sao Paulo has always been a freewheeling place of outrageous contrasts. Wealth has co-existed with abject poverty. Still, today's electronic economy has placed Sao Paulo's social fabric under a new strain. ''For the first time, large swaths of society seem as disposable as paper napkins,'' said Leda Aschermann, a social worker. ''They have no further use.''</p>
        <p>The city, third in size behind Tokyo and Mexico City, is lurching into a new century marked by a combustible juxtaposition: a marginalized majority beside a networked minority with access to a hypermobile virtual universe generating great riches. The static majority is marooned in a physical world where the unemployment rate has more than doubled, to 19 percent, since 1990. This seems to be one paradigm of modern society, or at least the developing areas where most of humanity lives: a city splinters into several cities and its fabric, woven from shared experience, is cut. Vastly different amounts of money were always made, but at least the money was made on the same streets. No longer.</p>
        <p>An advertising campaign for imported Audis says the cars ''go as fast as e-mail.'' For millions of this city's inhabitants, this is a foreign language. The Internet and German cars are apparitions of another world. And it is in this gulf where danger resides. Put simply, the disconnected could overwhelm the connected, the suffering territorialists could crush the dot-com globalists. ''I see the possibility of a terrible mess here,'' said Norman Gall, a sociologist.</p>
        <p>Today, creative energy and destructive violence seem about evenly balanced. Sao Paulo's restlessness produced the city's maxim, Sao Paulo nao para -- Sao Paulo never stops. The Avenida Paulista, heart of the city, remains a street that concentrates more purposefulness than any other in Latin America. People here are not out for a stroll; they are going places. The two best hospitals in town are the Einstein and the Sirio-Libanes: Jews and Arabs do fine together here, as do the Japanese, Italians, Germans and others who created the city's thrilling kaleidoscope.</p>
        <p>Part of that thrill comes from the money and ideas generated here. Lagos, Nigeria, is full of disorder. So is seething Calcutta. But Sao Paulo, unlike these cities, is not merely huge. It is a global city, plugged into the transnational networks where power increasingly lies as the century begins.</p>
        <p>Any large corporation with an interest in Latin America has to be here, because the economy of Sao Paulo state is bigger than that of Argentina and because this city has the critical mass of bankers, lawyers, accountants and others capable of managing data moving across borders. Call them the heedless modern saboteurs of the nation-state. Their meetings are necessary for the information economy, which is one reason why the lure of big cities seems likely to persist despite the opportunities for decentralization offered by the Internet.</p>
        <p>Sao Paulo is not New York or London or Tokyo; but it is in the tier of about 30 world cities just below, places that will be at the nexus of the world's affairs into the 21st century. So it is natural that the city have what Saskia Sassen of the University of Chicago calls an urban glamour zone. Indeed, it has several. These zones are familiar because they are interchangeable across the world. The fragrant malls, the Armani emporiums, the world-class restaurants, the Range Rover dealerships. The temples of a globalized mankind that lunches on sushi and dines on cassoulet.</p>
        <p>Such palaces of consumption are packed with cell-phone-clutching Paulistas spending to the hectic rhythm of Internet time. This new elite is relatively large, certainly much larger than the coterie of coffee barons who ran the city a century ago. Perhaps 20 percent of the population has seldom, if ever, had it so good.</p>
        <p>''The global tide certainly raises all yachts,'' Ms. Sassen said. ''You now have an immodest middle class of enormous dynamic potential. But the tide also sinks a lot of ordinary boats. This brings serious problems of disintegration that threaten the whole notion of the city.''</p>
        <p>What is that notion? Ever since humanity invented agriculture and became sedentary, collections of people linked first in villages and finally in megalopolises have been centers of vitality. They have propelled civilization through scientific and economic advances. Sao Paulo, with its superb universities, has been conspicuous in this regard, galvanizing Brazilian development as the city moved from coffee to automaking to Internet industries. But today it seems in danger of sliding backward as the cohesion essential to any community collapses.</p>
        <p>Already it is clear that, to avoid contact with the widespread urban wreckage, the affluent are privatizing their needs. Private schools. Private hospitals. Private, guarded condominiums where their children can play -- ''protected, comfortable jails,'' as John Arnstein, a Brazilian banker, put it.</p>
        <p>Yet what Sao Paulo seems to need is not this retreat to fortress privacy but public investment on a huge scale. It needs an extended subway system to alleviate the perennially clogged traffic. It needs schools to get more than 3,000 vagrant children off the streets. And it needs street lighting and sewers for the spreading favelas.</p>
        <p>But Celso Pitta, the mayor of Sao Paulo, says the city is heavily in debt. Waste and fraud are rampant. Money is squandered on police forces whose activities are often duplicated and on over-invoiced public works.</p>
        <p>An advantage of the open global economic system is that such waste becomes untenable. Markets demand fiscal discipline. But markets are skeptical of intense public-sector investment, and international capital is so volatile that Brazil is obliged to keep interest rates at levels that multiply debts like Sao Paulo's. This drains investments from social needs.</p>
        <p>''The danger now is that the only equalizer in Sao Paulo will be the revolver,'' said Jorge Wilheim, an urban planner.</p>
        <p>THE man battling the spread of guns -- 19,898 were seized by the city's police in 1998 -- is Marcio Vinicio Petrelluzzi, the secretary of public security for Sao Paulo state. He has a vision of the Paulista apocalypse. The slums on the periphery, already housing upward of two million people, spread southward toward the dams that provide the city's water supply. The water is infected by open sewage. As population density increases and the soil grows more impermeable, the annual flooding of the Rio Tiete gets worse. Sick, waterlogged, tempted by the goods that globalization places before them, the urban poor rise up. ''Chaos takes over,'' Mr. Petrelluzzi says.</p>
        <p>It has not happened yet; it may never. Indeed, there are encouraging signs. The city has stopped growing so fast as industries leave and other parts of Brazil develop. Population is expected to increase to 20 million from 17 million by 2015. But Bombay's projected growth over the same period is to 26.2 million from 15.1 million; Lagos to 24.6 million from 10 million.</p>
        <p>A new movement of what Marco Antonio Ramos de Almeida of BankBoston calls ''entrepreneurial citizenship'' is growing. The private sector is realizing it has a stake in Sao Paulo's future and is putting money into urban improvements. New enterprises like Universo On Line, or UOL, are springing up. Started four years ago, it is already the biggest Internet company in Latin America, with 1,000 employees.</p>
        <p>But the UOL jobs do not keep pace with jobs lost in old industries. And their qualifications are different. In his shanty, Geraldo Agostino da Cruz, 17, says drug trafficking is his principal job prospect. ''The rich find it easy to make money,'' he says. ''Why is it so difficult for us?''</p>
        <p>His bruised eyes in a youthful face tell a story evident in the developing world's megacities: the new globalism has not yet demonstrated that the resources it accumulates can be distributed in a way that builds broad avenues of civility through the earth's spreading urban jungle.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: CITIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
