<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brooklyn Man Charged in Terror Plot Is Held Without Bond</title>
    <meta content="01TERR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seattle (Wash)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiser, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ghani, Abdel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ressam, Ahmed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DF1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brooklyn Man Charged in Terror Plot Is Held Without Bond</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN WEISER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiser, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abdel Ghani, Algerian man arrested in Brooklyn on charges of being part of terrorist bomb plot, is ordered held without bond in court proceeding that offers few new details about suspect or his activities; Ghani's lawyers seek dismissal of charges, contending that specific acts Ghani is accused of did not occur in Manhattan, where charges were filed; prosecutors contend case is properly charged given Ghani's flights into New York and phone calls in jurisdiction; Ghani is accused of being accomplice of Ahmed Ressam, Algerian arrested at Canadian border near Seattle as he tried to bring explosives and bomb components into United States; Ghani's name and phone number were found among Ressam's possessions; prosecutor claims Ghani was in US illegally (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Algerian man arrested in Brooklyn on charges of being part of a terrorist bomb plot was ordered held without bond yesterday in a court proceeding that otherwise offered few new details about the suspect or his activities.</p>
        <p>The defendant, Abdel Ghani, sat quietly in a gray turtleneck sweater as his lawyer sought unsuccessfully to have the charges dismissed, contending that the specific acts Mr. Ghani was accused of had not occurred in Manhattan, where the charges had been filed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Algerian man arrested in Brooklyn on charges of being part of a terrorist bomb plot was ordered held without bond yesterday in a court proceeding that otherwise offered few new details about the suspect or his activities.</p>
        <p>The defendant, Abdel Ghani, sat quietly in a gray turtleneck sweater as his lawyer sought unsuccessfully to have the charges dismissed, contending that the specific acts Mr. Ghani was accused of had not occurred in Manhattan, where the charges had been filed.</p>
        <p>The magistrate, Ronald L. Ellis of Federal District Court in Manhattan, agreed that the issue was a ''close issue,'' but sided with the government after a prosecutor said the case was properly charged given Mr. Ghani's flights into New York and phone calls in the jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ghani, 31, was arrested on Thursday and accused in a criminal complaint of being an accomplice of Ahmed Ressam, an Algerian who was arrested at the Canadian border near Seattle in mid-December as he tried to bring explosives and bomb components into the United States. Mr. Ressam is believed to be part of a gangster-terrorist group with a base in Montreal, antiterrorism investigators have said.</p>
        <p>In court yesterday, an assistant United States attorney, David N. Kelley, revealed that Mr. Ghani, an Algerian national, had been in the United States illegally. He said little else about Mr. Ghani, whose name and phone number in Brooklyn were found on a scrap of paper Mr. Ressam had when he was arrested, according to a criminal complaint filed Thursday.</p>
        <p>The authorities said in the complaint that they had tracked Mr. Ghani's activities. F.B.I. agents staked out his apartment building at 944 Newkirk Avenue in the Midwood section of Brooklyn, went through a trash bin where he had discarded several documents including a ripped up plane ticket for a flight from Seattle to New York, and ultimately established that he had been in Seattle, waiting to meet Mr. Ressam, between Dec. 11 and Dec. 16, according to the criminal complaint.</p>
        <p>The complaint charged that Mr. Ghani had knowledge of ''a terrorist network of Algerian nationals'' that also included Mr. Ressam, and that Mr. Ghani was also planning to travel with Mr. Ressam to Chicago to raise money for the group.</p>
        <p>After court yesterday, Mr. Ghani's lawyer, Roland Thau, of the federal defender's office, said his client would plead not guilty to the charges, including one that contends he supported and concealed Mr. Ressam's effort to carry out the bomb plot and another of credit card fraud. Mr. Thau refused further comment about Mr. Ghani's activities or background.</p>
        <p>The mystery about the defendant and continuing questions about any broader plot only underscored yesterday that his arrest may signal the beginning rather than the end of a long and far-reaching investigation into what the authorities described as a well-organized Algerian group with anti-American aims.</p>
        <p>The government, for example, has not said whether Mr. Ghani is a member of the violent terrorist organization in Algeria called the Armed Islamic Group. A Canadian woman arrested last month as she crossed the border into Vermont with another Algerian man has been described by the authorities as having ties to two members of the Armed Islamic Group.</p>
        <p>A United States intelligence official has said that the C.I.A.'s latest assessment is still that the Armed Islamic Group, as an organization, is not coordinating attacks against the United States, although members of the group may be involved in carrying out attacks on their own.</p>
        <p>An official has said that contingency plans to arrest Mr. Ghani had been in place for several days. That raised the possibility that the authorities timed Mr. Ghani's arrest to coincide with planning for the millennium celebration.</p>
        <p>The arrest came on a day when the Federal Bureau of Investigation questioned, and in some cases held, Algerian immigrants in several cities. Federal agents indicated privately that they had intended the sweep as a warning or deterrent to potential terrorists.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in Manhattan announcing Mr. Ghani's arrest, both the police commissioner, Howard Safir, and Lewis D. Schiliro, the assistant director of the F.B.I. in charge of the New York office, opened their remarks by stressing that New York would be safe for a festive New Year's Eve.</p>
        <p>They each also repeated that there was no evidence of specific credible threats to New York City or its environs, and Mr. Schiliro said that no explosives or explosive devices had been found in connection with the arrest and investigation of Mr. Ghani.</p>
        <p>In court, Mr. Thau challenged the evidence against Mr. Ghani, saying there was ''not an iota of factual assertion in the complaint showing that the defendant assisted Mr. Ressam.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thau said that the detailed criminal complaint, based on an affidavit filed by an F.B.I. agent, ''does not even assert that the defendant ever met Mr. Ressam or spoke with him or communicated with him in any fashion.''</p>
        <p>But the prosecutor, Mr. Kelley, disagreed, and added that Mr. Ghani had sought to conceal his role in the plot, traveling under an assumed name, and later destroying his airplane ticket.</p>
        <p>In Brooklyn yesterday, Newkirk Avenue residents said they had noticed what they believed to be undercover officers in the neighborhood for at least a week. Plainclothes officers sat in unmarked cars, they said, and a small plane even repeatedly circled overhead.</p>
        <p>Several of the residents interviewed said they knew the men apprehended -- the authorities had initially detained a total of four men -- and believed they were innocent. They said they feared that the arrests would only add to bias against Muslims.</p>
        <p>''They are giving the impression that all Muslims are involved in terrorism,'' said Tariq Mahood Khokhar as he walked down Newkirk Avenue late Thursday night from his mosque. He said one of the men taken into custody had worked at a corner convenience store and had never been involved in any wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>''This is a police state,'' Mr. Khokhar said. ''Why are they blaming Muslims?''</p>
        <p>A man who answered the door at the apartment where the arrest occurred said late Thursday night that he had no comment. The door to the apartment -- which still had a large hole where the lock had been ripped out -- had been propped shut.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
