<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Praying for a Century That Is Not the American One</title>
    <meta content="01MULL$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hassani, Gholam-Reza (Hojatolislam)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1DD1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1312" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Praying for a Century That Is Not the American One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John F. Burns</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>URMIA, Iran</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gholam-Reza Hassani, the most conservative voice of Islam in Iran's clerical hierarchy, predicts downfall of American power in 21st century; says core of problem in modern world, which is at its worst in US, is that spiritual development has receded as technological progress has advanced; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR some in the ancient world, where civilizations crumbled into dust 1,000 years before the birth of Jesus, the arrival of a new millennium doesn't captivate the imagination quite as it does elsewhere. Instead of seeing the last 2,000 years as a ladder for mankind's ascent, they view much of the last two millenniums, and especially the 20th century, as a chronicle of moral decay.</p>
        <p>This view finds a natural home among conservative followers of Islam. In the face of a growing challenge from movements that offer a more tolerant vision of Islam, hard-liners remain implacably opposed to accommodation with ''Western values'' in matters of morality, social customs and criminal justice. For the 21st century, some would turn back the clock to the eye-for-an-eye, do-as-the-prophet-said values of Islam's origins in the seventh century A.D.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR some in the ancient world, where civilizations crumbled into dust 1,000 years before the birth of Jesus, the arrival of a new millennium doesn't captivate the imagination quite as it does elsewhere. Instead of seeing the last 2,000 years as a ladder for mankind's ascent, they view much of the last two millenniums, and especially the 20th century, as a chronicle of moral decay.</p>
        <p>This view finds a natural home among conservative followers of Islam. In the face of a growing challenge from movements that offer a more tolerant vision of Islam, hard-liners remain implacably opposed to accommodation with ''Western values'' in matters of morality, social customs and criminal justice. For the 21st century, some would turn back the clock to the eye-for-an-eye, do-as-the-prophet-said values of Islam's origins in the seventh century A.D.</p>
        <p>Among those who hold such views in Iran, few are more fervent than Gholam-Reza Hassani, a high-ranking cleric who is wedded to the social and political precepts that have been imposed on Iranians since the Islamic revolution in 1979. Like many of Iran's mullahs, Mr. Hassani sees the 20th century -- ''the American century,'' as he refers to it, with heavy sarcasm -- as a tale of decadence as much as of technological advance.</p>
        <p>After years as a political prisoner under the shah, Mr. Hassani became an acolyte of Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, Iran's absolute ruler for 10 years until his death in 1989. In 1983, at the height of antileftist purges, Mr. Hassani led Islamic guards to the hiding place of his eldest son, Rashid, a 25-year-old Marxist, and assented eagerly as a firing squad executed him. It was an event, he says, that proved his loyalty to Islam.</p>
        <p>The execution tied the mullah, at least in his own mind, to the beginning of biblical time, when God challenged Abraham to sacrifice his son, Isaac. ''Abraham didn't sacrifice his son, but I did,'' Mr. Hassani said with a quick chuckle. ''Even today, I don't regret it.'' And what of the reaction of Rashid's mother, one of two living wives who have borne the cleric five sons and seven daughters? ''I really don't know,'' he said. ''If she has any thoughts about it, she has kept them to herself, and I haven't asked.''</p>
        <p>If this seems unbearably harsh in Western terms, it is at least consistent with the view of the world that the 72-year-old cleric put forth during a three-hour conversation at his villa in Urmia, where the signature artwork is a machine gun suspended above his desk. He spoke with deep hostility for the United States, a country he said he respected for its technology but despised for its materialist culture, its ''godlessness'' and its pervasive ''evil'' influence.</p>
        <p>In the 21st century, Mr. Hassani said, the United States will find the tide running against it. ''The Koran says all injustice will vanish from the earth,'' he said. ''And so it will be for America, because it is a country that has lost its soul. Its power will disappear, as the power of all oppressors has before it. Look at the Egyptian pharaohs. They were once as powerful as America is today, but where are they today?''</p>
        <p>Ask almost any Iranian who is the most conservative voice of Islam in the country, and they identify Mr. Hassani, the top cleric in this city on the ancient Silk Road to China that nestles in the hills of northwestern Iran.  Each Friday, the Muslim holy day, he thunders from his pulpit in the Masjid-e-Jame mosque against everything he views as threatening to Islam and its rule in Iran.</p>
        <p>But in a broader sense, Hojatolislam Hassani -- the title places him in the second rank of mullahs, below an ayatollah -- stands for something that extends beyond Iran and the Islamic world: a deep-rooted anxiety about the pace of change that causes many people, especially in poorer countries, to take refuge in the certainties of ancient beliefs, and in a prideful reassertion of national identity and culture. In this, there is often deep resentment toward richer nations, and a fear that the future they have charted is one in which poorer nations and peoples will be even less able to compete.</p>
        <p>Like many others who blame the United States for the world's ills, Mr. Hassani likes to emphasize his familiarity with American ingenuity. He owned a computer until recently, he said, but sold it because it ''needed upgrading.'' With pride, he noted that he uses a mobile telephone. In this, at least, he distanced himself from the Taliban, Afghanistan's Islamic rulers, who have set vigilantes prowling for television sets, video recorders, radios, even hair dryers, then summoned crowds to watch these ''satanic instruments'' being hanged from trees.</p>
        <p>Told of this, Mr. Hassani was incredulous. ''You mean they actually hang television sets?'' he said. ''That is wrong; they should not refuse to learn what is going on in the world, good or bad. That is pure stupidity.''</p>
        <p>The core of the problem in the modern world, in Mr. Hassani's view, is that spiritual development has receded as technological progress has advanced. ''Do you want to know why we shout 'Death to America!'?'' he said. ''It is because America has not heeded our prophet's teachings. It has not matched its advances in science and technology with growth in moral and spiritual terms. Of course, there are decent people in America, many of them, but there is no vice that is not among them.''</p>
        <p>The issue that seemed to obsess Mr. Hassani above all others was sex. ''Look at Clinton!'' he said, referring to the president's relationship with Monica Lewinsky. ''Even he has said he is not a clean man.'' Then he offered his remedy: the adoption of strict Islamic codes for adultery. For a wife who commits adultery and has no mitigating circumstances to plead -- like a husband who travels frequently, or is ''handicapped'' or a drunkard -- the proper punishment, he said, is stoning to death, a punishment still inflicted in rural parts of Iran.</p>
        <p>As his unconcern about his wife's grief over their son's execution suggested, women, in Mr. Hassani's world, cannot hope for equal rights with men. At no point in his discussion of sexual misdemeanors, for example, did he even mention that men are equally liable for punishment under Islamic adultery codes, nor that they face stoning, when it occurs, alongside the women judged with them -- the difference being that the women are usually buried to their shoulders before rocks are thrown, the men left standing, their full bodies exposed.</p>
        <p>B UT if the cleric's prescriptions for the next millennium had an unrelenting grimness about them, it took only the few minutes on the streets outside his home to be reminded that even in Iran, men like Mr. Hassani face an uphill battle. The rush of modernity is visible on every side in Urmia, with Internet cafes and travel agencies offering cheap excursion fares to the United States.</p>
        <p>Iran, which gave the world its first Islamic revolution of the modern era, has also engendered the most powerful democratic  movement in the Islamic world, led by men who have rejected ancient Islamic verities for the teachings of Locke, Jefferson and Rousseau. Judging by recent elections in which Iran's 65 million people have given that movement landslide victories, the tide at the dawn of the 21st century, in Iran at least, seems to be running strongly away from Mr. Hassani and toward the more open and tolerant future he abhors.</p>
        <p>VISIONS: TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
