<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Crowd Flocks to the Mall</title>
    <meta content="01WASH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DB1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Crowd Flocks to the Mall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STOUT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although it had seen many huge crowds over the years, for inaugurations, Fourth of July fireworks, protests and parades, never in memory had the Mall in the nation's capital drawn multitudes for New Year's. But on this mild winter night with a lovely sunset, hundreds of thousands of people here thronged to the Mall for a long-planned celebration on the last New Year's Eve of the 1900's.</p>
        <p>''It's a very friendly crowd,'' Sgt. Frank R. Onolfi of the United States Park Police said as afternoon turned to evening.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although it had seen many huge crowds over the years, for inaugurations, Fourth of July fireworks, protests and parades, never in memory had the Mall in the nation's capital drawn multitudes for New Year's. But on this mild winter night with a lovely sunset, hundreds of thousands of people here thronged to the Mall for a long-planned celebration on the last New Year's Eve of the 1900's.</p>
        <p>''It's a very friendly crowd,'' Sgt. Frank R. Onolfi of the United States Park Police said as afternoon turned to evening.</p>
        <p>But by shortly after 10 p.m., there were so many people trying to get close to the Lincoln Memorial, the focal point of the observances where President Clinton was about to speak, that sections of temporary fencing were pushed down along Constitution Avenue. Multitudes stormed through the gaps instead of being funneled through several security points, where the police had been checking for alcohol.</p>
        <p>Police officers saw that the throngs could not be repulsed without the risk of serious injury or disorder, so they let the people come through. Another line of fences stopped them close to the reflecting pool, and the police said order was soon restored. No serious injuries were reported.</p>
        <p>Early in the evening, it was clear that the crowd was befitting of a cosmopolitan city and a changing America. The celebration drew people of different languages and accents, from other countries, from all over the United States and from Washington itself. People who live in the District of Columbia tend to be blase about motorcades and potentates and ceremonies, but many Washingtonians thought tonight's event was something they could not miss.</p>
        <p>''We normally stay home on New Year's, but we had to see the millennium celebration,'' Thea Anderson said. She and her husband, Clarence, who have lived here for 27 years, were at first a little nervous about venturing out, given the talk of danger, however remote. But in the end they took the Metro downtown, and were glad they did.</p>
        <p>Patrick and Jane Wilson of Greenville, S.C., arrived this morning, early enough to get close to Mr. Clinton at an event before midday. Mrs. Wilson was delighted to get pictures of the president, and the couple were pleased with the crowd-control measures, which they found efficient without being oppressive.</p>
        <p>''Everything is so laid-back,'' Mrs. Wilson said. ''There's no pushing or shoving.''</p>
        <p>Many people at the Mall tonight wore party hats. One merchandise tent offered ''millennium celebration'' certificates. An entrepreneur hawked T-shirts labeled, ''I survived Y2K.'' The going rate was $5.</p>
        <p>For a relative few, the evening called for tuxedos and formal gowns -- proper attire for the White House Millennium Dinner, where the first family greeted guests before leaving for fireworks festivities on the Mall.</p>
        <p>Joggers threaded their way nonchalantly through the Mall celebrators. There was lots of room, the Mall being one of the jewels that make this a pedestrian-friendly city.</p>
        <p>For all the anticipation, some people were just not getting it. Connie Liang took her children -- one 18 months, the other 3 years. ''My children are too young to remember this,'' she said, ''but at least they will be able to say they were here.''</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
