<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Will Longer Lives Be Different Lives? And Better Ones?</title>
    <meta content="01SPAN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Millennium" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="VISIONS: BIOLOGY: A GENETIC FUTURE BOTH TANTALIZING AND DISTURBING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Longevity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belluck, Pam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1DC1030F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1412" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Will Longer Lives Be Different Lives? And Better Ones?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Pam Belluck</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belluck, Pam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pam Belluck article on prospects for extending life expectancy in the next century; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was an exciting day in the life of a 2-month-old -- or at least it was exciting for her mother.</p>
        <p>We were at the pediatrician's for my daughter Arielle's two-month checkup, and the doctor was going over developmental milestones. Is she smiling? (Especially in the morning.) Cooing? (Like crazy.) Holding her head up? (More each day.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was an exciting day in the life of a 2-month-old -- or at least it was exciting for her mother.</p>
        <p>We were at the pediatrician's for my daughter Arielle's two-month checkup, and the doctor was going over developmental milestones. Is she smiling? (Especially in the morning.) Cooing? (Like crazy.) Holding her head up? (More each day.)</p>
        <p>She's not likely to be rolling over yet, the doctor said. But after he left the room, Arielle rolled over right there on the examination table.</p>
        <p>I had an attack of new mother's hubris. Not only had Arielle demonstrated what I decided was precocious athletic ability, but her height measured 25 inches -- off the charts for a 2-month-old, the doctor said. Maybe I should give the Women's National Basketball Association a heads up.</p>
        <p>Then again, what's the rush? Science could make it possible for Arielle's generation to live 120, 150, even 200 years. Born on the cusp of the millennium, on 9-9-99, my daughter could not only live through the 21st century but also see the 22nd.</p>
        <p>Cuddling my wriggling, cooing baby, I wonder how this will affect her life and the world in which she will be living.</p>
        <p>What if people can take a pill or alter their genes so that they can look and feel 60 at age 110? Will my daughter be going to college and ''finding herself'' at 35? Having children in her 50's? Six entirely separate careers? Four husbands? A weekly racquetball game at 112? Think of the extraordinary opportunity to do more and see more.</p>
        <p>It's not so far-fetched, the experts say.</p>
        <p>Scientists have used genetic alterations to create worms and fruit flies that live twice as long as normal -- and do not deteriorate with old age. They have discovered gene mutations that extend the life span of mice. They have found that restricting food calories of rats allows them to live longer. And they are making progress toward medical advances that may successfully treat cancer, Alzheimer's and heart disease.</p>
        <p>All this is going to come together in the 21st century, said Daniel Perry, executive director of the Alliance for Aging Research. ''Your daughter has a very strong chance of living in three centuries,'' he said.</p>
        <p>I have realized how time races by with a baby. Seeing her grow and change each day is indescribably exciting. But it is also poignant because as she ages, it is as though some of her infinite possibilities are slipping away. As I play piano for her, talk to her in French and Chinese, take her for walks, there is a desire to make every day count for her. I wonder if that feeling would seem less intense if parents knew that their children had decades longer to live.</p>
        <p>There is a theory that life gains its value from knowing that we have a limited time on earth. What happens to our notion of what it means to be human, which is so bound up with the idea that we grow steadily older and frailer and then die? Many scientists think the genetic and medical steps needed to extend life will essentially work by halting much of the deterioration that comes with aging; if so, people will be healthy for most of their old age.</p>
        <p>''It could separate us from our history,'' said Dr. Gregory Stock, director of the program on medicine, technology and society at the medical school of the University of California at Los Angeles, who organized a conference on increased life span last March. ''There's all this thinking in religion and other disciplines, there's been a discussion and a learning process of what human life is about, how we deal with mortality. That all changes when you talk about extending human life span.''</p>
        <p>The extra years could alter every phase of life, from childhood to grandparenthood and beyond. Dr. Thomas Murray, president of the Hastings Center, a bioethics research institute, wonders about family relationships. ''Will marriages survive 80 years?'' he asked. ''Will we invent other forms of relationships to supplement marriage? Forms of friendship?''</p>
        <p>More people would probably end up having several families, said Dr. Richard Suzman, associate director for behavioral and social research at the National Institute on Aging. ''There would be a higher proportion of stepchildren, who historically have had somewhat weaker family bonds,'' Dr. Suzman said, ''and they would have multiple obligations and maybe more geographic distance from parts of their family.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Murray noted that in my grandparents' time people often spent nearly a third of their lives living with their parents. Today, we might live less than a quarter of our lives with our parents. And my daughter might spend only a sixth of her life with my husband and me. Will her generation be more distant from their parents? Or will it be closer, because we have a good chance of being healthy long enough to see our children become old themselves?</p>
        <p>We just held a naming ceremony for Arielle, a Jewish ritual in which we celebrate the people after whom she is named --  my mother's parents, who died in 1982 and 1983. We culled stories about my grandparents from memories, and from a meandering audio tape of my grandmother and a scratchy videotape of my grandfather. There was, for example, the tale about how they met at a dance in the 1920's, and how, to induce him to call her, she dropped her handkerchief in his car. Imagine if they could be here to tell their story themselves.</p>
        <p>What kind of career advice should I give my daughter? Will everyone be expected to have five master's degrees? Will young people find the choicest jobs taken by 80-year-olds? Or will my daughter's generation make radical career shifts and take long sabbaticals -- say, a decade off to hike the Himalayas?</p>
        <p>And what will society be like?</p>
        <p>Dr. Stock said that early methods of extending life would be expensive, meaning some could not afford to live longer. That could engender an unprecedented kind of class warfare -- and even starker separation between richer and poorer nations.</p>
        <p>''Our mortality is basically an anchor that keeps us all moored in the same harbor,'' he said. ''If you start differentially allowing people, through expensive treatments, various ways to cheat death, that inevitably causes an enormous question. If only the wealthy can afford it, how do you deal with the distribution of it? I think there would be enormous pressure in liberal democracies to route public funds to pay for it.''</p>
        <p>There might be other kinds of societal divisions. How will public money -- Social Security and Medicare, for example -- be spent, and will that spending breed resentment among the young? The pattern of inheritance will be disrupted, Dr. Suzman said, and people may not have adequate savings for a longer life.</p>
        <p>Some foresee culture clashes, saying that the many elderly people might want to preserve the world as they know it. ''An increasingly bitter conflict could arise,'' Dr. Stock said. ''Often changes don't really occur until the previous generation dies out, so you can see all sorts of deep divisions that normally work themselves out over time not working themselves out.''</p>
        <p>There is no telling what else could happen. After all, in the 20th century, life expectancy increased 30 years with improvements in public health and sanitation. That probably helped galvanize such social groundswells as the women's movement because women lived so much longer after rearing children.</p>
        <p>If people, by seeing it firsthand, had a better sense of history, would there be fewer wars? And think of the energy and creativity that could come from a world in which people had more vital years to contribute.</p>
        <p>''You'll be able to take more chances,'' Dr. Stock said.</p>
        <p>He then left me with a challenge of sorts: ''Growing up with all those things, your daughter will deal with it just fine. The real question is, how will you deal with it?''</p>
        <p>VISIONS: BIOLOGY: A GENETIC FUTURE BOTH TANTALIZING AND DISTURBING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
