<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; Why Die?</title>
    <meta content="01SAFI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Longevity</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0DA1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; Why Die?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire column on the possibility of greatly extending human life in next century (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of all the instincts in animals, the strongest is the will to survive. In the human animal, that inborn defense is sometimes overcome by the maternal instinct, by love of country or comrades in battle, or by an illness like depression. But in most of us, nothing makes the weak strong or the fearful brave as much as our bodies' innate drive to stay alive.</p>
        <p>Because of that survival instinct, in the millennium to come a curious question will occupy the minds of our descendants. It seems almost nutty to ask it today, but tomorrow's question will be: Why die?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Of all the instincts in animals, the strongest is the will to survive. In the human animal, that inborn defense is sometimes overcome by the maternal instinct, by love of country or comrades in battle, or by an illness like depression. But in most of us, nothing makes the weak strong or the fearful brave as much as our bodies' innate drive to stay alive.</p>
        <p>Because of that survival instinct, in the millennium to come a curious question will occupy the minds of our descendants. It seems almost nutty to ask it today, but tomorrow's question will be: Why die?</p>
        <p>One sober-sided school of scientific thought holds that Homo sapiens sapiens, our species now celebrating its 100th millennium, is born with an inner clock. That genetic clock directs our cells not only to grow but to age and decay. It is set to run no more than 120 or 130 years.</p>
        <p>Few of us live to that full span because of illness, accident or war. But the clear trend is toward filling up more of that span: in the past century alone, life expectancy in the U.S. has gone from 46 to 76. Now add the ingredient of diseaselessness: conservative scientists say that in the coming century cures will be found for the leading killers -- heart disease, cancer and stroke -- and genetically influenced diseases will be engineered out of existence.</p>
        <p>With the major killers gone, and with organ transplants or prosthetic innards replacing worn-out human parts, more people will be pushing up against that presumed clock. Centenarians will be common.</p>
        <p>Now take the leap: What if the hypothesis of the clock-watchers is mistaken? As the lengthening of life in the 20th century showed us, a life span of ''three score and ten'' is not the most reliable prediction in the Bible. Where is it written in our genes that a signal will direct our bodies to close up shop at 120?</p>
        <p>I put that question to the great Johns Hopkins neuroscientist Dr. Guy McKhann. He and his wife, Prof. Marilyn Albert, the new head of the Harvard Mahoney Neuroscience Institute in Boston, are completing a book about the untapped potential of the aging brain. (They are ''experts on aging''; never call them ''aging experts.'')</p>
        <p>''Maybe you're asking the wrong question,'' says Dr. McKhann. ''Assume there is some finite span of time set by an internal clock, as studies of other species suggest. Then the real question becomes: Can we reset the clock?''</p>
        <p>That's what all the recent excitement among scientists over stem cells is about. If the next-to-last year of the second millennium is remembered for anything, it will be for the discovery of the human body's ability to regenerate itself.</p>
        <p>These stem cells -- non-differentiated globs of cells that divide randomly and blossom into nerve or muscle or brain cells -- are being shown to be a source of replacement of dead or dying cells. We never thought that to be possible. These wild-card cells may be found not just in embryos but in adult bodies, and could, in effect, reset the clock -- time and again, doubling and redoubling the life span. Ponce de Leon's fountain of youth may be within our reach.</p>
        <p>''Some organs, like the liver, will be relatively easy to regenerate,'' says Dr. McKhann. ''The brain is harder, but we should be able to replace parts of the brain afflicted with diseases, as well as to improve short- and long-term memory in the renewing brain.''</p>
        <p>At a millennium's turn, we can think even bigger. If the instinct for survival remains paramount, most of the geezers of the next few hundred years will want to stick around.  At first, that seems troubling; as the Ira Gershwin lyric observed: ''Methusaleh lived 900 years. / But who calls dat livin' / when no gal'll give in / to no man what's 900 years?''</p>
        <p>Answer: For future people, doddering will no longer be an option.  Throw out those second-millennium images of codgers in wheelchairs staring at the wall. The Gramps of a century or so from now will be swiveling on the dance floor with his replacement hips and fresh lungs and newly enlivened brain and pocketful of potency pills.</p>
        <p>Granted, as mortality recedes and babies keep coming, it could get a little crowded here. After the population of earth reaches 30 billion, what then? Solution: Start shipping the spry old folks out on a mission to colonize the solar system. ''Happy 200th birthday, Grandma -- here's your ticket to Mars, and say hello to your parents out there.''</p>
        <p>This calendar-induced speculation is not directed at those of us today who will probably keel over even before our genetic clocks run out. But for those readers of a distant tomorrow who will flip back through the millennia to access The New York Times Archive, one will say, ''You know, this fellow was incredibly prescient.'' And another will respond, with all human skepticism,  ''Sure, he was right -- but do you really want to live forever?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
