<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Year Of Fluff, Smut and Letting Go</title>
    <meta content="01NOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nineteen Hundred Ninety-Nine</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E2DD1238F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Year Of Fluff, Smut and Letting Go</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers Critic's Notebook recap of 1999 music scene, featuring fluff, smut and letting off steam on ethnic, gender and other issues of new generation; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ask any critic to comment upon this final year of the Century of American Music, and you're likely to hear a heavy sigh. The year 1999 gave us fluff and smut, the inflatable sweethearts of the teenage market and the foul-mouthed bullies of hip-hop and rock. Releases from aspiring legends like Nine Inch Nails, R. Kelly and Mary J. Blige failed to make the anticipated cultural impact, while previously dismissed artists like Limp Bizkit and Kid Rock rose to rule the Zeitgeist. People actually looked to Cher, rising again with her smash ''Believe,'' as a beacon of artistic integrity.</p>
        <p>Step outside the bubble of critical debate, though, and this year's pop sounds much more exciting. It was a great year for arrogant fans using music to air their opinions and elaborate upon their daydreams.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ask any critic to comment upon this final year of the Century of American Music, and you're likely to hear a heavy sigh. The year 1999 gave us fluff and smut, the inflatable sweethearts of the teenage market and the foul-mouthed bullies of hip-hop and rock. Releases from aspiring legends like Nine Inch Nails, R. Kelly and Mary J. Blige failed to make the anticipated cultural impact, while previously dismissed artists like Limp Bizkit and Kid Rock rose to rule the Zeitgeist. People actually looked to Cher, rising again with her smash ''Believe,'' as a beacon of artistic integrity.</p>
        <p>Step outside the bubble of critical debate, though, and this year's pop sounds much more exciting. It was a great year for arrogant fans using music to air their opinions and elaborate upon their daydreams.</p>
        <p>The year's hits expressed ethnic pride, encapsulated gender debates, and revealed some crucial attributes of a new generation. Only a few songs would prompt listeners to pause for reflection; their hearty jokes and bold declarations defeated subtlety. But for the crowds mightily singing along, the soundtrack to 1999 offered inspiration and release.</p>
        <p>Bratty boys and sassy girls faced off across the genres. TLC's ''No Scrubs,'' the spring's ubiquitous hit, refreshed the theme of the no-good man and became the favored chorus for finger-snapping groups of girlfriends nationwide. It inspired an answer song, ''No Pigeons,'' by Sporty Thieves and set the stage for similar pronouncements from Destiny's Child, Whitney Houston and Mariah Carey.</p>
        <p>In fact, ''. . . Baby Hit Me One More Time,'' which had parents worrying about the masochistic messages the high school heroine Britney Spears might be proffering, is really yet another song about romantic confrontation, and Ms. Spears's steely gaze was as suggestive an aspect of her video as her schoolgirl outfit.</p>
        <p>Male artists presented their own boot-camp chants for the battle of the sexes. Limp Bizkit's crassly sexist songs were the most likely to make it onto a World Federation Wrestling soundtrack, but they were hardly alone. The modern rock bands Lit and Blink 182 took callow whining to new heights with ''My Own Worst Enemy'' and ''What's My Age Again?'' LFO took a laid-back approach to the same cocky attitude in ''Summer Girls.''</p>
        <p>These songs were the antidotes to the craven entreaties of teenage idols like the Backstreet Boys, whose hyper-romanticism set impossibly high standards for average Romeos. They fed a mood of frustration that hit its nadir at Woodstock, where the old, shameful connection between rock's transgressiveness and misogyny resurfaced via sexual assaults.</p>
        <p>It was a horrifying moment, but hardly inexplicable given pop's rude mood. Musical expressions of racial identity were often as blatant, although not as hateful, as those about sex. The much touted ''Latin pop explosion,'' for example, was driven by Ricky Martin's ''Livin' la Vida Loca,'' a novelty song based on the most obvious stereotype: a mocha-skinned temptress who would have worn fruit on her head in another era. (''Smooth,'' the comeback hit for Carlos Santana, relied on similar images of Latin heat and coolness.) But because Mr. Martin delivered it with a self-aware grin, the cliche charmed instead of offended.</p>
        <p>The year's best-selling rock album also relied on a racial lampoon, which happened to expose a generational reality. With little fanfare, the  Offspring's late 1998 release, ''Americana,'' outsold both Limp Bizkit and Kid Rock, mostly because of a song that satirized what those groups stood for. ''Pretty Fly (for a White Guy)'' leveled scorn at a suburban would-be gangster, giving many white hip-hop fans a humorous way to face their dubious ghetto fantasies.</p>
        <p>The rapper Eminem, a protege of the venerated hip-hop producer Dr. Dre, threw the joke back with his single, ''My Name Is,'' which presented race-crossing as a trickster's game instead of a dangerous conquest.</p>
        <p>Amid these exaggerated expressions of pride and anxiety were pop moments that simply vented collective steam. Hip-hop is always fertile ground for creative babbling, and this year it turned the radio into a veritable playpen. Choruses of ''Holla, holla'' and ''Ay-yi-yi-yi . . . who dat?'' arose wherever hip-hop fans gathered to dance, echoing hits by Ja Rule and JT Money with Sole. Most successful was Jay-Z, who had millions shouting out his nickname with ''Jigga'' and whooping like owls along with the cleaned-up chorus of ''Can I Get a . . . !'' Modern rockers rode the nursery-rhyme mood with sing-alongs like ''Steal My Sunshine'' by Len and ''All Star'' by Smashmouth.</p>
        <p>There were exceptions to the year's ridiculously extroverted mood, even at the top of the charts. Marc Anthony dignified the fascination with all things Latin with the elegantly lustful ''I Need to Know.'' Brandy and Monica both encouraged teenage girls to stop screaming and start thinking with their modest, pensive ballads.</p>
        <p>TLC followed ''No Scrubs'' with ''Unpretty,'' a vision of the beauty myth that's remarkably complex, musically and lyrically. A few steps away from the hit parade, artists like Moby, Mos Def, Kelly Willis and Magnetic Fields made intricate music that rewarded careful listening.</p>
        <p>Yet as the nation's party people usher in a new era this weekend, they'll probably be listening to big, silly songs that reflect the year's rowdy mood.</p>
        <p>It all comes back to Cher: whether people believed in their machismo or feminine wiles, their cultural heritage or racial loyalties or simply the life after love that the bewigged diva touted in her high-energy anthem, they wanted to make known their most accessible emotions. And pop, more than ever the truly public art form, gave everyone the means to get good and loud.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
