<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Gift of Food, and Help for Depression and AIDS</title>
    <meta content="01NEED$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE NEEDIEST CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donovan, Aaron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DE1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Gift of Food, and Help for Depression and AIDS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AARON DONOVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Donovan, Aaron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Woman with AIDS and mental problems is given money to feed herself and her young son until their food stamps are reinstated; help comes from Momentum AIDS Project, beneficiary of Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, one of seven local charities supported by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most nights, P. J. Sanchez, 9, comes into his mother's bedroom while she is sleeping and feels her hand and forehead, checking to make sure she is still alive.</p>
        <p>His mother, Modesta Verdejo, 43, has AIDS and bipolar depression. She has tried to kill herself, as she put it, ''more times than I can count.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most nights, P. J. Sanchez, 9, comes into his mother's bedroom while she is sleeping and feels her hand and forehead, checking to make sure she is still alive.</p>
        <p>His mother, Modesta Verdejo, 43, has AIDS and bipolar depression. She has tried to kill herself, as she put it, ''more times than I can count.''</p>
        <p>She is too distraught to work full time, and to make matters worse, she had to file a complaint against a former husband because he was harassing her, said Ms. Verdejo and her social worker, Kevin Ranftle. A restraining order was granted.</p>
        <p>Last winter, she informed the government that she wanted to receive food stamps only for her and her son. But because of a bureaucratic error, the authorities accidentally cut off the $155 a month she had been entitled to.</p>
        <p>''First it was something about the address, then it was about something else and then something else,'' Ms. Verdejo said. ''They would transfer my call, and then the person who I had to speak with wasn't in.''</p>
        <p>She became obsessively worried about how she would put food on the table for herself and P. J. She worried about it so much that by the third month without food stamps, she had a nervous breakdown and tried to take her own life. A doctor who treated her after a suicide attempt told her it was a miracle that she was still alive, and she was put in a hospital for 28 days. ''They were trying to keep me from obsessing,'' she said. ''I have a tendency of obsessing when I have problems: 'How am I going to get out of this, how am I going to get out of this.' ''</p>
        <p>In the hospital, she was referred to a social worker, Mr. Ranftle, who works at the Momentum AIDS Project, which offers counseling and support services for people living with AIDS. The project is a beneficiary of the Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, one of the seven local charities supported by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ranftle provided her with counseling that helped her put things in perspective, helped her get the restraining order, and using $116.25 from the Neediest Cases Fund, provided her and her son with enough money to eat until her food stamps were reinstated.</p>
        <p>''It's not that much money,'' Mr. Ranftle said in a telephone interview. ''All she needed was a little leg up on life. She took $116, which most people would eat up in a week, and knowing that she had three weeks to go, really put it to good use.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Verdejo was grateful for the help. ''He was a real help, and he did it quick,'' she said. ''He was able to put my mind at ease for a month.''</p>
        <p>When she left the hospital, she returned to her son and they went food shopping, buying pork chops, steak, chicken, eggs, juice, milk and bacon, among other things, she said.</p>
        <p>In 1994, when Ms. Verdejo found out she had AIDS, she was so shocked she asked for the test to be done again. By now, she has come to grips with the disease, and is able to counsel others who have it.</p>
        <p>Ms. Verdejo works part time as a counselor and advocate for fellow AIDS victims at a support program in Harlem so she can be there to support others as Mr. Ranftle was there to support her. She said that while she enjoys the job, sometimes seeing the death of people she has worked with can send her into a depression.</p>
        <p>She is on medication to stabilize her mood swings, but she said that, too, had drawbacks.</p>
        <p>''He says, 'We really have to numb you up for a while,' '' Ms. Verdejo said of her doctor. ''I have no energy and my thoughts are all slow. I don't want to live like that.''</p>
        <p>Though it reminds her of her own mortality, her job as an advocate and counselor provides Ms. Verdejo with inspiration and a sense of accomplishment.</p>
        <p>She puts her knowledge of the welfare bureaucracy to work, helping to make sure that others do not lose their food stamp benefits. ''I'll push their buttons, and by the end of the day, she'll have her food stamps,'' she said. ''I've helped people, I really have.''</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to P.O. Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087, or any of these  organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK  Church Street Station, P.O. Box 4100, New York, N.Y. 10261-4100</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Donations may be made with a credit card online, courtesy of the Qpass digital commerce service, at www.nytimes.com/neediest. Online donors receive a free trial subscription to the crossword puzzle of The New York Times on the Web.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on Federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded $3,428,006.94  Recorded Thursday $164,651.29</p>
        <p>Total $3,592,658.23</p>
        <p>THE NEEDIEST CASES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
