<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yeltsin Leaves Russians Glad or Uninterested</title>
    <meta content="Y01MOS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YELTSIN RESIGNS: IN MOSCOW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smale, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3DC1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yeltsin Leaves Russians Glad or Uninterested</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON SMALE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smale, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many Moscovites are happy or seem not to care that Pres Boris N Yeltsin is resigning after eight years of topsy-turvy economics and countless maneuvers that made little difference to their daily lives; are not prepared to commit themselves to Vladimir V Putin, his handpicked successor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Boris N. Yeltsin really meant it about being forgiven for his mistakes when he made the stunning announcement of his resignation today, as far as many people on the streets of Moscow were concerned, he needn't have bothered.</p>
        <p>After decades of secretive and brutal Communist rule, eight years of topsy-turvy economics under Mr. Yeltsin and countless maneuvers that made little difference to their daily grind, many Muscovites seemed simply glad to see an aging, obviously unwell leader leave the scene -- or just did not care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Boris N. Yeltsin really meant it about being forgiven for his mistakes when he made the stunning announcement of his resignation today, as far as many people on the streets of Moscow were concerned, he needn't have bothered.</p>
        <p>After decades of secretive and brutal Communist rule, eight years of topsy-turvy economics under Mr. Yeltsin and countless maneuvers that made little difference to their daily grind, many Muscovites seemed simply glad to see an aging, obviously unwell leader leave the scene -- or just did not care.</p>
        <p>''Boris Nikolayevich can't spoil our mood today,'' said Mikhail, 39, a mathematician who refused to give his last name as he joked, drank beer with friends at an outdoor stand and savored the gentle snow on New Year's Eve, traditionally Russia's most thoroughly celebrated holiday. Without Mr. Yeltsin, Mikhail said, ''things definitely won't get worse.''</p>
        <p>''We've needed this for a long time,'' Valentina V. Paranina, 62, a vendor, said. ''What was he doing already? Nothing. He was old and sick and did nothing.''</p>
        <p>For 46 years, Mrs. Paranina has worked in what used to be GUM, the glum state department store on Red Square whose often empty shelves and drab assortment of wares symbolized the maudlin monotony of Communism in their contrast with the Czarist-era splendor of its building and location.</p>
        <p>Today, the GUM arcades are light, bright and packed with Russian and Western wares at prices beyond the reach of many Russians. Mrs. Paranina watched stoically as customers who were buying last-minute New Year's gifts cheerfully plonked down ruble sums that exceeded her monthly pension of 575 rubles, or $51, to buy the lacquer boxes and Russian dolls that she sells.</p>
        <p>''Yes, I came here as a young girl, and I will leave as a babushka,'' said Mrs. Paranina, who added that she worked because she had to supplement her pension. ''Of course, the difference between when I came and now is heaven and earth. After all these ups and downs, we really don't know what will be good or bad anymore. We hope for the better. We're sick of all these bolts from the blue. We want stability and a good leader.''</p>
        <p>Asked whether she saw that leader in Vladimir V. Putin, Mr. Yeltsin's handpicked successor, who rose from relative obscurity to become prime minister in August and is now president until new elections in March, Mrs. Paranina said: ''We don't know him. So far, he's done nothing bad. But it could well be that as a leader he won't know what to do.''</p>
        <p>In the gleaming DKNY store near the long-shuttered Central Market, there was far more palpable lack of interest in Mr. Putin and Mr. Yeltsin's fates, as well as that of Russia. Young Russians, those who have no real memory of Communism and are often consumed with enjoying the fruits of capitalism, wandered in and out, buying gifts or fingering a clothing trophy that they could not afford.</p>
        <p>''I don't care, really,'' said a 23-year-old vendor who gave his name only as Aleksei. ''The only real thing is that the dollar will go up. And that's all I think.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's popularity ratings have shot up in the last two months, as Russian soldiers have prosecuted what the military and much of the media have portrayed as a successful war against rebels in Chechnya. The party that he supported in parliamentary elections 12 days ago has emerged as the most likely commander of a majority in parliament's lower house.  Yet today, even those who applauded the sheer political skill of Mr. Yeltsin's move to make an all-powerful queen of his erstwhile pawn were not prepared to commit themselves to Mr. Putin, although almost everyone seemed to agree that he would be the next president.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Yeltsin, the resignation and how he announced it on television, ''is an absolutely wonderful move,'' Yelena Rubinchik, 55, a retired engineer, said.</p>
        <p>''I think it was planned long ago,'' Ms. Rubinchik said. ''It's politically well thought through. It's done so it seems like Yeltsin's own initiative, not made under any pressure. I liked his speech, apologizing. It made him seem sympathetic, and politically he's managed to make it seem a change, without change.''</p>
        <p>By the time of the presidential elections, ''everybody will be occupied with other problems, and Yeltsin's family will be safe,'' she predicted, alluding to a widespread belief that Mr. Yeltsin's family and associates have used his spell in the Kremlin to enrich themselves in ways that probably broke laws and could be prosecuted by a successor.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rubinchik was one of the few Russians who pondered Mr. Yeltsin's legacy, saying: ''His historical value will be understood in time. In my view, he made two big mistakes, the war in Chechnya and not banning the Communist Party when he could have. But he was a reformer. It's very Russian not to appreciate the person who brings change until long afterward.''</p>
        <p>Aleksandr Sharandak definitely had other things on his mind besides politics. He was, he said, among the 40 percent of Russians who did not vote in the parliamentary elections. ''For me,'' Mr. Sharandak, 33, said, ''time is literally money. If I hadn't worked that day, I really wouldn't even be able to put the bread on the table'' for his wife and two children.</p>
        <p>He makes his living driving around Moscow in a car whose dashboard bears the sign, ''I'm looking for work.'' He declined to say how much he earns or how else he might be able to make a living.</p>
        <p>''I'm very far from politics,'' he said. ''To vote, you have to know something. I know more about Bill Clinton or Ronald Reagan than I do about that Putin. Liberal? Democrat? People throw these terms around, but they don't know what they mean. They gave the people here freedom, but not knowledge. It's like putting a gun in the hands of a child.''</p>
        <p>YELTSIN RESIGNS: IN MOSCOW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
