<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smells Like Teen Spirit, or Whatever</title>
    <meta content="01INAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">McNeil, Lonnie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DeSisto, A Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Inappropriate (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0DD1238F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smells Like Teen Spirit, or Whatever</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gates, Anita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anita Gates reviews play Inappropriate by A Michael DeSisto and Lonnie McNeil; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Inappropriate'' is not ''Rent.'' A theatergoer might be forgiven for thinking it is, since the show, a rock musical, stars an ensemble of young actors wearing headset microphones, attitude and the combination of layers, mismatches, glitter and sportswear that make up homeless-person chic. Averie Boyer, who is excellent in his understated way as one of the central performers (there are no character names), even looks something like Anthony Rapp, who played Mark in ''Rent's'' original Broadway and Off Broadway cast.</p>
        <p>But ''Inappropriate'' is something else. Imagine that a group of troubled teenagers -- who have been sent away to a special boarding school, presumably to straighten them out -- put on a show. And that parts of it turn out to be so good that the show ends up on a New York stage. That's the history of ''Inappropriate,'' performed by the theater company of the DeSisto School in Stockbridge, Mass.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Inappropriate'' is not ''Rent.'' A theatergoer might be forgiven for thinking it is, since the show, a rock musical, stars an ensemble of young actors wearing headset microphones, attitude and the combination of layers, mismatches, glitter and sportswear that make up homeless-person chic. Averie Boyer, who is excellent in his understated way as one of the central performers (there are no character names), even looks something like Anthony Rapp, who played Mark in ''Rent's'' original Broadway and Off Broadway cast.</p>
        <p>But ''Inappropriate'' is something else. Imagine that a group of troubled teenagers -- who have been sent away to a special boarding school, presumably to straighten them out -- put on a show. And that parts of it turn out to be so good that the show ends up on a New York stage. That's the history of ''Inappropriate,'' performed by the theater company of the DeSisto School in Stockbridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>Of course the teenagers didn't create the show. A. Michael DeSisto and Lonnie McNeil (the company's director, who died this year) wrote the book. Michael Sottile wrote the music and lyrics. To call the results uneven would be a serious understatement. There are moments when this show really could be compared to the brilliant use of anger, hurt and exuberance in ''Rent'' and ''Hair.'' At other times, the show seems to have been written and staged by a self-confident high school student.</p>
        <p>But that's understandable, because ''Inappropriate'' is at least partly based on the journals of teenagers, DeSisto School alumni. And it shows, for good and bad. So you have Adam Schiffman saying that drug highs don't last long with the words ''but the glory is short and gives way to emptiness.'' And Josh Geyer relating people's reactions to his mother having dressed him up like a girl: ''After that, they looked at me like I was having feelings of inadequacy.'' The show begins with an actor in the fetal position talking about life in the womb and ends with the declarations ''I am the future'' and ''This is ecstasy.''</p>
        <p>So the show can be alternately pretentious and inarticulate. But the fact that ''Inappropriate'' was born from the pain and yearnings of young people also means that it does an excellent job of conveying the primal emotional themes of adolescence, particularly relationships with parents. That includes dealing with a parent who wants to live through his or her child (''It was his dream, not mine''), confronting one who has betrayed a child (''Weren't you supposed to be the one who rescued me from monsters?''), coping with divorce or just having to listen to what seem like constant harangues (one number includes a refrain in which mother figures repeat ''Try a little harder'' again and again).</p>
        <p>The song ''Dear Dad,'' performed by the four female members of the ensemble, is an angry response to sexual abuse. And the song about drug use is titled ''Feels Good,'' making a point about marijuana, Ecstasy, Special K and other substances that older observers often forget to put into the equation.</p>
        <p>More important, though, the show has flashes of brilliance. Parts of the number ''I Wonder,'' sung by Mr. Boyer and Liz Irwin, are positively transporting. So are parts of ''Found: The Discovery'' in which the ensemble sings, ''Love is always closer than you imagine it to be.''</p>
        <p>It's hard to know whom to blame for the busy, sometimes silly choreography. Mr. McNeil did the original work, but this production is choreographed by Ray Leeper. At one point Mr. Geyer is required to slink and slither in ways that make Alan Cumming's dance work in ''Cabaret'' look almost prim. Yet rather than coming across as sexy, the number -- despite Mr. Geyer's obvious talent -- just feels embarrassing.</p>
        <p>This show deserves a chance to go on developing and carrying its ''been there, done that, wish I hadn't'' message to the ensemble's peers. The entire cast has real energy, conviction and ability. Mia Benenate, the newest member of the ensemble, isn't given a lot to do, but when she has a chance she shines, with an intense stage presence and authenticity.</p>
        <p>''Inappropriate,'' directed by Mr. Leeper and Mr. Sottile, continues at the Theater Row Theater through Jan. 30.</p>
        <p>INAPPROPRIATE  By A. Michael DeSisto and Lonnie McNeil; directed by Ray Leeper and Michael Sottile; music and lyrics by Mr. Sottile; choreographed by Mr. Leeper; original choreography and direction by Mr. McNeil; sets by Shane Ballard; sound by David A. Arnold; lighting by S. Ryan Schmidt; dramaturg, Deborah Klezmer; production manager, Karma Productions; general management, Paul Morer; production stage manager, Richard Costabile. Presented by Mr. DeSisto and Butterfly Productions. At the Theater Row Theater, 424 West 42nd Street, Clinton.</p>
        <p>WITH: Mia Benenate, Averie Boyer, Josh Geyer, Liz Irwin, Jamie Ourisman, Diane Schwartz, Sarah Seckinger and Adam Schiffman.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
