<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Once Glorious City, Overlooked by Time</title>
    <meta content="Y01TIM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDA1338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Once Glorious City, Overlooked by Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Timbuktu 2000! Timbuktu 2000!'' cried 3-year-old Aboubacari Sidiki, as he dangled from the bumper of a truck parked on a sand-filled street here.</p>
        <p>The words meant nothing to him. The boy was simply parroting the slogan that city promoters had been using to draw in Westerners to mark the end of an era at the end of the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Timbuktu 2000! Timbuktu 2000!'' cried 3-year-old Aboubacari Sidiki, as he dangled from the bumper of a truck parked on a sand-filled street here.</p>
        <p>The words meant nothing to him. The boy was simply parroting the slogan that city promoters had been using to draw in Westerners to mark the end of an era at the end of the world.</p>
        <p>''Timbuktu, the City of Mystery,'' went the campaign. But the greater mystery to Aboubacari and to most grown-up residents of this city was this: What was the big deal with the year 2000 and why were all these foreigners -- known locally as toubab -- coming to celebrate it here?</p>
        <p>''I don't know anything about the year 2000,'' said Niele Maiga, a woman in her 50's, who like most Muslims here found little significance in the new year. ''It's this year that we first heard about the year 2000. On the radio, they told us women that we should keep the front of our houses and the streets clean because the toubab were coming for the year 2000. Tonight, we're going to sing in Songhai,'' a local language.</p>
        <p>Ms. Maiga was carrying a load of clothes through a winding street, past a mud-brick house where a British explorer, Gordon Laing, lived in 1826. Regarded as the first European to reach Timbuktu, Laing was killed before making it back home.</p>
        <p>Founded early in this millennium, Timbuktu reached its peak toward the middle, when the trans-Saharan caravan trade turned it into the center of trade between the African interior to the south and the Arab world to the north. Stories of great mosques, sub-Saharan Africa's first Islamic university and vast wealth -- all inaccessible to Westerners -- reached Europe.</p>
        <p>Today, with the millennium spent, so, too, is Timbuktu. A small city of crumbling, mud-brick houses, the caravan trade a distant memory, Timbuktu is blanketed in sand. The advancing Sahara has encircled the city in dunes. But the magic of its name has endured, enough certainly to attract some foreigners to ring in the new year here.</p>
        <p>''Why don't I get a camel and go into the desert for the first sunrise of the millennium,'' said Larry Blum, 36, of Cohasset, Minn., explaining why he had come here. ''Most people, especially Americans, don't even think this place exists.''</p>
        <p>''So what's happening in the States?'' asked Mr. Blum, who is on a ''four-month solo expedition'' through West Africa. ''Heard anything about the N.F.L.?''</p>
        <p>Part of the city's allure surely remains its remoteness, at the edge of the vast Sahara, with no paved roads leading south. Even for those who took the easy way here and flew Air Mali, complications arose in midweek. Mali's president, Alpha O. Konare, needed Air Mali -- that is to say, the one plane that makes up the airline -- for urgent business and so delayed passengers' arrival here by several hours.</p>
        <p>''The end of the world?'' asked Jehara Maiga, who was preparing fish in the middle of the street when she was told of the West's view of her city. She laughed uncontrollably at the thought.</p>
        <p>Mamadou Kamoute, a teacher, added: ''For you, Timbuktu may be a city of dreams. But for us, it's just another city in Mali.''</p>
        <p>About 80 Peace Corps volunteers from West Africa made up the largest group of foreigners here. Sixty-seven had taken a three-day boat trip from the southern city of Mopti.</p>
        <p>''We sort of figured we'd move in this direction and see what happened,'' said Petra Cahill, 24, of Greenwich, Conn.</p>
        <p>Tariq Zehawi, 27, of Houston, said: ''Timbuktu is something I didn't even know existed until two years ago, when I applied for the Peace Corps and was told that I was coming to Mali, and I saw Timbuktu on the map.''</p>
        <p>And so despite the locals' ho-hum attitude toward the new year, the toubab energetically went about their plans to celebrate the arrival of 2000 in Timbuktu. About 100 tourists rode on camels into the desert and planned to spend the night there -- a project that appeared incomprehensible to a group of boys hanging out near a hotel.</p>
        <p>''It's not good to go out in the desert at night,'' said Sidi Baby, 12. ''It's going to be windy.''</p>
        <p>''It'll be cold,'' added Elhaje Baby, 13.</p>
        <p>''These toubab, they're . . .'' began Mahaldane Traore, who was only 15, but wise enough not to complete his thought in the presence of one of those toubab.</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
