<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marking Time in a Place Without Calendars</title>
    <meta content="Y01AFR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DD1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1367" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marking Time in a Place Without Calendars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <dateline>EKAMBU, Namibia, Dec. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The red sun was falling, the cooking fires were burning and the village elder's naked shoulders were shivering in the afternoon cool as he described the eagerly awaited arrival of the new year.</p>
        <p>''When the thunderstorms start and the leaves grow from the ground, that's how we know it's the new year,'' said Maverihepisa Koruhama, wrinkling his brow as he tried to calculate the auspicious date.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The red sun was falling, the cooking fires were burning and the village elder's naked shoulders were shivering in the afternoon cool as he described the eagerly awaited arrival of the new year.</p>
        <p>''When the thunderstorms start and the leaves grow from the ground, that's how we know it's the new year,'' said Maverihepisa Koruhama, wrinkling his brow as he tried to calculate the auspicious date.</p>
        <p>''This time,'' he said finally, ''the new year came about one month ago.''</p>
        <p>Here in this tiny village of mud huts and wildflowers, in the craggy, arid hills of northwest Namibia, there are no calendars, no electricity and no words in the native language for millennium, computer or Y2K. A telephone is a three-hour drive away.</p>
        <p>As the modern world celebrated the coming of 2000 with confetti and champagne, the Himba people started and ended their day much as they have for nearly 300 years, whistling to their goats, milking their cows and sleeping with the sun.</p>
        <p>These nomadic shepherds in this remote corner of the world stand as living links between the old world and the new, walking proudly with their age-old traditions into the new century.</p>
        <p>They measure time by the shifting sun and mark the coming of the new year with the arrival of seasonal rains that transform the parched red soil here into a carpet of green. (In their Herero language, the word for ''day'' is the same as the word for ''sun,'' and the word for ''year'' means ''rain.'')</p>
        <p>Mr. Koruhama said his family had never heard of the year 2000 -- or the year 1999, for that matter -- because the Himba do not use numbers to count years.</p>
        <p>But he watched proudly today as his young sons chased wayward cattle and his three wives soured milk for butter, as their ancestors did when they came to this region centuries ago from what is now Angola.</p>
        <p>''Today is a day like any other,'' said Mr. Koruhama, amused by a foreign visitor's questions. ''My father and my grandfathers, they were surviving from goats and cattle. That is what I am doing today. And I am teaching my children to look after cattle. That is our way. That is our future.''</p>
        <p>But the challenges confronting the estimated 7,000 to 10,000 Himba who hope to carry the old ways into the future are great.</p>
        <p>Already, the modern world is beginning to touch isolated villages like this one in Kaokoland, where the huts in the hills are accessible only on foot or in vehicles with four-wheel drive.</p>
        <p>The Himba have begun to send some of their children far away to school, and some come home wearing Reebok baseball caps along with their traditional loincloths. In some places, shepherds trade goats for bright yellow tarpaulins to protect their mud roofs from leaks.</p>
        <p>Some Himba have left their villages altogether, turning their backs on the ways of their community, where bare-breasted women still stain their skin with glossy red ochre and men still cover their long hair in turban-like wraps.</p>
        <p>''Some of my extended family, they've left and gone to the towns,'' said Kamukazona Koruhama, Mr. Koruhama's sister-in-law.</p>
        <p>''They change the way they dress, the way they look,'' she said sadly. ''They don't come back. It's many, many Himba people living now in towns. People are asking: 'Why do they leave? Why do they move to the place that belongs to other people? Why don't they come back?' ''</p>
        <p>For the family of Mr. Koruhama, it is difficult to understand. They cannot understand the appeal of the western way of life. People in town often forget the old ways, they warn their children.</p>
        <p>Will they remember that the boiled root of the sour plum tree cures diarrhea, their parents ask. Or that the mopane tree makes the best firewood? Or that one cannot communicate with the ancestors without the sacred fire that burns in every village?</p>
        <p>''Move to town?'' repeated Mr. Koruhama, scoffing at the idea that his children might someday leave his village. ''That doesn't make any sense. Goats are afraid of cars. How will the goats live in town with all the cars down there?''</p>
        <p>But change is coming.</p>
        <p>The Namibian government is determined to develop their remote region, starting with a $550 million dam on the border with Angola that would flood the grazing grounds of 1,000 people and 100 ancestral graves while providing the country with much-needed power.</p>
        <p>The project -- still in the planning stages -- would bring thousands of workers to Kaoakoland, and with them the benefits of electricity, roads and clinics as well as the problems of prostitution and AIDS, government officials acknowledge.</p>
        <p>''That is the only region in Namibia that is completely in darkness, no roads, no infrastructure, nothing,'' said Paulinus Shilamba, director of energy for the Ministry of Mines and Energy here.</p>
        <p>''This project will change the whole face of that region,'' Mr. Shilamba said. ''The present culture of the Himba people will gradually disappear. The Himba will change. They will get cars, get jobs and go to school like everyone else. In my mind, that's better.''</p>
        <p>Advocates for the Himba are battling the plan, saying it would irreparably damage what is regarded as one of southern Africa's most successful, self-sufficient tribes.</p>
        <p>But Zepauandoui Tjambiru Koruhama, another of Mr. Koruhama's sisters-in-law who lives nearby, believe some change is good.</p>
        <p>She is a traditional wife. She covers her body with ochre and butterfat every morning and prays to her ancestors. She wears a conch shell around her neck and calf-skins to cover her hips. She knows her year of birth by its proper name, based on its most significant event.</p>
        <p>''I was born in the year of my great-grandfather's death,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She has never heard of New York or America and has no idea who won this country's presidential election, which was held last month. She has eight children and many more cows to manage. Her life is full.</p>
        <p>But it is also very hard, and she does not romanticize it.</p>
        <p>During the dry season, when water is scarce, her family moves as many as 10 times, searching for grass for the cattle to eat.</p>
        <p>Even during the rainy season, the soil is often too dry to grow corn or other vegetables, and her family must often subsist on milk.</p>
        <p>''These are hard ways, the same hard ways of my grandmothers,''  she said.</p>
        <p>So she and her husband decided to compromise. One son would tend the sheep in the traditional fashion. Another boy would go to school, to learn English and modern ways. And every year now, her husband trades three goats to cover the annual school fees.</p>
        <p>This week, the boy, Aaron, was at home from school on break, wearing an Adidas jacket and faded Puma sneakers. He is about 17 (most Himba do not know their exact ages), and he knows all about the millennium.</p>
        <p>In 2000, he says, he hopes to get a job, buy a car, help his family. He says he will make his life in a city somewhere, not here.</p>
        <p>''I want to get money to help my mother and father, to buy food, to buy blankets for them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His mother listens to him quietly and then sends him off to tend the cattle. She prays he will work for a while and then return home to his traditions.</p>
        <p>''He says now these new ways are so beautiful, but I hope someday he will realize it's not the best way,'' she said, sighing. ''But I can't see the future. Only the ancestors know what the new rains will bring.''</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
