<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping His Promise, Pope Opens New Year</title>
    <meta content="Y01ROM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4DC1038F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping His Promise, Pope Opens New Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Paul II gave his first blessing of the Year 2000 as fireworks exploded and church bells tolled, ushering in the new year across Rome.</p>
        <p>''As we cross the threshold of the new year, I would like to knock at the door of every home, to bring to each of you my cordial good wishes,'' the pope said to about 100,000 people gathered in St. Peter's Square beneath his study window, many holding up torches and candles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Paul II gave his first blessing of the Year 2000 as fireworks exploded and church bells tolled, ushering in the new year across Rome.</p>
        <p>''As we cross the threshold of the new year, I would like to knock at the door of every home, to bring to each of you my cordial good wishes,'' the pope said to about 100,000 people gathered in St. Peter's Square beneath his study window, many holding up torches and candles.</p>
        <p>After he spoke, the crowd erupted in cheers and applause.</p>
        <p>In past years, the pope has not made a midnight appearance on New Year's Eve, preferring to perform an evening vespers service, and then get a good night's sleep before a Jan. 1 Mass.</p>
        <p>But this New Year's Eve falls at the start of a Holy Year for the Roman Catholic Church, one that commemorates the 2,000th anniversary of the birth of Christ. Ever since he was elected in 1978, the pope has said he has been looking forward to the moment when he would lead the faithful into the third millennium.</p>
        <p>And people came from all over the world to witness the moment.</p>
        <p>''We thought this would be memorable, not only for the Christian meaning, but because Rome was the center of civilization 2,000 years ago,'' said Rory Conway, 21, a New Yorker.</p>
        <p>At a vespers service this evening, the ailing 79-year-old pope glided up the aisle of St. Peter's Basilica, his hands clutching the handle of a wheeled staircase pushed by his aides. It was the second time this week that he has used the device, which helps him preserve his strength and also allows the crowds to get a better glimpse of him.</p>
        <p>He gave thanks to God in his homily but also asked for forgiveness. ''Let us ask for pardon because too often, alas, the conquests of science and technology, so important to real human progress, are used against mankind.''</p>
        <p>Normally, the pope retires to his country residence of Castel Gandolfo outside of Rome to rest between Christmas and New Year's. This year, despite his fragile health, the pontiff elected to stay at the Vatican to remain close to the religious pilgrims who traveled to Rome for the Holy Year. On Saturday, he will open the holy door of Santa Maria Maggiore basilica, and celebrate  Mass there.</p>
        <p>Before the pope appeared, the waiting crowds were entertained by a multicultural concert which included from Queen Esther Marrow, a Harlem gospel singer, a choir of 5,000 children from various countries around the world, and Italian pop singer Claudio Baglioni.</p>
        <p>In tonight's homily, the pope cited the discovery of America, ''which initiated a new era in the history of humanity,'' as a key development of the last 1,000 years.</p>
        <p>1/1/00: AROUND THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
