<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Running Start to the Year 2000</title>
    <meta content="01MARA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARATHON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Millennium Marathon</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Zealand</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hutchinson, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E2D61338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Running Start to the Year 2000</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>HAMILTON, New Zealand, Saturday, Jan. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Hutchinson of New Zealand wins Millennium Marathon in Hamilton, NZ, on Jan 1; about 2,000 runners from 45 countries compete; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Welcome to the first marathon anywhere in the world this millennium,'' the public-address announcer said as approximately 2,000 runners applauded the news here on the first morning of 2000.</p>
        <p>They had come from 45 countries: from Thailand and Japan; from France and the Czech Republic; from Canada and the United States. In most cases, they had made their plans years ago, conserved their resources and sacrificed a night of carefree revelry for the chance to get up long before dawn and smile through the pain in the Millennium Marathon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Welcome to the first marathon anywhere in the world this millennium,'' the public-address announcer said as approximately 2,000 runners applauded the news here on the first morning of 2000.</p>
        <p>They had come from 45 countries: from Thailand and Japan; from France and the Czech Republic; from Canada and the United States. In most cases, they had made their plans years ago, conserved their resources and sacrificed a night of carefree revelry for the chance to get up long before dawn and smile through the pain in the Millennium Marathon.</p>
        <p>''I must confess that I was in bed before midnight,'' said Weston Holmes, a 61-year-old from Houston.</p>
        <p>But there were psychic rewards for those who bid farewell to the 1900's 18 hours ahead of the New Yorkers and Bostonians and Washingtonians they left behind.</p>
        <p>''They haven't even gathered in Times Square yet, and we already ran a marathon,'' said Fred Lipsky, a 42-year-old sergeant in the Suffolk County Police Department on Long Island.</p>
        <p>What the jet laggers and early risers did not get for their trouble was a spectacular sunrise. Instead, they got light rain and mist as they gathered for the 6 a.m. start that had been timed to coincide with first light.</p>
        <p>The early start also deprived the marathoners of a sizable audience. Only a few hundred spectators lined the streets of Hamilton, a city of more than 100,000 approximately 80 miles south of New Zealand's capital, Auckland. But neither the sparse crowd nor the soggy conditions dampened the enthusiasm of the competitors. They cheered as they prepared to start. Some were sporting floppy hats with ''2000'' written on them.</p>
        <p>The Americans were certainly here in force. A total of 626 competed in either the marathon or the much shorter fun runs that followed it, and though the fastest men's finisher in the marathon was an Aucklander and the fastest woman a Briton, the Americans had the biggest contingent: slightly bigger than the Germans and substantially bigger than the host nation.</p>
        <p>''I've been planning this for two years,'' said S. Mark Courtney, a 43-year-old from Grove City, Pa. ''This is my 100th career marathon, and I was trying to zero in on which one to pick, and New Zealand is a place I always wanted to go. That and this race were the perfect combination.''</p>
        <p>The race organizer, Andrew Galloway, expressed disappointment that more New Zealanders did not reach the same conclusion. ''New Zealanders generally have not accepted much to do with the millennium,'' he said. ''There have been a lot of canceled events here.''</p>
        <p>Galloway dreamed up the Millennium Marathon in 1995 when he was secretary of the Association of International Marathons. At a meeting in New York, he suggested to his organization and Unicef that they organize a run in every major city around the world as the year 2000 dawned. The interest was not there, and so after a meeting with international marathon tour operators, he settled for Hamilton.</p>
        <p>''Hey, it's not the New York City Marathon,'' Lipsky said after finishing the 26.2-mile course in 3 hours 32 minutes 10 seconds. ''But for a small town and a small country, it was still a beautiful race.''</p>
        <p>Lipsky is part of Fred's Team, the group of runners carrying on the fund-raising work begun by the New York City Marathon founder Fred Lebow, who died of brain cancer in 1994. All 30 of the team members who raced in Hamilton raised at least $9,000 for children's cancer research at Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center in Manhattan. Lipsky said he had raised $23,000 since his last marathon in an even more exotic Southern Hemisphere locale: Antarctica's King George Island.</p>
        <p>''We had to stay on a ship before the race for that one; there were no roads or hotels, only research camps,'' said Lipsky, whose goal is to run a marathon on all seven continents.</p>
        <p>Though Hamilton had no glaciers or penguins, it did have its own quirks, including a midrace wedding ceremony between two marathon competitors. Published reports that several world-class Ethiopian runners were to compete proved apocryphal, however, and the winner, Mark Hutchinson, had to settle for a time (2:21.58) that was much more modest than the race's title.</p>
        <p>Kamala Cornman and her husband, Lance, who came from Oklahoma City to run, chose to push the envelope, joining in the celebration in the streets of Hamilton and then watching the celebration in Sydney, Australia, on television before going to bed.</p>
        <p>''We got two hours of sleep,'' Kamala said. ''But we can sleep later. How many times do you get to experience something like this?''  MARATHON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
